<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText xml:lang='en' osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='EMTV'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='EMTV'>
        <title>English Majority Text Version</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>txt2zef</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject/>
        <date>2009-04-13</date>
        <description>Welcome to the third edition of  The English Majority Text Version (EMTV) of the Holy Bible. This latest edition has Greek explanatory notes throughout the Bible, to aid the reader in understanding the meanings in some select places of the original Koine Greek. Also, the third edition finds itself closer to the Robinson/Pierpoint printed edition of the Byzantine majority text, rather than the Hodges/Farstad text, which the EMTV was translated from. You will notice these differences in John 7:53-8:11, as well as the entire book of Revelation. The English Majority Text Version draws from the work of both Dr.’s Hodges and Farstad, and their text, “The Greek New Testament According to the Majority Text,” as well as from Dr. Wilbur Pickering, ThM. PhD., and the EMTV has incorporated his hard work in the field of producing evidence of just what does constitute a majority reading, and, as a result of his work, and the work of others, John 7:53-8:11, and the book of Revelation reflect these variant readings. This is one of the great things about having a Bible that is translated from the majority of the trustworthy Byzantine manuscripts that are in existence—the much greater probability of accuracy. On the other side of the fence, most modern Bibles are translated from a few scant manuscripts (literally), and more often than not they do not even agree with each other. Not so with a Bible that is translated out of the majority! The experts in linguistics who have put these readings together, and diligently compared the manuscripts, had hundreds and hundreds of manuscripts to compare. It is my prayer that this work will bring honor to our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ, and to our God and Father; because all of this, all that we do, we do to know Him better, and to better understand His word, which He has given to mankind. “Every word of God is pure; He is a shield to those who put their trust in Him. Do not add to His words, Lest He rebuke you, and you be found a liar. (Prove 30:5,6). Peace of Christ to you all.  In His service, Paul W Esposito Stauros Ministries</description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>EMTV</identifier>
        <source>TheWord</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>Paul W Esposito President, Stauros Ministries PO Box 3004 Cocoa, Fl. 32924 (321) 403-5782</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='2Tim'>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.1'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.1'>Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by the will of God, according to the promise of life which [is] in Christ Jesus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.2'>To Timothy, [my ]beloved son: Grace, mercy, and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.3'>I give thanks to God, whom I serve with a pure conscience, as my forefathers did, how unceasingly I have remembrance of you in my prayers night and day,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.4'>longing to see you, having recalled your tears, that I may be filled with joy,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.5'>taking recollection of the genuine faith [that is] in you, which dwelt first in your grandmother Lois and in your mother Eunice, and I am persuaded is in you also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.6'>For which cause I remind you to stir up the gift of God which is in you through the laying on of my hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.7'>For God has not given us a spirit of fear, but of power and of love and of a sound mind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.8'>Therefore do not be ashamed of the testimony of our Lord, nor of me His prisoner, but endure hardship with the gospel according to the power of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.9'>who having saved us, and having called us with a holy calling, not according to our works, but according to His own purpose and grace which was given to us in Christ Jesus before time [itself],</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.10'>but has now been revealed through the appearance of our Savior Jesus Christ, having abolished death on the one hand, [and] having brought to life immortality through the gospel on the other,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.11'>to which I was appointed a herald and apostle, and a teacher of the Gentiles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.12'>For which cause I also suffer these things; but I am not ashamed, for I know whom I have believed, and I have been persuaded that He is able to guard that which I have committed to Him until that Day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.13'>Hold to the pattern of sound words which you have heard from me, in faith and love which are in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.14'>That good thing which was committed to you, guard by the Holy Spirit who dwells in us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.15'>This you know, that all those in Asia have turned away from me, of whom are Phygellus and Hermogenes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.16'>May the Lord grant mercy to the household of Onesiphorus, because he often refreshed me, and he was not ashamed of my chain;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.17'>but when he arrived in Rome, he more diligently sought me out and found [me].</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.18'>May the Lord grant to him to find mercy from the Lord in that Day-and you very well know how many ways he served in Ephesus.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.2'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.1'>You therefore, my child, be empowered by the grace which is in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.2'>And the things which you have heard from me through many witnesses, commit these to faithful men who will be competent to teach others also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.3'>You therefore endure hardship as a good soldier of Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.4'>No one serving as a soldier entangles [himself] in the affairs of [civilian] life, in order that he may please the [one] having enlisted him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.5'>And also if anyone competes in athletics, he is not crowned unless he competes according to the rules.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.6'>It is necessary for the hard-working farmer [to be] first to receive of the fruits.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.7'>Consider the things I say, and may the Lord give you understanding in all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.8'>Remember that Jesus Christ, of the seed of David, was raised from the dead according to my gospel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.9'>in which I endure hardship unto chains as an evildoer; but the word of God is not chained.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.10'>Because of this, I endure all things for the sake of the elect, that they also may obtain the salvation which is in Christ Jesus with eternal glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.11'>Faithful is this word: For if we died with [Him], we shall also live with [Him].</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.12'>If we endure, we shall also reign with [Him]. If we deny [Him], He also will deny us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.13'>If we are faithless, He remains faithful; He cannot deny Himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.14'>Remind them of these things, charging them before the Lord not to dispute about words, useful for nothing, for the ruin of the hearers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.15'>Be diligent to show yourself approved unto God, a worker unashamed, rightly dividing the word of truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.16'>But shun profane and empty babblings; for they will advance to more ungodliness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.17'>And their word will spread like gangrene; of whom are Hymenaeus and Philetus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.18'>who have strayed concerning the truth, asserting that the resurrection has already occurred; and they overturn the faith of some.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.19'>Nevertheless the firm foundation of God stands, having this seal: "The Lord knows those that are His,"and, "Let everyone naming the name of the Lord depart from unrighteousness."</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.20'>Now in a great house there are not only vessels of gold and silver, but also of wood and clay, some for honor and some for dishonor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.21'>Therefore if anyone cleanses himself from the [latter], he will be a vessel for honor, having been consecrated and useful to the Master, having been prepared for every good work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.22'>Flee youthful lusts; but pursue righteousness, faith, love, peace with those who call on the Lord out of a pure heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.23'>But reject foolish and ignorant disputes, knowing that they bring forth fights.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.24'>And a servant of the Lord ought not to fight, but to be gentle to all, skillful at teaching, forbearing,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.25'>in meekness instructing those that oppose, if God perhaps may give them repentance, to a full knowledge of the truth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.26'>and they regain their senses [and escape] out of the snare of the devil, having been captured alive by him to do his will.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.3'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.1'>But know this, that in the last days perilous times shall come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.2'>For men will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boasters, proud, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.3'>unloving, unforgiving, slanderers, without self-control, brutal, not loving what is good,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.4'>traitors, headstrong, having been puffed up, lovers of pleasure rather than lovers of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.5'>having a form of godliness but denying its power. And from these people turn away!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.6'>For of these are those [who] creep into houses and captivate gullible women having been loaded down with sins, who are led by various lusts,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.7'>always learning and never being able to come to a full knowledge of the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.8'>And in just the way Jannes and Jambres resisted Moses, thus also these resist the truth: men corrupted in mind, disapproved regarding the faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.9'>But they shall not advance further, for their folly shall be manifest to all, as also theirs became.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.10'>You however have carefully followed my doctrine, lifestyle, purpose, faith, patience, love, endurance,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.11'>persecutions, [and ]afflictions, which happened to me at Antioch, in Iconium, at Lystra-what persecutions I endured. And out of them all the Lord delivered me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.12'>Yes, and all who desire to live godly in Christ Jesus will be persecuted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.13'>But evil men and impostors shall advance worse and worse, deceiving and being deceived.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.14'>But you must continue in the things which you have learned and been assured of, knowing from whom you learned them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.15'>and that from childhood you have known the Holy Scriptures, which are able to make you wise to salvation through faith which is in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.16'>All Scripture is given by inspiration of God, and is profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for instruction in righteousness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.17'>that the man of God may be proficient, having been thoroughly equipped for every good work.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.4'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.1'>I charge you therefore before God and the Lord Jesus Christ, who is going to judge the living and the dead in accordance with His appearing and His kingdom:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.2'>preach the word! Be ready in season and out of season. Reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all patience and teaching.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.3'>For there will be a time when they will not put up with sound doctrine, but according to their own lusts, they will heap up for themselves teachers, tickling their ears,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.4'>and they will turn their ears away from the truth, and be turned aside to myths.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.5'>You however be watchful in all things, endure hardship, do the work of an evangelist, fulfill your ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.6'>For I am already being poured out [as a drink offering], and the time of my departure has arrived.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.7'>I have fought the good fight. I have finished the race, I have kept the faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.8'>Finally, there is laid up for me the crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous Judge, will give to me on that Day, and not only to me, but also to all those who have loved His appearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.9'>Be diligent to come to me quickly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.10'>For Demas has forsaken me, having loved this present world, and traveled to Thessalonica-Crescens to Galatia, Titus to Dalmatia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.11'>Luke alone is with me. Take Mark, and bring him with you, for he is useful to me for ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.12'>And Tychicus I have sent to Ephesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.13'>Bring the cloak which I left with Carpus at Troas when you come-and the books, especially the parchments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.14'>Alexander the coppersmith did me much harm. May the Lord repay him according to his works;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.15'>whom you also should guard against, for he has greatly resisted our words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.16'>At my first defense no one stood with me, but all forsook me. May it not be reckoned to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.17'>But the Lord stood by me and strengthened me, so that through me the proclamation might be fulfilled, and all the Gentiles might hear, and I was delivered out of the mouth of the lion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.18'>And the Lord shall deliver me from every evil work and preserve me for His heavenly kingdom. To Him [be] glory forever and ever. Amen!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.19'>Greet Prisca and Aquila, and the household of Onesiphorus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.20'>Erastus stayed in Corinth, but Trophimus I have left in Miletus sick.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.21'>Be diligent to come before winter. Eubulus greets you, as well as Pudens, Linus, Claudia, and all the brothers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.22'>The Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Grace be with you. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>