<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='NHEB' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2012-02-07</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='NHEB'>
        <title>New Heart English Bible</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Mod2Zef (5)</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject/>
        <date>2012-02-07</date>
        <description>New Heart English Bible (NHEB) is not copyrighted and is dedicated to the Public Domain by the editors and translators.   You may publish, copy, memorize, translate, quote, and use the New Heart English Bible freely without additional permission.   Wayne A. Mitchell  Sep 22, 2009</description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>NHEB</identifier>
        <source>www.publicdomainbibles.com</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Joel'>
      <chapter osisID='Joel.1'>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.1'>The Word of the Lord that came to Joel, the son of Pethuel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.2'>Hear this, you elders,And listen, all you inhabitants of the land.Has this ever happened in your days,or in the days of your fathers?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.3'>Tell your children about it,and have your children tell their children,and their children, another generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.4'>What the swarming locust has left, the great locust has eaten.What the great locust has left, the grasshopper has eaten.What the grasshopper has left, the caterpillar has eaten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.5'>Wake up, you drunkards, and weep!Wail, all you drinkers of wine, because of the sweet wine;for it is cut off from your mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.6'>For a nation has come up on my land, strong, and without number.His teeth are the teeth of a lion,and he has the fangs of a lioness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.7'>He has laid my vine waste,and stripped my fig tree.He has stripped its bark, and thrown it away.Its branches are made white.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.8'>Mourn like a virgin dressed in sackcloth for the husband of her youth!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.9'>The meal offering and the drink offering are cut off from the Lord's house.The priests, the Lord's ministers, mourn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.10'>The field is laid waste.The land mourns, for the grain is destroyed,The new wine has dried up,and the oil languishes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.11'>Be confounded, you farmers!Wail, you vineyard keepers;for the wheat and for the barley;for the harvest of the field has perished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.12'>The vine has dried up, and the fig tree withered;the pomegranate tree, the palm tree also, and the apple tree,even all of the trees of the field are withered;for joy has withered away from the sons of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.13'>Put on sackcloth and mourn, you priests!Wail, you ministers of the altar.Come, lie all night in sackcloth, you ministers of my God,for the meal offering and the drink offering are withheld from your God's house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.14'>Sanctify a fast.Call a solemn assembly.Gather the elders,and all the inhabitants of the land, to the house of the Lord, your God,and cry to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.15'>Alas for the day!For the day of the Lord is at hand,and it will come as destruction from the Almighty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.16'>Isn't the food cut off before our eyes;joy and gladness from the house of our God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.17'>The seeds rot under their clods.The granaries are laid desolate.The barns are broken down, for the grain has withered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.18'>How the animals groan!The herds of livestock are perplexed, because they have no pasture.Yes, the flocks of sheep are made desolate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.19'>The Lord, I cry to you,For the fire has devoured the pastures of the wilderness,and the flame has burned all the trees of the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.1.20'>Yes, the animals of the field pant to you,for the water brooks have dried up,And the fire has devoured the pastures of the wilderness.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Joel.2'>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.1'>Blow the trumpet in Zion,and sound an alarm in my holy mountain!Let all the inhabitants of the land tremble,for the day of the Lord comes,for it is close at hand:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.2'>A day of darkness and gloominess,a day of clouds and thick darkness.As the dawn spreading on the mountains,a great and strong people;there has never been the like,neither will there be any more after them,even to the years of many generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.3'>A fire devours before them,and behind them, a flame burns.The land is as the garden of Eden before them,and behind them, a desolate wilderness.Yes, and no one has escaped them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.4'>The appearance of them is as the appearance of horses,and as horsemen, so do they run.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.5'>Like the noise of chariots on the tops of the mountains do they leap,like the noise of a flame of fire that devours the stubble,as a strong people set in battle array.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.6'>At their presence the peoples are in anguish.All faces have grown pale.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.7'>They run like mighty men.They climb the wall like warriors.They each march in his line, and they do not swerve off course.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.8'>Neither does one jostle another;they march everyone in his path,and they burst through the defenses,and do not break ranks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.9'>They rush on the city.They run on the wall.They climb up into the houses.They enter in at the windows like thieves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.10'>The earth quakes before them.The heavens tremble.The sun and the moon are darkened,and the stars withdraw their shining.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.11'>The Lord thunders his voice before his army;for his forces are very great;for he is strong who obeys his command;for the day of the Lord is great and very awesome,and who can endure it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.12'>"Yet even now," says the Lord, "turn to me with all your heart,and with fasting, and with weeping, and with mourning."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.13'>Tear your heart, and not your garments,and turn to the Lord, your God;for he is gracious and merciful,slow to anger, and abundant in loving kindness,and relents from sending calamity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.14'>Who knows? He may turn and relent,and leave a blessing behind him,even a meal offering and a drink offering to the Lord, your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.15'>Blow the trumpet in Zion!Sanctify a fast.Call a solemn assembly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.16'>Gather the people.Sanctify the assembly.Assemble the elders.Gather the children, and those who suck the breasts.Let the bridegroom go forth from his room,and the bride out of her chamber.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.17'>Let the priests, the ministers of the Lord, weep between the porch and the altar,and let them say, "Spare your people, Lord,and do not give your heritage to reproach,that the nations should rule over them.Why should they say among the peoples,'Where is their God?'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.18'>Then the Lord was jealous for his land,And had pity on his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.19'>The Lord answered his people,"Behold, I will send you grain, new wine, and oil,and you will be satisfied with them;and I will no more make you a reproach among the nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.20'>But I will remove the northern army far away from you,and will drive it into a barren and desolate land,its front into the eastern sea,and its back into the western sea;and its stench will come up,and its bad smell will rise."Surely he has done great things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.21'>Land, do not be afraid.Be glad and rejoice, for the Lord has done great things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.22'>Do not be afraid, you animals of the field;for the pastures of the wilderness spring up,for the tree bears its fruit.The fig tree and the vine yield their strength.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.23'>"Be glad then, you children of Zion,and rejoice in the Lord, your God;for he gives you the former rain in just measure,and he causes the rain to come down for you,the former rain and the latter rain,as before.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.24'>The threshing floors will be full of wheat,and the vats will overflow with new wine and oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.25'>I will restore to you the years that the swarming locust has eaten,the great locust, the grasshopper, and the caterpillar,my great army, which I sent among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.26'>You will have plenty to eat, and be satisfied,and will praise the name of the Lord, your God,who has dealt wondrously with you;and my people will never again be disappointed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.27'>You will know that I am in the midst of Israel,and that I am the Lord, your God, and there is no one else;and my people will never again be disappointed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.28'>"It will happen afterward, that I will pour out my Spirit on all flesh;and your sons and your daughters will prophesy.Your old men will dream dreams.Your young men will see visions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.29'>And also on the servants and on the handmaids in those days,I will pour out my Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.30'>I will show wonders in the heavens and in the earth:blood, fire, and pillars of smoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.31'>The sun will be turned into darkness,and the moon into blood,before the great and terrible day of the Lord comes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.2.32'>It will happen that whoever will call on the name of the Lord shall be saved;for in Mount Zion and in Jerusalem there will be those who escape,as the Lord has said,and among the remnant, those whom the Lord calls.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Joel.3'>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.1'>"For, behold, in those days,and in that time,when I restore the fortunes of Judah and Jerusalem,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.2'>I will gather all nations,and will bring them down into the valley of Jehoshaphat;and I will execute judgment on them there for my people,and for my heritage, Israel, whom they have scattered among the nations.They have divided my land,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.3'>and have cast lots for my people,and have given a boy for a prostitute,and sold a girl for wine, that they may drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.4'>"Yes, and what are you to me, Tyre, and Sidon,and all the regions of Philistia?Will you repay me?And if you repay me,I will swiftly and speedily return your repayment on your own head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.5'>Because you have taken my silver and my gold,and have carried my finest treasures into your temples,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.6'>and have sold the children of Judah and the children of Jerusalem to the sons of the Greeks,that you may remove them far from their border.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.7'>Behold, I will stir them up out of the place where you have sold them,and will return your repayment on your own head;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.8'>and I will sell your sons and your daughters into the hands of the children of Judah,and they will sell them to the men of Sheba,to a faraway nation,for the Lord has spoken it."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.9'>Proclaim this among the nations:"Prepare for war!Stir up the mighty men.Let all the warriors draw near.Let them come up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.10'>Beat your plowshares into swords,and your pruning hooks into spears.Let the weak say, 'I am strong.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.11'>Hurry and come, all you surrounding nations,and gather yourselves together."Cause your mighty ones to come down there, Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.12'>"Let the nations arouse themselves,and come up to the valley of Jehoshaphat;for there will I sit to judge all the surrounding nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.13'>Put in the sickle;for the harvest is ripe.Come, tread, for the winepress is full,the vats overflow, for their wickedness is great."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.14'>Multitudes, multitudes in the valley of decision!For the day of the Lord is near, in the valley of decision.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.15'>The sun and the moon are darkened,and the stars withdraw their shining.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.16'>The Lord will roar from Zion,and thunder from Jerusalem;and the heavens and the earth will shake;but the Lord will be a refuge to his people,and a stronghold to the children of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.17'>"So you will know that I am the Lord, your God,dwelling in Zion, my holy mountain.Then Jerusalem will be holy,and no strangers will pass through her any more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.18'>It will happen in that day,that the mountains will drop down sweet wine,the hills will flow with milk,all the brooks of Judah will flow with waters,and a fountain will come forth from the house of the Lord,and will water the valley of Shittim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.19'>Egypt will be a desolation,and Edom will be a desolate wilderness,for the violence done to the children of Judah,because they have shed innocent blood in their land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.20'>But Judah will be inhabited forever,and Jerusalem from generation to generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Joel.3.21'>I will cleanse their blood,that I have not cleansed:for the Lord dwells in Zion."</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>