<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='YLT' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='YLT'>
        <title>YLT</title>
        <contributor>Robert Young</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>Holy Bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>The Bible text designated YLT is from the 1898 Young's Literal Translation by Robert Young who also compiled Young's Analytical Concordance</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>YLT</identifier>
        <source>ftp://unboundftp.biola.edu/pub/ylt.zip</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>PD</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div osisID='Titus' type='book'>
      <chapter osisID='Titus.1'>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.1'>Paul, a servant of God, and an apostle of Jesus Christ,  according to the faith of the choice ones of God, and an  acknowledging of truth that [is] according to piety,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.2'>upon hope of life age-during, which God, who doth not lie,  did promise before times of ages,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.3'>(and He manifested in proper times His word,) in preaching,  which I was entrusted with, according to a charge of God our  Saviour,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.4'>to Titus -- true child according to a common faith: Grace,  kindness, peace, from God the Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ  our Saviour!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.5'>For this cause left I thee in Crete, that the things lacking  thou mayest arrange, and mayest set down in every city elders,  as I did appoint to thee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.6'>if any one is blameless, of one wife a husband, having  children stedfast, not under accusation of riotous living or  insubordinate --</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.7'>for it behoveth the overseer to be blameless, as God`s  steward, not self-pleased, nor irascible, not given to wine,  not a striker, not given to filthy lucre;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.8'>but a lover of strangers, a lover of good men, sober-minded,  righteous, kind, self-controlled,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.9'>holding -- according to the teaching -- to the stedfast  word, that he may be able also to exhort in the sound  teaching, and the gainsayers to convict;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.10'>for there are many both insubordinate, vain-talkers, and  mind-deceivers -- especially they of the circumcision --</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.11'>whose mouth it behoveth to stop, who whole households do  overturn, teaching what things it behoveth not, for filthy  lucre`s sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.12'>A certain one of them, a prophet of their own, said --  `Cretans! always liars, evil beasts, lazy bellies!`</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.13'>this testimony is true; for which cause convict them  sharply, that they may be sound in the faith,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.14'>not giving heed to Jewish fables and commands of men,  turning themselves away from the truth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.15'>all things, indeed, [are] pure to the pure, and to the  defiled and unstedfast [is] nothing pure, but of them defiled  [are] even the mind and the conscience;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.16'>God they profess to know, and in the works they deny [Him],  being abominable, and disobedient, and unto every good work  disapproved.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Titus.2'>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.1'>And thou -- be speaking what doth become the sound teaching;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.2'>aged men to be temperate, grave, sober, sound in the faith,  in the love, in the endurance;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.3'>aged women, in like manner, in deportment as doth become  sacred persons, not false accusers, to much wine not enslaved,  of good things teachers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.4'>that they may make the young women sober-minded, to be  lovers of [their] husbands, lovers of [their] children,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.5'>sober, pure, keepers of [their own] houses, good, subject to  their own husbands, that the word of God may not be evil  spoken of.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.6'>The younger men, in like manner, be exhorting to be  sober-minded;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.7'>concerning all things thyself showing a pattern of good  works; in the teaching uncorruptedness, gravity,  incorruptibility,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.8'>discourse sound, irreprehensible, that he who is of the  contrary part may be ashamed, having nothing evil to say  concerning you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.9'>Servants -- to their own masters [are] to be subject, in all  things to be well-pleasing, not gainsaying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.10'>not purloining, but showing all good stedfastness, that the  teaching of God our Saviour they may adorn in all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.11'>For the saving grace of God was manifested to all men,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.12'>teaching us, that denying the impiety and the worldly  desires, soberly and righteously and piously we may live in  the present age,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.13'>waiting for the blessed hope and manifestation of the glory  of our great God and Saviour Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.14'>who did give himself for us, that he might ransom us from  all lawlessness, and might purify to himself a peculiar  people, zealous of good works;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.15'>these things be speaking, and exhorting, and convicting,  with all charge; let no one despise thee!</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Titus.3'>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.1'>Remind them to be subject to principalities and authorities,  to obey rule, unto every good work to be ready,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.2'>of no one to speak evil, not to be quarrelsome -- gentle,  showing all meekness to all men,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.3'>for we were once -- also we -- thoughtless, disobedient, led  astray, serving desires and pleasures manifold, in malice and  envy living, odious -- hating one another;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.4'>and when the kindness and the love to men of God our Saviour  did appear</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.5'>(not by works that [are] in righteousness that we did but  according to His kindness,) He did save us, through a bathing  of regeneration, and a renewing of the Holy Spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.6'>which He poured upon us richly, through Jesus Christ our  Saviour,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.7'>that having been declared righteous by His grace, heirs we  may become according to the hope of life age-during.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.8'>Stedfast [is] the word; and concerning these things I  counsel thee to affirm fully, that they may be thoughtful, to  be leading in good works -- who have believed God; these are  the good and profitable things to men,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.9'>and foolish questions, and genealogies, and contentions, and  strivings about law, stand away from -- for they are  unprofitable and vain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.10'>A sectarian man, after a first and second admonition be  rejecting,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.11'>having known that he hath been subverted who [is] such, and  doth sin, being self-condemned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.12'>When I shall send Artemas unto thee, or Tychicus, be  diligent to come unto me to Nicopolis, for there to winter I  have determined.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.13'>Zenas the lawyer and Apollos bring diligently on their way,  that nothing to them may be lacking,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.14'>and let them learn -- ours also -- to be leading in good  works to the necessary uses, that they may not be unfruitful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.15'>Salute thee do all those with me; salute those loving us in  faith; the grace [is] with you all!</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>