<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='WMTH' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='WMTH'>
        <title>Weymouth NT</title>
        <contributor>*</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible new testament</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>The Translation of the New Testament offered to English-speaking Christians is a bona fide translation made directly from the Greek, and is in no sense a revision.</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>WMTH</identifier>
        <source>ftp://unboundftp.biola.edu/pub/weymouth_nt.zip</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>PD</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div osisID='2John' type='book'>
      <chapter osisID='2John.1'>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.1'>The Elder to the elect lady and her children. Truly I love you all, and not I alone, but also all who know the truth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.2'>for the sake of the truth which is continually in our hearts and will be with us for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.3'>Grace, mercy and peace will be with us from God the Father, and from Jesus Christ the Son of the Father, in truth and love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.4'>It is an intense joy to me to have found some of your children living true Christian lives, in obedience to the command which we have received from the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.5'>And now, dear lady, I pray you –writing to you, as I do, not a new command, but the one which we have had from the very beginning– let us love one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.6'>The love of which I am speaking consists in our living in obedience to God's commands. God's command is that you should live in obedience to what you all heard from the very beginning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.7'>For many deceivers have gone out into the world–men who do not acknowledge Jesus as Christ who has come in human nature. Such a one is `the deceiver' and `the anti-Christ.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.8'>Keep guard over yourselves, so that you may not lose the results of your good deeds, but may receive back a full reward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.9'>No one has God, who instead of remaining true to the teaching of Christ, presses on in advance: but he who remains true to that teaching has both the Father and the Son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.10'>If any one who comes to you does not bring this teaching, do not receive him under your roof nor bid him Farewell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.11'>He who bids him Farewell is a sharer in his evil deeds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.12'>I have a great deal to say to you all, but will not write it with paper and ink. Yet I hope to come to see you and speak face to face, so that your happiness may be complete.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.13'>The children of your elect sister send greetings to you.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>