<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='WMTH' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='WMTH'>
        <title>Weymouth NT</title>
        <contributor>*</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible new testament</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>The Translation of the New Testament offered to English-speaking Christians is a bona fide translation made directly from the Greek, and is in no sense a revision.</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>WMTH</identifier>
        <source>ftp://unboundftp.biola.edu/pub/weymouth_nt.zip</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>PD</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div osisID='2Tim' type='book'>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.1'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.1'>Paul, an Apostle of Christ Jesus, by the will of God, for proclaiming the promise of the Life which is in Christ Jesus:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.2'>To Timothy my dearly-loved child. May grace, mercy and peace be granted to you from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.3'>I thank God, whom I serve with a pure conscience –as my forefathers did– that night and day I unceasingly remember you in my prayers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.4'>being always mindful of your tears, and longing to see you that I may be filled with joy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.5'>For I recall the sincere faith which is in your heart–a faith which dwelt first in your grandmother Lois and then in your mother Eunice, and, I am fully convinced, now dwells in you also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.6'>For this reason let me remind you to rekindle God's gift which is yours through the laying on of my hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.7'>For the Spirit which God has given us is not a spirit of cowardice, but one of power and of love and of sound judgement.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.8'>Do not be ashamed then to bear witness for our Lord and for me His prisoner; but rather share suffering with me in the service of the Good News, strengthened by the power of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.9'>For He saved us and called us with a holy call, not in accordance with our desserts, but in accordance with His own purpose and the free grace which He bestowed on us in Christ Jesus before the commencement of the Ages,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.10'>but which has now been plainly revealed through the Appearing of our Saviour, Christ Jesus. He has put an end to death and has brought Life and Immortality to light through the Good News,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.11'>of which I have been appointed a preacher, Apostle and teacher, to the Gentiles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.12'>That indeed is the reason why I suffer as I do. But I am not ashamed, for I know in whom my trust reposes, and I am confident that He has it in His power to keep what I have entrusted to Him safe until that day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.13'>Provide yourself with an outline of the sound teaching which you have heard from my lips, and be true to the faith and love which are in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.14'>That precious treasure which is in your charge, guard through the Holy Spirit who has His home in our hearts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.15'>Of this you are aware, that all the Christians in Roman Asia have deserted me: and among them Phygelus and Hermogenes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.16'>May the Lord show mercy to the household of Onesiphorus; for many a time he cheered me and he was not ashamed of my chain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.17'>Nay, when he was here in Rome, he took great pains to inquire where I was living, and at last he found me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.18'>(The Lord grant that he may obtain mercy at His hands on that day!) And you yourself well know all the services which he rendered me in Ephesus.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.2'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.1'>You then, my child, must be strong in the grace that is in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.2'>All that you have been taught by me in the hearing of many witnesses, you must hand on to trusty men who shall themselves, in turn, be competent to instruct others also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.3'>As a good soldier of Christ Jesus accept your share of suffering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.4'>Every one who serves as a soldier keeps himself from becoming entangled in the world's business–so that he may satisfy the officer who enlisted him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.5'>And if any one takes part in an athletic contest, he gets no prize unless he obeys the rules.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.6'>The harvestman who labours in the field must be the first to get a share of the crop.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.7'>Mark well what I am saying: the Lord will give you discernment in everything.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.8'>Never forget that Jesus Christ has risen from among the dead and is a descendant of David, as is declared in the Good News which I preach.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.9'>For preaching the Good News I suffer, and am even put in chains, as if I were a criminal: yet the word of God is not imprisoned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.10'>For this reason I endure all things for the sake of God's own people; so that they also may obtain salvation –even the salvation which is in Christ Jesus– and with it eternal glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.11'>Faithful is the saying: »If we died with Him, we shall also live with Him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.12'>»If we patiently endure pain, we shall also share His Kingship;« If we disown Him, He will also disown us;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.13'>»And even if our faith fails, He remains true–He cannot prove false to Himself.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.14'>Bring all this to men's remembrances, solemnly charging them in the presence of God not to waste time in wrangling about mere words, a course which is altogether unprofitable and tends only to the ruin of the hearers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.15'>Earnestly seek to commend yourself to God as a servant who, because of his straightforward dealing with the word of truth, has no reason to feel any shame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.16'>But from irreligious and frivolous talk hold aloof, for those who indulge in it will proceed from bad to worse in impiety,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.17'>and their teaching will spread like a running sore. Hymenaeus and Philetus are men of that stamp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.18'>In the matter of the truth they have gone astray, saying that the Resurrection is already past, and so they are overthrowing the faith of some.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.19'>Yet God's solid foundation stands unmoved, bearing this inscription, »The Lord knows those who really belong to Him.« And this also, »Let every one who names the Name of the Lord renounce all wickedness.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.20'>Now in a great house there are not only articles of gold and silver, but also others of wood and of earthenware; and some are for specially honourable, and others for common use.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.21'>If therefore a man keeps himself clear of these latter, he himself will be for specially honourable use, consecrated, fit for the Master's service, and fully equipped for every good work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.22'>Keep a strong curb, however, on your youthful cravings; and strive for integrity, good faith, love, peace, in company with all who pray to the Lord with pure hearts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.23'>But avoid foolish discussions with ignorant men, knowing –as you do– that these lead to quarrels;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.24'>and a bondservant of the Lord must not quarrel, but must be inoffensive towards all men, a skilful teacher, and patient under wrongs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.25'>He must speak in a gentle tone when correcting the errors of opponents, in the hope that God will at last give them repentance, for them to come to a full knowledge of the truth</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.26'>and recover sober-mindedness and freedom from the Devil's snare, though they are now entrapped by him to do his will.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.3'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.1'>But of this be assured: in the last days grievous times will set in.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.2'>For men will be lovers of self, lovers of money, boastful, haughty, profane. They will be disobedient to parents, thankless, irreligious,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.3'>destitute of natural affection, unforgiving, slanderers. They will have no self-control, but will be brutal, opposed to goodness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.4'>treacherous, headstrong, self-important. They will love pleasure instead of loving God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.5'>and will keep up a make-believe of piety and yet live in defiance of its power. Turn away from people of this sort.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.6'>Among them are included the men who make their way into private houses and carry off weak women as their prisoners–women who, weighed down by the burden of their sins, are led by ever-changing caprice,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.7'>and are always learning something new, and yet are never able to arrive at real knowledge of the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.8'>And just as Jannes and Jambres withstood Moses, so also these false teachers withstand the truth–being, as they are, men of debased intellects, and of no real worth so far as faith is concerned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.9'>But they will have no further success; for their folly will be as clearly manifest to all men, as that of the opponents of Moses came to be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.10'>But you have intimately known my teaching, life, aims, faith, patience, love, resignation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.11'>and the persecutions and sufferings which I have endured; the things which happened to me in Antioch, Iconium and Lystra. You know the persecutions I endured, and how the Lord delivered me out of them all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.12'>And indeed every one who is determined to live a godly life as a follower of Christ Jesus will be persecuted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.13'>But bad men and impostors will go on from bad to worse, misleading and being misled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.14'>But you must cling to the things which you have learnt and have been taught to believe, knowing who your teachers were,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.15'>and that from infancy you have known the sacred writings which are able to make you wise to obtain salvation through faith in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.16'>Every Scripture is inspired by God and is useful for teaching, for convincing, for correction of error, and for instruction in right doing;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.17'>so that the man of God may himself be complete and may be perfectly equipped for every good work.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.4'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.1'>I solemnly implore you, in the presence of God and of Christ Jesus who is about to judge the living and the dead, and by His Appearing and His Kingship:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.2'>proclaim God's message, be zealous in season and out of season; convince, rebuke, encourage, with the utmost patience as a teacher.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.3'>For a time is coming when they will not tolerate wholesome instruction, but, wanting to have their ears tickled, they will find a multitude of teachers to satisfy their own fancies;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.4'>and will turn away from listening to the truth and will turn aside to fables.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.5'>But as for you, you must exercise habitual self-control, and not live a self-indulgent life, but do the duty of an evangelist and fully discharge the obligations of your office.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.6'>I for my part am like a drink-offering which is already being poured out; and the time for my departure is now close at hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.7'>I have gone through the glorious contest; I have run the race; I have guarded the faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.8'>From this time onward there is reserved for me the crown of righteousness which the Lord, the righteous Judge, will award to me on that day, and not only to me, but also to all who love the thought of His Appearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.9'>Make an effort to come to me speedily.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.10'>For Demas has deserted me –loving, as he does, the present age– and has gone to Thessalonica; Crescens has gone to Galatia, and Titus to Dalmatia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.11'>Luke is the only friend I now have with me. Call for Mark on your way and bring him with you, for he is a great help to me in my ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.12'>Tychicus I have sent to Ephesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.13'>When you come, bring with you the cloak which I left behind at Troas at the house of Carpus, and the books, but especially the parchments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.14'>Alexander the metal-worker showed bitter hostility towards me: the Lord will requite him according to his doings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.15'>You also should beware of him; for he has violently opposed our preaching.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.16'>At my first defence I had no one at my side, but all deserted me. May it not be laid to their charge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.17'>The Lord, however, stood by me and filled me with inward strength, that through me the Message might be fully proclaimed and that all the Gentiles might hear it; and I was rescued from the lion's jaws.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.18'>The Lord will deliver me from every cruel attack and will keep me safe in preparation for His heavenly Kingdom. To Him be the glory until the Ages of the Ages! Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.19'>Greet Prisca and Aquila, and the household of Onesiphorus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.20'>Erastus stayed in Corinth; Trophimus I left behind me at Miletus, ill.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.21'>Make an effort to come before winter. Eubulus greets you, and so do Pudens, Linus, Claudia, and all the brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.22'>The Lord be with your spirit. Grace be with you all.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>