<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='ACV' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='ACV'>
        <title>A Conservative Version</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description/>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>ACV</identifier>
        <source>http://www.e-sword.net/usermods/</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage/>
        <rights>www.stillvoices.org</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='1Cor'>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.1'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.1'>Paul, a called apostle of Jesus Christ through the will of God, and Sosthenes the brother,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.2'>to the congregation of God that is at Corinth, to called men, to holy men who have been sanctified in Christ Jesus with all in every place who call upon the name of our Lord Jesus Christ--both ours and theirs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.3'>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.4'>I thank my God always about you, for the grace of God that was given you in Christ Jesus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.5'>that in everything ye were enriched in him, in all speech and in all knowledge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.6'>Just as the testimony of Christ was confirmed in you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.7'>so that ye come behind in not one gift, waiting for the revealing of our Lord Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.8'>who will also confirm you until the end, irreproachable in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.9'>God is faithful through whom ye were called for the fellowship of his Son Jesus Christ our Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.10'>Now I beseech you, brothers, through the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that ye all speak the same thing, and there be no divisions among you, but ye may be thoroughly prepared in the same mind and in the same understanding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.11'>For it was declared to me about you, my brothers, by those of Chloe, that there are contentions among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.12'>Now I say this. That each of you actually say, I am of Paul, and I of Apollos, and I of Cephas, and I of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.13'>Has Christ been divided? Was Paul crucified for you, or were ye immersed in the name of Paul?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.14'>I thank God that I immersed none of you except Crispus and Gaius,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.15'>lest some man should say that I immersed in my name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.16'>And I also immersed the household of Stephanas. Besides, I know not whether I immersed any other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.17'>For Christ sent me not to immerse, but to preach the good-news, not in wisdom of speech lest the cross of Christ would be emptied.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.18'>For the message of the cross is of course, foolishness to those who are perishing, but to us who are being saved it is a power of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.19'>For it is written, I will destroy the wisdom of the wise, and I will frustrate the understanding of those of understanding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.20'>Where is a wise man? Where is a scholar? Where is a researcher of this age? Did not God make foolish the wisdom of this world?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.21'>For since in the wisdom of God the world did not know God through its wisdom, it pleased God through the foolishness of preaching to save those who believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.22'>And because Jews demand a sign and Greeks search for wisdom</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.23'>but we proclaim Christ crucified, truly to Jews a stumbling-block and to Gentiles foolishness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.24'>But to them, to the called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ is the power of God and the wisdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.25'>Because the foolishness of God is wiser than men, and the weak thing of God is stronger than men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.26'>For notice your calling, brothers, that not many are wise according to flesh, not many powerful, not many eminent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.27'>But God chose the foolish things of the world, so that he might humiliate the wise, and God chose the weak things of the world, so that he might humiliate the powerful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.28'>And God chose the common things of the world, and the disdained things, and the things that are not, so that he might make useless the things that are,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.29'>so that no flesh may boast before God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.30'>But ye are his, in Christ Jesus, who became for us wisdom from God, and righteousness and sanctification and redemption,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.31'>so that, just as it is written, He who boasts, let him boast in Lord.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.2'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.1'>And I, brothers, when I came to you, came not in eminence of speech or of wisdom proclaiming the testimony of God to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.2'>For I determined not to know anything among you except Jesus Christ, even this crucified man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.3'>And I was with you in weakness, and in fear, and in much trembling.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.4'>And my speech and my preaching were not in persuasive words of human wisdom, but in demonstration of spirit and of power,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.5'>so that your faith would not be in wisdom of men, but in the power of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.6'>But we speak wisdom among the fully developed, but not a wisdom of this age, nor of the rulers of this age who come to nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.7'>But we speak a wisdom of God in a hidden mystery, which God predestined before the ages for our glory,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.8'>which none of the rulers of this age know. For if they knew, they would not have crucified the Lord of glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.9'>But as it is written, What an eye has not seen, and an ear has not heard, and have not arisen in a heart of a man, are things that God prepared for those who love him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.10'>But God disclosed it to us through his Spirit, for the Spirit searches all things, even the deep things of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.11'>For what man knows the things of the man, except the spirit of the man in him? And so nobody knows the things of God except the Spirit of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.12'>But we did not receive the spirit of the world, but the spirit from God, so that we might know the things graciously given to us by God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.13'>Which things also we speak, not in things learned from mankind, in words of wisdom, but in things learned from Spirit, comparing spiritual things with spiritual things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.14'>Now the natural man does not accept the things of the Spirit of God, for they are foolishness to him, and he is unable to understand because they are evaluated spiritually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.15'>But truly the spiritual man evaluates all things, but he himself is evaluated by none.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.16'>For who has known the mind of Lord that he will stand with him? But we have the mind of Christ.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.3'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.1'>And I, brothers, could not speak to you as to spiritual, but as to carnal, as to the childlike in Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.2'>I gave you milk to drink and not solid food, for ye were not yet able. But not even yet are ye able,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.3'>for ye are still carnal. For whereas among you is envy and strife and divisions, are ye not carnal and walk according to man?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.4'>For while one may say, I am of Paul, and another, I am of Apollos, are ye not carnal?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.5'>Who therefore is Paul and who is Apollos? But rather helpers through whom ye believed, even as the Lord gave to each man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.6'>I planted, Apollos watered, but God caused growth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.7'>So then neither is he who plants anything, nor he who waters, but God who causes growth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.8'>Now he who plants and he who waters are one, but each man will receive his own payment according to his own labor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.9'>For we are co-workmen of God. Ye are a tillage of God, an edifice of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.10'>According to the grace of God that was given to me, as a wise master builder, I laid a foundation and another man is building on it. But let each man take heed how he is building on it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.11'>For no man can lay another foundation besides that which is laid, which is Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.12'>And if any man builds upon this foundation, gold, silver, precious stones, wood, hay, straw,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.13'>each man's work will become manifest. For the day will make it known, because it is revealed by fire. And the fire will test each man's work of what kind it is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.14'>If any man's work that he built on will remain, he will receive benefit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.15'>If any man's work will be burned, he will suffer loss, but he himself will be saved, but so as through fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.16'>Know ye not that ye are a temple of God and the Spirit of God dwells in you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.17'>If any man destroys the temple of God, God will destroy this man, for the temple of God is holy, which ye are.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.18'>Let not one man deceive himself. If any man among you seems to be wise in this age, let him become foolish so that he may become wise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.19'>For the wisdom of this world is foolishness before God. For it is written, He who catches the wise in their craftiness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.20'>and again, Lord knows the thoughts of the wise that they are vain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.21'>Therefore let not one man boast in men. For all things are yours,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.22'>whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or things present, or things coming, all are yours,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.23'>and ye are Christ's, and Christ is God's.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.4'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.1'>Thus let a man regard us as of helpers of Christ, and managers of mysteries of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.2'>And beyond that, it is sought in managers that any man should be found faithful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.3'>But it is a very small thing to me that I might be appraised by you or by a day of mankind. Yet neither do I appraise myself,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.4'>for I know nothing on myself. Yet I have not been made righteous in this, but he who appraises me is Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.5'>Therefore do not judge anything before time, until the Lord comes who will both bring to light the hidden things of darkness, and make public the deliberations of the hearts. And then praise will come to each man from God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.6'>Now these things, brothers, I applied to myself and Apollos for your sakes, so that in us ye might learn not to think above that which is written, so that ye may not be puffed up, one over the one against the other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.7'>For who makes thee different? And what have thou that thou did not receive? And also if thou received it, why do thou boast as not having received it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.8'>Already ye are filled. Already ye have become rich. Ye reigned without us, and O that ye did indeed reign, so that we also might reign with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.9'>For I think God has exhibited us the apostles least, as men sentenced to die, because we became a spectacle to the world, both to heavenly agents and to men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.10'>We are foolish for the sake of Christ, but ye are wise in Christ. We are weak, but ye are strong. Ye are esteemed, but we are disreputable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.11'>As far as the present hour we both hunger, and thirst, and are ill clothed, and are treated roughly, and are homeless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.12'>And we toil, working with our own hands. Being reviled, we bless; being persecuted, we endure;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.13'>being slandered, we entreat. We became as trash of the world, an offscouring of all things, until now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.14'>I do not write these things shaming you, but I warn you as my beloved children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.15'>For though ye have countless instructors in Christ, yet not many fathers. For in Christ Jesus I begot you through the good-news.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.16'>I beseech you therefore, become followers of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.17'>Because of this I sent Timothy to you, who is my beloved and faithful child in Lord, who will remind you of my ways in Christ, just as I teach everywhere in every congregation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.18'>But as of me not coming to you, some men are puffed up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.19'>But I will come to you shortly, if the Lord should will, and I will know, not the word of those who are puffed up, but the power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.20'>For the kingdom of God is not in word, but in power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.21'>What do ye want? Should I come to you with a rod, or in love and a spirit of gentleness?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.5'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.1'>Fornication is actually heard among you, and such fornication that is not even named among the Gentiles, for some man to have his father's wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.2'>And ye are puffed up and did not rather mourn, so that he who committed this deed might be taken away from the midst of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.3'>For I truly, as being absent in the body but present in the spirit, I have already, as though present, judged the man who committed this thing this way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.4'>In the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, when ye are gathered together, and my spirit with the power of our Lord Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.5'>to deliver such a man to Satan for destruction of the flesh, so that the spirit might be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.6'>Your boasting is not good. Know ye not that a little leaven leavens the whole lump?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.7'>Purge out the old leaven, so that ye may be a new lump, since ye are unleavened. For also Christ our Passover was sacrificed for us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.8'>Therefore we should feast, not by old leaven, nor by leaven of evil and wickedness, but by non-leaven of sincerity and truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.9'>I wrote to you in the letter not to associate with fornicators,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.10'>and not at all with the fornicators of this world, or with greedy men, or with predators, or with idolaters, since then ye would need to go out of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.11'>But now I write to you not to associate if any man who is called a brother is a fornicator, or a greedy man, or an idolater, or a slanderer, or a drunkard, or a predator, not even to eat with such kind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.12'>For what is in me to also judge those outside? Do ye not judge those inside?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.13'>But God judges those outside. And ye yourselves shall drive out the evil man from you.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.6'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.1'>Dare any of you, having a matter against the other, go to law before the unrighteous and not before the sanctified?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.2'>Or know ye not that the sanctified will judge the world? And if the world is judged by you, are ye unworthy of very small legal disputes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.3'>Know ye not that we will judge heavenly agents? Then why not mundane things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.4'>Indeed therefore whenever ye have mundane legal disputes, men who are disdained by the church, these ye seat to judge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.5'>I speak shame about you. So there is not among you not even one wise man who will be able to arbitrate between his brother?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.6'>But brother goes to law against brother, and this before unbelievers?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.7'>Now therefore it is indeed altogether a defeat for you because ye have legal disputes against yourselves. Why not rather be wronged? Why not rather be defrauded?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.8'>Instead ye do wrong, and defraud, and these things to brothers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.9'>Or know ye not that the unrighteous will not inherit the kingdom of God? Be not led astray. Neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate men, nor homosexuals,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.10'>nor greedy men, nor thieves, nor drunkards, nor the slanderous, nor the predatory will inherit the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.11'>And some of you were these things, but ye were washed, but ye were sanctified, but ye were made righteous in the name of the Lord Jesus, and in the Spirit of our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.12'>All things are lawful for me, but not all things are expedient. All things are lawful for me, but I will not be brought under control by anything.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.13'>The foods are for the belly and the belly for foods, but God will abolish both this and these things. But the body is not for fornication, but for the Lord, and the Lord for the body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.14'>And God both raised up the Lord and will raise us up through his power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.15'>Know ye not that your bodies are body-parts of Christ? Therefore, having taken the body-parts of the Christ, should I make them body-parts of a harlot? May it not happen!</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.16'>Or know ye not that he who is joined to a harlot is one body? For, The two, he says, will be in one flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.17'>But he who is joined to the Lord is one spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.18'>Flee fornication. Every sin, whatever a man may do, is outside the body, but he who fornicates sins against his own body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.19'>Or know ye not that your body is a temple of the Holy Spirit in you, which ye have from God? And ye are not your own,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.20'>for ye were bought with a price. Therefore glorify God in your body and your spirit, which is of God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.7'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.1'>Now concerning the things of which ye wrote to me. It is good for a man not to touch a woman.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.2'>But because of fornications, let each man have his own wife, and let each woman have her own husband.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.3'>Let the husband render the goodwill owed to the wife, and likewise also the wife to the husband.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.4'>The wife has not the right of her private body, but the husband, and likewise also the husband has not the right of his private body, but the wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.5'>Do not defraud each other except from agreement for a time, so that ye may have time for fasting and prayer. And come together again for the same thing, so that Satan not tempt you because of your lack of self-control.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.6'>But I say this from concession not from commandment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.7'>For I wish all men to be even as myself. However each man has his own gift from God, one in this way, and another after that.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.8'>But I say to the unmarried and to the widows, it is good for them if they remain even as I.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.9'>But if they have no self-control they should marry, for it is better to marry than to burn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.10'>And to those who are married, I do not command but the Lord. The wife is not to separate from her husband.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.11'>But even if she separates, she shall remain unmarried, or be reconciled to her husband. And a husband is not to leave his wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.12'>But to the rest I say, not the Lord. If any brother has an unbelieving wife, and this woman consents to dwell with him, he should not leave her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.13'>And whichever woman has an unbelieving husband, and he consents to dwell with her, she should not leave him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.14'>For the unbelieving husband has been sanctified by the wife, and the unbelieving wife has been sanctified by the husband, then otherwise your children are unclean, but now they are holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.15'>But if the unbeliever separates, he shall separate. The brother or the sister has not been bound in such things. And God has called us to peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.16'>For how do thou know, O wife, whether thou will save thy husband? Or how will thou know, O husband, whether thou will save thy wife?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.17'>Except, as God has distributed to each man, as the Lord has called each, so let him walk. And so I command in all the congregations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.18'>Was any man called circumcised? He should not become uncircumcised. Was any man called in uncircumcision? He should not be circumcised.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.19'>Circumcision is nothing and uncircumcision is nothing, instead, the keeping of God's commandments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.20'>Each man, in the situation in which he was called, in this he should remain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.21'>Were thou called being a bondman? It should not concern thee. However if also thou are able to become free, take advantage of it instead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.22'>For he who was called in Lord a bondman is a freedman of Lord. Likewise also he who was called a free man is a bondman of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.23'>Ye were bought with a price, become not bondmen of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.24'>Brothers, each man, in what he was called, should remain in this before God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.25'>Now concerning the virgins I have no commandment of Lord, but I give an opinion, as having obtained mercy from Lord to be trustworthy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.26'>I suppose therefore this to be good because of the present distress, that it is good for a man to be this way:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.27'>Are thou bound to a wife? Do not seek separation. Are thou free from a wife? Do not seek a wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.28'>But also if thou did marry thou have not sinned, and if the virgin married she has not sinned. Yet such kind will have stress in the flesh, but I spare you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.29'>But this I say, brothers, the time is shortened. It is the remaining, so that also those who have wives may be as not having,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.30'>and those who weep, as not weeping, and those who rejoice, as not rejoicing, and those who buy, as not possessing,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.31'>and those who use this world, as not making full use, for the form of this world passes away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.32'>But I want you to be without worry. The unmarried man cares for things of the Lord, how he will please the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.33'>But he who is married cares for things of the world, how he will please his wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.34'>And the wife and the virgin are differentiated. The unmarried woman is concerned for the things of the Lord, so that she may be holy both in body and in spirit. But she who is married is concerned for the things of the world, how s</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.35'>And I say this for your own benefit, not that I may cast restraint upon you, but for what is respectable and assiduous toward the Lord, undistracted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.36'>But if any man thinks to behave improperly toward his virgin, if it is past the best time, and so ought to happen, she should do what she wants, she does not sin, they should marry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.37'>But he who stands firm in his heart, not having necessity, but has power based upon his own will, and has decided this in his heart, to keep his own celibacy, does well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.38'>And therefore he who gives in marriage does well, but he who does not give in marriage does better.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.39'>A wife is bound by law as long a time as her husband lives, but also if the husband should sleep, she is free to be married to whom she desires, only in Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.40'>But she is more blessed if she remains this way according to my opinion. And I also seem to have Spirit of God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.8'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.1'>Now about the things sacrificed to idols. We know that all have knowledge. Knowledge puffs up, but love builds up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.2'>If any man presumes to know anything, he knows nothing yet as he ought to know.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.3'>But if any man loves God, this man is known by him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.4'>Therefore about eating the things sacrificed to idols, we know that an idol is nothing in the world, and that there is no other God except one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.5'>For also since there are things called gods, whether in heaven or on the earth, as there are many gods and many lords,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.6'>yet to us there is one God, the Father, from whom are all things, and we for him, and one Lord, Jesus Christ, through whom are all things, and we through him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.7'>Nevertheless the knowledge is not in all men, but some, with conscience of the idol until now, eat as sacrificed to idols, and their weak conscience is defiled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.8'>But food does not present us to God, for neither if we eat are we ahead, nor if we do not eat are we behind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.9'>But take heed lest somehow this privilege of yours becomes a stumbling-block to those who are weak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.10'>For if some man sees thee, who have knowledge, dining in an idol-temple, will not his conscience, being weak, be strengthened to eat things sacrificed to idols?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.11'>And by thy knowledge the brother, being weak, will be ruined, for whom Christ died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.12'>And sinning this way against the brothers, and wounding their weak conscience, ye sin against Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.13'>Therefore if food causes my brother to stumble, I will no, not eat meat into the age, so that I may not cause my brother to stumble.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.9'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.1'>Am I not an apostle? Am I not free? Have I not seen Jesus Christ our Lord? Are ye not my work in Lord?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.2'>If I am not an apostle to others, yet at least I am to you, for ye are the seal of my apostleship in Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.3'>My defense to those who examine me is this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.4'>Have we no, not a right to eat and to drink?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.5'>Have we no, not a right to lead about a sister wife, as also the other apostles, and the brothers of the Lord, and Cephas?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.6'>Or have only I and Barnabas no right not to be occupied earning a living?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.7'>Who ever enlists in an army at his own wage? Who plants a vineyard and does not eat from the fruit of it? Or who feeds a flock and does not eat from the milk of the flock?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.8'>Do I say these things according to man, or does not the law also say these things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.9'>For it is written in the law of Moses thou shall not muzzle an ox threshing grain. Is God concerned about oxen,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.10'>or does he speak altogether for our sake? For our sake, for it was written, He who plows ought to plow with hope, and he who threshes with his hope, with hope to share.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.11'>If we sowed spiritual things to you, is it a great thing if we will reap your carnal things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.12'>If others are partakers of the right from you, are not we more? Nevertheless we did not use this right, but we cover all things, so that we may not give any hindrance to the good-news of the Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.13'>Know ye not that those being employed at the sacred things eat from the temple, and those who serve at the altar are partakers at the altar?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.14'>And so the Lord commanded those who proclaim the good-news to live from the good-news.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.15'>But I have used none of these things, and I did not write these things so that it should be done to me this way. For it is good for me rather to die, than that any man should make my boasting empty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.16'>For if I preach the good-news, it is not a source of pride for me, for an obligation is laid upon me. And woe is to me if I do not preach the good-news.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.17'>For if I do this voluntarily, I have a reward, but if involuntarily, I have been entrusted with a commission.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.18'>What then is my reward? That, while preaching the good-news, I may make the good-news of the Christ without charge, in order not to make full use of my right in the good-news.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.19'>For although being free from all men, I made myself a servant to all, so that I might gain the more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.20'>And to the Jews I became as a Jew, so that I might gain Jews, to those under law, as under law, so that I might gain those under law,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.21'>to those without law, as without law (not being without law to God, but within law to Christ), so that I might gain men without law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.22'>To the weak I became as weak, so that I might gain the weak. I have become all things to all men, so that by all means I might save some.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.23'>And I do this for sake of the good-news, so that I might become a fellow participant of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.24'>Know ye not that those who run in an arena, indeed all run, but one receives the prize? So run that ye may seize it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.25'>And every man who strives for mastery exercises self-control in all things. Indeed therefore those men do it so that they might obtain a perishable crown, but we an imperishable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.26'>I therefore run this way, not as aimlessly. I fight this way, not as flaying air.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.27'>But I give my body a black eye and subdue it, lest somehow having preached to others, I myself might become disqualified.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.10'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.1'>But I want you not to be ignorant, brothers, that all our fathers were under the cloud, and all passed through the sea,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.2'>and all in Moses were immersed in the cloud and in the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.3'>And they all ate the same spiritual food,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.4'>and they all drank the same spiritual drink, for they drank from a spiritual rock that followed them. And the rock was the Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.5'>However with most of them God was not well pleased, for they were strewn in the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.6'>But these things became our examples, for us not to be men who lust for evil things as those also lusted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.7'>Neither become ye idolaters as some of them, as it is written, The people sat down to eat and drink, and rose up to revel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.8'>Nor should we fornicate as some of them fornicated, and three thousand fell in one day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.9'>Nor should we challenge the Christ as some of them also challenged, and were destroyed by the serpents.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.10'>And ye should not grumble as some of them grumbled, and were destroyed by the destroyer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.11'>Now all these things happened to those men for examples, and they were written for our admonition, to whom the ends of the ages came.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.12'>Therefore let him who seems to stand take heed lest he fall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.13'>No temptation has taken you except is common to man. But God is faithful who will not allow you to be tempted above what ye are able, but with the temptation will also make the way to escape, to enable you to endure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.14'>Therefore, my beloved, flee from idolatry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.15'>I speak as to wise men, judge ye what I say.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.16'>The cup of the blessing that we bless, is it not a participation of the blood of the Christ? The bread that we break, is it not a participation of the body of the Christ?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.17'>Because we, the many, are one bread, one body, for we are all partakers of the one bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.18'>Look at Israel according to flesh. Those who eat the sacrifices, are they not partakers of the altar?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.19'>What therefore do I say, that an idol is anything, or that a sacrifice to an idol is anything?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.20'>Rather, that which the Gentiles sacrifice, they sacrifice to demons and not to God, and I do not want you to become partakers of demons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.21'>Ye cannot drink the cup of Lord, and the cup of demons. Ye cannot be partakers of a table of Lord, and of a table of demons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.22'>Or do we provoke the Lord to jealousy? Are we stronger than he?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.23'>All things are permitted for me, but not all things are expedient. All things are permitted for me, but not all things are constructive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.24'>Let not one man seek that of himself, but each man that of the other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.25'>Eat everything being sold in a meat market, inquiring of nothing because of the conscience,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.26'>for the earth is the Lord's, and the fullness of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.27'>If any of those unbelievers invites you, and ye want to go, eat everything being set before you, inquiring of nothing because of the conscience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.28'>But if any man say to you, This is a sacrifice to an idol, do not eat for the sake of that man who informed, and the conscience, for the earth is the Lord's, and the fullness of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.29'>And I say conscience, not the one of himself, but the one of the other man. For why is my liberty judged by another conscience?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.30'>If I partake with thankfulness, why am I maligned about which I express thanks?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.31'>Therefore whether ye eat, or drink, or anything ye do, do all to the glory of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.32'>Become ye inoffensive both to Jews and to Greeks, and to the church of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.33'>just as I also strive to please in all things for all men, not seeking my own advantage, but that of the many, so that they may be saved.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.11'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.1'>Become ye followers of me, even as I also am of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.2'>Now I praise you, brothers, that ye remember me in all things and keep the traditions, just as I delivered them to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.3'>But I want you to know that the head of every man is the Christ, and the head of a woman is the man, and the head of Christ is God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.4'>Every man praying or prophesying having something upon his head dishonors his head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.5'>But every woman praying or prophesying with her head uncovered dishonors her head, for it is one and the same thing as the woman who has been shaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.6'>For if a woman is not covered, let her also shear herself. But if it is an ugly thing for a woman to shear herself or be shaven, she should be covered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.7'>For a man indeed ought not to cover his head, being an image and glory of God, but woman is a glory of man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.8'>For man is not from woman, but woman from man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.9'>For also man was not created for the woman, but woman for the man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.10'>Because of this the woman ought to have authority over her head, because of the heavenly agents.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.11'>Nevertheless, neither is man independent of woman, nor woman independent of man, in Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.12'>For just as the woman is from the man, so also the man is through the woman. But all things are from God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.13'>Judge ye among yourselves, is it proper for a woman to pray to God uncovered?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.14'>Or does not nature itself teach you that if a man actually wears long hair it is a disgrace to him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.15'>But if a woman wears long hair, it is a glory to her, because her hair has been given for a cloak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.16'>But if any man appears to be a lover of strife, we have no such custom, nor the congregations of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.17'>Now in this that is commanded, I do not praise you, because ye do not assemble for the better but for the worse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.18'>For indeed first, when ye come together in a congregation, I hear divisions are present among you, and I partly believe it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.19'>For there must also be factions among you, so that the genuine may become apparent among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.20'>When therefore ye come together in the same place, it is not to eat the Lord's supper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.21'>For each man proceeds to eat his own meal, and one is hungry and another is drunken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.22'>For have ye no houses to eat and to drink in? Or do ye disparage the church of God, and humiliate those not having? What shall I say to you? Shall I praise you in this? I do not praise you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.23'>For I received from the Lord what I also delivered to you, that the Lord Jesus in the night in which he was betrayed took bread,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.24'>and having expressed thanks, he broke in pieces, and said, Take ye, eat, this is my body broken for you. This do ye for my memorial.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.25'>Likewise also the cup after the supper, saying, This cup is the new covenant in my blood. This do, as often as ye drink it, for my memorial.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.26'>For as often as ye eat this bread and drink this cup, ye proclaim the Lord's death until he comes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.27'>Therefore whoever may eat this bread or drink the cup of the Lord unworthily of the Lord, will be guilty of the body and the blood of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.28'>But let a man examine himself, and let him so eat of the bread, and drink of the cup.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.29'>For he who eats and drinks unworthily, eats and drinks condemnation to himself, not discerning the body of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.30'>Because of this many are weak and sickly among you, and a considerable sleep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.31'>But if we were discerning ourselves we would not be judged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.32'>But when we are judged by Lord, we are chastened so that we may not be condemned with the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.33'>Therefore, my brothers, when ye come together to eat, await each other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.34'>And if any man is hungry, let him eat at home so that ye may not come together for condemnation. And the rest I will set in order as soon as I come.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.12'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.1'>Now concerning the spiritual things, brothers, I do not want you to be ignorant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.2'>Ye know that, while Gentiles, ye were being carried away to the voiceless idols, as ye were led.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.3'>Therefore I make known to you, that no man speaking by the Spirit of God says, Jesus is accursed, and no man can say, Jesus is Lord, except by Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.4'>Now there are varieties of gifts, but the same Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.5'>And there are varieties of services, and the same Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.6'>And there are varieties of functions, but it is the same God who works all in all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.7'>But the manifestation of the Spirit is given to each man toward that which is beneficial.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.8'>For to one, the word of wisdom is given through the Spirit, and to another, the word of knowledge according to the same Spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.9'>to a different man, faith by the same Spirit, and to another, gifts of healings by the same Spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.10'>and to another, workings of miracles, and to another, prophecy, and to another, discerning of spirits, and to a different man, kinds of tongues, and to another, the interpretation of tongues.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.11'>But the one and the same Spirit works all these things, distributing to each man individually as it wills.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.12'>For just as the body is one and has many parts, and all the parts of the body, being many, are one body, so also is the Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.13'>For also by one Spirit we are all immersed into one body, whether Jews or Greeks, whether bondmen or freemen, and we were all made to drink into one Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.14'>For the body also is not one part, but many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.15'>If the foot should say, Because I am not a hand I am not of the body, it is not by this not of the body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.16'>And if the ear should say, Because I am not an eye I am not of the body, it is not by this not of the body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.17'>If the whole body were an eye, where would be the hearing? If the whole were hearing, where would be the smelling?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.18'>But now God has placed the parts, each one of them, in the body just as he intended.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.19'>And if they were all one part, where would be the body?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.20'>But now of course there are many body-parts, but one body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.21'>And the eye cannot say to the hand, I have no need of thee, nor again the head to the feet, I have no need of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.22'>Instead, much more the parts of the body that seem to be more feeble are necessary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.23'>And those things of the body presumed to be without esteem, we place around these more abundant worth. And our unpresentable parts have more abundant propriety,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.24'>whereas our presentable parts have no need. Instead, God united the body together, having given more abundant worth to the part that lacks,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.25'>so that there would be no schisms in the body, but that the parts would have the same care for each other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.26'>And if one part suffers, all the parts suffer together, or one part is honored, all the parts rejoice together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.27'>Now ye are the body of Christ, and body-parts individually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.28'>And in the church God has placed men who are first apostles, secondly prophets, thirdly teachers, then miracles, then gifts of healings, helps, administrations, kinds of tongues.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.29'>Are all apostles? Are all prophets? Are all teachers? Do all do miracles?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.30'>Do all have gifts of healing? Do all speak with tongues? Do all interpret?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.31'>But be zealous for the better gifts. And yet I show you a more excellent way.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.13'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.1'>If I speak with the tongues of men and of heavenly agents, but have not love, I have become sounding brass, or a clashing cymbal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.2'>And if I have prophecy, and know all mysteries and all knowledge, and if I have all faith so as to remove mountains, and have not love, I am nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.3'>And if I dole out all things possessed by me, and if I deliver my body so that I may be burned, and have not love, I benefit nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.4'>Love is patient and is kind. Love does not envy. Love does not brag, and is not puffed up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.5'>It does not behave improperly, does not seek the things of itself, is not made sharp, does not contemplate evil,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.6'>does not rejoice in wrong but rejoices in the truth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.7'>covers all things, believes all things, hopes all things, endures all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.8'>Love never fails. But whether prophecies, they will be abolished, whether tongues, they will cease, whether knowledge, it will be abolished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.9'>But we know in part, and we prophesy in part,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.10'>but when the perfect comes, then what is in part will be abolished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.11'>When I was a child, I spoke as a child, I understood as a child, I reasoned as a child, but when I became a man, I abolished the childish things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.12'>For now we see by polished metal, in dimness, but then face to face. Now I know in part, but then I will know just as also I was known.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.13'>And now remain faith, hope, love, these three, but the greater of these is love.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.14'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.1'>Pursue love, and be zealous for the spiritual things, but more that ye may prophesy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.2'>For he who speaks in a tongue speaks not to men, but to God, for no man hears, but in spirit he speaks mysteries.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.3'>But he who prophesies speaks to men edification and encouragement and comfort.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.4'>He who speaks in a tongue builds himself up, but he who prophesies builds up the congregation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.5'>Now I want you all to speak in tongues, but more that ye may prophesy. For greater is he who prophesies than he who speaks in tongues, unless he interprets, so that the congregation may receive edification.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.6'>But now, brothers, if I come to you speaking in tongues, what will I benefit you, unless I would speak to you either in a revelation, or in knowledge, or in prophesying, or in doctrine?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.7'>Likewise lifeless things that give a sound, whether flute or harp, if they give no distinction in the sounds, how will it be known what is being piped or harped?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.8'>For also if a trumpet gives an uncertain sound, who will prepare himself for battle?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.9'>So also ye, unless ye give understandable speech by the tongue, how will that which is spoken be known? For ye will be talking into the air.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.10'>Since there are perhaps, so many kinds of voices in the world, and none of them is without significance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.11'>If therefore I know not the force of the voice, I will be a foreigner to him who speaks, and he who speaks will be a foreigner to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.12'>So also ye, since ye are zealots of spirits, seek so that ye may excel for the edification of the church.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.13'>Therefore let him who speaks in a tongue pray that he may interpret.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.14'>For if I pray in a tongue my spirit prays, but my intellect is unfruitful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.15'>What is it therefore? I will pray with the spirit, and I will pray with the intellect also. I will sing with the spirit, and I will sing with the intellect also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.16'>Otherwise if thou would bless with the spirit, how will the man who fills the place of the unlearned, say the Truly at thy thanksgiving, since he knows not what thou say?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.17'>For thou indeed express thanks well, but the other man is not edified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.18'>I thank my God that I speak in tongues more than all of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.19'>Yet in an assembly I would rather speak five words with my intellect, so that I might also make others understand, than countless words in a tongue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.20'>Brothers, become not children in your thoughts. Instead be childlike in wickedness, but in your thoughts become mature.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.21'>In the law it is written, In other tongues and in other lips I will speak to this people, and not even so will they hear me, says Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.22'>Therefore tongues are for a sign, not to those who believe, but to the unbelieving. But prophesying is not to the unbelieving, but to those who believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.23'>If therefore the whole congregation comes together in the same place, and all speak in tongues, and unlearned or unbelieving men come in, will they not say that ye are mad?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.24'>But if all prophesy, and some unbelieving or unlearned man comes in, he is convicted by all, he is called to account by all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.25'>And so the secrets of his heart are made manifest. And so having fallen down on his face he will worship God, declaring that God is really among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.26'>What is it therefore, brothers? When ye come together, each of you has a psalm, has a teaching, has a tongue, has a revelation, has an interpretation. Let all things be done for edification.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.27'>If any man speaks in a tongue, be according to two, or at the most three, and in succession. And let one interpret.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.28'>But if there is no interpreter, let him keep silence in an assembly, and let him speak to himself and to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.29'>And let two or three prophets speak, and let the other men pass judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.30'>But if it should be revealed to another man who is seated, let the first be silent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.31'>For ye can all prophesy one by one, so that all may learn, and all may be encouraged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.32'>And the spirits of prophets are subject to prophets,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.33'>for God is not a God of confusion, but of peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.34'>As in all the churches of the sanctified, let the women keep silent in the churches. For it is not permitted for them to speak, but to be subordinate, as the law also says.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.35'>And if they want to learn anything, let them question their own husbands at home, for it is an ugly thing for women to speak in an assembly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.36'>Or did the word of God come forth from you? Or did it come to you only?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.37'>If any man presumes to be a prophet or spiritual, let him acknowledge what I write to you, that they are commandments of Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.38'>But if any man is ignorant, let him be ignorant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.39'>Therefore brothers, be zealous for prophesying, and do not forbid to speak in tongues.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.40'>Let all things be done decently and in order.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.15'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.1'>And, brothers, I make known to you the good-news that I preached to you, which also ye received, and in which ye stand,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.2'>by which also ye are saved if ye hold firm that word I preached to you, unless ye believed in vain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.3'>For I delivered to you at first what I also received, that Christ died for our sins according to the scriptures,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.4'>and that he was buried, and that he arose on the third day according to the scriptures,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.5'>and that he appeared to Cephas, then to the twelve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.6'>Then he appeared to over five hundred brothers at once, of whom the greater part remain until now, but some also slept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.7'>Then he appeared to James, then to all the apostles,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.8'>and last of all, as to the untimely birth, he also appeared to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.9'>For I am the least of the apostles, who am not worthy to be called an apostle, because I persecuted the church of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.10'>But by the grace of God I am what I am. And his grace for me did not become empty, but I labored more abundantly than them all, yet not I, but the grace of God with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.11'>Therefore whether I or those men, so we proclaim, and so ye believed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.12'>Now if Christ is proclaimed that he has risen from the dead, how say some among you that there is no resurrection of the dead?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.13'>But if there is no resurrection of the dead, neither has Christ risen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.14'>And if Christ has not risen, then our preaching is empty, and your faith is also empty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.15'>And also we are found FALSE witnesses of God, because we witnessed according to God that he raised up the Christ, whom he did not raise up, if therefore the dead are really not raised.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.16'>For if the dead are not raised, neither has Christ been raised.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.17'>And if Christ has not been raised, your faith is vain. Ye are still in your sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.18'>Then also those who slept in Christ have perished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.19'>If we are men who have hoped in Christ in this life only, we are of all men more miserable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.20'>But now Christ has been raised from the dead. He became the first fruit of those who are asleep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.21'>For since death is because of a man, the resurrection of the dead is also because of a man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.22'>For as by Adam all die, so also by Christ all will be made alive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.23'>But each in his own order. Christ the first fruit, then those of Christ at his coming.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.24'>Afterwards the end, when he delivers up the kingdom to the God and Father, when he will abolishes all rule, and all authority and power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.25'>For he must reign until he will put all his enemies under his feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.26'>The last enemy abolished is death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.27'>For he subordinated all things under his feet. But when he says that all things have been subordinated, it is clear that he who subordinated all things under him, is excepted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.28'>And when all things are made subordinate to him, then the Son himself will also be made subordinate to him who subordinated all things to him, so that God may be all in all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.29'>Otherwise what will they do who are immersed for the dead? If the dead do not rise at all, why then are they immersed for the dead?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.30'>And we, why are we in peril every hour?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.31'>By the pride that belongs to you, that I keep in Christ Jesus our Lord, I die daily.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.32'>If in respect to men I fought with beasts at Ephesus, what is the benefit to me if the dead are not raised? Let us eat and drink, for tomorrow we die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.33'>Be not led astray. Evil associations corrupt good habits.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.34'>Sober up rightly, and do not sin, for some have ignorance of God. I speak shame about you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.35'>But some man will say, How are the dead raised, and with what kind of body do they come?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.36'>Thou foolish man, what thou sow is not made alive unless it dies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.37'>And what thou sow, thou do not sow the body that it will become, but a bare grain, if it may happen of wheat, or of some other kind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.38'>But God gives it a body as he wills, and to each of the seeds its own body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.39'>All flesh is not the same flesh, but one of men, and another flesh of beasts, and another of fishes, and another of birds,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.40'>and heavenly bodies, and earthly bodies (but the glory of the heavenly is different, and the glory of the earthly is different),</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.41'>another glory is of the sun, and another glory of the moon, and another glory of the stars, for star differs from star in glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.42'>So also is the resurrection of the dead. It is sown in the perishable, it is raised in imperishability.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.43'>It is sown in dishonor, it is raised in glory. It is sown in weakness, it is raised in power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.44'>It is sown a natural body, it is raised a spiritual body. There is a natural body, and there is a spiritual body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.45'>And so it is written, The first man Adam developed into a living soul. The last Adam a life giving spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.46'>Nevertheless the spiritual is not first, but the natural, then the spiritual.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.47'>The first man was of the earth, earthly. The second man is the Lord from heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.48'>As is the earthly, such also are the earthly. And as is the heavenly, such also are the heavenly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.49'>And just as we have worn the form of the earthly, we will also wear the form of the heavenly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.50'>Now this I affirm, brothers, that flesh and blood cannot inherit the kingdom of God, nor does the perishable inherit imperishability.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.51'>Behold, I tell you a mystery. We will actually not all sleep, but we will all be transformed,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.52'>in an instant, in the blink of an eye, at the last trumpet. For it will sound, and the dead will be raised imperishable, and we will be transformed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.53'>For this perishable must put on imperishability, and this mortal put on immortality.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.54'>But when this perishable will have put on imperishability, and this mortal will have put on immortality, then will come to pass the saying that is written, Death was swallowed up in victory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.55'>O death, where is thy sting? O Hades, where is thy victory?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.56'>The sting of death is sin, and the power of sin is the law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.57'>But thanks is to God who gives us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.58'>Therefore, my beloved brothers, become ye steadfast, unmovable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, knowing that your labor is not empty in Lord.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.16'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.1'>Now concerning the collection for the sanctified, as I arranged for the congregations of Galatia, so also do ye.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.2'>Upon the first day of the week let each of you set something aside near himself, storing up whatever he may prosper, so that when I come no collections may be made then.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.3'>And when I arrive, whomever ye may approve by letters, I will send these men to bring your gift to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.4'>And if it is fitting for me to go also, they will go with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.5'>But I will come to you when I pass through Macedonia, for I do pass through Macedonia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.6'>And it may be that I will remain with you, or I will even spend winter, so that ye may set me on my way wherever I go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.7'>For I do not want to see you now in passing, but I hope to remain some time with you, if the Lord allows.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.8'>But I will remain at Ephesus until Pentecost.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.9'>For a great and effective door has opened to me, and yet there are many who are hostile.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.10'>But if Timothy comes, see that he becomes without fear with you, for he works the work of Lord, as I also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.11'>Let not any man therefore disparage him, but send him forth in peace, so that he may come to me, for I expect him with the brothers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.12'>And about Apollos the brother, I urged him much that he would come to you with the brothers, and it was not at all his will that he should come now, but he will come when he has opportunity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.13'>Watch ye, stand firm in the faith, act like men, be strong.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.14'>Let all things of you be done in love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.15'>Now I beseech you, brothers (ye know the house of Stephanas, that it is the first fruit of Achaia, and that they committed themselves to service for the sanctified),</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.16'>that ye also be subject to such men, and to every man working together and laboring.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.17'>And I rejoice at the coming of Stephanas and Fortunatus and Achaicus, because these men filled your lack.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.18'>For they refreshed my spirit and yours. Therefore acknowledge ye such men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.19'>The congregations of Asia salute you. Aquila and Priscilla salute you much in Lord, with the congregation associated with their house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.20'>All the brothers salute you. Salute each other by a holy kiss.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.21'>The salutation of Paul by my hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.22'>If any man does not love the Lord Jesus Christ, let him be accursed. Maranatha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.23'>The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ is with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.24'>My love is with you all in Christ Jesus. Truly.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>