<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='ACV' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='ACV'>
        <title>A Conservative Version</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description/>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>ACV</identifier>
        <source>http://www.e-sword.net/usermods/</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage/>
        <rights>www.stillvoices.org</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='2Kgs'>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.1'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.1'>And Moab rebelled against Israel after the death of Ahab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.2'>And Ahaziah fell down through the lattice in his upper chamber that was in Samaria, and was sick. And he sent messengers, and said to them, Go, inquire of Baal-zebub, the god of Ekron, whether I shall recover of this sickness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.3'>But the agent of LORD said to Elijah the Tishbite, Arise, go up to meet the messengers of the king of Samaria, and say to them, Is it because there is no God in Israel that ye go to inquire of Baal-zebub, the god of Ekron?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.4'>Now therefore thus says LORD, Thou shall not come down from the bed where thou have gone up, but shall surely die. And Elijah departed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.5'>And the messengers returned to him, and he said to them, Why is it that ye are returned?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.6'>And they said to him, There came up a man to meet us, and said to us, Go, turn again to the king that sent you, and say to him, Thus says LORD, Is it because there is no God in Israel that thou send to inquire of Baal-zebub, the go</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.7'>And he said to them, What manner of man was he who came up to meet you, and told you these words?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.8'>And they answered him, He was a hairy man, and girt with a belt of leather about his loins. And he said, It is Elijah the Tishbite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.9'>Then [the king] sent to him a captain of fifty with his fifty. And he went up to him, and, behold, he was sitting on the top of the hill. And he spoke to him, O man of God, the king has said, Come down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.10'>And Elijah answered and said to the captain of fifty, If I be a man of God, let fire come down from heaven, and consume thee and thy fifty. And there came down fire from heaven, and consumed him and his fifty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.11'>And again he sent to him another captain of fifty and his fifty. And he answered and said to him, O man of God, thus has the king said, Come down quickly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.12'>And Elijah answered and said to them, If I be a man of God, let fire come down from heaven, and consume thee and thy fifty. And the fire of God came down from heaven, and consumed him and his fifty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.13'>And again he sent the captain of a third fifty with his fifty. And the third captain of fifty went up, and came and fell on his knees before Elijah, and besought him, and said to him, O man of God, I pray thee, let my life, and the</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.14'>Behold, there came fire down from heaven, and consumed the two former captains of fifty with their fifties, but now let my life be precious in thy sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.15'>And the agent of LORD said to Elijah, Go down with him; do not be afraid of him. And he arose, and went down with him to the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.16'>And he said to him, Thus says LORD, Inasmuch as thou have sent messengers to inquire of Baal-zebub, the god of Ekron, is it because there is no God in Israel to inquire of his word? Therefore thou shall not come down from the bed w</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.17'>So he died according to the word of LORD which Elijah had spoken. And Jehoram began to reign in his stead in the second year of Jehoram the son of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, because he had no son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.1.18'>Now the rest of the acts of Ahaziah which he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.2'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.1'>And it came to pass, when LORD would take up Elijah by a whirlwind into heaven, that Elijah went with Elisha from Gilgal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.2'>And Elijah said to Elisha, Remain here, I pray thee, for LORD has sent me as far as Bethel. And Elisha said, As LORD lives, and as thy soul lives, I will not leave thee. So they went down to Bethel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.3'>And the sons of the prophets who were at Bethel came forth to Elisha, and said to him, Do thou know that LORD will take away thy master from thy head today? And he said, Yes, I know it; hold ye your peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.4'>And Elijah said to him, Elisha, remain here, I pray thee, for LORD has sent me to Jericho. And he said, As LORD lives, and as thy soul lives, I will not leave thee. So they came to Jericho.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.5'>And the sons of the prophets who were at Jericho came near to Elisha, and said to him, Do thou know that LORD will take away thy master from thy head today? And he answered, Yes, I know it; hold ye your peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.6'>And Elijah said to him, Remain here, I pray thee, for LORD has sent me to the Jordan. And he said, As LORD lives, and as thy soul lives, I will not leave thee. And the two went on.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.7'>And fifty men of the sons of the prophets went, and stood opposite them afar off. And the two stood by the Jordan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.8'>And Elijah took his mantle, and wrapped it together, and struck the waters, and they were divided here and there, so that the two went over on dry ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.9'>And it came to pass, when they were gone over, that Elijah said to Elisha, Ask what I shall do for thee before I am taken from thee. And Elisha said, I pray thee, let a double portion of thy spirit be upon me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.10'>And he said, Thou have asked a hard thing. [Nevertheless], if thou see me when I am taken from thee, it shall be so to thee, but if not, it shall not be so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.11'>And it came to pass, as they still went on, and talked, that, behold, [there appeared] a chariot of fire, and horses of fire, which divided them both apart. And Elijah went up by a whirlwind into heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.12'>And Elisha saw it, and he cried, My father, my father, the chariots of Israel and the horsemen of it! And he saw him no more. And he took hold of his own clothes, and tore them in two pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.13'>He also took up the mantle of Elijah that fell from him, and went back, and stood by the bank of the Jordan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.14'>And he took the mantle of Elijah that fell from him, and struck the waters, and said, Where is LORD, the God of Elijah? And when he also had smitten the waters, they were divided here and there, and Elisha went over.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.15'>And when the sons of the prophets who were at Jericho opposite him saw him, they said, The spirit of Elijah rests on Elisha. And they came to meet him, and bowed themselves to the ground before him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.16'>And they said to him, Behold now, there are fifty strong men with thy servants. Let them go, we pray thee, and seek thy master, lest the Spirit of LORD has taken him up, and cast him upon some mountain, or into some valley. And he</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.17'>And when they urged him till he was ashamed, he said, Send. Therefore they sent fifty men. And they sought three days, but did not find him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.18'>And they came back to him while he remained at Jericho. And he said to them, Did I not say to you, Do not go?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.19'>And the men of the city said to Elisha, Behold, we pray thee, the situation of this city is pleasant, as my lord sees, but the water is bad, and the ground barren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.20'>And he said, Bring me a new cruse, and put salt therein. And they brought it to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.21'>And he went forth to the spring of the waters, and cast salt therein, and said, Thus says LORD, I have healed these waters. There shall not be from there any more death or barren land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.22'>So the waters were healed to this day, according to the word of Elisha which he spoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.23'>And he went up from there to Bethel. And as he was going up by the way, there came forth young lads out of the city, and mocked him, and said to him, Go up, thou baldhead; go up, thou baldhead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.24'>And he looked behind him and saw them, and cursed them in the name of LORD. And there came forth two she-bears out of the wood, and tore forty-two lads of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.2.25'>And he went from there to mount Carmel, and from there he returned to Samaria.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.3'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.1'>Now Jehoram the son of Ahab began to reign over Israel in Samaria in the eighteenth year of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, and reigned twelve years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.2'>And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD, but not like his father and like his mother, for he put away the pillar of Baal that his father had made.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.3'>Nevertheless he clung to the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, with which he made Israel to sin; he did not depart therefrom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.4'>Now Mesha king of Moab was a sheep-master. And he rendered to the king of Israel the wool of a hundred thousand lambs, and of a hundred thousand rams.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.5'>But it came to pass, when Ahab was dead, that the king of Moab rebelled against the king of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.6'>And king Jehoram went out of Samaria at that time, and mustered all Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.7'>And he went and sent to Jehoshaphat the king of Judah, saying, The king of Moab has rebelled against me. Will thou go with me against Moab to battle? And he said, I will go up. I am as thou are, my people as thy people, my horses a</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.8'>And he said, Which way shall we go up? And he answered, The way of the wilderness of Edom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.9'>So the king of Israel went, and the king of Judah, and the king of Edom. And they made a circuit of seven days' journey, and there was no water for the army, nor for the beasts that followed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.10'>And the king of Israel said, Alas! For LORD has called these three kings together to deliver them into the hand of Moab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.11'>But Jehoshaphat said, Is there not here a prophet of LORD, that we may inquire of LORD by him? And one of the king of Israel's servants answered and said, Elisha the son of Shaphat is here, who poured water on the hands of Elijah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.12'>And Jehoshaphat said, The word of LORD is with him. So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat and the king of Edom went down to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.13'>And Elisha said to the king of Israel, What have I to do with thee? Get thee to the prophets of thy father, and to the prophets of thy mother. And the king of Israel said to him, No, for LORD has called these three kings together t</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.14'>And Elisha said, As LORD of hosts lives, before whom I stand, surely, were it not that I regard the presence of Jehoshaphat the king of Judah, I would not look toward thee, nor see thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.15'>But now bring me a minstrel. And it came to pass, when the minstrel played, that the hand of LORD came upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.16'>And he said, Thus says LORD, Make this valley full of trenches.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.17'>For thus says LORD, Ye shall not see wind, neither shall ye see rain, yet that valley shall be filled with water, and ye shall drink, both ye and your cattle and your beasts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.18'>And this is but a light thing in the sight of LORD. He will also deliver the Moabites into your hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.19'>And ye shall smite every fortified city, and every choice city, and shall fell every good tree, and stop all fountains of water, and mar every good piece of land with stones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.20'>And it came to pass in the morning, about the time of offering the oblation, that, behold, there came water by the way of Edom, and the country was filled with water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.21'>Now when all the Moabites heard that the kings came up to fight against them, they gathered themselves together, all that were able to put on armor, and upward, and stood on the border.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.22'>And they rose up early in the morning, and the sun shone upon the water, and the Moabites saw the water opposite them as red as blood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.23'>And they said, This is blood. The kings are surely destroyed, and they have smitten each man his fellow. Now therefore, Moab, to the spoil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.24'>And when they came to the camp of Israel, the Israelites rose up and smote the Moabites, so that they fled before them, and they went forward into the land smiting the Moabites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.25'>And they beat down the cities. And on every good piece of land they cast every man his stone, and filled it. And they stopped all the fountains of water, and felled all the good trees, until in Kir-hareseth [only] they left the sto</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.26'>And when the king of Moab saw that the battle was too hard for him, he took with him seven hundred men that drew sword to break through to the king of Edom, but they could not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.3.27'>Then he took his eldest son who should have reigned in his stead, and offered him for a burnt-offering upon the wall. And there was great wrath against Israel, and they departed from him, and returned to their own land.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.4'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.1'>Now a certain woman of the wives of the sons of the prophets cried out to Elisha, saying, Thy servant my husband is dead, and thou know that thy servant feared LORD, and the creditor has come to take my two children to him to be bo</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.2'>And Elisha said to her, What shall I do for thee? Tell me, what have thou in the house? And she said, Thy handmaid has not anything in the house except a pot of oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.3'>Then he said, Go, borrow for thee vessels abroad from all thy neighbors, even empty vessels; borrow not a few.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.4'>And thou shall go in, and shut the door upon thee and upon thy sons, and pour out into all those vessels, and thou shall set aside that which is full.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.5'>So she went from him, and shut the door upon her and upon her sons. They brought [the vessels] to her, and she poured out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.6'>And it came to pass, when the vessels were full, that she said to her son, Bring me yet a vessel. And he said to her, There is no more a vessel. And the oil halted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.7'>Then she came and told the man of God. And he said, Go, sell the oil, and pay thy debt, and live thou and thy sons from the rest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.8'>And it fell on a day that Elisha passed to Shunem where there was a prominent woman. And she constrained him to eat bread. And so it was, that as often as he passed by he turned in there to eat bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.9'>And she said to her husband, Behold now, I perceive that this is a holy man of God who passes by us continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.10'>Let us make, I pray thee, a little chamber on the wall. And let us set a bed for him there, and a table, and a seat, and a candlestick. And it shall be, when he comes to us, that he shall turn in there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.11'>And it fell on a day that he came there, and he turned into the chamber and lay there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.12'>And he said to Gehazi his servant, Call this Shunammite. And when he had called her, she stood before him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.13'>And he said to him, Say now to her, Behold, thou have been caring for us with all this care. What is to be done for thee? Would thou be spoken for to the king, or to the captain of the army? And she answered, I dwell among my own p</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.14'>And he said, What then is to be done for her? And Gehazi answered, Truly she has no son, and her husband is old.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.15'>And he said, Call her. And when he had called her, she stood in the door.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.16'>And he said, At this season, when the time comes round, thou shall embrace a son. And she said, No, my lord, thou man of God, do not lie to thy handmaid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.17'>And the woman conceived, and bore a son at that season, when the time came round, as Elisha had said to her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.18'>And when the child was grown, it fell on a day that he went out to his father to the reapers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.19'>And he said to his father, My head, my head. And he said to his servant, Carry him to his mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.20'>And when he had taken him, and brought him to his mother, he sat on her knees till noon, and then died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.21'>And she went up and laid him on the bed of the man of God, and shut [the door] upon him, and went out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.22'>And she called to her husband, and said, Send me, I pray thee, one of the servants, and one of the donkeys, that I may run to the man of God, and come again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.23'>And he said, Why will thou go to him today? It is neither new moon nor Sabbath. And she said, It shall be well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.24'>Then she saddled a donkey, and said to her servant, Drive, and go forward. Do not restrain my riding unless I bid thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.25'>So she went, and came to the man of God to mount Carmel. And it came to pass, when the man of God saw her afar off, that he said to Gehazi his servant, Behold, yonder is the Shunammite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.26'>Run now, I pray thee, to meet her, and say to her, Is it well with thee? Is it well with thy husband? Is it well with the child? And she answered, It is well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.27'>And when she came to the man of God to the hill, she caught hold of his feet. And Gehazi came near to thrust her away, but the man of God said, Let her alone, for her soul is vexed within her, and LORD has hid it from me, and has n</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.28'>Then she said, Did I desire a son of my lord? Did I not say, do not deceive me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.29'>Then he said to Gehazi, Gird up thy loins, and take my staff in thy hand, and go thy way. If thou meet any man, do not salute him, and if any salute thee, do not answer him again. And lay my staff upon the face of the child.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.30'>And the mother of the child said, As LORD lives, and as thy soul lives, I will not leave thee. And he arose, and followed her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.31'>And Gehazi passed on before them, and laid the staff upon the face of the child, but there was neither voice, nor hearing. Therefore he returned to meet him, and told him, saying, The child has not awakened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.32'>And when Elisha came into the house, behold, the child was dead, and laid upon his bed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.33'>He went in therefore, and shut the door upon the two of them, and prayed to LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.34'>And he went up, and lay upon the child, and put his mouth upon his mouth, and his eyes upon his eyes, and his hands upon his hands. And he stretched himself upon him, and the flesh of the child grew warm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.35'>Then he returned, and walked in the house once to and fro, and went up, and stretched himself upon him. And the child sneezed seven times, and the child opened his eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.36'>And he called Gehazi, and said, Call this Shunammite. So he called her. And when she came in to him, he said, Take up thy son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.37'>Then she went in, and fell at his feet, and bowed herself to the ground. And she took up her son, and went out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.38'>And Elisha came again to Gilgal. And there was a dearth in the land, and the sons of the prophets were sitting before him. And he said to his servant, Set on the great pot, and boil pottage for the sons of the prophets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.39'>And one went out into the field to gather herbs, and found a wild vine, and gathered wild gourds from it, his lap full, and came and shred them into the pot of pottage, for they did not know them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.40'>So they poured out for the men to eat. And it came to pass, as they were eating of the pottage, that they cried out, and said, O man of God, there is death in the pot. And they could not eat of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.41'>But he said, Then bring meal. And he cast it into the pot, and he said, Pour out for the people, that they may eat. And there was no harm in the pot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.42'>And a man came from Baal-shalishah, and brought the man of God bread of the first-fruits, twenty loaves of barley, and fresh ears of grain in his sack. And he said, Give to the people that they may eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.43'>And his servant said, What, should I set this before a hundred men? But he said, Give to the people that they may eat, for thus says LORD, They shall eat, and shall leave of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.4.44'>So he set it before them, and they ate, and left of it according to the word of LORD.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.5'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.1'>Now Naaman, captain of the army of the king of Syria, was a great man with his master, and honorable, because by him LORD had given victory to Syria. He was also a mighty man of valor, [but he was] a leper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.2'>And the Syrians had gone out in bands, and had brought away captive out of the land of Israel a little maiden, and she waited on Naaman's wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.3'>And she said to her mistress, Would that my lord were with the prophet who is in Samaria! Then he would heal him of his leprosy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.4'>And a man went in, and told his lord, saying, Thus and thus said the maiden who is of the land of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.5'>And the king of Syria said, Go now, and I will send a letter to the king of Israel. And he departed, and took with him ten talents of silver, and six thousand [pieces] of gold, and ten changes of raiment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.6'>And he brought the letter to the king of Israel, saying, And now when this letter has come to thee, behold, I have sent Naaman my servant to thee that thou may heal him of his leprosy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.7'>And it came to pass, when the king of Israel had read the letter, that he tore his clothes, and said, Am I God, to kill and to make alive, that this man sends to me to heal a man of his leprosy? But consider, I pray you, and see ho</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.8'>And it was so, when Elisha the man of God heard that the king of Israel had torn his clothes, that he sent to the king, saying, Why have thou torn thy clothes? Let him come now to me, and he shall know that there is a prophet in Is</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.9'>So Naaman came with his horses and with his chariots, and stood at the door of the house of Elisha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.10'>And Elisha sent a messenger to him, saying, Go and wash in the Jordan seven times, and thy flesh shall come again to thee, and thou shall be clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.11'>But Naaman was angry, and went away, and said, Behold, I thought he will surely come out to me, and stand, and call on the name of LORD his God, and wave his hand over the place, and heal the leper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.12'>Are not Abanah and Pharpar, the rivers of Damascus, better than all the waters of Israel? May I not wash in them, and be clean? So he turned and went away in a rage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.13'>And his servants came near, and spoke to him, and said, My father, if the prophet had bid thee do some great thing, would thou not have done it? How much rather then, when he says to thee, Wash, and be clean?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.14'>Then went he down, and dipped [himself] seven times in the Jordan, according to the saying of the man of God. And his flesh came again like the flesh of a little child, and he was clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.15'>And he returned to the man of God, he and all his company, and came, and stood before him. And he said, Behold, now I know that there is no God in all the earth, but in Israel. Now therefore, I pray thee, take a present from thy se</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.16'>But he said, As LORD lives, before whom I stand, I will receive none. And he urged him to take it, but he refused.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.17'>And Naaman said, If not, yet, I pray thee, let there be given to thy servant two mules' burden of dirt, for thy servant will henceforth offer neither burnt-offering nor sacrifice to other gods, but to LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.18'>In this thing LORD pardon thy servant: when my master goes into the house of Rimmon to worship there, and he leans on my hand, and I bow myself in the house of Rimmon, when I bow myself in the house of Rimmon, LORD pardon thy serva</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.19'>And he said to him, Go in peace. So he departed from him a little way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.20'>But Gehazi the servant of Elisha the man of God, said, Behold, my master has spared this Naaman the Syrian, in not receiving at his hands that which he brought. As LORD lives, I will run after him, and take something from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.21'>So Gehazi followed after Naaman. And when Naaman saw him running after him, he alighted from the chariot to meet him, and said, Is all well?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.22'>And he said, All is well. My master has sent me, saying, Behold, even now there come to me from the hill-country of Ephraim two young men of the sons of the prophets. Give them, I pray thee, a talent of silver, and two changes of r</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.23'>And Naaman said, Be pleased to take two talents. And he urged him, and bound two talents of silver in two bags, with two changes of raiment, and laid them upon two of his servants, and they bore them before him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.24'>And when he came to the hill, he took them from their hand, and bestowed them in the house, and he let the men go, and they departed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.25'>But he went in, and stood before his master. And Elisha said to him, From where did thou come, Gehazi? And he said, Thy servant went nowhere.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.26'>And he said to him, Did not my heart go [with thee] when the man turned from his chariot to meet thee? Is it a time to receive money, and to receive garments, and oliveyards and vineyards, and sheep and oxen, and men-servants and m</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.5.27'>The leprosy therefore of Naaman shall cling to thee, and to thy seed forever. And he went out from his presence a leper [as white] as snow.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.6'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.1'>And the sons of the prophets said to Elisha, Behold now, the place where we dwell before thee is too confined for us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.2'>Let us go, we pray thee, to the Jordan, and every man take a beam from there, and let us make us a place there, where we may dwell. And he answered, Go ye.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.3'>And one said, Be pleased, I pray thee, to go with thy servants. And he answered, I will go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.4'>So he went with them. And when they came to the Jordan, they cut down wood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.5'>But as one was felling a beam, the axe-head fell into the water. And he cried, and said, Alas, my master! For it was borrowed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.6'>And the man of God said, Where did it fall? And he showed him the place. And he cut down a stick, and cast it in there, and made the iron to float.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.7'>And he said, Take it up to thee. So he put out his hand, and took it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.8'>Now the king of Syria was warring against Israel, and he took counsel with his servants, saying, In such and such a place shall be my camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.9'>And the man of God sent to the king of Israel, saying, Beware that thou not pass such a place, for the Syrians are coming down there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.10'>And the king of Israel sent to the place which the man of God told him and warned him of. And he saved himself there, not once nor twice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.11'>And the heart of the king of Syria was greatly troubled for this thing, and he called his servants, and said to them, Will ye not show me which of us is for the king of Israel?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.12'>And one of his servants said, No, my lord, O king, but Elisha, the prophet who is in Israel tells the king of Israel the words that thou speak in thy bedchamber.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.13'>And he said, Go and see where he is that I may send and fetch him. And it was told him, saying, Behold, he is in Dothan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.14'>Therefore he sent there horses, and chariots, and a great army. And they came by night, and encompassed the city about.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.15'>And when the servant of the man of God was risen early, and gone forth, behold, an army with horses and chariots was round about the city. And his servant said to him, Alas, my master! What shall we do?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.16'>And he answered, Fear not, for those who are with us are more than those who are with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.17'>And Elisha prayed, and said, LORD, I pray thee, open his eyes that he may see. And LORD opened the eyes of the young man, and he saw. And, behold, the mountain was full of horses and chariots of fire round about Elisha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.18'>And when they came down to him, Elisha prayed to LORD, and said, Smite this people, I pray thee, with blindness. And he smote them with blindness according to the word of Elisha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.19'>And Elisha said to them, This is not the way, neither is this the city. Follow me, and I will bring you to the man whom ye seek. And he led them to Samaria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.20'>And it came to pass, when they came into Samaria, that Elisha said, LORD, open the eyes of these men that they may see. And LORD opened their eyes, and they saw. And, behold, they were in the midst of Samaria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.21'>And the king of Israel said to Elisha, when he saw them, My father, shall I smite them? Shall I smite them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.22'>And he answered, Thou shall not smite them. Would thou smite those whom thou have taken captive with thy sword and with thy bow? Set bread and water before them that they may eat and drink, and go to their master.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.23'>And he prepared great provision for them. And when they had eaten and drunk, he sent them away, and they went to their master. And the bands of Syria came no more into the land of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.24'>And it came to pass after this, that Benhadad king of Syria gathered all his army, and went up, and besieged Samaria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.25'>And there was a great famine in Samaria. And, behold, they besieged it until a donkey's head was sold for eighty [pieces] of silver, and the fourth part of a kab of dove's dung for five [pieces] of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.26'>And as the king of Israel was passing by upon the wall, a woman cried out to him, saying, Help, my lord, O king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.27'>And he said, If LORD does not help thee, from where shall I help thee? Out of the threshing-floor, or out of the winepress?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.28'>And the king said to her, What troubles thee? And she answered, This woman said to me, Give thy son that we may eat him today, and we will eat my son tomorrow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.29'>So we boiled my son, and ate him. And I said to her on the next day, Give thy son that we may eat him. And she has hid her son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.30'>And it came to pass, when the king heard the words of the woman, that he tore his clothes (now he was passing by upon the wall). And the people looked, and, behold, he had sackcloth inside upon his flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.31'>Then he said, God do so to me, and more also, if the head of Elisha the son of Shaphat shall stand on him this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.32'>But Elisha was sitting in his house, and the elders were sitting with him. And [the king] sent a man from before him, but before the messenger came to him, he said to the elders, Do ye see how this son of a murderer has sent to tak</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.6.33'>And while he was yet talking with them, behold, the messenger came down to him, and he said, Behold, this evil is of LORD. Why should I wait for LORD any longer?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.7'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.1'>And Elisha said, Hear ye the word of LORD. Thus says LORD, Tomorrow about this time a measure of fine flour shall be [sold] for a shekel, and two measures of barley for a shekel, in the gate of Samaria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.2'>Then the captain on whose hand the king leaned answered the man of God, and said, Behold, if LORD should make windows in heaven, might this thing be? And he said, Behold, thou shall see it with thine eyes, but shall not eat of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.3'>Now there were four leprous men at the entrance of the gate, and they said one to another, Why do we sit here until we die?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.4'>If we say, We will enter into the city, then the famine is in the city, and we shall die there. And if we sit still here, we die also. Now therefore come, and let us fall to the army of the Syrians. If they save us alive, we shall</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.5'>And they rose up in the twilight, to go to the camp of the Syrians. And when they came to the outermost part of the camp of the Syrians, behold, there was no man there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.6'>For LORD had made the army of the Syrians to hear a noise of chariots, and a noise of horses, even the noise of a great army. And they said one to another, Lo, the king of Israel has hired against us the kings of the Hittites, and</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.7'>Therefore they arose and fled in the twilight, and left their tents, and their horses, and their donkeys, even the camp as it was, and fled for their life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.8'>And when these lepers came to the outermost part of the camp, they went into one tent, and ate and drank, and carried from there silver, and gold, and raiment, and went and hid it. And they came back, and entered into another tent,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.9'>Then they said one to another, We are not doing right. This day is a day of good news, and we keep silent. If we delay till the morning light, punishment will overtake us. Now therefore come, let us go and tell the king's household</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.10'>So they came and called to the porter of the city. And they told them, saying, We came to the camp of the Syrians, and, behold, there was no man there, neither voice of man, but the horses tied, and the donkeys tied, and the tents</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.11'>And he called the porters, and they told it to the king's household within.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.12'>And the king arose in the night, and said to his servants, I will now show you what the Syrians have done to us. They know that we are hungry. Therefore they have gone out of the camp to hide themselves in the field, saying, When t</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.13'>And one of his servants answered and said, Let, I pray thee, some men take five of the horses that remain, which are left in the city (behold, they are as all the multitude of Israel that are left in it; behold, they are as all the</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.14'>Therefore they took two chariots with horses. And the king sent after the army of the Syrians, saying, Go and see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.15'>And they went after them to the Jordan. And, lo, all the way was full of garments and vessels, which the Syrians had cast away in their haste. And the messengers returned, and told the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.16'>And the people went out, and plundered the camp of the Syrians. So a measure of fine flour was [sold] for a shekel, and two measures of barley for a shekel, according to the word of LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.17'>And the king appointed the captain on whose hand he leaned to have the charge of the gate. And the people trampled upon him in the gate, and he died as the man of God had said, who spoke when the king came down to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.18'>And it came to pass, as the man of God had spoken to the king, saying, Two measures of barley for a shekel, and a measure of fine flour for a shekel, shall be tomorrow about this time in the gate of Samaria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.19'>And that captain answered the man of God, and said, Now, behold, if LORD should make windows in heaven, might such a thing be? And he said, Behold, thou shall see it with thine eyes, but shall not eat of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.7.20'>It came to pass even so to him, for the people trampled upon him in the gate, and he died.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.8'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.1'>Now Elisha had spoken to the woman, whose son he had restored to life, saying, Arise, and go thou and thy household, and sojourn wherever thou can sojourn, for LORD has called for a famine, and it shall also come upon the land seve</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.2'>And the woman arose, and did according to the word of the man of God. And she went with her household, and sojourned in the land of the Philistines seven years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.3'>And it came to pass at the end of seven years, that the woman returned out of the land of the Philistines, and she went forth to cry to the king for her house and for her land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.4'>Now the king was talking with Gehazi the servant of the man of God, saying, Tell me, I pray thee, all the great things that Elisha has done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.5'>And it came to pass, as he was telling the king how he had restored to life him who was dead, that, behold, the woman, whose son he had restored to life, cried to the king for her house and for her land. And Gehazi said, My lord, O</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.6'>And when the king asked the woman, she told him. So the king appointed to her a certain officer, saying, Restore all that was hers, and all the fruits of the field since the day that she left the land, even until now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.7'>And Elisha came to Damascus, and Benhadad the king of Syria was sick. And it was told him, saying, The man of God has come here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.8'>And the king said to Hazael, Take a present in thy hand, and go, meet the man of God, and inquire of LORD by him, saying, Shall I recover of this sickness?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.9'>So Hazael went to meet him, and took a present with him, even of every good thing of Damascus, forty camels' burden, and came and stood before him, and said, Thy son Benhadad king of Syria has sent me to thee, saying, Shall I recov</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.10'>And Elisha said to him, Go, say to him, Thou shall surely recover. However LORD has shown me that he shall surely die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.11'>And he settled his countenance steadfastly [upon him], until he was ashamed. And the man of God wept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.12'>And Hazael said, Why do thou weep my lord? And he answered, Because I know the evil that thou will do to the sons of Israel: their strongholds thou will set on fire, and their young men thou will kill with the sword, and will dash</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.13'>And Hazael said, But what is thy servant, who is but a dog, that he should do this great thing? And Elisha answered, LORD has shown me that thou shall be king over Syria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.14'>Then he departed from Elisha, and came to his master, who said to him, What did Elisha say to thee? And he answered, He told me that thou would surely recover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.15'>And it came to pass on the morrow, that he took the coverlet, and dipped it in water, and spread it on his face, so that he died. And Hazael reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.16'>And in the fifth year of Joram the son of Ahab king of Israel, Jehoshaphat being then king of Judah, Jehoram the son of Jehoshaphat king of Judah began to reign.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.17'>He was thirty-two years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eight years in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.18'>And he walked in the way of the kings of Israel, as did the house of Ahab, for he had the daughter of Ahab to wife. And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.19'>However LORD would not destroy Judah, for David his servant's sake, as he promised him to give to him a lamp for his sons always.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.20'>In his days Edom revolted from under the hand of Judah, and made a king over themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.21'>Then Joram passed over to Zair, and all his chariots with him. And he rose up by night, and smote the Edomites that encompassed him about, and the captains of the chariots. And the people fled to their tents.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.22'>So Edom revolted from under the hand of Judah to this day. Then Libnah revolted at the same time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.23'>And the rest of the acts of Joram, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.24'>And Joram slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David, and Ahaziah his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.25'>In the twelfth year of Joram the son of Ahab king of Israel, Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah began to reign.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.26'>Ahaziah was twenty-two years old when he began to reign, and he reigned one year in Jerusalem. And his mother's name was Athaliah the daughter of Omri king of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.27'>And he walked in the way of the house of Ahab, and did that which was evil in the sight of LORD, as did the house of Ahab, for he was the son-in-law of the house of Ahab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.28'>And he went with Joram the son of Ahab to war against Hazael king of Syria at Ramoth-gilead, and the Syrians wounded Joram.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.8.29'>And king Joram returned to be healed in Jezreel of the wounds which the Syrians had given him at Ramah when he fought against Hazael king of Syria. And Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah went down to see Joram the son of Ahab</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.9'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.1'>And Elisha the prophet called one of the sons of the prophets, and said to him, Gird up thy loins, and take this vial of oil in thy hand, and go to Ramoth-gilead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.2'>And when thou come there, look out there for Jehu the son of Jehoshaphat the son of Nimshi, and go in, and make him arise up from among his brothers, and carry him to an inner chamber.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.3'>Then take the vial of oil, and pour it on his head, and say, Thus says LORD, I have anointed thee king over Israel. Then open the door, and flee, and delay not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.4'>So the young man, even the young man the prophet, went to Ramoth-gilead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.5'>And when he came, behold, the captains of the army were sitting. And he said, I have an errand to thee, O captain. And Jehu said, To which of us all? And he said, To thee, O captain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.6'>And he arose, and went into the house. And he poured the oil on his head, and said to him, Thus says LORD, the God of Israel, I have anointed thee king over the people of LORD, even over Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.7'>And thou shall smite the house of Ahab thy master, that I may avenge the blood of my servants the prophets, and the blood of all the servants of LORD, at the hand of Jezebel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.8'>For the whole house of Ahab shall perish. And I will cut off from Ahab every man-child, and him who is shut up and him who is left at large in Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.9'>And I will make the house of Ahab like the house of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, and like the house of Baasha the son of Ahijah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.10'>And the dogs shall eat Jezebel in the portion of Jezreel, and there shall be none to bury her. And he opened the door, and fled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.11'>Then Jehu came forth to the servants of his lord, and one said to him, Is all well? Why did this mad fellow come to thee? And he said to them, Ye know the man and what his talk was.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.12'>And they said, It is not true; tell us now. And he said, Thus and thus he spoke to me, saying, Thus says LORD, I have anointed thee king over Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.13'>Then they hastened, and every man took his garment, and put it under him on the top of the stairs, and blew the trumpet, saying, Jehu is king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.14'>So Jehu the son of Jehoshaphat the son of Nimshi conspired against Joram. (Now Joram was keeping Ramoth-gilead, he and all Israel, because of Hazael king of Syria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.15'>But king Joram was returned to be healed in Jezreel of the wounds which the Syrians had given him when he fought with Hazael king of Syria.) And Jehu said, If this be your mind, then let none escape and go forth out of the city to</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.16'>So Jehu rode in a chariot, and went to Jezreel, for Joram lay there. And Ahaziah king of Judah came down to see Joram.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.17'>Now the watchman was standing on the tower in Jezreel, and he spied the company of Jehu as he came, and said, I see a company. And Joram said, Take a horseman, and send to meet them, and let him say, Is it peace?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.18'>So one went on horseback to meet him, and said, Thus says the king, Is it peace? And Jehu said, What have thou to do with peace? Turn thee behind me. And the watchman told, saying, The messenger came to them, but he does not come b</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.19'>Then he sent out a second on horseback who came to them, and said, Thus says the king, Is it peace? And Jehu answered, What have thou to do with peace? Turn thee behind me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.20'>And the watchman told, saying, He came to them, and does not come back. And the driving is like the driving of Jehu the son of Nimshi, for he drives furiously.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.21'>And Joram said, Make ready. And they made his chariot ready. And Joram king of Israel and Ahaziah king of Judah went out, each in his chariot, and they went out to meet Jehu, and found him in the portion of Naboth the Jezreelite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.22'>And it came to pass, when Joram saw Jehu, that he said, Is it peace, Jehu? And he answered, What peace, so long as the whoredoms of thy mother Jezebel and her witchcrafts are so many?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.23'>And Joram turned his hands, and fled, and said to Ahaziah, There is treachery, O Ahaziah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.24'>And Jehu drew his bow with his full strength, and smote Joram between his arms. And the arrow went out at his heart, and he sunk down in his chariot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.25'>Then [Jehu] said to Bidkar his captain, Take up, and cast him in the portion of the field of Naboth the Jezreelite. For remember how that, when I and thou rode together after Ahab his father, LORD laid this burden upon him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.26'>Surely I have seen yesterday the blood of Naboth, and the blood of his sons, says LORD, and I will requite thee in this plot, says LORD. Now therefore take and cast him into the plot [of ground], according to the word of LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.27'>But when Ahaziah the king of Judah saw this, he fled by the way of the garden-house. And Jehu followed after him, and said, Smite him also in the chariot. [And they smote him] at the ascent of Gur, which is by Ibleam. And he fled t</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.28'>And his servants carried him in a chariot to Jerusalem, and buried him in his sepulcher with his fathers in the city of David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.29'>(And [it was] in the eleventh year of Joram the son of Ahab Ahaziah began to reign over Judah.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.30'>And when Jehu came to Jezreel, Jezebel heard of it. And she painted her eyes, and attired her head, and looked out at the window.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.31'>And as Jehu entered in at the gate, she said, Is it peace, thou Zimri, thy master's murderer?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.32'>And he lifted up his face to the window, and said, Who is on my side? Who? And two or three eunuchs looked out to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.33'>And he said, Throw her down. So they threw her down. And some of her blood was sprinkled on the wall, and on the horses. And he trampled her under foot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.34'>And when he came in, he ate and drank, and he said, Now see to this cursed woman, and bury her, for she is a king's daughter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.35'>And they went to bury her, but they found no more of her than the skull, and the feet, and the palms of her hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.36'>Therefore they came back, and told him. And he said, This is the word of LORD, which he spoke by his servant Elijah the Tishbite, saying, In the portion of Jezreel shall the dogs eat the flesh of Jezebel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.9.37'>and the body of Jezebel shall be as dung upon the face of the field in the portion of Jezreel, so that they shall not say, This is Jezebel.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.10'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.1'>Now Ahab had seventy sons in Samaria. And Jehu wrote letters, and sent to Samaria, to the rulers of Jezreel, even the elders, and to those who brought up [the sons of] Ahab, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.2'>And now as soon as this letter comes to you, seeing your master's sons are with you, and there are with you chariots and horses, also a fortified city, and armor,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.3'>look ye out for the best and fittest of your master's sons, and set him on his father's throne, and fight for your master's house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.4'>But they were exceedingly afraid, and said, Behold, the two kings did not stand before him. How then shall we stand?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.5'>And he who was over the household, and he who was over the city, the elders also, and those who brought up [the sons], sent to Jehu, saying, We are thy servants, and will do all that thou shall bid us. We will not make any man king</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.6'>Then he wrote a letter the second time to them, saying, If ye be on my side, and if ye will hearken to my voice, take ye the heads of the men your master's sons, and come to me to Jezreel by tomorrow this time. Now the king's sons,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.7'>And it came to pass, when the letter came to them, that they took the king's sons, and killed them, even seventy persons, and put their heads in baskets, and sent them to him to Jezreel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.8'>And a messenger came, and told him, saying, They have brought the heads of the king's sons. And he said, Lay ye them in two heaps at the entrance of the gate until the morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.9'>And it came to pass in the morning, that he went out, and stood, and said to all the people, Ye are righteous. Behold, I conspired against my master, and killed him. But who smote all these?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.10'>Know now that there shall fall to the earth nothing of the word of LORD, which LORD spoke concerning the house of Ahab, for LORD has done that which he spoke by his servant Elijah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.11'>So Jehu smote all who remained of the house of Ahab in Jezreel, and all his great men, and his familiar friends, and his priests, until he left to him none remaining.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.12'>And he arose and departed, and went to Samaria. And as he was at the shearing-house of the shepherds in the way,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.13'>Jehu met with the brothers of Ahaziah king of Judah, and said, Who are ye? And they answered, We are the brothers of Ahaziah, and we go down to salute the sons of the king and the sons of the queen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.14'>And he said, Take them alive. And they took them alive, and killed them at the pit of the shearing-house, even forty-two men; neither did he leave any of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.15'>And when he was departed from there, he came upon on Jehonadab the son of Rechab coming to meet him. And he saluted him, and said to him, Is thy heart right, as my heart is with thy heart? And Jehonadab answered, It is. If it be, g</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.16'>And he said, Come with me, and see my zeal for LORD. So they made him ride in his chariot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.17'>And when he came to Samaria, he smote all who remained to Ahab in Samaria, till he had destroyed him, according to the word of LORD, which he spoke to Elijah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.18'>And Jehu gathered all the people together, and said to them, Ahab served Baal a little, but Jehu will serve him much.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.19'>Now therefore call to me all the prophets of Baal, all his worshippers, and all his priests. Let none be lacking, for I have a great sacrifice [to do] to Baal. Whoever shall be lacking, he shall not live. But Jehu did it in subtlet</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.20'>And Jehu said, Sanctify a solemn assembly for Baal. And they proclaimed it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.21'>And Jehu sent through all Israel. And all the worshippers of Baal came, so that there was not a man left who did not come. And they came into the house of Baal, and the house of Baal was filled from one end to another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.22'>And he said to him who was over the vestry, Bring forth vestments for all the worshippers of Baal. And he brought forth for them vestments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.23'>And Jehu went, and Jehonadab the son of Rechab, into the house of Baal. And he said to the worshippers of Baal, Search, and look that there be here with you none of the servants of LORD, but the worshippers of Baal only.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.24'>And they went in to offer sacrifices and burnt-offerings. Now Jehu had appointed for him eighty men outside, and said, If any of the men whom I bring into your hands escape, [he who lets him go], his life shall be for the life of h</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.25'>And it came to pass, as soon as he had made an end of offering the burnt-offering, that Jehu said to the guard and to the captains, Go in, and kill them; let none come forth. And they smote them with the edge of the sword. And the</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.26'>And they brought forth the pillars that were in the house of Baal, and burned them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.27'>And they broke down the pillar of Baal, and broke down the house of Baal, and made it an out-house to this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.28'>Thus Jehu destroyed Baal out of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.29'>However from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, with which he made Israel to sin, Jehu did not depart from after them, [namely], the golden calves that were in Bethel, and that were in Dan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.30'>And LORD said to Jehu, Because thou have done well in executing that which is right in my eyes, [and] have done to the house of Ahab according to all that was in my heart, thy sons of the fourth generation shall sit on the throne o</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.31'>But Jehu did not take heed to walk in the law of LORD, the God of Israel, with all his heart. He did not depart from the sins of Jeroboam, with which he made Israel to sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.32'>In those days LORD began to cut off from Israel. And Hazael smote them in all the borders of Israel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.33'>from the Jordan eastward, all the land of Gilead, the Gadites, and the Reubenites, and the Manassites, from Aroer, which is by the valley of the Arnon, even Gilead and Bashan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.34'>Now the rest of the acts of Jehu, and all that he did, and all his might, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.35'>And Jehu slept with his fathers, and they buried him in Samaria. And Jehoahaz his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.10.36'>And the time that Jehu reigned over Israel in Samaria was twenty-eight years.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.11'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.1'>Now when Athaliah the mother of Ahaziah saw that her son was dead, she arose and destroyed all the royal seed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.2'>But Jehosheba, the daughter of king Joram, sister of Ahaziah, took Joash the son of Ahaziah, and stole him away from among the king's sons who were slain, even him and his nurse, [and put them] in the bedchamber. And they hid him f</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.3'>And he was with her hidden in the house of LORD six years. And Athaliah reigned over the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.4'>And in the seventh year Jehoiada sent and fetched the captains over hundreds of the Carites and of the guard, and brought them to him into the house of LORD. And he made a covenant with them, and took an oath of them in the house o</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.5'>And he commanded them, saying, This is the thing that ye shall do: a third part of you, who come in on the Sabbath, shall be keepers of the watch of the king's house;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.6'>and a third part shall be at the gate Sur; and a third part at the gate behind the guard. So shall ye keep the watch of the house, and be a barrier.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.7'>And the two companies of you, even all who go forth on the Sabbath, shall keep the watch of the house of LORD around the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.8'>And ye shall encompass the king round about, every man with his weapons in his hand. And he who comes within the ranks, let him be slain. And be ye with the king when he goes out, and when he comes in.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.9'>And the captains over hundreds did according to all that Jehoiada the priest commanded. And every man took his men, those who were to come in on the Sabbath, with those who were to go out on the Sabbath, and came to Jehoiada the pr</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.10'>And the priest delivered to the captains over hundreds the spears and shields that had been king David's, which were in the house of LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.11'>And the guard stood, every man with his weapons in his hand, from the right side of the house to the left side of the house, along by the altar and the house, by the king round about.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.12'>Then he brought out the king's son, and put the crown upon him, and [gave him] the testimony. And they made him king, and anointed him. And they clapped their hands, and said, Live, O king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.13'>And when Athaliah heard the noise of the guard [and of] the people, she came to the people into the house of LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.14'>And she looked, and, behold, the king stood by the pillar, as the manner was, and the captains and the trumpets by the king. And all the people of the land rejoiced, and blew trumpets. Then Athaliah tore her clothes, and cried, Tre</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.15'>And Jehoiada the priest commanded the captains of hundreds who were set over the army, and said to them, Have her forth between the ranks, and kill with the sword the man who follows her. For the priest said, Let her not be slain i</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.16'>So they made way for her. And she went by the way of the horses' entry to the king's house, and there was she slain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.17'>And Jehoiada made a covenant between LORD and the king and the people, that they should be LORD's people; between the king also and the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.18'>And all the people of the land went to the house of Baal, and broke it down. They broke in pieces his altars and his images thoroughly, and killed Mattan the priest of Baal before the altars. And the priest appointed officers over</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.19'>And he took the captains over hundreds, and the Carites, and the guard, and all the people of the land, and they brought down the king from the house of LORD, and came by the way of the gate of the guard to the king's house. And he</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.20'>So all the people of the land rejoiced, and the city was quiet. And they had slain Athaliah with the sword at the king's house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.11.21'>Joash was seven years old when he began to reign.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.12'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.1'>Joash began to reign in the seventh year of Jehu. And he reigned forty years in Jerusalem, and his mother's name was Zibiah of Beersheba.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.2'>And Joash did that which was right in the eyes of LORD all his days in which Jehoiada the priest instructed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.3'>However the high places were not taken away; the people still sacrificed and burnt incense in the high places.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.4'>And Joash said to the priests, All the money of the hallowed things that is brought into the house of LORD, in current money, the money of the persons for whom each man is rated, and all the money that it come in any man's heart to</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.5'>let the priests take it to them, every man from his acquaintance, and they shall repair the broken parts of the house wherever any breach shall be found.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.6'>But it was so, that in the twenty-third year of king Joash the priests had not repaired the broken parts of the house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.7'>Then king Joash called for Jehoiada the priest, and for the [other] priests, and said to them, Why do ye not repair the broken parts of the house? Now therefore take no [more] money from your acquaintance, but deliver it for the br</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.8'>And the priests consented that they should take no [more] money from the people, neither repair the broken parts of the house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.9'>But Jehoiada the priest took a chest, and bored a hole in the lid of it, and set it beside the altar, on the right side as a man comes into the house of LORD. And the priests who kept the threshold put in it all the money that was</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.10'>And it was so, when they saw that there was much money in the chest, that the king's scribe and the high priest came up, and they put up in bags and counted the money that was found in the house of LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.11'>And they gave the money that was weighed out into the hands of those who did the work, who had the oversight of the house of LORD. And they paid it out to the carpenters and the builders who worked upon the house of LORD,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.12'>and to the masons and the hewers of stone, and for buying timber and hewn stone to repair the broken parts of the house of LORD, and for all that was laid out for the house to repair it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.13'>But there were not made for the house of LORD cups of silver, snuffers, basins, trumpets, any vessels of gold, or vessels of silver, of the money that was brought into the house of LORD,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.14'>for they gave that to those who did the work, and with it repaired the house of LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.15'>Moreover they did not reckon with the men into whose hand they delivered the money to give to those who did the work, for they dealt faithfully.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.16'>The money for the trespass-offerings, and the money for the sin-offerings, was not brought into the house of LORD; it was the priests'.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.17'>Then Hazael king of Syria went up, and fought against Gath, and took it. And Hazael set his face to go up to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.18'>And Joash king of Judah took all the hallowed things that Jehoshaphat and Jehoram and Ahaziah, his fathers, kings of Judah, had dedicated, and his own hallowed things, and all the gold that was found in the treasures of the house o</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.19'>Now the rest of the acts of Joash, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.20'>And his servants arose, and made a conspiracy, and smote Joash at the house of Millo, [on the way] that goes down to Silla.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.12.21'>For Jozacar the son of Shimeath, and Jehozabad the son of Shomer, his servants, smote him, and he died. And they buried him with his fathers in the city of David. And Amaziah his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.13'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.1'>In the twenty-third year of Joash the son of Ahaziah, king of Judah, Jehoahaz the son of Jehu began to reign over Israel in Samaria, [and reigned] seventeen years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.2'>And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD, and followed the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, with which he made Israel to sin. He did not depart from it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.3'>And the anger of LORD was kindled against Israel, and he delivered them into the hand of Hazael king of Syria, and into the hand of Benhadad the son of Hazael, continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.4'>And Jehoahaz besought LORD, and LORD hearkened to him, for he saw the oppression of Israel, how that the king of Syria oppressed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.5'>(And LORD gave Israel a savior, so that they went out from under the hand of the Syrians, and the sons of Israel dwelt in their tents as beforetime.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.6'>Nevertheless they did not depart from the sins of the house of Jeroboam, with which he made Israel to sin, but walked therein. And the Asherah also remained in Samaria.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.7'>For he did not leave to Jehoahaz of the people except fifty horsemen, and ten chariots, and ten thousand footmen, for the king of Syria destroyed them, and made them like the dust in threshing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.8'>Now the rest of the acts of Jehoahaz, and all that he did, and his might, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.9'>And Jehoahaz slept with his fathers, and they buried him in Samaria. And Joash his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.10'>In the thirty-seventh year of Joash king of Judah, Jehoash the son of Jehoahaz began to reign over Israel in Samaria, [and reigned] sixteen years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.11'>And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD. He did not depart from all the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, with which he made Israel to sin, but he walked therein.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.12'>Now the rest of the acts of Joash, and all that he did, and his might with which he fought against Amaziah king of Judah, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.13'>And Joash slept with his fathers, and Jeroboam sat upon his throne. And Joash was buried in Samaria with the kings of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.14'>Now Elisha was fallen sick of his sickness of which he died. And Joash the king of Israel came down to him, and wept over him, and said, My father, my father, the chariots of Israel and the horsemen of it!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.15'>And Elisha said to him, Take bow and arrows. And he took to him bow and arrows.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.16'>And he said to the king of Israel, Put thy hand upon the bow. And he put his hand [upon it]. And Elisha laid his hands upon the king's hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.17'>And he said, Open the window eastward. And he opened it. Then Elisha said, Shoot. And he shot. And he said, LORD's arrow of victory, even the arrow of victory over Syria, for thou shall smite the Syrians in Aphek till thou have con</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.18'>And he said, Take the arrows. And he took them. And he said to the king of Israel, Smite upon the ground. And he smote thrice, and stopped.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.19'>And the man of God was angry with him, and said, Thou should have smitten five or six times. Then thou would have smitten Syria till thou had consumed it, whereas now thou shall smite Syria but thrice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.20'>And Elisha died, and they buried him. Now the bands of the Moabites invaded the land at the coming in of the year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.21'>And it came to pass, as they were burying a man, that, behold, they spied a band, and they cast the man into the sepulcher of Elisha. And as soon as the man touched the bones of Elisha, he revived, and stood up on his feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.22'>And Hazael king of Syria oppressed Israel all the days of Jehoahaz.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.23'>But LORD was gracious to them, and had compassion on them, and had respect to them, because of his covenant with Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, and would not destroy them, neither did he cast them from his presence as yet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.24'>And Hazael king of Syria died, and Benhadad his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.13.25'>And Jehoash the son of Jehoahaz again took out of the hand of Benhadad the son of Hazael the cities, which he had taken out of the hand of Jehoahaz his father by war. Three times Joash smote him, and recovered the cities of Israel.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.14'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.1'>In the second year of Joash son of Joahaz king of Israel, Amaziah the son of Joash king of Judah began to reign.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.2'>He was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. And his mother's name was Jehoaddin of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.3'>And he did that which was right in the eyes of LORD, yet not like David his father. He did according to all that Joash his father had done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.4'>However the high places were not taken away; the people still sacrificed and burnt incense in the high places.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.5'>And it came to pass, as soon as the kingdom was established in his hand, that he killed his servants who had slain the king his father,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.6'>but he did not put to death the sons of the murderers, according to that which is written in the book of the law of Moses, as LORD commanded, saying, The fathers shall not be put to death for the sons, nor the sons be put to death</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.7'>He killed ten thousand of Edom in the Valley of Salt, and took Sela by war, and called the name of it Joktheel, to this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.8'>Then Amaziah sent messengers to Jehoash, the son of Jehoahaz son of Jehu, king of Israel, saying, Come, let us look each other in the face.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.9'>And Jehoash the king of Israel sent to Amaziah king of Judah, saying, The thistle that was in Lebanon sent to the cedar that was in Lebanon, saying, Give thy daughter to my son to wife. And a wild beast that was in Lebanon passed b</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.10'>Thou have indeed smitten Edom, and thy heart has lifted thee up. Glory by it, and abide at home, for why should thou meddle to [thy] hurt, that thou should fall, even thou, and Judah with thee?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.11'>But Amaziah would not hear. So Jehoash king of Israel went up. And he and Amaziah king of Judah looked each other in the face at Beth-shemesh, which belongs to Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.12'>And Judah was put to the worse before Israel, and they fled every man to his tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.13'>And Jehoash king of Israel took Amaziah king of Judah, the son of Jehoash the son of Ahaziah, at Beth-shemesh, and came to Jerusalem, and broke down the wall of Jerusalem from the gate of Ephraim to the corner gate, four hundred cu</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.14'>And he took all the gold and silver, and all the vessels that were found in the house of LORD, and in the treasures of the king's house, the hostages also, and returned to Samaria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.15'>Now the rest of the acts of Jehoash which he did, and his might, and how he fought with Amaziah king of Judah, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.16'>And Jehoash slept with his fathers, and was buried in Samaria with the kings of Israel. And Jeroboam his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.17'>And Amaziah the son of Joash king of Judah lived fifteen years after the death of Jehoash son of Jehoahaz king of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.18'>Now the rest of the acts of Amaziah, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.19'>And they made a conspiracy against him in Jerusalem. And he fled to Lachish. But they sent after him to Lachish, and killed him there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.20'>And they brought him upon horses, and he was buried at Jerusalem with his fathers in the city of David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.21'>And all the people of Judah took Azariah, who was sixteen years old, and made him king in the place of his father Amaziah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.22'>He built Elath, and restored it to Judah, after the king slept with his fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.23'>In the fifteenth year of Amaziah the son of Joash king of Judah, Jeroboam the son of Joash king of Israel began to reign in Samaria, [and reigned] forty-one years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.24'>And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD. He did not depart from all the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, with which he made Israel to sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.25'>He restored the border of Israel from the entrance of Hamath to the sea of the Arabah, according to the word of LORD, the God of Israel, which he spoke by his servant Jonah the son of Amittai, the prophet, who was of Gath-hepher.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.26'>For LORD saw the affliction of Israel, that it was very bitter, for there was none shut up nor left at large, neither was there any helper for Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.27'>And LORD did not say that he would blot out the name of Israel from under heaven, but he saved them by the hand of Jeroboam the son of Joash.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.28'>Now the rest of the acts of Jeroboam, and all that he did, and his might, how he warred, and how he recovered Damascus, and Hamath, [which had belonged] to Judah, for Israel, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of th</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.14.29'>And Jeroboam slept with his fathers, even with the kings of Israel, and Zechariah his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.15'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.1'>In the twenty-seventh year of Jeroboam king of Israel, Azariah son of Amaziah king of Judah began to reign.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.2'>He was sixteen years old when he began to reign, and he reigned fifty-two years in Jerusalem. And his mother's name was Jecoliah of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.3'>And he did that which was right in the eyes of LORD, according to all that his father Amaziah had done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.4'>However the high places were not taken away; the people still sacrificed and burnt incense in the high places.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.5'>And LORD smote the king, so that he was a leper to the day of his death, and dwelt in a separate house. And Jotham the king's son was over the household, judging the people of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.6'>Now the rest of the acts of Azariah, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.7'>And Azariah slept with his fathers, and they buried him with his fathers in the city of David. And Jotham his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.8'>In the thirty-eighth year of Azariah king of Judah, Zechariah the son of Jeroboam reigned over Israel in Samaria six months.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.9'>And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD, as his fathers had done. He did not depart from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, with which he made Israel to sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.10'>And Shallum the son of Jabesh conspired against him, and smote him before the people, and killed him, and reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.11'>Now the rest of the acts of Zechariah, behold, they are written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.12'>This was the word of LORD which he spoke to Jehu, saying, Thy sons to the fourth generation shall sit upon the throne of Israel. And so it came to pass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.13'>Shallum the son of Jabesh began to reign in the thirty-ninth year of Uzziah king of Judah, and he reigned the space of a month in Samaria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.14'>And Menahem the son of Gadi went up from Tirzah, and came to Samaria, and smote Shallum the son of Jabesh in Samaria, and killed him, and reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.15'>Now the rest of the acts of Shallum, and his conspiracy which he made, behold, they are written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.16'>Then Menahem smote Tiphsah, and all that were therein, and the borders of it, from Tirzah, because they did not open to him, therefore he smote it. And all the women in it who were with child he ripped up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.17'>In the thirty-ninth year of Azariah king of Judah, Menahem the son of Gadi began to reign over Israel, [and reigned] ten years in Samaria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.18'>And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD. He did not depart all his days from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, with which he made Israel to sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.19'>The king of Assyria came against the land Pul. And Menahem gave Pul a thousand talents of silver that his hand might be with him to confirm the kingdom in his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.20'>And Menahem exacted the money from Israel, even of all the mighty men of wealth, of each man fifty shekels of silver, to give to the king of Assyria. So the king of Assyria turned back, and did not stay there in the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.21'>Now the rest of the acts of Menahem, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.22'>And Menahem slept with his fathers, and Pekahiah his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.23'>In the fiftieth year of Azariah king of Judah, Pekahiah the son of Menahem began to reign over Israel in Samaria, [and reigned] two years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.24'>And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD. He did not depart from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, with which he made Israel to sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.25'>And Pekah the son of Remaliah, his captain, conspired against him, and smote him in Samaria, in the castle of the king's house, with Argob and Arieh. And fifty men of the Gileadites with him were there. And he killed him, and reign</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.26'>Now the rest of the acts of Pekahiah, and all that he did, behold, they are written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.27'>In the fifty-second year of Azariah king of Judah, Pekah the son of Remaliah began to reign over Israel in Samaria, [and reigned] twenty years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.28'>And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD. He did not depart from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, with which he made Israel to sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.29'>In the days of Pekah king of Israel, Tiglath-pileser king of Assyria came, and took Ijon, and Abel-beth-maacah, and Janoah, and Kedesh, and Hazor, and Gilead, and Galilee, all the land of Naphtali. And he carried them captive to As</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.30'>And Hoshea the son of Elah made a conspiracy against Pekah the son of Remaliah, and smote him, and killed him, and reigned in his stead in the twentieth year of Jotham the son of Uzziah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.31'>Now the rest of the acts of Pekah, and all that he did, behold, they are written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.32'>In the second year of Pekah the son of Remaliah king of Israel, Jotham the son of Uzziah king of Judah began to reign.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.33'>He was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. And his mother's name was Jerusha the daughter of Zadok.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.34'>And he did that which was right in the eyes of LORD. He did according to all that his father Uzziah had done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.35'>However the high places were not taken away. The people still sacrificed and burned incense in the high places. He built the upper gate of the house of LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.36'>Now the rest of the acts of Jotham, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.37'>In those days LORD began to send against Judah Rezin the king of Syria, and Pekah the son of Remaliah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.15.38'>And Jotham slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David his father. And Ahaz his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.16'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.1'>In the seventeenth year of Pekah the son of Remaliah, Ahaz the son of Jotham king of Judah began to reign.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.2'>Ahaz was twenty years old when he began to reign, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. And he did not do that which was right in the eyes of LORD his God, like David his father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.3'>But he walked in the way of the kings of Israel. Yes, and made his son to pass through the fire, according to the abominations of the nations whom LORD cast out from before the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.4'>And he sacrificed and burnt incense in the high places, and on the hills, and under every green tree.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.5'>Then Rezin king of Syria and Pekah son of Remaliah king of Israel came up to Jerusalem to war, and they besieged Ahaz, but could not overcome him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.6'>At that time Rezin king of Syria recovered Elath to Syria, and drove the Jews from Elath. And the Syrians came to Elath, and dwelt there to this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.7'>So Ahaz sent messengers to Tiglath-pileser king of Assyria, saying, I am thy servant and thy son. Come up, and save me out of the hand of the king of Syria, and out of the hand of the king of Israel, who rise up against me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.8'>And Ahaz took the silver and gold that was found in the house of LORD, and in the treasures of the king's house, and sent it for a present to the king of Assyria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.9'>And the king of Assyria hearkened to him. And the king of Assyria went up against Damascus, and took it, and carried [the people of] it captive to Kir, and killed Rezin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.10'>And king Ahaz went to Damascus to meet Tiglath-pileser king of Assyria, and saw the altar that was at Damascus. And king Ahaz sent to Urijah the priest the form of the altar, and the pattern of it, according to all the workmanship</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.11'>And Urijah the priest built an altar. According to all that king Ahaz had sent from Damascus, so Urijah the priest made it until the coming of king Ahaz from Damascus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.12'>And when the king came from Damascus, the king saw the altar. And the king drew near to the altar, and offered thereon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.13'>And he burnt his burnt-offering and his meal-offering, and poured his drink-offering, and sprinkled the blood of his peace-offerings, upon the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.14'>And the brazen altar, which was before LORD, he brought from the forefront of the house, from between his altar and the house of LORD, and put it on the north side of his altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.15'>And king Ahaz commanded Urijah the priest, saying, Upon the great altar burn the morning burnt-offering, and the evening meal-offering, and the king's burnt-offering, and his meal-offering, with the burnt-offering of all the people</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.16'>Thus did Urijah the priest, according to all that king Ahaz commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.17'>And king Ahaz cut off the panels of the bases, and removed the laver from off them, and took down the sea from off the brazen oxen that were under it, and put it upon a pavement of stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.18'>And the covered place for the Sabbath that they had built in the house, and the king's entry outside, he turned from the house of LORD, because of the king of Assyria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.19'>Now the rest of the acts of Ahaz which he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.16.20'>And Ahaz slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David. And Hezekiah his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.17'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.1'>In the twelfth year of Ahaz king of Judah, Hoshea the son of Elah began to reign in Samaria over Israel, [and reigned] nine years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.2'>And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD, yet not as the kings of Israel who were before him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.3'>Shalmaneser king of Assyria came up against him. And Hoshea became his servant, and brought him tribute.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.4'>And the king of Assyria found conspiracy in Hoshea, for he had sent messengers to So king of Egypt, and offered no tribute to the king of Assyria, as he had done year by year. Therefore the king of Assyria shut him up, and bound hi</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.5'>Then the king of Assyria came up throughout all the land, and went up to Samaria, and besieged it three years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.6'>In the ninth year of Hoshea, the king of Assyria took Samaria, and carried Israel away to Assyria, and placed them in Halah, and on the Habor, the river of Gozan, and in the cities of the Medes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.7'>And it was so, because the sons of Israel had sinned against LORD their God who brought them up out of the land of Egypt from under the hand of Pharaoh king of Egypt, and had feared other gods,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.8'>and walked in the statutes of the nations, whom LORD cast out from before the sons of Israel, and of the kings of Israel, which they made.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.9'>And the sons of Israel did things secretly that were not right against LORD their God. And they built for them high places in all their cities, from the tower of the watchmen to the fortified city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.10'>And they set up for them pillars and Asherim upon every high hill, and under every green tree,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.11'>and there they burnt incense in all the high places, as the nations did whom LORD carried away before them. And they wrought wicked things to provoke LORD to anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.12'>And they served idols, of which LORD had said to them, Ye shall not do this thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.13'>Yet LORD testified to Israel, and to Judah, by every prophet, and every seer, saying, Turn ye from your evil ways, and keep my commandments and my statutes, according to all the law which I commanded your fathers, and which I sent</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.14'>Notwithstanding, they would not hear, but stiffened their neck, like the neck of their fathers who did not believed in LORD their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.15'>And they rejected his statutes, and his covenant that he made with their fathers, and his testimonies which he testified to them. And they followed vanity, and became vain, and [went] after the nations that were round about them, c</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.16'>And they forsook all the commandments of LORD their God, and made for them molten images, even two calves, and made an Asherah, and worshipped all the host of heaven, and served Baal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.17'>And they caused their sons and their daughters to pass through the fire, and used divination and enchantments, and sold themselves to do that which was evil in the sight of LORD to provoke him to anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.18'>Therefore LORD was very angry with Israel, and removed them out of his sight. There was none left but only the tribe of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.19'>Also Judah did not keep the commandments of LORD their God, but walked in the statutes of Israel which they made.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.20'>And LORD rejected all the seed of Israel, and afflicted them, and delivered them into the hand of spoilers, until he had cast them out of his sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.21'>For he tore Israel from the house of David. And they made Jeroboam the son of Nebat king. And Jeroboam drove Israel from following LORD, and made them sin a great sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.22'>And the sons of Israel walked in all the sins of Jeroboam which he did. They did not depart from them</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.23'>until LORD removed Israel out of his sight, as he spoke by all his servants the prophets. So Israel was carried away out of their own land to Assyria to this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.24'>And the king of Assyria brought men from Babylon, and from Cuthah, and from Avva, and from Hamath and Sepharvaim, and placed them in the cities of Samaria instead of the sons of Israel. And they possessed Samaria, and dwelt in the</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.25'>And so it was, at the beginning of their dwelling there, that they did not fear LORD. Therefore LORD sent lions among them, which killed some of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.26'>Therefore they spoke to the king of Assyria, saying, The nations which thou have carried away, and placed in the cities of Samaria know not the law of the god of the land. Therefore he has sent lions among them, and, behold, they k</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.27'>Then the king of Assyria commanded, saying, Carry there one of the priests whom ye brought from there, and let them go and dwell there. And let him teach them the law of the god of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.28'>So one of the priests whom they had carried away from Samaria came and dwelt in Bethel, and taught them how they should fear LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.29'>However every nation made gods of their own, and put them in the houses of the high places which the Samaritans had made, every nation in their cities wherein they dwelt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.30'>And the men of Babylon made Succoth-benoth, and the men of Cuth made Nergal, and the men of Hamath made Ashima,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.31'>and the Avvites made Nibhaz and Tartak. And the Sepharvites burnt their sons in the fire to Adrammelech and Anammelech, the gods of Sepharvaim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.32'>So they feared LORD, and made for them priests of the high places from among themselves, who sacrificed for them in the houses of the high places.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.33'>They feared LORD, and served their own gods, after the manner of the nations from among whom they had been carried away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.34'>To this day they do after the former manner. They do not fear LORD, neither do they after their statutes, or after their ordinances, or after the law or after the commandment which LORD commanded the sons of Jacob, whom he named Is</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.35'>with whom LORD had made a covenant, and charged them, saying, Ye shall not fear other gods, nor bow yourselves to them, nor serve them, nor sacrifice to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.36'>But LORD, who brought you up out of the land of Egypt with great power and with an outstretched arm, him ye shall fear, and to him ye shall bow yourselves, and to him ye shall sacrifice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.37'>And the statutes and the ordinances, and the law and the commandment, which he wrote for you, ye shall observe to do for evermore. And ye shall not fear other gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.38'>And the covenant that I have made with you ye shall not forget. Neither shall ye fear other gods,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.39'>but ye shall ye fear LORD your God, and he will deliver you out of the hand of all your enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.40'>However they did not hearken, but they did after their former manner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.17.41'>So these nations feared LORD, and served their graven images, their sons likewise, and their son's sons, as did their fathers, so do they to this day.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.18'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.1'>Now it came to pass in the third year of Hoshea son of Elah king of Israel, that Hezekiah the son of Ahaz king of Judah began to reign.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.2'>He was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. And his mother's name was Abi the daughter of Zechariah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.3'>And he did that which was right in the eyes of LORD, according to all that David his father had done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.4'>He removed the high places, and broke the pillars, and cut down the Asherah, and he broke in pieces the brazen serpent that Moses had made. For to those days the sons of Israel burned incense to it, and he called it Nehushtan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.5'>He trusted in LORD, the God of Israel, so that there was none like him among all the kings of Judah after him, nor [among those] who were before him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.6'>For he clung to LORD. He did not depart from following him, but kept his commandments, which LORD commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.7'>And LORD was with him. Wherever he went forth he prospered. And he rebelled against the king of Assyria, and did not serve him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.8'>He smote the Philistines to Gaza and the borders of it, from the tower of the watchmen to the fortified city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.9'>And it came to pass in the fourth year of king Hezekiah, which was the seventh year of Hoshea son of Elah king of Israel, that Shalmaneser king of Assyria came up against Samaria, and besieged it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.10'>And at the end of three years they took it. Samaria was taken in the sixth year of Hezekiah, which was the ninth year of Hoshea king of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.11'>And the king of Assyria carried Israel away to Assyria, and put them in Halah, and on the Habor, the river of Gozan, and in the cities of the Medes,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.12'>because they did not obey the voice of LORD their God, but transgressed his covenant, even all that Moses the servant of LORD commanded, and would not hear it, nor do it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.13'>Now in the fourteenth year of king Hezekiah, Sennacherib king of Assyria came up against all the fortified cities of Judah, and took them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.14'>And Hezekiah king of Judah sent to the king of Assyria to Lachish, saying, I have offended. Return from me. That which thou put on me I will bear. And the king of Assyria appointed to Hezekiah king of Judah three hundred talents of</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.15'>And Hezekiah gave [him] all the silver that was found in the house of LORD, and in the treasures of the king's house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.16'>At that time Hezekiah cut off [the gold from] the doors of the temple of LORD, and [from] the pillars which Hezekiah king of Judah had overlaid, and gave it to the king of Assyria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.17'>And the king of Assyria sent Tartan and Rab-saris and Rabshakeh from Lachish to king Hezekiah with a great army to Jerusalem. And they went up and came to Jerusalem. And when they came up, they came and stood by the conduit of the</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.18'>And when they had called to the king, there came out to them Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, who was over the household, and Shebnah the scribe, and Joah the son of Asaph the recorder.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.19'>And Rabshakeh said to them, Say ye now to Hezekiah, Thus says the great king, the king of Assyria, What confidence is this in which thou trust?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.20'>Thou say (but they are but vain words), [There is] counsel and strength for the war. Now on whom do thou trust that thou have rebelled against me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.21'>Now, behold, thou trust upon the staff of this bruised reed, even upon Egypt, on which if a man leans it will go into his hand, and pierce it. So is Pharaoh king of Egypt to all who trust on him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.22'>But if ye say to me, We trust in LORD our God, is that not he whose high places and whose altars Hezekiah has taken away, and has said to Judah and to Jerusalem, Ye shall worship before this altar in Jerusalem?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.23'>Now therefore, I pray thee, give pledges to my master the king of Assyria, and I will give thee two thousand horses, if thou be able on thy part to set riders upon them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.24'>How then can thou turn away the face of one captain of the least of my master's servants, and put thy trust on Egypt for chariots and for horsemen?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.25'>Have I now come up without LORD against this place to destroy it? LORD said to me, Go up against this land, and destroy it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.26'>Then Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, and Shebnah, and Joah, said to Rabshakeh, Speak, I pray thee, to thy servants in the Syrian language, for we understand it. And do not speak with us in the Jews' language, in the ears of the people</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.27'>But Rabshakeh said to them, Has my master sent me to thy master, and to thee, to speak these words? [Has he] not [sent me] to the men who sit on the wall, to eat their own dung, and to drink their own urine with you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.28'>Then Rabshakeh stood, and cried with a loud voice in the Jews' language, and spoke, saying, Hear ye the word of the great king, the king of Assyria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.29'>Thus says the king, Let not Hezekiah deceive you, for he will not be able to deliver you out of his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.30'>Neither let Hezekiah make you trust in LORD, saying, LORD will surely deliver us, and this city shall not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.31'>Do not hearken to Hezekiah. For thus says the king of Assyria, Make your peace with me, and come out to me. And eat ye every man of his vine, and every man of his fig tree, and drink ye every man the waters of his own cistern,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.32'>until I come and take you away to a land like your own land, a land of grain and new wine, a land of bread and vineyards, a land of olive trees and of honey, that ye may live, and not die. And do not hearken to Hezekiah when he per</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.33'>Have any of the gods of the nations ever delivered his land out of the hand of the king of Assyria?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.34'>Where are the gods of Hamath, and of Arpad? Where are the gods of Sepharvaim, of Hena, and Ivvah? Have they delivered Samaria out of my hand?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.35'>Who are they among all the gods of the countries that have delivered their country out of my hand, that LORD should deliver Jerusalem out of my hand?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.36'>But the people were silent, and did not answer him a word, for the king's commandment was, saying, Do not answer him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.18.37'>Then Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, who was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah the son of Asaph the recorder, came to Hezekiah with their clothes torn, and told him the words of Rabshakeh.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.19'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.1'>And it came to pass, when king Hezekiah heard it, that he tore his clothes, and covered himself with sackcloth, and went into the house of LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.2'>And he sent Eliakim, who was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and the elders of the priests (covered with sackcloth) to Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.3'>And they said to him, Thus says Hezekiah, This day is a day of trouble, and of rebuke, and of blasphemy, for the sons have come to the birth, and there is no strength to bring forth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.4'>It may be that LORD thy God will hear all the words of Rabshakeh whom the king of Assyria his master has sent to defy the living God, and will rebuke the words which LORD thy God has heard. Therefore lift up thy prayer for the remn</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.5'>So the servants of king Hezekiah came to Isaiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.6'>And Isaiah said to them, Thus shall ye say to your master, Thus says LORD, Do not be afraid of the words that thou have heard, with which the servants of the king of Assyria have blasphemed me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.7'>Behold, I will put a spirit in him, and he shall hear news, and shall return to his own land. And I will cause him to fall by the sword in his own land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.8'>So Rabshakeh returned, and found the king of Assyria warring against Libnah, for he had heard that he was departed from Lachish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.9'>And when he heard say of Tirhakah king of Ethiopia, Behold, he comes out to fight against thee, he sent messengers again to Hezekiah, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.10'>Thus shall ye speak to Hezekiah king of Judah, saying, Do not let thy God in whom thou trust deceive thee, saying, Jerusalem shall not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.11'>Behold, thou have heard what the kings of Assyria have done to all lands, by destroying them utterly. And shall thou be delivered?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.12'>Have the gods of the nations delivered them, which my fathers have destroyed, Gozan, and Haran, and Rezeph, and the sons of Eden that were in Telassar?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.13'>Where is the king of Hamath, and the king of Arpad, and the king of the city of Sepharvaim, of Hena, and Ivvah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.14'>And Hezekiah received the letter from the hand of the messengers, and read it. And Hezekiah went up to the house of LORD, and spread it before LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.15'>And Hezekiah prayed before LORD, and said, O LORD, the God of Israel, who sits [above] the cherubim, thou are the God, even thou alone, of all the kingdoms of the earth. Thou have made heaven and earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.16'>Incline thine ear, O LORD, and hear. Open thine eyes, O LORD, and see. And hear the words of Sennacherib, with which he has sent for him to defy the living God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.17'>Of a truth, LORD, the kings of Assyria have laid waste the nations and their lands,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.18'>and have cast their gods into the fire, for they were no gods, but the work of men's hands, wood and stone. Therefore they have destroyed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.19'>Now therefore, O LORD our God, save thou us, I beseech thee, out of his hand, that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that thou LORD are God alone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.20'>Then Isaiah the son of Amoz sent to Hezekiah, saying, Thus says LORD, the God of Israel, Whereas thou have prayed to me against Sennacherib king of Assyria, I have heard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.21'>This is the word that LORD has spoken concerning him: The virgin daughter of Zion has despised thee and laughed thee to scorn. The daughter of Jerusalem has shaken her head at thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.22'>Whom have thou defied and blasphemed? And against whom have thou exalted thy voice and lifted up thine eyes on high? [Even] against the Holy One of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.23'>By thy messengers thou have defied LORD, and have said, With the multitude of my chariots I have come up to the height of the mountains, to the innermost parts of Lebanon. And I will cut down the tall cedars of it, and the choice f</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.24'>I have dug and drunk strange waters, and with the sole of my feet I will dry up all the rivers of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.25'>Have thou not heard how I have done it long ago, and formed it of ancient times? Now I have brought it to pass, that thou should be to lay waste fortified cities into ruinous heaps.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.26'>Therefore their inhabitants were of small power, they were dismayed and confounded. They were as the grass of the field, and as the green herb, as the grass on the housetops, and as grain blasted before it is grown up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.27'>But I know thy sitting down, and thy going out, and thy coming in, and thy raging against me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.28'>Because of thy raging against me, and because thine arrogance has come up into my ears, therefore I will put my hook in thy nose, and my bridle in thy lips, and I will turn thee back by the way by which thou came.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.29'>And this shall be the sign to thee: Ye shall eat this year that which grows of itself, and in the second year that which springs of the same. And in the third year sow ye, and reap, and plant vineyards, and eat the fruit of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.30'>And the remnant that is escaped of the house of Judah shall again take root downward, and bear fruit upward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.31'>For out of Jerusalem shall go forth a remnant, and out of mount Zion those who shall escape. The zeal of LORD shall perform this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.32'>Therefore thus says LORD concerning the king of Assyria, He shall not come to this city, nor shoot an arrow there, neither shall he come before it with shield, nor cast up a mound against it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.33'>By the way that he came, by the same shall he return, and he shall not come to this city, says LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.34'>For I will defend this city to save it, for my own sake, and for my servant David's sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.35'>And it came to pass that night, that the agent of LORD went forth, and smote in the camp of the Assyrians a hundred eighty-five thousand. And when men arose early in the morning, behold, these were all dead bodies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.36'>So Sennacherib king of Assyria departed, and went and returned, and dwelt at Nineveh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.19.37'>And it came to pass, as he was worshipping in the house of Nisroch his god, that Adrammelech and Sharezer smote him with the sword, and they escaped into the land of Ararat. And Esar-haddon his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.20'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.1'>In those days Hezekiah was sick to death. And Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz came to him, and said to him, Thus says LORD, Set thy house in order, for thou shall die, and not live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.2'>Then he turned his face to the wall, and prayed to LORD, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.3'>Remember now, O LORD, I beseech thee, how I have walked before thee in truth and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy sight. And Hezekiah wept greatly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.4'>And it came to pass, before Isaiah was gone out into the middle part of the city, that the word of LORD came to him, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.5'>Turn back, and say to Hezekiah the prince of my people, Thus says LORD, the God of David thy father, I have heard thy prayer, I have seen thy tears. Behold, I will heal thee. On the third day thou shall go up to the house of LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.6'>And I will add to thy days fifteen years. And I will deliver thee and this city out of the hand of the king of Assyria. And I will defend this city for my own sake, and for my servant David's sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.7'>And Isaiah said, Take a cake of figs. And they took and laid it on the boil, and he recovered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.8'>And Hezekiah said to Isaiah, What shall be the sign that LORD will heal me, and that I shall go up to the house of LORD the third day?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.9'>And Isaiah said, This shall be the sign to thee from LORD, that LORD will do the thing that he has spoken: Shall the shadow go forward ten steps, or go back ten steps?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.10'>And Hezekiah answered, It is a light thing for the shadow to go forward ten steps. No, but let the shadow return backward ten steps.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.11'>And Isaiah the prophet cried to LORD, and he brought the shadow ten steps backward, by which it had gone down on the dial of Ahaz.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.12'>At that time Berodach-baladan the son of Baladan, king of Babylon, sent letters and a present to Hezekiah, for he had heard that Hezekiah had been sick.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.13'>And Hezekiah hearkened to them, and showed them all the house of his precious things, the silver, and the gold, and the spices, and the precious oil, and the house of his armor, and all that was found in his treasures. There was no</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.14'>Then Isaiah the prophet came to king Hezekiah, and said to him, What did these men say, and from where did they come to thee? And Hezekiah said, They have come from a far country, even from Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.15'>And he said, What have they seen in thy house? And Hezekiah answered, They have seen all that is in my house. There is nothing among my treasures that I have not shown them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.16'>And Isaiah said to Hezekiah, Hear the word of LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.17'>Behold, the days come that all that is in thy house, and that which thy fathers have laid up in store to this day, shall be carried to Babylon. Nothing shall be left, says LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.18'>And of thy sons who shall issue from thee, whom thou shall beget, they shall take away. And they shall be eunuchs in the palace of the king of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.19'>Then Hezekiah said to Isaiah, The word of LORD which thou have spoken is good. He said moreover, Is it not so, if peace and truth shall be in my days?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.20'>Now the rest of the acts of Hezekiah, and all his might, and how he made the pool, and the conduit, and brought water into the city, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.20.21'>And Hezekiah slept with his fathers, and Manasseh his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.21'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.1'>Manasseh was twelve years old when he began to reign, and he reigned fifty-five years in Jerusalem. And his mother's name was Hephzibah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.2'>And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD, according to the abominations of the nations whom LORD cast out before the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.3'>For he built again the high places which Hezekiah his father had destroyed. And he reared up altars for Baal, and made an Asherah, as did Ahab king of Israel, and worshipped all the host of heaven, and served them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.4'>And he built altars in the house of LORD, of which LORD said, In Jerusalem I will put my name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.5'>And he built altars for all the host of heaven in the two courts of the house of LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.6'>And he made his son to pass through the fire, and practiced augury, and used enchantments, and dealt with psychics, and with sorcery. He wrought much evil in the sight of LORD to provoke him to anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.7'>And he set the graven image of Asherah, that he had made, in the house of which LORD said to David and to Solomon his son, In this house, and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, I will put my name for</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.8'>Neither will I cause the feet of Israel to wander any more out of the land which I gave their fathers, if only they will observe to do according to all that I have commanded them, and according to all the law that my servant Moses</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.9'>But they did not hearken. And Manasseh seduced them to do that which is evil more than did the nations whom LORD destroyed before the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.10'>And LORD spoke by his servants the prophets, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.11'>Because Manasseh king of Judah has done these abominations, and has done wickedly above all that the Amorites did who were before him, and has made Judah also to sin with his idols,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.12'>therefore thus says LORD, the God of Israel, Behold, I bring such evil upon Jerusalem and Judah, that whoever hears of it, both his ears shall tingle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.13'>And I will stretch over Jerusalem the line of Samaria, and the plummet of the house of Ahab. And I will wipe Jerusalem as a man wipes a dish, wiping it and turning it upside down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.14'>And I will cast off the remnant of my inheritance, and deliver them into the hand of their enemies. And they shall become a prey and a spoil to all their enemies,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.15'>because they have done that which is evil in my sight, and have provoked me to anger, since the day their fathers came forth out of Egypt even to this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.16'>Moreover Manasseh shed very much innocent blood till he had filled Jerusalem from one end to another, besides his sin with which he made Judah to sin in doing that which was evil in the sight of LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.17'>Now the rest of the acts of Manasseh, and all that he did, and his sin that he sinned, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.18'>And Manasseh slept with his fathers, and was buried in the garden of his own house, in the garden of Uzza, and Amon his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.19'>Amon was twenty-two years old when he began to reign, and he reigned two years in Jerusalem. And his mother's name was Meshullemeth the daughter of Haruz of Jotbah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.20'>And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD as did Manasseh his father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.21'>And he walked in all the way that his father walked in, and served the idols that his father served, and worshipped them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.22'>And he forsook LORD, the God of his fathers, and did not walk in the way of LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.23'>And the servants of Amon conspired against him, and put the king to death in his own house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.24'>But the people of the land killed all those who had conspired against king Amon. And the people of the land made Josiah his son king in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.25'>Now the rest of the acts of Amon which he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.21.26'>And he was buried in his sepulcher in the garden of Uzza, and Josiah his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.22'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.1'>Josiah was eight years old when he began to reign, and he reigned thirty-one years in Jerusalem. And his mother's name was Jedidah the daughter of Adaiah of Bozkath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.2'>And he did that which was right in the eyes of LORD, and walked in all the way of David his father, and did not turn aside to the right hand or to the left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.3'>And it came to pass, in the eighteenth year of king Josiah, that the king sent Shaphan, the son of Azaliah the son of Meshullam, the scribe, to the house of LORD, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.4'>Go up to Hilkiah the high priest that he may sum the money which is brought into the house of LORD, which the keepers of the threshold have gathered of the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.5'>And let them deliver it into the hand of the workmen who have the oversight of the house of LORD. And let them give it to the workmen who are in the house of LORD, to repair the broken parts of the house,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.6'>to the carpenters, and to the builders, and to the masons, and for buying timber and hewn stone to repair the house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.7'>However there was no reckoning made with them of the money that was delivered into their hand, for they dealt faithfully.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.8'>And Hilkiah the high priest said to Shaphan the scribe, I have found the book of the law in the house of LORD. And Hilkiah delivered the book to Shaphan, and he read it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.9'>And Shaphan the scribe came to the king, and brought the king word again, and said, Thy servants have emptied out the money that was found in the house, and have delivered it into the hand of the workmen who have the oversight of t</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.10'>And Shaphan the scribe told the king, saying, Hilkiah the priest has delivered to me a book. And Shaphan read it before the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.11'>And it came to pass, when the king had heard the words of the book of the law, that he tore his clothes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.12'>And the king commanded Hilkiah the priest, and Ahikam the son of Shaphan, and Achbor the son of Micaiah, and Shaphan the scribe, and Asaiah the king's servant, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.13'>Go ye, inquire of LORD for me, and for the people, and for all Judah, concerning the words of this book that is found, for great is the wrath of LORD that is kindled against us, because our fathers have not hearkened to the words o</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.14'>So Hilkiah the priest, and Ahikam, and Achbor, and Shaphan, and Asaiah, went to Huldah the prophetess, the wife of Shallum the son of Tikvah, the son of Harhas, keeper of the wardrobe (now she dwelt in Jerusalem in the second quart</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.15'>And she said to them, Thus says LORD, the God of Israel: Tell ye the man who sent you to me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.16'>Thus says LORD, Behold, I will bring evil upon this place, and upon the inhabitants of it, even all the words of the book which the king of Judah has read.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.17'>Because they have forsaken me, and have burned incense to other gods, that they might provoke me to anger with all the work of their hands, therefore my wrath shall be kindled against this place, and it shall not be quenched.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.18'>But to the king of Judah, who sent you to inquire of LORD, thus shall ye say to him, Thus says LORD, the God of Israel: As concerning the words which thou have heard,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.19'>because thy heart was tender, and thou humbled thyself before LORD when thou heard what I spoke against this place, and against the inhabitants of it, that they should become a desolation and a curse, and have torn thy clothes, and</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.22.20'>Therefore, behold, I will gather thee to thy fathers, and thou shall be gathered to thy grave in peace, neither shall thine eyes see all the evil which I will bring upon this place. And they brought the king word again.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.23'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.1'>And the king sent, and they gathered to him all the elders of Judah and of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.2'>And the king went up to the house of LORD, and all the men of Judah and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem with him, and the priests, and the prophets, and all the people, both small and great. And he read in their ears all the words</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.3'>And the king stood by the pillar, and made a covenant before LORD to walk after LORD, and to keep his commandments, and his testimonies, and his statutes, with all [his] heart, and all [his] soul, to confirm the words of this coven</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.4'>And the king commanded Hilkiah the high priest, and the priests of the second order, and the keepers of the threshold, to bring forth out of the temple of LORD all the vessels that were made for Baal, and for the Asherah, and for a</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.5'>And he put down the idolatrous priests, whom the kings of Judah had ordained to burn incense in the high places in the cities of Judah, and in the places round about Jerusalem; those also who burned incense to Baal, to the sun, and</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.6'>And he brought out the Asherah from the house of LORD, outside Jerusalem, to the brook Kidron, and burned it at the brook Kidron, and beat it to dust, and cast the dust of it upon the graves of the common people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.7'>And he broke down the houses of the sodomites that were in the house of LORD where the women wove hangings for the Asherah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.8'>And he brought all the priests out of the cities of Judah, and defiled the high places where the priests had burned incense, from Geba to Beersheba. And he broke down the high places of the gates that were at the entrance of the ga</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.9'>Nevertheless the priests of the high places did not come up to the altar of LORD in Jerusalem, but they ate unleavened bread among their brothers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.10'>And he defiled Topheth, which is in the valley of the sons of Hinnom, that no man might make his son or his daughter to pass through the fire to Molech.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.11'>And he took away the horses that the kings of Judah had given to the sun, at the entrance of the house of LORD, by the chamber of Nathan-melech the chamberlain, which was in the suburbs. And he burned the chariots of the sun with f</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.12'>And the altars that were on the roof of the upper chamber of Ahaz, which the kings of Judah had made, and the altars which Manasseh had made in the two courts of the house of LORD, the king broke down, and beat [them] down from the</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.13'>And the king defiled the high places that were before Jerusalem, which were on the right hand of the mount of corruption, which Solomon the king of Israel had built for Ashtoreth the abomination of the Sidonians, and for Chemosh th</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.14'>And he broke in pieces the pillars, and cut down the Asherim, and filled their places with the bones of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.15'>Moreover the altar that was at Bethel, and the high place which Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who made Israel to sin, had made, even that altar and the high place he broke down. And he burned the high place and beat it to dust, and bu</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.16'>And as Josiah turned himself, he noticed the sepulchers that were there in the mount. And he sent, and took the bones out of the sepulchers, and burned them upon the altar, and defiled it, according to the word of LORD which the ma</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.17'>Then he said, What monument is that which I see? And the men of the city told him, It is the sepulcher of the man of God who came from Judah, and proclaimed these things that thou have done against the altar of Bethel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.18'>And he said, Let him be; let no man move his bones. So they let his bones alone, with the bones of the prophet who came out of Samaria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.19'>And Josiah also took away all the houses of the high places that were in the cities of Samaria, which the kings of Israel had made to provoke [LORD] to anger. And he did to them according to all the acts that he had done in Bethel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.20'>And he killed all the priests of the high places that were there, upon the altars, and burned men's bones upon them. And he returned to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.21'>And the king commanded all the people, saying, Keep the Passover to LORD your God, as it is written in this book of the covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.22'>Surely such a Passover was not kept from the days of the judges who judged Israel, nor in all the days of the kings of Israel, nor of the kings of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.23'>But in the eighteenth year of king Josiah this Passover was kept to LORD in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.24'>Moreover Josiah put away the psychics, and the wizards, and the teraphim, and the idols, and all the abominations that were seen in the land of Judah and in Jerusalem, that he might perform the words of the law which were written i</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.25'>And there was no king before him like him, who turned to LORD with all his heart, and with all his soul, and with all his might, according to all the law of Moses; neither arose any like him after him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.26'>Notwithstanding, LORD did not turn from the fierceness of his great wrath, with which his anger was kindled against Judah, because of all the provocations with which Manasseh had provoked him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.27'>And LORD said, I will remove Judah also out of my sight as I have removed Israel, and I will cast off this city which I have chosen, even Jerusalem, and the house of which I said, My name shall be there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.28'>Now the rest of the acts of Josiah, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.29'>In his days Pharaoh-necoh king of Egypt went up against the king of Assyria to the river Euphrates, and king Josiah went against him. And [Pharaoh-necoh] killed him at Megiddo when he had seen him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.30'>And his servants carried him in a chariot dead from Megiddo, and brought him to Jerusalem, and buried him in his own sepulcher. And the people of the land took Jehoahaz the son of Josiah, and anointed him, and made him king in his</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.31'>Jehoahaz was twenty-three years old when he began to reign, and he reigned three months in Jerusalem. And his mother's name was Hamutal the daughter of Jeremiah of Libnah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.32'>And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD, according to all that his fathers had done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.33'>And Pharaoh-necoh put him in bonds at Riblah in the land of Hamath, that he might not reign in Jerusalem. And he put the land to a tribute of a hundred talents of silver, and a talent of gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.34'>And Pharaoh-necoh made Eliakim the son of Josiah king in the place of Josiah his father, and changed his name to Jehoiakim. But he took Jehoahaz away, and he came to Egypt, and died there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.35'>And Jehoiakim gave the silver and the gold to Pharaoh, but he taxed the land to give the money according to the commandment of Pharaoh. He exacted the silver and the gold from the people of the land, of every one according to his t</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.36'>Jehoiakim was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem. And his mother's name was Zebidah the daughter of Pedaiah of Rumah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.23.37'>And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD, according to all that his fathers had done.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.24'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.1'>In his days Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came up, and Jehoiakim became his servant three years. Then he turned and rebelled against him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.2'>And LORD sent against him bands of the Chaldeans, and bands of the Syrians, and bands of the Moabites, and bands of the sons of Ammon, and sent them against Judah to destroy it, according to the word of LORD, which he spoke by his</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.3'>Surely at the commandment of LORD this came upon Judah, to remove them out of his sight, for the sins of Manasseh, according to all that he did,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.4'>and also for the innocent blood that he shed, for he filled Jerusalem with innocent blood, and LORD would not pardon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.5'>Now the rest of the acts of Jehoiakim, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.6'>So Jehoiakim slept with his fathers, and Jehoiachin his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.7'>And the king of Egypt did not come again any more out of his land, for the king of Babylon had taken, from the brook of Egypt to the river Euphrates, all that pertained to the king of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.8'>Jehoiachin was eighteen years old when he began to reign, and he reigned in Jerusalem three months. And his mother's name was Nehushta the daughter of Elnathan of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.9'>And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD, according to all that his father had done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.10'>At that time the servants of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came up to Jerusalem, and the city was besieged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.11'>And Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came to the city while his servants were besieging it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.12'>And Jehoiachin the king of Judah went out to the king of Babylon, he, and his mother, and his servants, and his princes, and his officers. And the king of Babylon took him in the eighth year of his reign.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.13'>And he carried out from there all the treasures of the house of LORD, and the treasures of the king's house, and cut in pieces all the vessels of gold, which Solomon king of Israel had made in the temple of LORD, as LORD had said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.14'>And he carried away all Jerusalem, and all the rulers, and all the mighty men of valor, even ten thousand captives, and all the craftsmen and the blacksmiths. None remained except the poorest sort of the people of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.15'>And he carried away Jehoiachin to Babylon. And the king's mother, and the king's wives, and his officers, and the chief men of the land, he carried into captivity from Jerusalem to Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.16'>And all the men of might, even seven thousand, and the craftsmen and the blacksmiths a thousand, all of them strong and apt for war, even them the king of Babylon brought captive to Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.17'>And the king of Babylon made Mattaniah, [Jehoiachin's] father's brother, king is his stead, and changed his name to Zedekiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.18'>Zedekiah was twenty-one years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem. And his mother's name was Hamutal the daughter of Jeremiah of Libnah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.19'>And he did that which was evil in the sight of LORD, according to all that Jehoiakim had done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.24.20'>For it came to pass in Jerusalem and Judah through the anger of LORD, until he had cast them out from his presence. And Zedekiah rebelled against the king of Babylon.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Kgs.25'>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.1'>And it came to pass in the ninth year of his reign, in the tenth month, in the tenth day of the month, that Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came, he and all his army, against Jerusalem, and encamped against it. And they built forts</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.2'>So the city was besieged to the eleventh year of king Zedekiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.3'>On the ninth day of the [fourth] month the famine was severe in the city, so that there was no bread for the people of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.4'>Then a breach was made in the city, and all the men of war [fled] by night by the way of the gate between the two walls, which was by the king's garden (now the Chaldeans were against the city round about), and [the king] went by t</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.5'>But the army of the Chaldeans pursued after the king, and overtook him in the plains of Jericho. And all his army was scattered from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.6'>Then they took the king, and carried him up to the king of Babylon to Riblah. And they gave judgment upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.7'>And they killed the sons of Zedekiah before his eyes, and put out the eyes of Zedekiah, and bound him in fetters, and carried him to Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.8'>Now in the fifth month, on the seventh day of the month, which was the nineteenth year of king Nebuchadnezzar, king of Babylon, Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard, a servant of the king of Babylon, came to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.9'>And he burnt the house of LORD, and the king's house. And all the houses of Jerusalem, even every great house, he burnt with fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.10'>And all the army of the Chaldeans, that were [with] the captain of the guard, broke down the walls of Jerusalem round about.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.11'>And the remnant of the people that were left in the city, and those that fell away, that fell to the king of Babylon, and the remnant of the multitude, Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard carried away captive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.12'>But the captain of the guard left of the poorest of the land to be vinedressers and husbandmen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.13'>And the pillars of brass that were in the house of LORD, and the bases and the brazen sea that were in the house of LORD, the Chaldeans broke in pieces, and carried the brass of them to Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.14'>And they took away the pots, and the shovels, and the snuffers, and the spoons, and all the vessels of brass with which they ministered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.15'>And the captain of the guard took away the firepans, and the basins, that which was of gold, in gold, and that which was of silver, in silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.16'>The two pillars, the one sea, and the bases, which Solomon had made for the house of LORD, the brass of all these vessels was without weight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.17'>The height of the one pillar was eighteen cubits, and a capital of brass was upon it. And the height of the capital was three cubits, with network and pomegranates upon the capital round about, all of brass. And the second pillar h</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.18'>And the captain of the guard took Seraiah the chief priest, and Zephaniah the second priest, and the three keepers of the threshold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.19'>And he took an officer out of the city who was set over the men of war; and five men of those who saw the king's face, who were found in the city; and the scribe, the captain of the army, who mustered the people of the land; and si</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.20'>And Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard took them, and brought them to the king of Babylon to Riblah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.21'>And the king of Babylon smote them, and put them to death at Riblah in the land of Hamath. So Judah was carried away captive out of his land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.22'>And as for the people who were left in the land of Judah, whom Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon had left, he made Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, governor over them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.23'>Now when all the captains of the forces, they and their men, heard that the king of Babylon had made Gedaliah governor, they came to Gedaliah to Mizpah, even Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, and Johanan the son of Kareah, and Seraiah</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.24'>And Gedaliah swore to them and to their men, and said to them, Fear not because of the servants of the Chaldeans. Dwell in the land, and serve the king of Babylon, and it shall be well with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.25'>But it came to pass in the seventh month, that Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, the son of Elishama, of the royal seed, came, and ten men with him, and smote Gedaliah, so that he died, and the Jews and the Chaldeans who were with him</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.26'>And all the people, both small and great, and the captains of the forces, arose, and came to Egypt, for they were afraid of the Chaldeans.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.27'>And it came to pass in the thirty-seventh year of the captivity of Jehoiachin king of Judah, in the twelfth month, on the twenty-seventh day of the month, that Evil-merodach king of Babylon, in the year that he began to reign, lift</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.28'>And he spoke kindly to him, and set his throne above the throne of the kings that were with him in Babylon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.29'>and changed his prison garments. And [Jehoiachin] ate bread before him continually all the days of his life,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Kgs.25.30'>and for his allowance. There was a continual allowance given him from the king, every day a portion, all the days of his life.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>