<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='ACV' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='ACV'>
        <title>A Conservative Version</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description/>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>ACV</identifier>
        <source>http://www.e-sword.net/usermods/</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage/>
        <rights>www.stillvoices.org</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Dan'>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.1'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.1'>In the third year of the reign of Jehoiakim king of Judah, Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came to Jerusalem, and besieged it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.2'>And LORD gave Jehoiakim king of Judah into his hand, with part of the vessels of the house of God. And he carried them into the land of Shinar to the house of his god, and he brought the vessels into the treasure-house of his god.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.3'>And the king spoke to Ashpenaz the master of his eunuchs, that he should bring in [certain] of the sons of Israel, even of the seed royal and of the ranking men,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.4'>youths in whom was no blemish, but well-favored, and skilful in all wisdom, and endued with knowledge, and understanding science, and such as had ability to stand in the king's palace. And that he should teach them the learning and</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.5'>And the king appointed for them a daily portion of the king's food, and of the wine which he drank. And that they should be nourished three years, that at the end of it they should stand before the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.6'>Now among these were, of the sons of Judah: Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.7'>And the ruler of the eunuchs gave names to them. To Daniel he gave [the name of] Belteshazzar, and to Hananiah, [of] Shadrach, and to Mishael, [of] Meshach, and to Azariah, [of] Abednego.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.8'>But Daniel purposed in his heart that he would not defile himself with the king's food, nor with the wine which he drank. Therefore he requested of the ruler of the eunuchs that he might not defile himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.9'>Now God made Daniel find kindness and compassion in the sight of the ruler of the eunuchs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.10'>And the ruler of the eunuchs said to Daniel, I fear my lord the king, who has appointed your food and your drink. For why should he see your faces worse looking than the youths that are of your own age? So ye would endanger my head</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.11'>Then Daniel said to the steward whom the ruler of the eunuchs had appointed over Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.12'>Test thy servants, I beseech thee, ten days, and let them give us vegetables to eat, and water to drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.13'>Then let our countenances be looked upon before thee, and the countenance of the youths that eat of the king's food. And as thou see, deal with thy servants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.14'>So he hearkened to them in this matter, and tested them ten days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.15'>And at the end of ten days their countenances appeared finer, and they were fuller in flesh, than all the youths who ate of the king's dainties.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.16'>So the steward took away their food, and the wine that they should drink, and gave them vegetables.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.17'>Now as for these four youths, God gave them knowledge and skill in all learning and wisdom. And Daniel had understanding in all visions and dreams.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.18'>And at the end of the days which the king had appointed for bringing them in, the ruler of the eunuchs brought them in before Nebuchadnezzar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.19'>And the king conversed with them. And among them all none was found like Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah. Therefore they stood before the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.20'>And in every matter of wisdom and understanding, concerning which the king inquired of them, he found them ten times better than all the magicians and enchanters who were in all his realm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.21'>And Daniel continued even to the first year of king Cyrus.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.2'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.1'>And in the second year of the reign of Nebuchadnezzar, Nebuchadnezzar dreamed dreams. And his spirit was troubled, and his sleep went from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.2'>Then the king commanded to call the magicians, and the enchanters, and the sorcerers, and the Chaldeans, to tell the king his dreams. So they came in and stood before the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.3'>And the king said to them, I have dreamed a dream, and my spirit is troubled to know the dream.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.4'>Then the Chaldeans spoke to the king in the Syrian language, O king, live forever. Tell thy servants the dream, and we will show the interpretation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.5'>The king answered and said to the Chaldeans, The thing is gone from me. If ye do not make the dream and the interpretation of it known to me, ye shall be cut in pieces, and your houses shall be made a dunghill.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.6'>But if ye show the dream and the interpretation of it, ye shall receive gifts and rewards and great honor from me. Therefore show the dream and the interpretation of it to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.7'>They answered the second time and said, Let the king tell his servants the dream, and we will show the interpretation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.8'>The king answered and said, I know of a certainty that ye would gain time, because ye see the thing has gone from me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.9'>But if ye do not make known to me the dream, there is but one law for you, for ye have prepared lying and corrupt words to speak before me till the time is changed. Therefore tell me the dream, and I shall know that ye can show me</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.10'>The Chaldeans answered before the king, and said, There is not a man upon the earth who can show the king's matter. Inasmuch as no king, lord, or ruler, has asked such a thing of any magician or enchanter or Chaldean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.11'>And it is a rare thing that the king requires, and there is no other who can show it before the king, except the gods, whose dwelling is not with flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.12'>For this reason the king was angry and very furious, and commanded to destroy all the wise men of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.13'>So the decree went forth, and the wise men were to be slain. And they sought Daniel and his companions to be slain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.14'>Then Daniel returned answer with counsel and prudence to Arioch, the captain of the king's guard, who went forth to kill the wise men of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.15'>He answered and said to Arioch the king's captain, Why is the decree so urgent from the king? Then Arioch made the thing known to Daniel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.16'>And Daniel went in, and desired of the king that he would appoint him a time, and he would show the king the interpretation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.17'>Then Daniel went to his house, and made the thing known to Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah, his companions,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.18'>that they would desire mercies of the God of heaven concerning this secret, that Daniel and his companions should nor perish with the rest of the wise men of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.19'>Then the secret was shown to Daniel in a vision of the night. Then Daniel blessed the God of heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.20'>Daniel answered and said, Blessed be the name of God forever and ever, for wisdom and might are his.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.21'>And he changes the times and the seasons. He removes kings, and sets up kings. He gives wisdom to the wise, and knowledge to those who have understanding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.22'>He reveals the deep and secret things. He knows what is in the darkness, and the light dwells with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.23'>I thank thee, and praise thee, O thou God of my fathers, who has given me wisdom and might, and has now made known to me what we desired of thee, for thou have made known to us the king's matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.24'>Therefore Daniel went in to Arioch, whom the king had appointed to destroy the wise men of Babylon. He went and said thus to him: Do not destroy the wise men of Babylon. Bring me in before the king, and I will show to the king the</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.25'>Then Arioch brought Daniel in before the king in haste, and said thus to him: I have found a man of the sons of the captivity of Judah, who will make known the interpretation to the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.26'>The king answered and said to Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, Are thou able to make known to me the dream which I have seen, and the interpretation of it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.27'>Daniel answered before the king, and said, The secret which the king has demanded, neither wise men, enchanters, magicians, nor soothsayers, can show to the king,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.28'>but there is a God in heaven who reveals secrets. And he has made known to the king Nebuchadnezzar what shall be in the latter days. Thy dream, and the visions of thy head upon thy bed, are these:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.29'>As for thee, O king, thy thoughts came upon thy bed, what should come to pass hereafter. And he who reveals secrets has made known to thee what shall come to pass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.30'>But as for me, this secret is not revealed to me for any wisdom that I have more than any living man, but to the intent that the interpretation may be made known to the king, and that thou may know the thoughts of thy heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.31'>Thou, O king, saw, and, behold, a great image. This image, which was mighty, and whose brightness was excellent, stood before thee, and the appearance of it was fearful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.32'>As for this image, its head was of fine gold, its breast and its arms of silver, its belly and its thighs of brass,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.33'>its legs of iron, its feet part of iron, and part of clay.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.34'>Thou looked until a stone was cut out without hands, which smote the image upon its feet that were of iron and clay, and broke them in pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.35'>Then the iron, the clay, the brass, the silver, and the gold, was broken in pieces together, and became like the chaff of the summer threshing floors. And the wind carried them away, so that no place was found for them. And the sto</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.36'>This is the dream, and we will tell the interpretation of it before the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.37'>Thou, O king, are a king of kings, to whom the God of heaven has given the kingdom, the power, and the strength, and the glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.38'>And wherever the sons of men dwell, the beasts of the field and the birds of the heavens, he has given into thy hand, and has made thee to rule over them all. Thou are the head of gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.39'>And after thee shall arise another kingdom inferior to thee, and another third kingdom of brass, which shall bear rule over all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.40'>And the fourth kingdom shall be strong as iron, inasmuch as iron breaks in pieces and subdues all things. And as iron that crushes all these, it shall break in pieces and crush.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.41'>And whereas thou saw the feet and toes, part of potters' clay, and part of iron, it shall be a divided kingdom. But there shall be of the strength of the iron in it, inasmuch as thou saw the iron mixed with miry clay.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.42'>And as the toes of the feet were part of iron, and part of clay, so the kingdom shall be partly strong, and partly broken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.43'>And whereas thou saw the iron mixed with miry clay, they shall mingle themselves with the seed of men, but they shall not cling one to another, even as iron does not mix with clay.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.44'>And in the days of those kings the God of heaven shall set up a kingdom that shall never be destroyed, nor shall the sovereignty of it be left to another people, but it shall break in pieces and consume all these kingdoms, and it s</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.45'>Inasmuch as thou saw that a stone was cut out of the mountain without hands, and that it broke in pieces the iron, the brass, the clay, the silver, and the gold, the great God has made known to the king what shall come to pass here</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.46'>Then the king Nebuchadnezzar fell upon his face, and worshipped Daniel, and commanded that they should offer an oblation and sweet odors to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.47'>The king answered to Daniel, and said, Of a truth your God is the God of gods, and LORD of kings, and a revealer of secrets, since thou have been able to reveal this secret.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.48'>Then the king made Daniel great, and gave him many great gifts, and made him to rule over the whole province of Babylon, and to be chief governor over all the wise men of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.49'>And Daniel requested of the king, and he appointed Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, over the affairs of the province of Babylon, but Daniel was in the gate of the king.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.3'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.1'>Nebuchadnezzar the king made an image of gold, whose height was sixty cubits, and the breadth of it six cubits. He set it up in the plain of Dura, in the province of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.2'>Then Nebuchadnezzar the king sent to gather together the satraps, the deputies, and the governors, the judges, the treasurers, the counselors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the provinces, to come to the dedication of the imag</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.3'>Then the satraps, the deputies, and the governors, the judges, the treasurers, the counselors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the provinces, were gathered together to the dedication of the image that Nebuchadnezzar the king ha</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.4'>Then the herald cried aloud, To you it is commanded, O peoples, nations, and languages,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.5'>that at what time ye hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, dulcimer, and all kinds of music, ye fall down and worship the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king has set up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.6'>And he who does not fall down and worship shall the same hour be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.7'>Therefore at that time, when all the peoples heard the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and all kinds of music, all the peoples, the nations, and the languages, fell down and worshipped the golden image that Neb</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.8'>Therefore at that time certain Chaldeans came near, and brought accusation against the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.9'>They answered and said to Nebuchadnezzar the king, O king, live forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.10'>Thou, O king, have made a decree, that every man who shall hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and dulcimer, and all kinds of music, shall fall down and worship the golden image.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.11'>And he who does not fall down and worship, shall be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.12'>There are certain Jews whom thou have appointed over the affairs of the province of Babylon: Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. These men, O king, have not regarded thee. They do not serve thy gods, nor worship the golden image which</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.13'>Then Nebuchadnezzar in [his] rage and fury commanded to bring Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. Then they brought these men before the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.14'>Nebuchadnezzar answered and said to them, Is it of purpose, O Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, that ye do not serve my god, nor worship the golden image which I have set up?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.15'>Now if ye be ready that at what time ye hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and dulcimer, and all kinds of music, ye fall down and worship the image which I have made, [well]. But if ye do not worship, ye</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.16'>Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego answered and said to the king, O Nebuchadnezzar, we have no need to answer thee in this matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.17'>If it be [so], our God whom we serve is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace, and he will deliver us out of thy hand, O king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.18'>But if not, be it known to thee, O king, that we will not serve thy gods, nor worship the golden image which thou have set up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.19'>Then Nebuchadnezzar was full of fury, and the form of his visage was changed against Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. [Therefore] he spoke, and commanded that they should heat the furnace seven times more than it was accustomed to</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.20'>And he commanded certain mighty men who were in his army to bind Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, [and] to cast them into the burning fiery furnace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.21'>Then these men were bound in their coats, their tunics, and their turbans, and their [other] garments, and were cast into the midst of the burning fiery furnace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.22'>Therefore because the king's commandment was urgent, and the furnace very hot, the flame of the fire killed those men who took up Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.23'>And these three men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, fell down bound into the midst of the burning fiery furnace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.24'>Then Nebuchadnezzar the king was astonished, and rose up in haste. He spoke and said to his counselors, Did we not cast three men bound into the midst of the fire? They answered and said to the king, True, O king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.25'>He answered and said, Lo, I see four men loose, walking in the midst of the fire, and they have no harm. And the appearance of the fourth is like a son of the gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.26'>Then Nebuchadnezzar came near to the mouth of the burning fiery furnace. He spoke and said, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, ye servants of the Most High God, come forth, and come here. Then Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego came for</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.27'>And the satraps, the deputies, and the governors, and the king's counselors, being gathered together, saw these men, that the fire had no power upon their bodies, nor was the hair of their head singed. Neither were their coats chan</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.28'>Nebuchadnezzar spoke and said, Blessed be the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, who has sent his [heavenly] agent, and delivered his servants who trusted in him, and have changed the king's word, and have yielded their bodies</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.29'>Therefore I make a decree, that every people, nation, and language, which speaks anything amiss against the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, shall be cut in pieces, and their houses shall be made a dunghill, because there is</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.30'>Then the king promoted Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego in the province of Babylon.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.4'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.1'>Nebuchadnezzar the king, to all the peoples, nations, and languages, who dwell in all the earth: Peace be multiplied to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.2'>It has seemed good to me to show the signs and wonders that the Most High God has wrought toward me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.3'>How great are his signs, and how mighty are his wonders! His kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and his dominion is from generation to generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.4'>I, Nebuchadnezzar, was at rest in my house, and flourishing in my palace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.5'>I saw a dream which made me afraid, and the thoughts upon my bed and the visions of my head troubled me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.6'>Therefore I made a decree to bring in all the wise men of Babylon before me, that they might make known to me the interpretation of the dream.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.7'>Then the magicians, the enchanters, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers came in, and I told the dream before them, but they did not make the interpretation of it known to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.8'>But at the last Daniel came in before me, whose name was Belteshazzar, according to the name of my god, and in whom is the spirit of the holy gods. And I told the dream before him, [saying],</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.9'>O Belteshazzar, master of the magicians, because I know that the spirit of the holy gods is in thee, and no secret troubles thee, tell me the visions of my dream that I have seen, and the interpretation thereof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.10'>Thus were the visions of my head upon my bed: I saw, and, behold, a tree in the midst of the earth, and the height of it was great.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.11'>The tree grew, and was strong, and the height of it reached to heaven, and the sight of it to the end of all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.12'>The leaves of it were fine, and the fruit of it much, and food was in it for all. The beasts of the field had shadow under it, and the birds of the heavens dwelt in the branches of it. And all flesh was fed from it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.13'>I saw in the visions of my head upon my bed, and, behold, a watcher and a holy one came down from heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.14'>He cried aloud, and said thus, Hew down the tree, and cut off its branches. Shake off its leaves, and scatter its fruit. Let the beasts get away from under it, and the fowls from its branches.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.15'>Nevertheless leave the stump of its roots in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the field. And let it be wet with the dew of heaven, and let his portion be with the beasts in the grass of the eart</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.16'>Let his heart be changed from man's, and let a beast's heart be given to him. And let seven times pass over him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.17'>The sentence is by the decree of the watchers, and the demand by the word of the holy ones, to the intent that the living may know that the Most High rules in the kingdom of men, and gives it to whomever he will, and sets up over i</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.18'>This dream I, king Nebuchadnezzar, have seen. And thou, O Belteshazzar, declare the interpretation, inasmuch as all the wise men of my kingdom are not able to make known to me the interpretation. But thou are able, for the spirit o</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.19'>Then Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, was stricken mute for a while, and his thoughts troubled him. The king answered and said, Belteshazzar, let not the dream, or the interpretation, trouble thee. Belteshazzar answered and sai</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.20'>The tree that thou saw, which grew, and was strong, whose height reached to heaven, and the sight of it to all the earth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.21'>whose leaves were fine, and the fruit of it much, and in it was food for all, under which the beasts of the field dwelt, and upon whose branches the birds of the heavens had their habitation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.22'>it is thou, O king, who have grown and become strong. For thy greatness has grown, and reaches to heaven, and thy dominion to the end of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.23'>And whereas the king saw a watcher and a holy one coming down from heaven, and saying, Hew down the tree, and destroy it. Nevertheless leave the stump of the roots of it in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tend</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.24'>This is the interpretation, O king, and it is the decree of the Most High, which has come upon my lord the king:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.25'>That thou shall be driven from men, and thy dwelling shall be with the beasts of the field. And thou shall be made to eat grass as oxen, and shall be wet with the dew of heaven. And seven times shall pass over thee till thou know t</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.26'>And whereas they commanded to leave the stump of the roots of the tree, thy kingdom shall be sure to thee, after thou shall have known that the heavens do rule.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.27'>Therefore, O king, let my counsel be acceptable to thee, and break off thy sins by righteousness, and thine iniquities by showing mercy to the poor, if there may be a lengthening of thy tranquility.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.28'>All this came upon the king Nebuchadnezzar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.29'>At the end of twelve months he was walking in the royal palace of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.30'>The king spoke and said, Is not this great Babylon, which I have built for the royal dwelling-place by the might of my power and for the glory of my majesty?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.31'>While the word was in the king's mouth, a voice from heaven fell, [saying], O king Nebuchadnezzar, to thee it is spoken: The kingdom is departed from thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.32'>And thou shall be driven from men, and thy dwelling shall be with the beasts of the field. Thou shall be made to eat grass as oxen, and seven times shall pass over thee, until thou know that the Most High rules in the kingdom of me</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.33'>The same hour the thing was fulfilled upon Nebuchadnezzar. And he was driven from men, and ate grass as oxen. And his body was wet with the dew of heaven, till his hair was grown like eagles' [feathers], and his nails like birds' [</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.34'>And at the end of the days I, Nebuchadnezzar, lifted up my eyes to heaven, and my understanding returned to me. And I blessed the Most High, and I praised and honored him who lives forever. For his dominion is an everlasting domini</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.35'>And all the inhabitants of the earth are reputed as nothing, and he does according to his will in the army of heaven, and among the inhabitants of the earth. And none can stay his hand, or say to him, What are thou doing?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.36'>At the same time my understanding returned to me, and for the glory of my kingdom, my majesty and brightness returned to me, and my counselors and my lords sought to me. And I was established in my kingdom, and excellent greatness</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.37'>Now I, Nebuchadnezzar, praise and extol and honor the King of heaven, for all his works are truth, and his ways justice. And he is able to abase those who walk in pride.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.5'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.1'>Belshazzar the king made a great feast for a thousand of his lords, and drank wine before the thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.2'>Belshazzar, while he tasted the wine, commanded to bring the golden and silver vessels which Nebuchadnezzar his father had taken out of the temple which was in Jerusalem, that the king and his lords, his wives and his concubines, m</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.3'>Then they brought the golden vessels that were taken out of the temple of the house of God which was at Jerusalem. And the king and his lords, his wives and his concubines, drank from them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.4'>They drank wine, and praised the gods of gold, and of silver, of brass, of iron, of wood, and of stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.5'>In the same hour the fingers of a man's hand came forth, and wrote opposite the candlestick upon the plaster of the wall of the king's palace. And the king saw the part of the hand that wrote.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.6'>Then the king's countenance was changed in him, and his thoughts troubled him. And the joints of his loins were loosed, and his knees smote one against another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.7'>The king cried aloud to bring in the enchanters, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers. The king spoke and said to the wise men of Babylon, Whoever shall read this writing, and show me the interpretation of it, shall be clothed with p</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.8'>Then all the king's wise men came in, but they could not read the writing, nor make known to the king the interpretation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.9'>Then king Belshazzar was greatly troubled, and his countenance was changed in him, and his lords were perplexed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.10'>[Now] the queen came into the banquet house because of the words of the king and his lords. The queen spoke and said, O king, live forever. Let not thy thoughts trouble thee, nor let thy countenance be changed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.11'>There is a man in thy kingdom, in whom is the spirit of the holy gods. And in the days of thy father light and understanding and wisdom, like the wisdom of the gods, were found in him. And the king Nebuchadnezzar thy father, the ki</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.12'>inasmuch as an excellent spirit, and knowledge, and understanding, interpreting of dreams, and showing of dark sentences, and dissolving of doubts, were found in the same Daniel, whom the king named Belteshazzar. Now let Daniel be</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.13'>Then Daniel was brought in before the king. The king spoke and said to Daniel, Are thou that Daniel, who are of the sons of the captivity of Judah, whom my father the king brought out of Judah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.14'>I have heard of thee, that the spirit of the gods is in thee, and that light and understanding and excellent wisdom are found in thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.15'>And now the wise men, the enchanters, have been brought in before me, that they should read this writing, and make known to me the interpretation of it, but they could not show the interpretation of the thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.16'>But I have heard of thee, that thou can give interpretations, and dissolve doubts. Now if thou can read the writing, and make known to me the interpretation of it, thou shall be clothed with purple, and have a chain of gold about t</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.17'>Then Daniel answered and said before the king, Let thy gifts be to thyself, and give thy rewards to another. Nevertheless I will read the writing to the king, and make known to him the interpretation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.18'>O thou king, the Most High God gave Nebuchadnezzar thy father the kingdom and greatness and glory and majesty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.19'>And because of the greatness that he gave him, all the peoples, nations, and languages trembled and feared before him. Whom he wanted, he killed, and whom he wanted, he kept alive, and whom he wanted, he raised up, and whom he want</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.20'>But when his heart was lifted up, and his spirit was hardened so that he dealt proudly, he was deposed from his kingly throne. And they took his glory from him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.21'>and he was driven from the sons of men. And his heart was made like the beasts', and his dwelling was with the wild donkeys. He was fed with grass like oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of heaven, until he knew that the Most</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.22'>And thou his son, O Belshazzar, have not humbled thy heart, though thou knew all this,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.23'>but have lifted up thyself against LORD of heaven. And they have brought the vessels of his house before thee, and thou and thy lords, thy wives and thy concubines, have drunk wine from them. And thou have praised the gods of silve</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.24'>Then the part of the hand was sent from before him, and this writing was inscribed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.25'>And this is the writing that was inscribed: MENE, MENE, TEKEL, UPHARSIN.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.26'>This is the interpretation of the thing: MENE, God has numbered thy kingdom, and brought it to an end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.27'>TEKEL, thou are weighed in the balances, and are found wanting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.28'>PERES, thy kingdom is divided, and given to the Medes and Persians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.29'>Then Belshazzar commanded, and they clothed Daniel with purple, and put a chain of gold about his neck, and made proclamation concerning him, that he should be the third ruler in the kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.30'>In that night Belshazzar the Chaldean King was slain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.31'>And Darius the Mede received the kingdom, being about sixty-two years old.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.6'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.1'>It pleased Darius to set over the kingdom a hundred and twenty satraps, who should be throughout the whole kingdom,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.2'>and over them three presidents, of whom Daniel was one, that these satraps might give account to them, and that the king should have no damage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.3'>Then this Daniel was distinguished above the presidents and the satraps, because an excellent spirit was in him, and the king thought to set him over the whole realm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.4'>Then the presidents and the satraps sought to find occasion against Daniel concerning the kingdom, but they could find no occasion nor fault, inasmuch as he was faithful, nor was there any error or fault found in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.5'>Then these men said, We shall not find any occasion against this Daniel unless we find it against him concerning the law of his God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.6'>Then these presidents and satraps assembled together to the king, and said thus to him: King Darius, live forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.7'>All the presidents of the kingdom, the deputies and the satraps, the counselors and the governors, have consulted together to establish a royal statute, and to make a strong interdict, that whoever shall ask a petition of any god o</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.8'>Now, O king, establish the interdict, and sign the writing, that it be not changed, according to the law of the Medes and Persians, which does not alter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.9'>Therefore king Darius signed the writing and the interdict.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.10'>And when Daniel knew that the writing was signed, he went into his house (now his windows were open in his chamber toward Jerusalem) and he knelt upon his knees three times a day, and prayed, and gave thanks before his God, as he d</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.11'>Then these men assembled together, and found Daniel making petition and supplication before his God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.12'>Then they came near, and spoke before the king concerning the king's interdict. Have thou not signed an interdict, that every man who shall make petition to any god or man within thirty days, except to thee, O king, shall be cast i</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.13'>Then they answered and said before the king, That Daniel, who is of the sons of the captivity of Judah, does not regard thee, O king, nor the interdict that thou have signed, but makes his petition three times a day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.14'>Then the king, when he heard these words, was very displeased, and set his heart on Daniel to deliver him. And he labored till the going down of the sun to rescue him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.15'>Then these men assembled together to the king, and said to the king, Know, O king, that it is a law of the Medes and Persians, that no interdict nor statute which the king establishes may be changed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.16'>Then the king commanded, and they brought Daniel, and cast him into the den of lions. [Now] the king spoke and said to Daniel, Thy God whom thou serve continually, he will deliver thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.17'>And a stone was brought, and laid upon the mouth of the den. And the king sealed it with his own signet, and with the signet of his lords, that nothing might be changed concerning Daniel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.18'>Then the king went to his palace, and passed the night fasting, nor were instruments of music brought before him. And his sleep fled from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.19'>Then the king arose very early in the morning, and went in haste to the den of lions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.20'>And when he came near to the den to Daniel, he cried with a lamentable voice. The king spoke and said to Daniel, O Daniel, servant of the living God, is thy God, whom thou serve continually, able to deliver thee from the lions?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.21'>Then Daniel said to the king, O king, live forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.22'>My God has sent his [heavenly] agent, and has shut the lions' mouths, and they have not hurt me, inasmuch as before him innocence was found in me. And also before thee, O king, I have done no harm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.23'>Then the king was exceedingly glad, and commanded that they should take Daniel up out of the den. So Daniel was taken up out of the den, and no manner of harm was found upon him, because he had trusted in his God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.24'>And the king commanded, and they brought those men who had accused Daniel, and they cast them into the den of lions, them, their sons, and their wives. And the lions had the mastery of them, and broke all their bones in pieces, bef</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.25'>Then king Darius wrote to all the peoples, nations, and languages, who dwell in all the earth: Peace be multiplied to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.26'>I make a decree, that in all the dominion of my kingdom men tremble and fear before the God of Daniel, for he is the living God, and steadfast forever. And his kingdom [is] that which shall not be destroyed, and his dominion shall</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.27'>He delivers and rescues, and he works signs and wonders in heaven and in earth, who has delivered Daniel from the power of the lions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.28'>So this Daniel prospered in the reign of Darius, and in the reign of Cyrus the Persian.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.7'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.1'>In the first year of Belshazzar king of Babylon, Daniel had a dream and visions of his head upon his bed. Then he wrote the dream and told the sum of the matters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.2'>Daniel spoke and said, I saw in my vision by night, and, behold, the four winds of heaven broke forth upon the great sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.3'>And four great beasts came up from the sea, different one from another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.4'>The first was like a lion, and had eagle's wings. I beheld till the wings of it were plucked, and it was lifted up from the earth, and made to stand upon two feet as a man, and a man's heart was given to it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.5'>And, behold, another beast, a second, like a bear, and it was raised up on one side, and three ribs were in its mouth between its teeth. And they said thus to it: Arise, devour much flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.6'>After this I beheld, and, lo, another, like a leopard, which had upon its back four wings of a bird. The beast also had four heads, and dominion was given to it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.7'>After this I saw in the night visions, and, behold, a fourth beast, fearful and powerful, and exceedingly strong. And it had great iron teeth. It devoured and broke in pieces, and stamped the residue with its feet. And it was diffe</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.8'>I considered the horns, and, behold, there came up among them another horn, a little one, before which three of the first horns were plucked up by the roots. And, behold, in this horn were eyes like the eyes of a man, and a mouth s</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.9'>I beheld till thrones were placed, and one who was ancient of days sat. His raiment was white as snow, and the hair of his head like pure wool. His throne was fiery flames, [and] the wheels of it burning fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.10'>A fiery stream issued and came forth from before him. Thousands of thousands ministered to him, and ten thousand times ten thousand stood before him. The judgment was set, and the books were opened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.11'>I beheld at that time because of the voice of the great words which the horn spoke. I beheld even till the beast was slain, and its body destroyed, and it was given to be burned with fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.12'>And as for the rest of the beasts, their dominion was taken away. Yet their lives were prolonged for a season and a time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.13'>I saw in the night visions, and, behold, there came with the clouds of heaven [somebody] like a son of man. And he came even to the ancient of days, and they brought him near before him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.14'>And there was given him dominion, and glory, and a kingdom, that all the peoples, nations, and languages should serve him. His dominion is an everlasting dominion, which shall not pass away, and his kingdom that which shall not be</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.15'>As for me, Daniel, my spirit was grieved in the midst of my body, and the visions of my head troubled me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.16'>I came near to one of those who stood by, and asked him the truth concerning all this. So he told me, and made me know the interpretation of the things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.17'>These great beasts, which are four, are four kings who shall arise out of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.18'>But the sanctified of the Most High shall receive the kingdom, and possess the kingdom forever, even forever and ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.19'>Then I desired to know the truth concerning the fourth beast, which was different from all of them, exceedingly fearful, whose teeth were of iron, and its nails of brass, which devoured, broke in pieces, and stamped the residue wit</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.20'>and concerning the ten horns that were on its head, and the other [horn] which came up, and before which three fell, even that horn that had eyes, and a mouth that spoke great things, whose look was greater than its fellows.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.21'>I beheld, and the same horn made war with the sanctified, and prevailed against them</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.22'>until the ancient of days came. And judgment was given to the sanctified of the Most High, and the time came that the sanctified possessed the kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.23'>Thus he said, The fourth beast shall be a fourth kingdom upon earth, which shall be different from all the kingdoms, and shall devour the whole earth, and shall tread it down, and break it in pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.24'>And as for the ten horns, out of this kingdom ten kings shall arise. And another shall arise after them, and he shall be different from the former. And he shall put down three kings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.25'>And he shall speak words against the Most High, and shall wear out the sanctified of the Most High. And he shall think to change the times and the law, and they shall be given into his hand until a time and times and half a time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.26'>But the judgment shall be set, and they shall take away his dominion, to consume and to destroy it to the end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.27'>And the kingdom and the dominion, and the greatness of the kingdoms under the whole heaven, shall be given to the people of the sanctified of the Most High. His kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and all dominions shall serve and o</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.28'>Here is the end of the matter. As for me, Daniel, my thoughts troubled me much, and my countenance was changed in me, but I kept the matter in my heart.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.8'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.1'>In the third year of the reign of king Belshazzar a vision appeared to me, even to me, Daniel, after that which appeared to me at the first.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.2'>And I saw in the vision, now it was so, that when I saw, I was in Shushan the palace, which is in the province of Elam, and I saw in the vision, and I was by the river Ulai.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.3'>Then I lifted up my eyes, and saw, and, behold, there stood before the river a ram which had two horns. And the two horns were high, but one was higher than the other, and the higher came up last.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.4'>I saw the ram pushing westward, and northward, and southward, and no beasts could stand before him, nor was there any that could deliver out of his hand, but he did according to his will, and magnified himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.5'>And as I was considering, behold, a he-goat came from the west over the face of the whole earth, and did not touch the ground. And the goat had a notable horn between his eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.6'>And he came to the ram that had the two horns, which I saw standing before the river, and ran upon him in the fury of his power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.7'>And I saw him come close to the ram. And he was moved with anger against him, and smote the ram, and broke his two horns. And there was no power in the ram to stand before him, but he cast him down to the ground, and trampled upon</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.8'>And the he-goat magnified himself exceedingly. And when he was strong, the great horn was broken, and instead of it there came up four notable [horns] toward the four winds of heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.9'>And out of one of them came forth a little horn, which grew exceedingly great, toward the south, and toward the east, and toward the glorious [land].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.10'>And it grew great, even to the host of heaven. And it cast down some of the host and of the stars to the ground, and trampled upon them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.11'>Yea, it magnified itself, even to the Prince of the host. And it took away from him the continual [burnt-offering], and the place of his sanctuary was cast down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.12'>And the host was given over [to it] together with the continual [burnt-offering] through transgression. And it cast down truth to the ground, and it did [its pleasure] and prospered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.13'>Then I heard a holy one speaking, and another holy one said to that certain one who spoke, How long shall be the vision [of] the continual [burnt-offering], and the transgression that make desolate, to give both the sanctuary and t</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.14'>And he said to me, To two thousand and three hundred evenings [and] mornings. Then the sanctuary shall be cleansed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.15'>And it came to pass, when I, even I Daniel, had seen the vision, that I sought to understand it, and, behold, there stood before me [someone] as the appearance of a man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.16'>And I heard a man's voice between [the banks of] the Ulai, which called, and said, Gabriel, make this man to understand the vision.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.17'>So he came near where I stood. And when he came, I was frightened, and fell upon my face. But he said to me, Understand, O son of man, for the vision belongs to the time of the end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.18'>Now as he was speaking with me, I fell into a deep sleep with my face toward the ground, but he touched me, and set me upright.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.19'>And he said, Behold, I will make thee know what shall be in the latter time of the indignation, for it belongs to the appointed time of the end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.20'>The ram which thou saw, that had the two horns, they are the kings of Media and Persia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.21'>And the rough he-goat is the king of Greece. And the great horn that is between his eyes is the first king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.22'>And as for that which was broken, in the place of which four stood up, four kingdoms shall stand up out of the nation, but not with his power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.23'>And in the latter time of their kingdom, when the transgressors have come to the full, a king of fierce countenance, and understanding hidden things, shall stand up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.24'>And his power shall be mighty, but not by his own power, and he shall destroy amazingly, and shall prosper and do [his pleasure]. And he shall destroy the mighty ones and the holy people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.25'>And through his policy he shall cause deceit to prosper in his hand, and he shall magnify himself in his heart. And he shall destroy many in [their] security. He shall also stand up against the Prince of princes, but he shall be br</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.26'>And the vision of the evenings and mornings which has been told is true. But shut thou up the vision, for it belongs to many days [to come].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.27'>And I, Daniel, fainted, and was sick certain days. Then I rose up, and did the king's business. And I wondered at the vision, but none understood it.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.9'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.1'>In the first year of Darius the son of Ahasuerus, of the seed of the Medes, who was made king over the realm of the Chaldeans,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.2'>in the first year of his reign, I, Daniel, understood by the books the number of the years of which the word of LORD came to Jeremiah the prophet, for the accomplishing of the desolations of Jerusalem, even seventy years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.3'>And I set my face to LORD God, to seek by prayer and supplications, with fasting and sackcloth and ashes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.4'>And I prayed to LORD my God, and made confession, and said, Oh, LORD, the great and fearful God, who keeps covenant and loving kindness with those who love him and keep his commandments,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.5'>we have sinned, and have dealt perversely, and have done wickedly, and have rebelled, even turning aside from thy precepts and from thine ordinances,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.6'>nor have we hearkened to thy servants the prophets, who spoke in thy name to our kings, our rulers, and our fathers, and to all the people of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.7'>O LORD, righteousness belongs to thee, but to us confusion of face, as at this day, to the men of Judah, and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and to all Israel, who are near, and who are far off, through all the countries where tho</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.8'>O LORD, to us belongs confusion of face, to our kings, to our rulers, and to our fathers, because we have sinned against thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.9'>To LORD our God belong mercies and forgiveness, for we have rebelled against him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.10'>nor have we obeyed the voice of LORD our God, to walk in his laws, which he set before us by his servants the prophets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.11'>Yea, all Israel have transgressed thy law, even turning aside, that they should not obey thy voice. Therefore the curse has been poured out upon us, and the oath that is written in the law of Moses the servant of God. For we have s</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.12'>And he has confirmed his words, which he spoke against us, and against our judges who judged us, by bringing upon us a great evil, for under the whole heaven has not been done as has been done upon Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.13'>As it is written in the law of Moses, all this evil has come upon us. Yet we have not entreated the favor of LORD our God, that we should turn from our iniquities, and have discernment in thy truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.14'>Therefore LORD has watched over the evil, and brought it upon us, for LORD our God is righteous in all his works which he does, and we have not obeyed his voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.15'>And now, O LORD our God, who has brought thy people forth out of the land of Egypt with a mighty hand, and has gotten thee renown, as at this day, we have sinned, we have done wickedly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.16'>O LORD, according to all thy righteousness, let thine anger and thy wrath, I pray thee, be turned away from thy city Jerusalem, thy holy mountain. Because for our sins, and for the iniquities of our fathers, Jerusalem and thy peopl</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.17'>Now therefore, O our God, hearken to the prayer of thy servant, and to his supplications, and cause thy face to shine upon thy sanctuary that is desolate, for LORD's sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.18'>O my God, incline thine ear, and hear. Open thine eyes, and behold our desolations, and the city which is called by thy name. For we do not present our supplications before thee for our righteousness, but for thy great mercies' sak</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.19'>O LORD, hear. O LORD, forgive. O LORD, hearken and do. Defer not, for thine own sake, O my God, because thy city and thy people are called by thy name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.20'>And while I was speaking, and praying, and confessing my sin and the sin of my people Israel, and presenting my supplication before LORD my God for the holy mountain of my God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.21'>yea, while I was speaking in prayer, the man Gabriel, whom I had seen in the vision at the beginning, being caused to fly swiftly, touched me about the time of the evening oblation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.22'>And he instructed me, and talked with me, and said, O Daniel, I have now come forth to give thee wisdom and understanding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.23'>At the beginning of thy supplications the commandment went forth, and I have come to tell thee, for thou are greatly beloved. Therefore consider the matter, and understand the vision.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.24'>Seventy weeks are decreed upon thy people and upon thy holy city, to finish transgression, and to make an end of sins, and to make reconciliation for iniquity, and to bring in everlasting righteousness, and to seal up vision and pr</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.25'>Know therefore and discern, that from the going forth of the commandment to restore and to build Jerusalem to the anointed one, the Prince, shall be seven weeks, and sixty-two weeks. It shall be built again, with street and moat, e</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.26'>And after the sixty-two weeks the anointed one shall be cut off, and shall have nothing. And the people of the prince who shall come shall destroy the city and the sanctuary, and the end of it shall be with a flood. And even to the</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.27'>And he shall make a firm covenant with many for one week. And in the midst of the week he shall cause the sacrifice and the oblation to cease. And upon the wing of abominations [shall come] one who makes desolate. And even to the f</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.10'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.1'>In the third year of Cyrus king of Persia a thing was revealed to Daniel, whose name was called Belteshazzar, and the thing was true, even a great warfare. And he understood the thing, and had understanding of the vision.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.2'>In those days I, Daniel, was mourning three whole weeks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.3'>I ate no pleasant bread. Neither flesh nor wine came into my mouth. Neither did I anoint myself at all, till three whole weeks were fulfilled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.4'>And in the twenty-fourth day of the first month, as I was by the side of the great river, which is Hiddekel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.5'>I lifted up my eyes, and looked. And, behold, a man clothed in linen, whose loins were girded with pure gold of Uphaz.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.6'>Also his body was like the beryl, and his face as the appearance of lightning, and his eyes as flaming torches, and his arms and his feet like burnished brass, and the voice of his words like the voice of a multitude.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.7'>And I, Daniel, alone saw the vision, for the men who were with me did not see the vision, but a great quaking fell upon them, and they fled to hide themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.8'>So I was left alone, and saw this great vision. And there remained no strength in me, for my fitness was turned in me into debility, and I retained no strength.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.9'>Yet I heard the voice of his words. And when I heard the voice of his words, then I fell into a deep sleep on my face, with my face toward the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.10'>And, behold, a hand touched me, which set me upon my knees and upon the palms of my hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.11'>And he said to me, O Daniel, thou man greatly beloved, understand the words that I speak to thee, and stand upright, for I am now sent to thee. And when he had spoken this word to me, I stood, trembling.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.12'>Then he said to me, Fear not, Daniel, for from the first day that thou set thy heart to understand, and to humble thyself before thy God, thy words were heard. And I have come for thy words' sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.13'>But the ruler of the kingdom of Persia withstood me twenty-one days, but, lo, Michael, one of the chief princes, came to help me. And I remained there with the kings of Persia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.14'>I have come now to make thee understand what shall befall thy people in the latter days, for the vision is yet for [many] days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.15'>And when he had spoken to me according to these words, I set my face toward the ground, and was mute.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.16'>And, behold, somebody in the likeness of the sons of men touched my lips. Then I opened my mouth, and spoke and said to him who stood before me, O my lord, because of the vision my pains have turned upon me, and I retain no strengt</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.17'>For how can the servant of this my lord talk with this my lord? For as for me, straightaway there remained no strength in me, nor was there breath left in me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.18'>Then somebody like the appearance of a man touched me again, and he strengthened me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.19'>And he said, O man greatly beloved, fear not. Peace be to thee. Be strong, yea, be strong. And when he spoke to me, I was strengthened, and said, Let my lord speak, for thou have strengthened me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.20'>Then he said, Do thou know why I have come to thee? And now I will return to fight with the ruler of Persia. And when I go forth, lo, the ruler of Greece shall come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.21'>But I will tell thee that which is inscribed in the writing of truth. And there is none who holds with me against these, but Michael your prince.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.11'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.1'>And as for me, in the first year of Darius the Mede, I stood up to confirm and strengthen him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.2'>And now I will show thee the truth. Behold, there shall stand up yet three kings in Persia, and the fourth shall be far richer than them all. And when he has grown strong through his riches, he shall stir up all against the realm o</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.3'>And a mighty king shall stand up, who shall rule with great dominion, and do according to his will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.4'>And when he shall stand up, his kingdom shall be broken, and shall be divided toward the four winds of heaven, but not to his posterity, nor according to his dominion with which he ruled, for his kingdom shall be plucked up, even f</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.5'>And the king of the south shall be strong, and [one] of his rulers. And he shall be powerful over him, and have dominion. His dominion shall be a great dominion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.6'>And at the end of years they shall join themselves together. And the daughter of the king of the south shall come to the king of the north to make an agreement, but she shall not retain the strength of her arm, nor shall he stand,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.7'>But out of a shoot from her roots shall [a man] stand up in his place, who shall come to the army, and shall enter into the fortress of the king of the north, and shall deal against them, and shall prevail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.8'>And also their gods, with their molten images, [and] with their goodly vessels of silver and of gold, he shall carry captive into Egypt, and he shall refrain from the king of the north some years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.9'>And he shall come into the realm of the king of the south, but he shall return into his own land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.10'>And his sons shall war, and shall assemble a multitude of great forces, which shall come on, and overflow, and pass through. And they shall return and war, even to his fortress.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.11'>And the king of the south shall be moved with anger, and shall come forth and fight with him, even with the king of the north. And he shall set forth a great multitude, and the multitude shall be given into his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.12'>And the multitude shall be lifted up, and his heart shall be exalted. And he shall cast down tens of thousands, but he shall not prevail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.13'>And the king of the north shall return, and shall set forth a multitude greater than the former, and he shall come on at the end of the times, [even of] years, with a great army and with much substance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.14'>And in those times many shall stand up against the king of the south. Also the sons of the violent among thy people shall lift themselves up to establish the vision, but they shall fall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.15'>So the king of the north shall come, and cast up a mound, and take a well-fortified city. And the forces of the south shall not stand, nor his chosen people. Neither shall there be any strength to stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.16'>But he who comes against him shall do according to his own will, and none shall stand before him. And he shall stand in the glorious land, and in his hand shall be destruction.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.17'>And he shall set his face to come with the strength of his whole kingdom, and with him equitable conditions, and he shall perform them. And he shall give him the daughter of women, to corrupt her, but she shall not stand, nor be fo</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.18'>After this he shall turn his face to the isles, and shall take many. But a ruler shall cause the reproach offered by him to cease. Yea, moreover, he shall cause his reproach to turn upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.19'>Then he shall turn his face toward the fortresses of his own land, but he shall stumble and fall, and shall not be found.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.20'>Then somebody shall stand up in his place who shall cause an exactor to pass through the glory of the kingdom, but within a few days he shall be destroyed, neither in anger, nor in battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.21'>And in his place he who is contemptible shall stand up, to whom they had not given the honor of the kingdom. But he shall come in time of security, and shall obtain the kingdom by flatteries.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.22'>And the overwhelming forces shall be overwhelmed from before him, and shall be broken, yea, also the ruler of the covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.23'>And after the league made with him, he shall work deceitfully, for he shall come up, and shall become strong, with a small people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.24'>He shall come in time of security even upon the fattest places of the province, and he shall do that which his fathers have not done, nor his fathers' fathers. He shall scatter among them prey, and spoil, and substance. Yea, he sha</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.25'>And he shall stir up his power and his courage against the king of the south with a great army. And the king of the south shall war in battle with a very great and mighty army, but he shall not stand, for they shall devise devices</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.26'>Yea, those who eat of his food shall destroy him, and his army shall overflow, and many shall fall down slain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.27'>And as for both these kings, their hearts shall be to do mischief, and they shall speak lies at one table. But it shall not prosper, for yet the end shall be at the time appointed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.28'>Then he shall return into his land with great substance. And his heart [shall be] against the holy covenant, and he shall do [his pleasure], and return to his own land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.29'>At the time appointed he shall return, and come into the south, but it shall not be in the latter time as it was in the former.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.30'>For ships of Kittim shall come against him. Therefore he shall be grieved, and shall return, and have indignation against the holy covenant, and shall do [his pleasure]. He shall even return, and have regard to those who forsake th</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.31'>And forces shall stand on his part, and they shall profane the sanctuary, even the fortress, and shall take away the continual [burnt-offering], and they shall set up the abomination that makes desolate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.32'>And he shall pervert by flatteries such as do wickedly against the covenant. But the people who know their God shall be strong, and do [exploits].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.33'>And those who are wise among the people shall instruct many, yet they shall fall by the sword and by flame, by captivity and by spoil, [many] days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.34'>Now when they shall fall, they shall be helped with a little help, but many shall join themselves to them with flatteries.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.35'>And some of those who are wise shall fall, to refine them, and to purify, and to make them white, even to the time of the end, because it is yet for the time appointed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.36'>And the king shall do according to his will. And he shall exalt himself, and magnify himself above every god, and shall speak marvelous things against the God of gods. And he shall prosper till the indignation be accomplished, for</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.37'>Neither shall he regard the gods of his fathers, nor the desire of women, nor regard any god, for he shall magnify himself above all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.38'>But in his place he shall honor the god of fortresses. And a god whom his fathers did not know, he shall honor with gold, and silver, and with precious stones, and pleasant things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.39'>And he shall deal with the strongest fortresses by the help of a foreign god. Whoever acknowledges [him] he will increase with glory, and he shall cause them to rule over many, and shall divide the land for a price.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.40'>And at the time of the end, the king of the south shall contend with him, and the king of the north shall come against him like a whirlwind, with chariots, and with horsemen, and with many ships, and he shall enter into the countri</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.41'>He shall also enter into the glorious land, and many [countries] shall be overthrown. But these shall be delivered out of his hand: Edom, and Moab, and the chief of the sons of Ammon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.42'>He shall stretch forth his hand also upon the countries, and the land of Egypt shall not escape.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.43'>But he shall have power over the treasures of gold and of silver, and over all the precious things of Egypt. And the Libyans and the Ethiopians shall be at his steps.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.44'>But news out of the east and out of the north shall trouble him, and he shall go forth with great fury to destroy and to utterly sweep away many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.45'>And he shall plant the tents of his palace between the sea and the glorious holy mountain, yet he shall come to his end, and none shall help him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.12'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.1'>And at that time Michael shall stand up, the great prince who stands for the sons of thy people. And there shall be a time of trouble, such as never was since there was a nation even to that same time. And at that time thy people s</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.2'>And many of those who sleep in the dust of the earth shall awake, some to everlasting life, and some to shame and everlasting contempt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.3'>And those who are wise shall shine as the brightness of the firmament, and those who turn many to righteousness as the stars forever and ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.4'>But thou, O Daniel, shut up the words, and seal the book, even to the time of the end. Many shall run to and fro, and knowledge shall be increased.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.5'>Then I, Daniel, looked, and, behold, another two stood, the one on the brink of the river on this side, and the other on the brink of the river on that side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.6'>And one said to the man clothed in linen, who was above the waters of the river, How long shall it be to the end of these wonders?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.7'>And I heard the man clothed in linen, who was above the waters of the river, when he held up his right hand and his left hand to heaven, and swore by him who lives forever that it shall be for a time, times, and a half. And when th</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.8'>And I heard, but I did not understand. Then I said, O my lord, what shall be the outcome of these things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.9'>And he said, Go thy way, Daniel, for the words are shut up and sealed till the time of the end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.10'>Many shall purify themselves, and make themselves white, and be refined, but the wicked shall do wickedly. And none of the wicked shall understand, but those who are wise shall understand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.11'>And from the time that the continual [burnt-offering] shall be taken away, and the abomination that makes desolate is set up, there shall be a thousand and two hundred and ninety days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.12'>Blessed is he who waits, and comes to the thousand three hundred and thirty-five days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.13'>But go thou thy way till the end is. For thou shall rest, and shall stand in thy lot at the end of the days.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>