<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='ACV' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='ACV'>
        <title>A Conservative Version</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description/>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>ACV</identifier>
        <source>http://www.e-sword.net/usermods/</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage/>
        <rights>www.stillvoices.org</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Eph'>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.1'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.1'>Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ through the will of God, to the sanctified who are at Ephesus, and faithful in Christ Jesus:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.2'>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.3'>Blessed is the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who has blessed us with every spiritual blessing in the heavenly things in Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.4'>Just as he chose us in him before the foundation of the world, for us to be holy and unblemished before him in love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.5'>Who predestined us for sonship through Jesus Christ for himself, according to the desire of his will,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.6'>for appreciation of the glory of his grace, by which he blessed us in him who is beloved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.7'>In whom we have redemption through his blood, the forgiveness of transgressions, according to the wealth of his grace,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.8'>which he abounded for us in all wisdom and intelligence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.9'>Having made known to us the mystery of his will according to his desire, which he purposed within himself</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.10'>for an administration of the fullness of the times. To gather together all things in the Christ, things in the heavens and things upon the earth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.11'>in him in whom also we obtained an inheritance. Having been predestined according to the purpose of him who works all things according to the deliberation of his will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.12'>For us to be for appreciation of his glory, men who have first hoped in the Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.13'>In whom ye also, having heard the word of the truth, the good-news of your salvation, in whom also having believed, ye were sealed with the Holy Spirit of the promise,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.14'>which is a pledge of our inheritance for the redemption of the acquired possession, for appreciation of his glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.15'>Because of this I also, having heard of your faith in the Lord Jesus, and love for all the sanctified,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.16'>I cease not expressing thanks for you, making remembrance of you in my prayers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.17'>So that the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of glory, may give you a spirit of wisdom and revelation in knowledge of him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.18'>having the eyes of your heart enlightened. For you to know what is the hope of his calling, and what is the wealth of the glory of his inheritance in the sanctified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.19'>And what is the transcending greatness of his power toward us who believe, according to the working of the dominion of his might,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.20'>which he wrought in the Christ, having raised him from the dead and seated at his right hand in the heavenly things,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.21'>far above every principle office, and position of authority, and power, and lordship, and every name that is named, not only in this age, but also in that which is coming.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.22'>And he subordinated all things under his feet, and appointed him head over all things for the church,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.23'>which is his body, the fulfillment of him who fills all in all.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.2'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.1'>Even you, who were dead in trespasses and sins</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.2'>in which ye once walked according to the era of this world, according to the ruler of the power of the air, the spirit that now works in the sons of disobedience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.3'>Among whom we also all once behaved in the lusts of our flesh, doing the intentions of the flesh and of the thoughts, and were by nature children of wrath as also the others.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.4'>But God, being rich in mercy, through his great love that he loved us,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.5'>even us being dead in the transgressions, he made alive together with the Christ (ye are saved by grace),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.6'>and raised us up together, and seated us together in the heavenly things in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.7'>So that in the coming ages he might show the transcending wealth of his grace in kindness toward us in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.8'>For ye are saved by grace through faith, and this a gift of God, not from you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.9'>not from works, so that not any man may boast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.10'>For we are his workmanship, created in Christ Jesus for good works, which God preordained that we should walk in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.11'>Remember therefore that once ye, the Gentiles in flesh, who are called uncircumcision by that which is called circumcision (in flesh, made by hands),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.12'>that ye were at that time independent of Christ, alienated from the citizenship of Israel, and alien of the covenants of the promise, having no hope and godless in the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.13'>But now in Christ Jesus ye, being formerly far off, became near in the blood of the Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.14'>For he is our peace, who made both one, and broke down the dividing wall of partition,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.15'>having abolished in his flesh the enmity--the law of the commandments in ordinances--so that he might create in himself the two into one new man, making peace,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.16'>and might reconcile them both in one body to God through the cross, having slain the enmity by it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.17'>And after coming he preached good-news, peace to you, to those far off and to those near,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.18'>because through him we both have the access in one Spirit to the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.19'>So then ye are no more alien and foreign, but fellow citizens of the sanctified, and belonging to the household of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.20'>Which was built upon the foundation of the apostles and prophets, Christ Jesus himself being the chief corner,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.21'>in whom the whole building joined together grows into a holy temple in Lord,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.22'>in whom ye also are built together in Spirit into a habitation of God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.3'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.1'>For this reason I Paul, the prisoner of Christ Jesus on behalf of you Gentiles,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.2'>since indeed ye heard of the administration of the grace of God, which was given to me for you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.3'>that according to revelation he made known to me the mystery, as I wrote before in brief.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.4'>With which reading ye can recognize my understanding in the mystery of the Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.5'>which in other generations was not made known to the sons of men, as it has now been revealed by Spirit to his holy apostles and prophets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.6'>For Gentiles to be fellow-heirs, and of the same body, and fellow partakers of his promise in the Christ through the good-news.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.7'>Of which I became a helper according to the gift of that grace of God, which was given to me according to the working of his power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.8'>To me, a man less than the least of all the sanctified, this grace was given to preach good-news among the Gentiles, the unsearchable wealth of Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.9'>and to make all men see what is the administration of the mystery hidden from the ages in God who created all things through Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.10'>So that now the manifold wisdom of God might be made known to the principal offices and the positions of authority in the heavenly things, through the church,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.11'>according to the purpose of the ages, which he made in Christ Jesus our Lord,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.12'>in whom we have boldness and access in confidence through his faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.13'>Therefore I ask that ye not become discouraged at my tribulations on your behalf, which is your glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.14'>For this reason I bow my knees to the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.15'>from whom every patriarchy in heavens and on earth is named.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.16'>So that he would grant you, according to the wealth of his glory, to be strengthened with power through his Spirit for the inner man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.17'>For the Christ to dwell in your hearts through faith,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.18'>having been rooted and grounded in love, so that ye may be able to grasp with all the sanctified what is the breadth and length and depth and height,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.19'>and to become aware of the love of the Christ, which transcends knowledge, so that ye may be filled in all the fullness of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.20'>Now to him who is able to do above extraordinary--above all things that we ask or think--according to the power that works in us,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.21'>to him is the glory in the church in Christ Jesus for all generations of the age of the ages. Truly.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.4'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.1'>I therefore, the prisoner in Lord, call on you to walk worthily of the calling in which ye were called,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.2'>with all humility and mildness, with longsuffering, forbearing each other in love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.3'>Endeavoring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.4'>one body, and one Spirit. Just as also ye were called in one hope of your calling,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.5'>one Lord, one faith, one immersion,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.6'>one God and Father of all. He is over all, and through all, and in us all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.7'>But the grace was given to each of us, according to the measure of the gift of the Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.8'>Therefore he says, Having ascended on high, he led captivity captive, and gave gifts to men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.9'>And what is the ascended, except that he also first descended into the lower parts of the earth?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.10'>He who descended is also the same man who ascended high above all the heavens, so that he might fill all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.11'>And indeed he gave the apostles, and the prophets, and the evangelists, and the shepherds and teachers</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.12'>for the perfecting of the sanctified, for the work of ministry, for edification of the body of the Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.13'>Until we all attain to the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, to a perfect man, to a standard of stature of the fullness of the Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.14'>So that we may no longer be childish, tossed about and carried about by every wind of doctrine by the trickery of men in craftiness with the methodology of error.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.15'>But being truthful in love, we may cause all things to grow for him who is the head--the Christ--</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.16'>from whom the whole body, joined together and united together through every connection of the supply, according to the working of each one part within a standard, makes the growth of the body for the construction of itself by love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.17'>This I say therefore, and solemnly declare in Lord, for you to walk no longer as also the other Gentiles walk, in the vanity of their mind,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.18'>darkened in their understanding, alienated from the life of God through the ignorance that is in them, because of the callousness of their heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.19'>Who, having become callous, gave themselves over to licentiousness for the work of all uncleanness in greed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.20'>But ye did not so learn the Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.21'>if indeed ye heard him, and were taught in him, as truth is in Jesus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.22'>for you to put off the old man according to your former conduct, the man who is corrupt according to the desires of deceitfulness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.23'>and to be renewed in the spirit of your mind,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.24'>and to put on the new man according to God, the man who was created in righteousness and piety of the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.25'>Therefore having put off falsehood, let each man speak truth with his neighbor, because we are body-parts of each other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.26'>Be ye angry, and sin not. Let not the sun go down upon your wrath,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.27'>neither give place to the devil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.28'>Let the man who steals steal no more, but rather let him labor, working with his hands the good, so that he may have to give to him who has need.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.29'>Let no corrupt speech go out of your mouth, rather if there is any good word for edification of a need, so that it may give grace to those who hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.30'>And do not grieve the Holy Spirit of God, in which ye are sealed for a day of redemption.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.31'>Let all bitterness, and wrath, and anger, and clamor, and reviling be taken away from you, with all evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.32'>And become good toward each other, compassionate, forgiving each other, even as also God in Christ forgave us.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.5'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.1'>Become ye therefore imitators of God, as beloved children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.2'>And walk in love, as also the Christ loved us, and delivered himself up for us, an offering and a sacrifice to God for a fragrant aroma.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.3'>But fornication, and all uncleanness, or greed, shall not even be named among you as befits the sanctified,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.4'>also indecency, and foolish talking or jesting, things not befitting, but thankfulness instead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.5'>For ye are men who know this, that no fornicator, or unclean man, or covetous man, who is an idolater, has any inheritance in the kingdom of the Christ and God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.6'>Let no man deceive you by empty words, for because of these things the wrath of God comes upon the sons of disobedience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.7'>Do not become ye therefore partakers with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.8'>For ye were once darkness, but now light in Lord. Walk as children of light</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.9'>(for the fruit of the spirit is in all goodness and righteousness and truth),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.10'>proving what is acceptable to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.11'>And do not associate with the unfruitful works of darkness, but instead even rebuke them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.12'>For it is disgusting even to speak of the things happening by them secretly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.13'>But all things exposed are revealed by the light, for everything that is seen is light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.14'>Therefore he says, Awake, thou who sleep. And arise from the dead, and the Christ will shine upon thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.15'>Therefore watch carefully how ye walk, not as unwise but as wise,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.16'>redeeming the time, because the days are evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.17'>Because of this do not become foolish, but understanding what is the will of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.18'>And do not become intoxicated with wine, during which is debauchery, but be filled in Spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.19'>speaking to yourselves in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing and striking strings in your heart to the Lord,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.20'>expressing thanks always for all things in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ to the God and Father,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.21'>submitting yourselves to each other in the fear of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.22'>Wives, submit to your own husbands as to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.23'>Because a husband is head of the wife, as also Christ is head of the church, and himself the savior of the body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.24'>But as the church is subject to the Christ, so also the wives to their own husbands in everything.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.25'>Husbands, love your own wives even as Christ also loved the church, and delivered himself up for it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.26'>so that he might sanctify it, having cleansed it with the washing of water by the word,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.27'>so that he might present it to himself, the glorious church, not having spot or wrinkle or any such thing, but that it should be holy and unblemished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.28'>So ought the husbands to love their own wives as their own bodies. He who loves his own wife loves himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.29'>For no man ever hated his own flesh, but nourishes and cherishes it, just as also Christ the church,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.30'>because we are parts of his body, of his flesh and of his bones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.31'>Separate from this a man will leave his father and mother behind, and will be bonded with his wife, and the two will be in one flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.32'>This mystery is great, but I speak for Christ and for the church.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.33'>Nevertheless ye also, each one in particular, shall so love his own wife as himself, and the wife that she fear her husband.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.6'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.1'>Children, obey your parents in Lord, for this is right.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.2'>Honor thy father and mother, which is the first commandment with promise,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.3'>so that it may become well with thee, and thou will be long lasting on the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.4'>And ye fathers, do not exasperate your children, but rear them in the training and admonition of Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.5'>Bondmen, be obedient to the masters according to flesh, with fear and trembling, in simplicity of your heart as to the Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.6'>Not according to eye-service, as men-pleasers, but as bondmen of Christ, doing the will of God from the soul,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.7'>bond-serving with goodwill, as to the Lord and not to men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.8'>Knowing that whatever good thing each may do, he will receive this from the Lord, whether bondman or freeman.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.9'>And ye masters, do the same things to them, easing up the threats, knowing also that the master of you yourselves is in the heavens, and there is no partiality from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.10'>Finally my brothers, be strong in Lord and in the power of his might.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.11'>Put on the full armor of God to enable you to stand against the wiles of the devil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.12'>Because our wrestling is not against flesh and blood, but against the principal offices, against the positions of authority, against the world-rulers of the darkness of this age, against the spiritual things of wickedness in the he</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.13'>Because of this take ye up the full armor of God, so that ye may be able to withstand in the evil day, and having done all, to stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.14'>Stand ye therefore having girded your loins with truth, and having put on the breastplate of righteousness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.15'>and having shod your feet in preparation of the good-news of peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.16'>Above all having taken up the shield of faith, by which ye will be able to quench all the fiery darts of evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.17'>And take the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.18'>praying through every prayer and entreaty at every time in spirit, and being alert in this same thing in all perseverance and entreaty for all the sanctified,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.19'>and for me, so that utterance may be given to me in boldness in opening my mouth to make known the mystery of the good-news,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.20'>for which I am an ambassador in bondage, so that in it I may speak boldly, as I ought to speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.21'>But that ye also may know the things concerning me, what I do, Tychicus, the beloved brother and faithful helper in Lord, will make known all things to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.22'>Whom I sent to you for this same thing, so that ye might know the things about us, and that he might encourage your hearts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.23'>Peace to the brothers, and love with faith from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.24'>The grace is with all those who love our Lord Jesus Christ with incorruptibility. Truly.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>