<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='ACV' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='ACV'>
        <title>A Conservative Version</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description/>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>ACV</identifier>
        <source>http://www.e-sword.net/usermods/</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage/>
        <rights>www.stillvoices.org</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Heb'>
      <chapter osisID='Heb.1'>
        <verse osisID='Heb.1.1'>God, who formerly spoke in many portions and in many ways to the fathers by the prophets, spoke to us in these last days by a Son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.1.2'>whom he appointed heir of all things, through whom also he made the ages.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.1.3'>Who, being the radiance of his glory, and the exact image of his essence, and upholding all things by the word of his power, having made purification of our sins through himself, he sat down at the right hand of the Majesty in the</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.1.4'>Having become so much better than the heavenly agents, as he has inherited a more excellent name than they.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.1.5'>For to which of the heavenly agents did he ever say, Thou are my Son, today I have begotten thee? And again, I will be to him for a Father, and he will be to me for a Son?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.1.6'>And again when he brings the firstborn into the world he says, And let all the agents of God worship him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.1.7'>And indeed toward the heavenly agents he says, He who makes his agents spirits, and his ministers a flame of fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.1.8'>But toward the Son, Thy throne, O God, is into the age of the age. The scepter of thy kingdom is a scepter of straightness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.1.9'>Thou have loved righteousness and hated lawlessness. Because of this, God, thy God, anointed thee with the oil of gladness above thy companions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.1.10'>And thou, Lord, at the beginnings founded the earth, and the heavens are the works of thy hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.1.11'>They will perish, but thou are permanent. And they will all become old as a garment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.1.12'>And thou will roll them up as a mantle, and they will be changed. But thou are the same, and thy years will not cease.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.1.13'>But to which of the heavenly agents has he ever said, Sit thou by my right hand until I place thine enemies a footstool of thy feet?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.1.14'>Are they not all ministering spirits sent forth for service for the sake of those who are going to inherit salvation?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Heb.2'>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.1'>Because of this we ought to give more earnest heed to the things that were heard, lest we might slip away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.2'>For if the word spoken through heavenly agents became certain, and every transgression and disobedience received a just recompense of reward,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.3'>how will we escape, having neglected so great a salvation? Which first, having taken to be spoken by the Lord, was verified for us by those who heard;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.4'>God also testifying simultaneously by signs and wonders, and by various powers and distributions of Holy Spirit according to his will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.5'>For he did not subject the coming world to heavenly agents, about which we speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.6'>But a certain man has somewhere testified, saying, What is man, that thou remember him? Or a son of man, that thou help him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.7'>Thou made him a little something less than the heavenly agents. Thou crowned him with glory and honor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.8'>Thou subordinated all things under his feet. For in subordinating all things to him, he left nothing not subordinate to him. But now we do not yet see all things subordinated to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.9'>But we see Jesus who has been made a little something less than the heavenly agents, who, because of the suffering of death, has been crowned with glory and honor, so that by the grace of God he would taste of death for every man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.10'>For it was fitting for him, through whom are all things, and because of whom are all things, having brought many sons to glory, to make the pathfinder of their salvation fully perfect through sufferings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.11'>For both he who sanctifies and those being sanctified are all of one, because of which reason he is not ashamed to call them brothers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.12'>saying, I will declare thy name to my brothers. In the midst of the congregation I will sing praise to thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.13'>And again, I will be a man who has trusted in him. And again, Behold, I and the children that God has given me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.14'>Since therefore the children have partaken of flesh and blood, he also himself likewise shared the same things, so that through death he might make him who has the power of death impotent, that is, the devil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.15'>And he might liberate these, as many as throughout all their lifetime were deserving of bondage, with a specter of death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.16'>For he certainly did not embrace heavenly agents, but he embraced the seed of Abraham.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.17'>Therefore he was obligated to be made like his brothers in accordance with all things, so that he might become a merciful and faithful high priest in things toward God, in order to make reconciliation for the sins of the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.2.18'>For in that he himself has suffered, having been tempted, he is able to help those being tempted.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Heb.3'>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.1'>Because of which, holy brothers, companions of a heavenly calling, consider the Apostle and High Priest of our affirmation, Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.2'>who was faithful to him who appointed him, as also was Moses in all his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.3'>For this man was considered worthy of more glory than Moses, by so much as he who built it has more esteem than the house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.4'>For every house is built by some man, but he who built all things is God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.5'>And Moses was indeed faithful in all his house as a servant, for a testimony of the things that were going to be spoken,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.6'>but Christ as a Son over his house, whose house we are, if only we keep in possession our confidence and pride of hope, firm until the end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.7'>Therefore, as the Holy Spirit says, Today if ye hear his voice,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.8'>do not harden your hearts as in the rebellion, according to the day of the trial in the wilderness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.9'>where your fathers challenged me, tested me, and saw my works forty years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.10'>Therefore I was angry with that generation, and said, They are always led astray in their heart, and they did not know my ways.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.11'>So I swore in my wrath, They will not enter into my rest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.12'>Watch, brothers, lest there will be in any of you an evil heart of unbelief in withdrawing from the living God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.13'>But exhort each other during each day, while it is called Today, lest any of you may be hardened by the deceitfulness of sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.14'>For we have become companions of the Christ, if only we keep in possession the primacy of the essence, steadfast until the end,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.15'>while it is said, Today if ye will hear his voice, do not harden your hearts as in the rebellion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.16'>For some who heard rebelled, but not all those who came out of Egypt by Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.17'>But with whom was he angry forty years? Was it not with those who sinned, whose carcasses fell in the wilderness?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.18'>And to whom did he swear were not going to enter into his rest, if not to those who were disobedient?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.3.19'>And we see that they were not able to enter in because of unbelief.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Heb.4'>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.1'>Let us be afraid therefore, lest, a promise being left behind to enter into his rest, any of you should seem to have come short.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.2'>For we also are having good-news preached, just as also those men, but the word of hearing did not benefit those men, not having been mixed together with faith in those who heard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.3'>For those who believe enter into that rest, just as he said, So I swore in my wrath, They will not enter into my rest, although the works occurred from the foundation of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.4'>For he spoke somewhere about the seventh this way, And God rested during the seventh day from all his works,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.5'>and in this again, They will not enter into my rest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.6'>Since therefore it remains for some to enter into it, and those who formerly had good-news did not enter because of disobedience,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.7'>again he appoints a certain day, Today, saying in David after so long a time (as it is said), Today if ye will hear his voice, do not harden your hearts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.8'>For if Joshua had given them rest, he would not have spoken about another day after these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.9'>There remains therefore a Sabbath for the people of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.10'>For a man who has entered into his rest, he has also rested from his works, as God did from his own.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.11'>Let us therefore be diligent to enter into that rest, so that not any man may fall by the same example of disobedience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.12'>For the word of God is living, and potent, and sharper, above every two-edged sword, and piercing as far as the division both of soul and spirit, of both joints and marrow, and discernible of the thoughts and intentions of the hear</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.13'>And there is no creature concealed from his presence, but all things are naked and vulnerable to his eyes, before whom is the word to us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.14'>Having therefore a great high priest who has passed through the heavens, Jesus the Son of God, let us take hold of the affirmation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.15'>For we do not have a high priest who is unable to sympathize with our weaknesses, but who was tempted in all things in the same way, without sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.4.16'>Let us therefore come near with boldness to the throne of grace, so that we may take mercy, and may find grace for timely help.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Heb.5'>
        <verse osisID='Heb.5.1'>For every high priest taken from men is appointed for men in things toward God, so that he may offer both gifts and sacrifices for sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.5.2'>Who can be gentle to those who are ignorant and led astray, since he himself is also encompassed with weakness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.5.3'>And because of this he is obligated, as for the people, so also for himself, to offer for sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.5.4'>And not any man takes the honor to himself, but being called by God, just as also Aaron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.5.5'>So also Christ did not glorify himself to become a high priest, but it was he who said to him, Thou are my Son, today I have begotten thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.5.6'>(And just as he says in another, Thou are a priest into the age according to the order of Melchizedek.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.5.7'>Who, in the days of his flesh, having offered up both prayers and supplications with strong shouting and tears to him who was able to save him from death, and who was heard because of his reverence,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.5.8'>although being a Son, he learned obedience from the things that he suffered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.5.9'>And having been fully perfected, he became the source of eternal salvation to all those who obey him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.5.10'>having been designated by God a high priest according to the order of Melchizedek.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.5.11'>About whom, much subject matter from us is also difficult to explain, since ye have become sluggish in hearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.5.12'>For also men who ought to be teachers because of the time, ye have need again for some man to teach you the rudiments of the beginning of the oracles of God, and have become men who have need of milk, and not of solid food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.5.13'>For every man partaking of milk is unskilled in the word of righteousness, for he is childlike.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.5.14'>But solid food is for mature men, those having their sensibilities trained through practice for the discernment of both good and evil.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Heb.6'>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.1'>Therefore having left the word of the primacy of Christ, let us be brought forward to perfection, not again laying a foundation of repentance from dead works, and of faith toward God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.2'>of doctrine of washings, and of laying on of hands, and of resurrection of the dead, and of eternal judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.3'>And this we will do, if of course God will permit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.4'>For it is impossible for those who were once enlightened, and who tasted of the heavenly gift, and who became partakers of Holy Spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.5'>and who tasted the good word of God and the powers of the coming age,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.6'>and who fell away, to restore again to repentance, crucifying to themselves the Son of God, and disgracing him publicly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.7'>For the soil that has drunk the rain often coming upon it, and bringing forth vegetation useful for those by whom also it is cultivated, partakes of a blessing from God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.8'>But producing thorns and thistles it is unfit and near a curse, the end of which is for burning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.9'>But we are persuaded better things about you, beloved, and things that have salvation, even though we speak this way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.10'>For God is not unrighteous to forget your work, and the labor of love that ye showed toward his name, having served the sanctified, and who are serving.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.11'>And we earnestly desire each of you to show the same diligence toward the full assurance of the hope until the end,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.12'>so that ye may not become lazy, but imitators of those who, through faith and longsuffering, inherit the promises.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.13'>For God who promised to Abraham, since he had none greater to swear by, swore by himself,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.14'>saying, Surely indeed, blessing I will bless thee, and multiplying I will multiply thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.15'>And this way, having patiently endured, he obtained the promise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.16'>For men certainly swear by the greater, and of every dispute with them the oath is final for confirmation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.17'>By which God, wanting to demonstrate more abundantly to the heirs of the promise the immutableness of his resolve, confirmed it by an oath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.18'>So that by two immutable events, in which it is impossible for God to lie, we may have strong encouragement, having fled for refuge to seize the hope being openly displayed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.19'>Which we have as an anchor of the soul, both sure and steadfast, and that enters into the interior of the veil,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.6.20'>where the forerunner, Jesus, entered for us, having become a high priest into the age according to the order of Melchizedek.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Heb.7'>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.1'>For this Melchizedek, king of Salem, priest of God Most High, having met Abraham returning from the slaughter of the kings, also blessed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.2'>To whom also Abraham divided a tenth of all. Being actually translated, first, king of righteousness, and then also, king of Salem, which is king of peace,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.3'>without father, without mother, without genealogy, having neither beginning of days nor end of life, but having been made like the Son of God, remains a priest continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.4'>And notice how great this man was, to whom also the patriarch Abraham gave a tenth out of the best spoils.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.5'>Now indeed those of the sons of Levi who receive the priesthood have commandment to collect tithes from the people according to the law, that is, of their brothers, although having come out of the loins of Abraham.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.6'>But the man who did not descend from them has received tithes from Abraham, and has blessed the man having the promises.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.7'>And without all contradiction the inferior is blessed by the superior.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.8'>And here indeed, men who die receive tithes, but there, he who is testified about that he lives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.9'>And, so to speak, Levi also, the man who receives tithes, has paid tithes through Abraham,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.10'>for he was still in the loins of his father when Melchizedek met him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.11'>If indeed therefore perfection was through the Levitical priesthood (for under it the people had received the law), what further need is there for another priest to arise according to the order of Melchizedek, and not be designated</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.12'>For the priesthood being changed, of necessity a change of law also occurs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.13'>For he of whom these things are spoken pertains to another tribe, from which no man has attended to the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.14'>For it is evident that our Lord arose out of Judah, regarding which tribe Moses spoke nothing about the priesthood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.15'>And it is still far more evident, if according to the likeness of Melchizedek, there arises another priest,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.16'>who has become, not according to a law of a carnal commandment, but according to the power of an indestructible life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.17'>For he testifies, Thou are a priest into the age according to the order of Melchizedek.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.18'>For indeed there becomes an annulment of a preceding commandment because of its weakness and uselessness</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.19'>(for the law made nothing fully perfect), and an introduction of a better hope, through which we approach God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.20'>And inasmuch as it is not without an oath. For actually those who become priests are so without an oath,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.21'>but he with an oath, because of him who says to him, The Lord swore and will not change his mind, Thou are a priest into the age according to the order of Melchizedek.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.22'>By so much, Jesus has become the surety of a better covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.23'>And of course those who have become priests are more, because of being prevented to continue by death,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.24'>but he, because of his remaining into the age, has the priesthood unchangeable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.25'>Whereupon he is able also to save to the uttermost those who come to God through him, being always alive in order to intercede on their behalf.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.26'>For such a high priest is fitting for us, devout, innocent, undefiled, separated from sinners, and having become higher than the heavens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.27'>Who has no need to offer up sacrifices each day, as those high priests, first for his own sins, then for those of the people, for this he did, once, when he offered up himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.7.28'>For the law appoints men high priests who have weakness, but the word of the oath after the law, a Son who has been fully perfected into the age.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Heb.8'>
        <verse osisID='Heb.8.1'>Now a summation about the things being spoken is, we have such a high priest who was seated at the right hand of the throne of the Majesty in the heavens,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.8.2'>a minister of the holy things, and of the TRUE tabernacle, which the Lord erected and not man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.8.3'>For every high priest is appointed in order to offer both gifts and sacrifices, whereupon it is necessary for this man also have something that he may offer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.8.4'>For certainly if he were on earth, he would not even be a priest, there being the priests who offer the gifts according to the law,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.8.5'>who serve for an example and shadow of the heavenly things. Just as Moses who was divinely warned while going to complete the tabernacle, for he says, See thou make all things according to the pattern that was shown thee on the mou</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.8.6'>But now he has obtained a superior ministry, by so much as he is also the mediator of a superior covenant, which has been enacted upon superior promises.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.8.7'>For if that first one was faultless, no place would have been sought for a second.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.8.8'>For, finding fault with them, he says, Behold, the days come, says Lord, and I will perfect a new covenant with the house of Israel and with the house of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.8.9'>Not according to the covenant that I made with their fathers in the day when I took them by my hand to lead them out of the land of Egypt. Because they did not continue in my covenant, and I disregarded them, says Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.8.10'>Because this is the covenant that I will ordain with the house of Israel after those days, says Lord, giving my laws into their mind, and I will write them on their hearts. And I will be to them for a God, and they will be to me fo</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.8.11'>And they will, no, not teach each man his fellow citizen, and each man his brother, saying, Know the Lord, because all will know me, from their small as far as their great.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.8.12'>Because I will be merciful to their iniquities, and their sins and their lawlessness I will no, not further remember.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.8.13'>In saying, New, he has made the first old. And what is becoming old and obsolete is near disappearance.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Heb.9'>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.1'>Now indeed therefore the first had ordinances of divine service and the earthly sanctuary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.2'>For a tabernacle was prepared, the first in which was also the lampstand, and the table, and the presentation of the loaves, which is called the Holy place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.3'>And behind the second curtain, the tabernacle called the Holy of holies,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.4'>having a golden censer, and the ark of the covenant overlaid entirely in gold, in which was a golden pot holding the manna, and Aaron's rod that budded, and the tablets of the covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.5'>And above it were cherubim of glory overshadowing the place of forgiveness, about which things it is not now to speak in detail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.6'>And these things thus having been prepared, the priests indeed enter into the first part of the tabernacle continually, accomplishing the services.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.7'>But into the second part, the high priest alone, once a year, not without blood, which he offers for himself and for the unintentional sins of the people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.8'>this signifying from the Holy Spirit, the way into the holy things is not yet to be made known while the first tabernacle still remains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.9'>Which is a figure for the present time, according to which both gifts and sacrifices are offered that are not able to make the man officiating fully perfect in respect to conscience,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.10'>only in foods and drinks and various washings: carnal ordinances imposed until a time of reformation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.11'>But Christ, having arrived a high priest of the good things that are coming, through the greater and more perfect tabernacle not made with hands, that is, not of this creation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.12'>and not through the blood of goats and calves, but through his own blood, he entered in once into the Holy things, having found eternal redemption.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.13'>For if the blood of bulls and goats, and the ashes of a heifer, sprinkling those who were defiled, sanctifies for the purification of the flesh,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.14'>how much more the blood of Christ, who, through the eternal Spirit, offered himself unblemished to God, will cleanse your conscience from dead works in order to serve a living God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.15'>And because of this he is mediator of a new covenant, so that a death having occurred for the redemption of the transgressions against the first covenant, those who are called might take the promise of the eternal inheritance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.16'>For where a covenant is, a necessity is to present the death of the man who made the covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.17'>For a covenant is effective with the dead, since it is never enforced while the man who made the covenant lives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.18'>Whereupon neither has the first been dedicated without blood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.19'>For of every commandment according to law that was spoken by Moses to all the people, after taking the blood of the calves and goats, with water and scarlet wool and hyssop, he sprinkled both the book itself and all the people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.20'>saying, This is the blood of the covenant that God made for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.21'>And likewise he sprinkled with the blood both the tabernacle and all the vessels of the service.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.22'>And almost all things, according to the law, are cleansed with blood, and remission does not occur without bloodshed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.23'>Indeed therefore, a necessity was for the models of the things in the heavens themselves to be cleansed with these, but the heavenly things with better sacrifices than these.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.24'>For the Christ entered not into a holy place made with hands, representative of the true, but into heaven itself, now to appear in the presence of God for us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.25'>And not so that he might offer himself often, as the high priest enters into the Holy things each year with blood by another,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.26'>since it would be necessary for him to suffer often, from the foundation of the world. But now once, at the end of the ages, he was made known for an annulment of sin by the sacrifice of himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.27'>And inasmuch as it is reserved to men once to die, and after this, judgment,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.9.28'>so also the Christ, having been offered once in order to take up the sins of many, will appear a second time, independent of sin, to those waiting for him for salvation.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Heb.10'>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.1'>For the law having a shadow of the good things that are coming, not the same substance of the events, with the same sacrifices that are offered continually each year, they are never able to fully perfect those who are approaching.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.2'>Otherwise would they not have ceased being offered, because of those who worship, once having been cleansed, to have no further conscience of sins?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.3'>But in them is a reminder of sins each year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.4'>For it is impossible for the blood of bulls and goats to take away sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.5'>Therefore when he comes into the world, he says, Sacrifice and offering thou did not desire, but thou prepared for me a body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.6'>In whole burnt offerings, and for sin thou were not pleased.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.7'>Then I said, Lo, I come (in the volume of a book it is written about me) to do thy will, O God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.8'>saying above, Sacrifice and offering and whole burnt offerings and for sin thou did not desire, nor were thou pleased with things that are offered according to the law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.9'>Then he said, Lo, I come to do thy will, O God. He takes away the first, so that he may establish the second.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.10'>By which will we are sanctified through the one time offering of the body of Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.11'>And indeed every priest stands daily serving and offering the same sacrifices often, which can never take away sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.12'>But this man, having offered one sacrifice on behalf of sins forever, sat down at the right hand of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.13'>waiting henceforth until his enemies are placed a footstool of his feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.14'>For by one offering he has fully perfected forever those being sanctified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.15'>And the Holy Spirit also testifies to us, after indeed foretelling,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.16'>This is the covenant that I will ordain with them after those days, says Lord, giving my laws on their hearts, and on their minds I will write them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.17'>and, Their sins and their lawlessness I will, no, not further remember.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.18'>Now where there is remission of these, there is no more offering for sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.19'>Having therefore, brothers, boldness for entrance into the holy things by the blood of Jesus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.20'>which he inaugurated for us, a new and living way through the curtain, that is, his flesh,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.21'>and a great priest over the house of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.22'>let us approach with a TRUE heart in full assurance of faith, our hearts sprinkled from an evil conscience, and our body washed in pure water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.23'>Let us hold firm the affirmation of the hope unwavering, for he who promised is faithful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.24'>And let us examine each other for provocation of love and good works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.25'>Not forsaking the assembling together of ourselves, as is the habit of some, but exhorting, and so much the more as long as ye see the day approaching.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.26'>For when we sin willfully after taking the knowledge of the truth, there remains no more a sacrifice for sins,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.27'>but a certain fearful expectation of judgment and of fire, a fervor that is going to devour the opposition.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.28'>Any man who has disregarded the law of Moses dies without mercies from two or three witnesses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.29'>By how much worse punishment do ye think he will deserve who has trampled the Son of God, and who considered profane the blood of the covenant by which he was sanctified, and who treated the Spirit of grace contemptuously?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.30'>For we know him who said, Vengeance is for me, I will repay, says Lord. And again, Lord will judge his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.31'>It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.32'>But remember the former days, in which, after being enlightened, ye endured a great contest of sufferings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.33'>Partly made a spectacle, both by reviling and afflictions, and partly having become companions of those so treated.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.34'>For ye were both compassionate about my bonds, and ye accepted with joy the plundering of your possessions, knowing yourselves to have a superior and an enduring existence in the heavens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.35'>Therefore do not throw off your boldness, which has great recompense of reward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.36'>For ye have need of perseverance, so that, having done the will of God, ye may receive the promise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.37'>For yet a very little while, he who is coming will come, and will not delay.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.38'>But the righteous man will live from faith, and if he should withdraw, my soul is not pleased with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.10.39'>But we are not of retreat for destruction, but of faith for the preservation of the soul.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Heb.11'>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.1'>Now faith is the foundation of hoping, the evidence of events not being seen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.2'>For by this the ancients were well reported.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.3'>By faith we understand the ages to have been prepared by the word of God. For the things that are seen do not come to be from that which is visible.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.4'>By faith Abel offered to God a better sacrifice than Cain, because of which he was reported to be righteous, God testifying about his gifts, and through it, he who died still speaks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.5'>By faith Enoch was transferred to not see death, and he was not found, because God transferred him. For before his removal he was reported to be pleasing to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.6'>And apart from faith it is impossible to please him. For he who comes to God must believe that he is, and becomes a rewarder of those who search for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.7'>By faith Noah, being divinely warned about things not yet seen, moved with awe, prepared an ark for the salvation of his house, through which he condemned the world, and became an heir of righteousness according to faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.8'>By faith Abraham, when called, obeyed to go out to the place that he was going to take for an inheritance. And he went out, not knowing where he was going.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.9'>By faith he lived alien in the land of promise as a foreigner, having dwelt in tents with Isaac and Jacob, the fellow heirs of the same promise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.10'>For he anticipated the city that has the foundations, whose builder and architect is God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.11'>By faith even Sarah herself received power for conception of seed, and she gave birth beyond the time of age, because she considered him faithful who promised.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.12'>And therefore from one man, and these things having become deadened, were begotten as the stars of the heaven for multitude, and as the sand of the seashore, countless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.13'>All these died in faith, not having taken the promises, but who saw and greeted them from afar, and who confessed that they were foreigners and sojourners on the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.14'>For those who say such things show that they are seeking a fatherland.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.15'>And if indeed they remembered that from which they came out, they would have had time to return.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.16'>But now they aspire for a superior one, that is, a heavenly one. Therefore God is not ashamed of them, to be called their God, for he has prepared for them a city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.17'>By faith Abraham, being tested, offered Isaac. And he who received the promises offered his only begotten son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.18'>about whom it was said, The seed by thee will be called in Isaac.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.19'>Having reckoned that God is able to raise up even from the dead, from where also, in a figure, he did receive him back.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.20'>By faith Isaac blessed Jacob and Esau about things coming.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.21'>By faith Jacob, while dying, blessed each of the sons of Joseph, and bowed in worship upon the top of his staff.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.22'>By faith Joseph, while perishing, remembered about the exodus of the sons of Israel, and commanded about his bones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.23'>By faith Moses, after being born, was hid three months by his parents, because they saw the child well-formed, and they were not afraid of the king's edict.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.24'>By faith Moses, having become great, refused to be called the son of Pharaoh's daughter,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.25'>having chosen rather to be mistreated with the people of God, than to have the pleasure of sin temporarily.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.26'>Having esteemed the vilification of the Christ greater wealth than the treasures of Egypt, for he focused toward the recompense of reward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.27'>By faith he forsook Egypt, not having feared the wrath of the king, for he persevered as seeing the invisible.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.28'>By faith he performed the Passover and the sprinkling of the blood, so that he who was destroying the firstborn would not touch them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.29'>By faith they passed through the Red sea as by dry land, of which the Egyptians, having taken an attempt, were drowned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.30'>By faith the walls of Jericho fell down, having been encircled for seven days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.31'>By faith Rahab the harlot was not destroyed with those who were disobedient, having received the spies with peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.32'>And what shall I say further? For the time would fail me telling about Gideon, also Barak and Samson and Jephthah, also of David and Samuel and the prophets,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.33'>who, through faith, conquered kingdoms, wrought righteousness, obtained promises, closed the mouths of lions,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.34'>quenched the force of fire, escaped the jaw of the sword. Out of weakness were made strong, became mighty in war, bowed down armies of aliens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.35'>Women took hold of their dead from a resurrection, but others were tortured, not having accepted deliverance, so that they might experience a superior resurrection.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.36'>And others took a trial of mockings and scourgings, and moreover of bonds and imprisonment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.37'>They were stoned, they were sawed apart, they were tempted, they died in murder by sword. They wandered about in sheepskins, in goatskins, being destitute, restricted, tormented</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.38'>(of whom the world was not worthy), wandering in deserts and mountains and caves, and the holes of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.39'>And all these, having been well reported through faith, did not receive the promise,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.11.40'>God having foreseen something superior concerning us, so that without us they would not be made fully perfect.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Heb.12'>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.1'>Therefore we also, having so great a cloud of witnesses surrounding us, having put off every weight and cleverly entangling sin, let us run by perseverance the contest being set before us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.2'>Looking to Jesus the pathfinder and perfecter of the faith, who, against the joy set before him, endured a cross, having despised the shame, and has sat down at the right hand of the throne of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.3'>For consider the man who endured such hostility against him by sinners, so that ye may not be weary in your souls, being disheartened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.4'>Ye have not yet resisted as far as blood, struggling against sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.5'>And have ye forgotten the exhortation that reasons with you as with sons, My son, do not disparage the chastening of Lord, nor become disheartened when punished by him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.6'>For whom Lord loves he chastens. And he whips every son whom he receives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.7'>Because of chastening ye endure; God is treating you as with sons, for what son is there whom a father does not chasten?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.8'>And if ye are without chastening, of which all have become participants, then ye are bastards, and not sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.9'>Besides, we indeed have had chastisers--the fathers of our flesh--and we were turned around. Shall we not much more be subordinate to the Father of the spirits, and we will live?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.10'>For those men indeed for a few days chastened us according to that which seemed good to them, but he for that which is advantageous, in order to be partakers of his holiness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.11'>But of course no chastening for the present seems to be of joy but of sorrow, yet afterward it yields peaceable fruit of righteousness to those who have been trained by it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.12'>Therefore lift up the drooping hands, and the feeble knees,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.13'>and make straight paths for your feet, so that what is lame may not be turned away, but may be healed instead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.14'>Pursue peace with all men, and the sanctification without which no man will see the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.15'>Looking carefully lest any man fall short, away from the grace of God, lest any root of bitterness sprouting up would cause trouble, and by this many may be defiled,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.16'>lest a fornicator or profane man like Esau, who, in place of one meal sold his birthright.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.17'>For ye also know that wanting afterward to inherit the blessing, he was rejected, for he found no place of repentance, though having sought it with tears.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.18'>For ye have not come to a mountain being felt, and which burned with fire, and to darkness, and gloom, and a tempest,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.19'>and a sound of a trumpet, and a voice of words, of which those who heard begged that a word not be added to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.20'>For they did not bear that which was commanded, if even a beast should touch the mountain, it shall be stoned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.21'>And so fearful was that which was made visible, that Moses said, I am terrified and trembling.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.22'>But ye have come to mount Zion, and to the city of a living God, a heavenly Jerusalem, and to myriads of heavenly agents,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.23'>to a festal gathering and assembly of firstborn sons who were enrolled in the heavens, and to God, a Judge of all, and to spirits of righteous men who were made fully perfect,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.24'>and to Jesus a mediator of a new covenant, and to blood of sprinkling that speaks better than Abel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.25'>Watch, that ye not refuse him who speaks. For if those men did not escape, having refused him who spoke a divine message on earth, much more we, those who turn away from him from the heavens,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.26'>whose voice then shook the earth. But now he has promised, saying, Yet once, I shake not only the earth, but also the heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.27'>And the, Yet once, signifies the removal of the things being shaken--as of things that were made--so that the things not being shaken may remain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.28'>Therefore, receiving an immovable kingdom, we may have grace, through which we may serve God acceptably with reverence and awe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.12.29'>For our God is also a consuming fire.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Heb.13'>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.1'>Let brotherly love abide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.2'>Do not forget love for strangers, for by this some lodged heavenly agents, unaware.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.3'>Remember the prisoners as being in bondage together, those who are ill-treated as also yourselves being in the body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.4'>Marriage is precious in every way, and the undefiled bed, but God will judge fornicators and adulterers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.5'>The Way of life is to be without love of money, being content with the things that are present, for he has said, I will, no, not leave thee, and also, I will, no, not forsake thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.6'>So then we have confidence to say, Lord is a helper to me, and I will not fear. What will man do to me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.7'>Remember those who lead you, men who spoke the word of God to you, of whom, carefully observing the outcome of their conduct, imitate the faith--</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.8'>Jesus Christ, the same yesterday and today, and into the ages.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.9'>Be not carried away by various and foreign doctrines. For it is good that the heart be established with grace, not with foods by which those who walked were not benefited.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.10'>We have an altar from which they have no right to eat, those officiating at the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.11'>For of the beasts whose blood is brought into the holy things for sin by the high priest, the bodies of these are burned outside the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.12'>Therefore Jesus also, so that he might sanctify the people through his own blood, suffered outside the gate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.13'>Let us therefore go forth to him outside the camp, bearing his reproach.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.14'>For here we have no enduring city, but we seek that which is coming.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.15'>Through him therefore, let us offer up a sacrifice of praise to God continually, that is, fruit of lips acknowledging his name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.16'>But do not forget benevolence and fellowship, for God is well pleased with such sacrifices.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.17'>Have confidence in those who lead you, and yield yourselves, for they watch for your souls as men who will render account, so that they may do this with joy, and not groaning, for this is unprofitable for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.18'>Pray about us, for we trust that we have a good conscience, desiring to behave well in all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.19'>But I urge you to do this even more, so that I may be restored to you sooner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.20'>Now the God of peace, who brought up from the dead the great shepherd of the sheep by the blood of an eternal covenant--our Lord Jesus--</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.21'>may he make you fully qualified in every good work in order to do his will, doing in you what is well-pleasing in his sight, through Jesus Christ, to whom is the glory into the ages of the ages. Truly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.22'>And I urge you, brothers, bear with the word of exhortation, for I also wrote to you in brief.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.23'>Know ye, brother Timothy who was set free is with whom I will see you, if he comes sooner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.24'>Salute all those who lead you, and all the sanctified. The men from Italy salute you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Heb.13.25'>Grace is with you all. Truly.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>