<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText xml:lang='en' osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='Etheridge'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='Etheridge'>
        <title>The Peschito Syriac New Testament</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Mod2Zef (5)</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject/>
        <date>2010-02-21</date>
        <description>The Peschito Syriac New Testament by J.W. Etheridge, comprising:  The Syrian Churches: their Early History, Liturgies, and Literature. With a literal Translation of the Four Gospels, from the Peschito, etc. 1846  and  The Apostolical Acts and Epistles fromt he Peschito or Ancient Syriac: to which are added, the remaining epistles and the Book of Revelation, after a later syrian text, etc. 1849.</description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>Etheridge</identifier>
        <source>http://www.peshito.com/</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='2Tim'>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.1'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.1'>PAULOS, an apostle of Jeshu Meshiha by the will of Aloha, and on account of the promise of life which is in Jeshu Meshiha,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.2'>to Timotheos my beloved son: grace and mercies and peace from Aloha our Father, and from our Lord Jeshu Meshiha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.3'>I thank Aloha, whom I serve from my fathers with a pure conscience, that constantly I remember thee in my prayers of the night and of the day;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.4'>and have longed to see thee, being mindful of thy tears, that I may be filled with joy:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.5'>in remembrance of thee (and) of thy true faith which dwelt first in the mother of thy mother Lois, and in thy mother Eunika, and which, I am persuaded, (is) in thee also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.6'>On account of this I put thee in mind to keep awake the gift of Aloha, which is in thee by the laying on of my hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.7'>For Aloha hath not given to us the spirit of fear, but of power and of love and of discipline.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.8'>Wherefore be not thou ashamed of the testimony of our Lord, nor of me his prisoner; but sustain evil with the gospel, through the power of Aloha,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.9'>who hath saved us, and called us with an holy calling; not according to our works, but according to his will, and that grace of his which was given to us in Jeshu Meshiha before the time of the worlds,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.10'>and is now revealed by the revelation of our Saviour Jeshu Meshiha, who hath abolished death, and hath demonstrated life and incorruption, through the gospel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.11'>of which I am appointed an herald and an apostle and a teacher of the nations:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.12'>on account of which I suffer these, and am not ashamed. I know in whom I have believed, and am persuaded that there is power in his hands my deposite to keep for me unto that day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.13'>Let the outline of sound words be with thee, which thou hast heard from me, with the faith and love which are in Jeshu Meshiha:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.14'>that good deposite keep through the Spirit of Holiness who dwelleth in us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.15'>Know this, that all those of Asia are turned from me, of whom are Phygellos and Harmogenes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.16'>Our Lord give mercies to the house of Onesiphoros, who many times hath refreshed me, and of the chains of my bonds hath not been ashamed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.17'>But when also he came to Ruma, with diligence he sought me, and found me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.18'>Our Lord grant that he may find mercies with our Lord in that day: and how he ministered to me in Ephesos thou especially knowest.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.2'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.1'>Thou therefore, my son, be strong in the grace of our Lord Jeshu Meshiha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.2'>And those (doctrines) which thou hast heard from me by many witnesses, them commit to faithful men, who are also able to teach others.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.3'>And endure evils as a good soldier of Jeshu Meshiha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.4'>No man serveth as a soldier, and entangleth himself with the affairs of the world, that he might please him who hath chosen him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.5'>And if one contendeth, he is not crowned, unless according to his law he contend.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.6'>It becometh the husbandman who laboureth that he should first eat of his fruits.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.7'>Understand what I say to thee. Our Lord give thee wisdom in all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.8'>Remember Jeshu Meshiha, that he arose from among the dead, he who is of the seed of David, according to my gospel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.9'>for which I endure evils unto bonds, as an evil-doer: but the word of Aloha is not bound.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.10'>Therefore I endure every thing on account of the elect, that they also may find salvation in Jeshu Meshiha, with the glory that is eternal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.11'>Faithful is the word: For if we be dead with him, With him also we shall live;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.12'>And if we endure, We shall also reign with him; But, if we deny him, He also will deny us!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.13'>And if we believe him not, He in his faithfulness abideth; For deny himself he cannot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.14'>Of these (truths) remind them, and testify before our Lord, that they contend not with unprofitable words, to the overturning of those who hear them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.15'>And be careful to establish thyself perfectly before Aloha, a workman without shame, preaching rightly the word of truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.16'>From vain words which have no utility in them withdraw; for they add greatly to the wickedness of those who are occupied with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.17'>And their words as an eating cancer will lay hold upon many: but one of them is Hymeneos, and another Philetos,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.18'>who have erred from the truth, saying, that the resurrection of the dead hath been, and the faith of some overturning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.19'>But the true foundation of Aloha standeth; and it hath this signature: And the Lord knoweth them who are his. And, Let every one who invoketh the name of the Lord depart from iniquity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.20'>But in a great house there are not vessels of gold only or of silver, but also of wood, also of clay: of them (some are) to honour, and of them (some) to dishonour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.21'>If a man then purify himself from these, he will be a pure vessel unto honour, fitted for the use of his Lord, and prepared for every good work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.22'>From all the lusts of youth escape; and pursue after righteousness, and faith, and charity, and peace, with them who call upon the Lord with a pure heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.23'>From foolish controversies which are without instruction withdraw; for thou knowest that they beget strifes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.24'>But a servant of the Lord oweth not to strive, but to be gentle towards every man, and teaching, and long-suffering,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.25'>that he may instruct them who would contend against him with meekness, if by any means Aloha may give them conversion, and they may acknowledge the truth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.26'>and be mindful of themselves, and remove from the snare of Satana, by whom they have been entrapped at his will.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.3'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.1'>But know this, that in the last days hard times will come;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.2'>and men will be lovers of themselves, and lovers of money, boastful, lofty, blasphemous, to their men not obedient, deniers of grace, impious, calumniators,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.3'>subjected to lust, brutal, haters of the good,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.4'>traitors, impetuous, puffed up, lovers of lusts rather than the love of Aloha;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.5'>having a form of the worship of Aloha, but from the power of Aloha afar off: (them) who are such put from thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.6'>For of them are they who creep into houses, and captivate women who are overladen with sins, and led away by divers lusts;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.7'>who, in all time learning, never to the knowledge of the truth are able to come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.8'>But as Yonis and Yanbris stood against Musha, so also these stand against the truth: men whose understanding is corrupted, and reprobate from the faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.9'>But they shall not come further, for their folly is known to all men, as also of them it is known.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.10'>BUT thou hast followed my doctrine and my manners, and my purpose, and my faith, and my prolongedness of mind, and my charity, and my patience,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.11'>and my persecution, and my sufferings. And thou knowest what things I endured in Antioch, and in Ikonion, and in Lystra, what persecution I endured; and out of all these my Lord delivered me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.12'>But all they who will in the fear of Aloha to live in Jeshu Meshiha, are persecuted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.13'>But wicked men and seducers add to their wickedness, deceiving, and being deceived.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.14'>But abide thou in those things that thou hast learned, and in which thou art confirmed; for thou knowest from whom thou hast learned:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.15'>and that from thy childhood thou hast learned the holy writings, which are able to make thee wise to salvation, through faith which is in Jeshu Meshiha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.16'>FOR all scripture which from the Spirit is written, is profitable for doctrine, and for rebuke, and for correction, and for instruction which is in righteousness:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.17'>that the man of God may be perfect unto every good work, and completed.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.4'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.1'>I attest thee before Aloha, and our Lord Jeshu Meshiha, who is to judge the living and the dead at the revelation of his kingdom:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.2'>preach the word, and stand with diligence in season, and (that) which is not season; confute, and rebuke with all prolongedness of mind and doctrine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.3'>For the time will come, when sound doctrine they will not hear; but according to their desires will multiply to themselves teachers, in the itching of their hearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.4'>And from the truth they will turn away their ear, but to fables will decline.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.5'>But watch thou in every thing, and endure evils, and work the work of an evangelist, and thy ministry fulfil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.6'>But I am sacrificed, and the time when I shall be dissolved cometh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.7'>The good agony I have fought, and my running I have completed, and my faith I have kept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.8'>And from now there is kept for me the crown of righteousness, which my Lord will give me in that day, because he is a righteous judge: yet, not only to me, but to all them who love his manifestation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.9'>BE careful to come to me speedily;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.10'>for Dema hath left me, and hath loved this world, and is gone to Thessalonika; Krispos to Galatia, Titos to Dalmatia;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.11'>Luka only is with me. Take Markos and bring him with thee; for helpful to me is he in the ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.12'>But Tykikos have I sent to Ephesos.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.13'>The case (for) books which I left at Troas with Karpos, when thou comest bring, and the books, and especially the roll of parchments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.14'>Alexander the brass-worker many evils hath showed me: our Lord awardeth to him according to his deeds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.15'>But be thou also aware of him, for he is much uplifted against our words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.16'>In the first defence no man was with me, but all of them left me. May this not be reckoned to them!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.17'>But my Lord stood with me, that by me the preaching might be fulfilled, and (that) all the Gentiles might hear: and I was delivered from the mouth of the lion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.18'>And my Lord will deliver me from every evil work, and will save me into his kingdom, which is in heaven. To Him be glory for ever and ever. Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.19'>Give salutation to Priskela, and to Akilos, and to the house of Onesiphoros.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.20'>Erastos remains at Kurinthos; but Trophimos I left ill in Miletos the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.21'>Be careful to come before winter. Ebulos and Pudis, and Linos, and Klaudia, and all the brethren, ask for your peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.22'>Our Lord Jeshu Meshiha be with thy spirit. Grace be with thee. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>