<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
<osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='Bible.en.LEB.2010' xml:lang='en'>
<header>
<work osisWork='Bible.en.LEB.2010'>
<title>The Lexham English Bible</title>
<creator type='x-edt'>W. Hall Harris III</creator>
<date>2010-03-23</date>
<publisher>Logos Research Systems, Inc.</publisher>
<type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
<format type='x-MIME'>text/xml</format>
<source>LEB.xml, 2010-03-23</source>
<language type='IETF'>en</language>
<rights>Copyright 2010 Logos Research Systems, Inc. All rights reserved. Further licensing information is provided in the License and Trademark sections at the start of the text.</rights>
<scope>Matt-Rev</scope>
<refSystem>Bible.NRSVA</refSystem>
</work>
</header>
<div type='front'>
<titlePage>
<p>The Lexham English Bible</p>
<p>W. Hall Harris III</p>
<p>General Editor</p>
<p>Copyright 2010 Logos Research Systems, Inc.</p>
<p>All rights reserved.</p>
</titlePage>
<div type='x-license'>
<title>License</title>
<p>You can give away the Lexham English Bible, but you can’t sell it on its own. If the LEB comprises less than 25% of the content of a larger work, you can sell it as part of that work.</p>
<p>If you give away the LEB for use with a commercial product, or sell a work containing more than 1,000 verses from the LEB, you must annually report the number of units sold, distributed, and/or downloaded.</p>
<p>You must always attribute quotations of the LEB.</p>
<p>If you quote less than 100 verses of the LEB in a single work you can attribute it by simply adding (LEB) after the quotation. Longer quotations, or use of 100 or more verses in a single work, must be accompanied by the following statement:</p>
<p>Scripture quotations marked (LEB) are from the Lexham English Bible. Copyright 2010 Logos Bible Software. Lexham is a registered trademark of Logos Bible Software.</p>
<p>In electronic use, link “LEB” and “Lexham English Bible” to <a href='http://lexhamenglishbible.com'>http://lexhamenglishbible.com</a>, and “Logos Bible Software” to <a href='http://logos.com'>http://logos.com</a>. If all quotations are unmarked and from the LEB, you may remove “marked (LEB) are” from the statement.</p>
<p>In support of non-English Bible translation, non-profit organizations may use 50% as the maximum portion the LEB may comprise of a work offered for sale. (This specifically allows the creation and commercial sale of diglot Bibles.)</p>
</div>
<div type='x-trademark'>
<p>Lexham is a registered trademark of Logos Bible Software. You may use LEB or Lexham English Bible to refer to the Lexham English Bible, but may not use the Lexham trademark as any part of the name of a larger work quoting or containing it.</p>
</div>
<div type='preface'>
<p>With approximately one hundred different English translations of the Bible already published,<note>This figure includes translations of the New Testament alone. For one of the most comprehensive lists, see Wikipedia (<a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_English_Bible_translations'>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_English_Bible_translations</a>).</note> the reader may well wonder why yet another English version has been produced. Those actually engaged in the work of translating the Bible might answer that the quest for increased accuracy, the incorporation of new scholarly discoveries in the fields of semantics, lexicography, linguistics, new archaeological discoveries, and the continuing evolution of the English language all contribute to the need for producing new translations. But in the case of the Lexham English Bible (LEB), the answer to this question is much simpler; in fact, it is merely twofold.</p>
<p>First, the LEB achieves an unparalleled level of transparency with the original language text because the LEB had as its starting point the <hi type='italic'>Lexham Greek-English Interlinear New Testament</hi>. It was produced with the specific purpose of being used alongside the original language text of the Bible. Existing translations, however excellent they may be in terms of English style and idiom, are frequently so far removed from the original language texts of scripture that straightforward comparison is difficult for the average user. Of course distance between the original language text and the English translation is not a criticism of any modern English translation. To a large extent this distance is the result of the philosophy of translation chosen for a particular English version, and it is almost always the result of an attempt to convey the meaning of the original in a clearer and more easily understandable way to the contemporary reader. However, there are many readers, particularly those who have studied some biblical Greek, who desire a translation that facilitates straightforward and easy comparisons between the translation and the original language text. The ability to make such comparisons easily in software formats like Logos Bible Software makes the need for an English translation specifically designed for such comparison even more acute.</p>
<p>Second, the LEB is designed from the beginning to make extensive use of the most up-to-date lexical reference works available. For the New Testament this is primarily the third edition of Walter Bauer’s <hi type='italic'>A Greek-English Lexicon of the New Testament and Other Early Christian Literature</hi> (BDAG). Users can be assured that the LEB as a translation is based on the best scholarly research available. The Greek text on which the LEB New Testament is based is that of NA27 (<hi type='italic'>Novum Testamentum Graece</hi> editio XXVII). Often referred to as the “critical” text, this is the most widely used Greek text of the New Testament in use today.</p>
<p>Naturally, when these two factors are taken into consideration, it should not be surprising that the character of the LEB as a translation is fairly literal. This is a necessary by-product of the desire to have the English translation correspond transparently to the original language text. Nevertheless, a serious attempt has been made within these constraints to produce a clear and readable English translation instead of a woodenly literal one.<note>A small amount of foreignness in a Bible translation is not necessarily a bad thing, because it reminds us that we are reading an ancient text from a different culture. Not only do the linguistic constructions differ considerably from our own, but the cultural presuppositions and assumptions differ as well. I am not convinced that, as a reader of the Bible in the early twenty-first century, I am particularly well-served if Paul comes across sounding like an op-ed columnist in the newspaper or Luke sounds like the anchor of a cable news channel on television. Clarity in translation is one thing, but obliterating the cultural distance that separate the modern reader from the first century is something else again.</note></p>
<p>There are three areas in particular that need to be addressed to make a translation like the LEB more accessible to readers today, while at the same time maintaining easy comparison with the original language text. First, differences in word order have to be addressed. In this regard, the LEB follows standard English word order, not the word order of Koiné Greek.<note>Koiné Greek (sometimes called Hellenistic Greek) is the form of Greek in which the New Testament is written.</note> Anyone who needs to see the word order of the original Greek can readily consult the <hi type='italic'>Lexham Greek-English Interlinear New Testament</hi>, which contains a sequence line which gives this information. Second, some expressions in biblical Greek are idiomatic, so that a literal translation would be meaningless or would miscommunicate the true meaning. The LEB uses <seg type='x-idiom'>˻lower corner˼</seg> brackets to indicate such expressions, with a literal rendering given in a note. Third, words which have no equivalent in the original language text must sometimes be supplied in the English translation. Because the LEB is designed to be used alongside the original language texts of scripture, these supplied words are indicated with <hi type='italic'>italics</hi>. In some cases the need for such supplied words is obvious, but in other cases where it is less clear a note has been included.</p>
<p>Finally, the reader should remember that any Bible translation, to be useful to the person using it, must actually be read. I would encourage every user of the LEB, whether reading it alongside the original languages text or not, to remember that once we understand the meaning of a biblical text we are responsible to apply it first in our own lives, and then to share it with those around us.</p>
<p>W. Hall Harris III</p>
<p>General Editor</p>
<p>Lexham English Bible</p>
<p>For the word of God <hi type='italic'>is</hi> living and active and sharper than any double-edged sword, and piercing as far as the division of soul and spirit, both joints and marrow, and able to judge the reflections and thoughts of the heart. (<reference osisRef='Heb.4.12'>Heb 4:12</reference> LEB)</p>
</div>
</div>



























<div type='book' osisID='Mark'>
<chapter osisID='Mark.1'>
<div type='section'>
<title>John the Baptist Begins His Ministry</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.1.1' sID='Mark.1.1'/>The beginning of the gospel of Jesus Christ, the Son of God.<verse eID='Mark.1.1'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.2' sID='Mark.1.2'/>Just as it is written in the prophet Isaiah,</p>
<lg>
<l level='1'>“Behold, I am sending my messenger before your face,</l>
<l level='2'>who will prepare your way,<verse eID='Mark.1.2'/></l>
<l level='1'><verse osisID='Mark.1.3' sID='Mark.1.3'/>the voice of one shouting in the wilderness,</l>
<l level='2'>‘Prepare the way of the Lord,</l>
<l level='2'>make straight his paths!’ ”<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Isa.40.3'>Isa 40:3</reference></note><verse eID='Mark.1.3'/></l>
</lg>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.1.4' sID='Mark.1.4'/>John was there baptizing in the wilderness and proclaiming a baptism of repentance for the forgiveness of sins.<verse eID='Mark.1.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.5' sID='Mark.1.5'/>And all the Judean region and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem went out to him and were being baptized by him in the Jordan River, confessing their sins.<verse eID='Mark.1.5'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.6' sID='Mark.1.6'/>And John was dressed in camel’s hair and a belt made of leather around his waist, and he ate locusts and wild honey.<verse eID='Mark.1.6'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.7' sID='Mark.1.7'/>And he was preaching, saying, “One <transChange type='added'>who is</transChange> more powerful than I is coming after me, of whom I am not worthy to bend down <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“bend down”) has been translated as an infinitive</note> untie the strap of his sandals.<verse eID='Mark.1.7'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.8' sID='Mark.1.8'/>I baptized you with water, but he will baptize you with the Holy Spirit.”<verse eID='Mark.1.8'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Baptism of Jesus</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.1.9' sID='Mark.1.9'/>And it happened that in those days Jesus came from Nazareth in Galilee and was baptized in the Jordan by John.<verse eID='Mark.1.9'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.10' sID='Mark.1.10'/>And immediately <transChange type='added'>as he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was coming up”) which is understood as temporal</note> was coming up out of the water, he saw the heavens being split apart and the Spirit descending like a dove on him.<verse eID='Mark.1.10'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.11' sID='Mark.1.11'/>And a voice came from heaven, “You are my beloved Son; with you I am well pleased.”<verse eID='Mark.1.11'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Temptation of Jesus</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.1.12' sID='Mark.1.12'/>And immediately the Spirit drove him out into the wilderness.<verse eID='Mark.1.12'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.13' sID='Mark.1.13'/>And he was in the wilderness forty days being tempted by Satan. And he was with the wild animals, and the angels were ministering to him.<verse eID='Mark.1.13'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Public Ministry in Galilee</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.1.14' sID='Mark.1.14'/>Now after John <seg type='x-idiom'>˻had been taken into custody˼</seg>,<note>Literally “had been handed over”</note> Jesus went into Galilee proclaiming the gospel of God<verse eID='Mark.1.14'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.15' sID='Mark.1.15'/>and saying, “The time is fulfilled and the kingdom of God has come near. Repent and believe in the gospel!”<verse eID='Mark.1.15'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus Calls His First Disciples</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.1.16' sID='Mark.1.16'/>And <transChange type='added'>as he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was passing by”) which is understood as temporal</note> was passing by along the Sea of Galilee, he saw Simon and Andrew, Simon’s brother, casting <transChange type='added'>a net</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> into the sea (for they were fishermen).<verse eID='Mark.1.16'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.17' sID='Mark.1.17'/>And Jesus said to them, “<seg type='x-idiom'>˻Follow˼</seg><note>Literally “come after”</note> me and I will make you become fishers of people.”<verse eID='Mark.1.17'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.18' sID='Mark.1.18'/>And immediately they left their nets <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“left”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> followed him.<verse eID='Mark.1.18'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.19' sID='Mark.1.19'/>And going on a little <transChange type='added'>farther</transChange>, he saw James the <transChange type='added'>son</transChange> of Zebedee and his brother John, and they <transChange type='added'>were</transChange> in the boat mending the nets.<verse eID='Mark.1.19'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.20' sID='Mark.1.20'/>And immediately he called them, and they left their father Zebedee in the boat with the hired men <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“left”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went away after him.<verse eID='Mark.1.20'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.21' sID='Mark.1.21'/>And they went into Capernaum and immediately on the Sabbath he went into the synagogue <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to teach.<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to teach”)</note><verse eID='Mark.1.21'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Man with an Unclean Spirit Healed</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.1.22' sID='Mark.1.22'/>And they were amazed at his teaching, because he was teaching them like one who had authority, and not like the scribes.<verse eID='Mark.1.22'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.23' sID='Mark.1.23'/>And so then there was a man in their synagogue with an unclean spirit, and he cried out,<verse eID='Mark.1.23'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.24' sID='Mark.1.24'/>saying, “<seg type='x-idiom'>˻Leave us alone˼</seg>,<note>Literally “what to us and to you”</note> Jesus the Nazarene! Have you come to destroy us? I know who you are—the Holy One of God!”<verse eID='Mark.1.24'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.25' sID='Mark.1.25'/>And Jesus rebuked him, saying, “Be silent, and come out of him!”<verse eID='Mark.1.25'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.26' sID='Mark.1.26'/>And <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“convulsing”) which is understood as temporal</note> convulsing him and crying out with a loud voice, the unclean spirit came out of him.<verse eID='Mark.1.26'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.27' sID='Mark.1.27'/>And they were all amazed, so that <transChange type='added'>they began</transChange> to discuss with one another, saying, “What is this? A new teaching with authority! He even commands the unclean spirits and they obey him.”<verse eID='Mark.1.27'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.28' sID='Mark.1.28'/>And the report about him then went out everywhere in the whole surrounding region of Galilee.<verse eID='Mark.1.28'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Many at Capernaum Are Healed</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.1.29' sID='Mark.1.29'/>And so then he departed from the synagogue <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“departed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> came into the house of Simon and Andrew with James and John.<verse eID='Mark.1.29'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.30' sID='Mark.1.30'/>Now Simon’s mother-in-law was lying down, suffering with a fever, and at once they told him about her.<verse eID='Mark.1.30'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.31' sID='Mark.1.31'/>And he came <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> raised her up <transChange type='added'>by</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>by</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“taking hold of”) which is understood as means</note> taking hold of her<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hand, and the fever left her, and she began to serve them.<verse eID='Mark.1.31'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.1.32' sID='Mark.1.32'/>Now <transChange type='added'>when it</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> was evening, when the sun had set, they began bringing<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began bringing”)</note> to him all those <seg type='x-idiom'>˻who were sick˼</seg><note>Literally “who were having badly”</note> and those who were demon-possessed.<verse eID='Mark.1.32'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.33' sID='Mark.1.33'/>And the whole town was gathered together at the door.<verse eID='Mark.1.33'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.34' sID='Mark.1.34'/>And he healed many <seg type='x-idiom'>˻who were sick˼</seg><note>Literally “who were having badly”</note> with various diseases and expelled many demons. And he did not permit the demons to speak, because they knew him.<verse eID='Mark.1.34'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Preaching Throughout Galilee</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.1.35' sID='Mark.1.35'/>And getting up early in the morning <transChange type='added'>while it was</transChange> very dark, he departed and went to a deserted place, and there he was praying.<verse eID='Mark.1.35'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.36' sID='Mark.1.36'/>And Simon and those <transChange type='added'>who were</transChange> with him searched diligently for him.<verse eID='Mark.1.36'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.37' sID='Mark.1.37'/>And they found him and said to him, “Everyone is looking for you!”<verse eID='Mark.1.37'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.38' sID='Mark.1.38'/>And he said to them, “Let us go elsewhere, into the neighboring rural towns, so that I can preach there also, because I have come out for this <transChange type='added'>very</transChange> reason.”<verse eID='Mark.1.38'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.39' sID='Mark.1.39'/>And he went into all Galilee preaching in their synagogues and expelling demons.<verse eID='Mark.1.39'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Leper Cleansed</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.1.40' sID='Mark.1.40'/>And a leper came to him, entreating him and kneeling down and saying to him, “If you are willing, you are able to make me clean.”<verse eID='Mark.1.40'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.41' sID='Mark.1.41'/>And having compassion, he stretched out his hand <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stretched out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> touched <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note>, and said to him, “I am willing; be made clean.”<verse eID='Mark.1.41'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.42' sID='Mark.1.42'/>And immediately the leprosy went away from him and he was made clean.<verse eID='Mark.1.42'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.43' sID='Mark.1.43'/>And warning him sternly, he sent him away at once.<verse eID='Mark.1.43'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.44' sID='Mark.1.44'/>And he said to him, “See to it that you say nothing to anyone, but go, show yourself to the priest and bring for your cleansing <transChange type='added'>the things</transChange> which Moses commanded, for a testimony to them.<verse eID='Mark.1.44'/> <verse osisID='Mark.1.45' sID='Mark.1.45'/>But he went out <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to proclaim <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> freely and to spread abroad the account, so that he was no longer able to enter publicly into a town. But he was staying outside in deserted places, and they were coming to him from all directions.<verse eID='Mark.1.45'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
<chapter osisID='Mark.2'>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Paralytic Healed</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.2.1' sID='Mark.2.1'/>And <transChange type='added'>when he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“entered”) which is understood as temporal</note> entered again into Capernaum after <transChange type='added'>some</transChange> days, it became known that he was at home.<verse eID='Mark.2.1'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.2' sID='Mark.2.2'/>And many had gathered, so that <transChange type='added'>there was</transChange> no longer room, not even at the door, and he was speaking the word to them.<verse eID='Mark.2.2'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.3' sID='Mark.2.3'/>And they came bringing to him a paralytic, carried by four <transChange type='added'>of them</transChange>.<verse eID='Mark.2.3'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.4' sID='Mark.2.4'/>And <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“able”) which is understood as temporal</note> they were not able to bring <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to him because of the crowd, they removed the roof where he was. And <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“digging through”) which is understood as temporal</note> digging through, they lowered the stretcher on which the paralytic was lying.<verse eID='Mark.2.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.5' sID='Mark.2.5'/>And <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus saw their faith, he said to the paralytic, “Child, your sins are forgiven.”<verse eID='Mark.2.5'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.2.6' sID='Mark.2.6'/>Now some of the scribes were sitting there and reasoning in their hearts,<verse eID='Mark.2.6'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.7' sID='Mark.2.7'/>“Why does this man speak like this? He is blaspheming! Who is able to forgive sins except God alone?”<verse eID='Mark.2.7'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.8' sID='Mark.2.8'/>And immediately Jesus, perceiving in his spirit that they were reasoning like this within themselves, said to them, “Why are you considering these <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> in your hearts?<verse eID='Mark.2.8'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.9' sID='Mark.2.9'/>Which is easier to say to the paralytic, ‘Your sins are forgiven,’ or to say ‘Get up and pick up your stretcher and walk’?<verse eID='Mark.2.9'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.10' sID='Mark.2.10'/>But so that you may know that the Son of Man has authority on earth to forgive sins,”—he said to the paralytic—<verse eID='Mark.2.10'/><verse osisID='Mark.2.11' sID='Mark.2.11'/>“I say to you, get up, pick up your stretcher, and go to your home.”<verse eID='Mark.2.11'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.12' sID='Mark.2.12'/>And he got up and immediately picked up his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> stretcher <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“picked up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went out in front of <transChange type='added'>them</transChange> all, so that they were all amazed and glorified God, saying, “We have never seen <transChange type='added'>anything</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> like this!”<verse eID='Mark.2.12'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Levi Called to Follow Jesus</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.2.13' sID='Mark.2.13'/>And he went out again beside the sea,<note>That is, the Sea of Galilee</note> and all the crowd was coming to him, and he began to teach<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to teach”)</note> them.<verse eID='Mark.2.13'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.14' sID='Mark.2.14'/>And <transChange type='added'>as he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was passing by”) which is understood as temporal</note> was passing by, he saw Levi the <transChange type='added'>son</transChange> of Alphaeus sitting at the tax booth, and he said to him, “Follow me!” And he stood up <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stood up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> followed him.<verse eID='Mark.2.14'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.2.15' sID='Mark.2.15'/>And it happened that he <seg type='x-idiom'>˻was dining˼</seg><note>Literally “was reclining for a meal”</note> in his house, and many tax collectors and sinners <seg type='x-idiom'>˻were dining with˼</seg><note>Literally “were reclining at table with”</note> Jesus and his disciples, for there were many and they were following him.<verse eID='Mark.2.15'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.16' sID='Mark.2.16'/>And the scribes of the Pharisees, <transChange type='added'>when they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw that he was eating with sinners and tax collectors, began to say<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to say”)</note> to his disciples, “Why does he eat with tax collectors and sinners?”<verse eID='Mark.2.16'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.17' sID='Mark.2.17'/>And <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus heard <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note>, he said to them, “Those who are healthy do not have need of a physician, but those <seg type='x-idiom'>˻who are sick˼</seg>.<note>Literally “having badly”</note> I have not come to call the righteous, but sinners.”<verse eID='Mark.2.17'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>On Fasting</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.2.18' sID='Mark.2.18'/>And John’s disciples and the Pharisees were fasting, and they came and said to him, “<seg type='x-idiom'>˻Why˼</seg><note>Literally “for what” <catchWord>reason</catchWord></note> do the disciples of John and the disciples of the Pharisees fast, but your disciples do not fast?”<verse eID='Mark.2.18'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.19' sID='Mark.2.19'/>And Jesus said to them, “The <seg type='x-idiom'>˻bridegroom’s attendants˼</seg><note>Literally “the sons of the bridal chamber”</note> are not able to fast while the bridegroom is with them, <transChange type='added'>are they</transChange>?<note>The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<catchWord>are they</catchWord>”</note> As long a time <transChange type='added'>as</transChange> they have the bridegroom with them, they are not able to fast.<verse eID='Mark.2.19'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.20' sID='Mark.2.20'/>But days will come when the bridegroom is taken away from them, and then they will fast in that day.<verse eID='Mark.2.20'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.21' sID='Mark.2.21'/>No one sews a patch of unshrunken cloth on an old garment. <seg type='x-idiom'>˻Otherwise˼</seg><note>Literally “but if not”</note> the patch pulls away from it—the new from the old—and the tear becomes worse.<verse eID='Mark.2.21'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.22' sID='Mark.2.22'/>And no one puts new wine into old wineskins. <seg type='x-idiom'>˻Otherwise˼</seg><note>Literally “but if not”</note> the wine will burst the wineskins and the wine is destroyed and the wineskins <transChange type='added'>too</transChange>. But new wine <transChange type='added'>is put</transChange> into new wineskins.”<verse eID='Mark.2.22'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Plucking Grain on the Sabbath</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.2.23' sID='Mark.2.23'/>And it happened that he was going through the grain fields on the Sabbath, and his disciples began to make <transChange type='added'>their</transChange> way <transChange type='added'>while</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>while</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“picking”) which is understood as temporal</note> plucking off the heads of grain.<verse eID='Mark.2.23'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.24' sID='Mark.2.24'/>And the Pharisees began to say<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to say”)</note> to him, “Behold, why are they doing what is not permitted on the Sabbath?”<verse eID='Mark.2.24'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.25' sID='Mark.2.25'/>And he said to them, “Have you never read what David did when he had need and he and those <transChange type='added'>who were</transChange> with him were hungry—<verse eID='Mark.2.25'/><verse osisID='Mark.2.26' sID='Mark.2.26'/>how he entered into the house of God in the time of Abiathar the high priest and ate the bread of the presentation, which it is not permitted to eat (except the priests) and also gave <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to those who were with him?”<verse eID='Mark.2.26'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.27' sID='Mark.2.27'/>And he said to them, “The Sabbath was established for people, and not people for the Sabbath.<verse eID='Mark.2.27'/> <verse osisID='Mark.2.28' sID='Mark.2.28'/>So then, the Son of Man is lord even of the Sabbath.”<verse eID='Mark.2.28'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
<chapter osisID='Mark.3'>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Man with a Withered Hand Healed</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.3.1' sID='Mark.3.1'/>And he entered into the synagogue again, and a man who had a withered hand was there.<verse eID='Mark.3.1'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.2' sID='Mark.3.2'/>And they were watching him closely <transChange type='added'>to see</transChange> if he would heal him on the Sabbath, in order that they could accuse him.<verse eID='Mark.3.2'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.3' sID='Mark.3.3'/>And he said to the man who had the withered hand, “Come into the middle.”<verse eID='Mark.3.3'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.4' sID='Mark.3.4'/>And he said to them, “Is it permitted on the Sabbath to do good or to do evil, to save life or to kill?” But they were silent.<verse eID='Mark.3.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.5' sID='Mark.3.5'/>And looking around at them with anger, grieved at the hardness of their hearts, he said to the man, “Stretch out your<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hand.” And he stretched <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> out, and his hand was restored.<verse eID='Mark.3.5'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.6' sID='Mark.3.6'/>And the Pharisees went out immediately with the Herodians <seg type='x-idiom'>˻and began to conspire˼</seg><note>Literally “began to give counsel”; the imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive (“began to”)</note> against him with regard to how they could destroy him.<verse eID='Mark.3.6'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus Heals Crowds by the Sea</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.3.7' sID='Mark.3.7'/>And Jesus went away with his disciples to the sea,<note>That is, the Sea of Galilee</note> and a great crowd from Galilee followed <transChange type='added'>him</transChange>.<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> And from Judea<verse eID='Mark.3.7'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.8' sID='Mark.3.8'/>and from Jerusalem and from Idumea and the other side of the Jordan and around Tyre and Sidon a great crowd came to him <transChange type='added'>because they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>because</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as causal</note> heard all that he was doing.<verse eID='Mark.3.8'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.9' sID='Mark.3.9'/>And he told his disciples that a small boat should stand ready for him because of the crowd, so that they would not press upon him.<verse eID='Mark.3.9'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.10' sID='Mark.3.10'/>For he had healed many, so that all those who <seg type='x-idiom'>˻were suffering from diseases˼</seg><note>Literally “had suffering”</note> pressed about him in order that they could touch him.<verse eID='Mark.3.10'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.11' sID='Mark.3.11'/>And the unclean spirits, whenever they saw him, were falling down before him and crying out, saying, “You are the Son of God!”<verse eID='Mark.3.11'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.12' sID='Mark.3.12'/>And he warned them strictly that they should not make him known.<verse eID='Mark.3.12'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Selection of the Twelve Apostles</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.3.13' sID='Mark.3.13'/>And he went up on the mountain and summoned <transChange type='added'>those</transChange> whom he wanted, and they came to him.<verse eID='Mark.3.13'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.14' sID='Mark.3.14'/>And he appointed twelve, whom he also named apostles,<note>Most later Greek manuscripts omit the phrase “whom he also named apostles”</note> so that they would be with him and so that he could send them out to preach<verse eID='Mark.3.14'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.15' sID='Mark.3.15'/>and to have authority to expel demons.<verse eID='Mark.3.15'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.16' sID='Mark.3.16'/>And he appointed the twelve.<note>Most Greek manuscripts omit the phrase “and he appointed the twelve”</note> And to Simon he gave the name Peter,<verse eID='Mark.3.16'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.17' sID='Mark.3.17'/>and James the <transChange type='added'>son</transChange> of Zebedee and John the brother of James (and he gave to them the name Boanerges, that is, “Sons of Thunder”),<verse eID='Mark.3.17'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.18' sID='Mark.3.18'/>and Andrew, and Philip, and Bartholomew, and Matthew, and Thomas, and James the <transChange type='added'>son</transChange> of Alphaeus, and Thaddaeus, and Simon the Zealot,<note>Literally “the Cananean,” but according to BDAG 507 s.v., this term has no relation at all to the geographical terms for Cana or Canaan, but is derived from the Aramaic term for “enthusiast, zealot” (see <reference osisRef='Luke.6.15'>Luke 6:15</reference>; <reference osisRef='Acts.1.13'>Acts 1:13</reference>)</note><verse eID='Mark.3.18'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.19' sID='Mark.3.19'/>and Judas Iscariot, who also betrayed him.<verse eID='Mark.3.19'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>A House Divided Cannot Stand</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.3.20' sID='Mark.3.20'/>And he went home, and the crowd gathered again, so that they were not even able to eat a meal.<verse eID='Mark.3.20'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.21' sID='Mark.3.21'/>And <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> <seg type='x-idiom'>˻his family˼</seg><note>Literally <catchWord>those</catchWord> “close to him”</note> heard <transChange type='added'>this</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they went out to restrain him, for they were saying, “He has lost his mind!”<verse eID='Mark.3.21'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.3.22' sID='Mark.3.22'/>And the scribes who had come down from Jerusalem were saying, “He is possessed by Beelzebul!” and “By the ruler of the demons he expels the demons!”<verse eID='Mark.3.22'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.23' sID='Mark.3.23'/>And he called them to himself <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“called”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> was speaking to them in parables, “How can Satan expel Satan?<verse eID='Mark.3.23'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.24' sID='Mark.3.24'/>And if a kingdom is divided against itself, that kingdom is not able to stand.<verse eID='Mark.3.24'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.25' sID='Mark.3.25'/>And if a house is divided against itself, that house will not be able to stand.<verse eID='Mark.3.25'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.26' sID='Mark.3.26'/>And if Satan has risen up against himself and is divided, he is not able to stand, but is at an end!<verse eID='Mark.3.26'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.27' sID='Mark.3.27'/>But no one is able to enter into the house of a strong <transChange type='added'>man</transChange> <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“enter”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> plunder his property unless he first ties up the strong <transChange type='added'>man</transChange>, and then he can thoroughly plunder his house.<verse eID='Mark.3.27'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.3.28' sID='Mark.3.28'/>“Truly I say to you that all the sins and the blasphemies will be forgiven the sons of men, however much they blaspheme.<verse eID='Mark.3.28'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.29' sID='Mark.3.29'/>But whoever blasphemes against the Holy Spirit does not have forgiveness <seg type='x-idiom'>˻forever˼</seg>,<note>Literally “for the age”</note> but is guilty of <transChange type='added'>an</transChange> eternal sin”—<verse eID='Mark.3.29'/><verse osisID='Mark.3.30' sID='Mark.3.30'/>because they were saying, “He has an unclean spirit.”<verse eID='Mark.3.30'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus’ Mother and Brothers</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.3.31' sID='Mark.3.31'/>And his mother and his brothers arrived, and standing outside, they sent <transChange type='added'>word</transChange> to him to summon him.<verse eID='Mark.3.31'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.32' sID='Mark.3.32'/>And a crowd was sitting around him, and they told him, “Behold, your mother and your brothers and your sisters<note>Some significant manuscripts omit the phrase “and your sisters”</note> <transChange type='added'>are</transChange> outside looking for you.<verse eID='Mark.3.32'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.33' sID='Mark.3.33'/>And he answered them <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Who are my mother and my brothers?”<verse eID='Mark.3.33'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.34' sID='Mark.3.34'/>And looking around at those who were sitting around him in a circle, he said, “Behold, my mother and my brothers!<verse eID='Mark.3.34'/> <verse osisID='Mark.3.35' sID='Mark.3.35'/>For whoever does the will of God, this person is my brother and sister and mother.”<verse eID='Mark.3.35'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
<chapter osisID='Mark.4'>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Parable of the Sower</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.4.1' sID='Mark.4.1'/>And again he began to teach beside the sea,<note>That is, the Sea of Galilee</note> and a very large crowd was gathered to him, so that he got into a boat <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “and” is supplied because the previous participle (“got”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> sat on the sea, and the whole crowd was at the sea on the land.<verse eID='Mark.4.1'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.2' sID='Mark.4.2'/>And he began to teach<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to teach”)</note> them many <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> in parables, and was saying to them in his teaching,<verse eID='Mark.4.2'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.3' sID='Mark.4.3'/>“Listen! Behold, the sower went out to sow.<verse eID='Mark.4.3'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.4' sID='Mark.4.4'/>And it happened that while <transChange type='added'>he</transChange> was sowing, <seg type='x-idiom'>˻some seed˼</seg><note>Literally “<catchWord>some of</catchWord> which”</note> fell on the side of the path, and the birds came and devoured it.<verse eID='Mark.4.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.5' sID='Mark.4.5'/>And other <transChange type='added'>seed</transChange> fell on the rocky ground where it did not have much soil, and it sprang up at once, because it did not have <transChange type='added'>any</transChange> depth of soil.<verse eID='Mark.4.5'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.6' sID='Mark.4.6'/>And when the sun rose it was scorched, and because it did not have <transChange type='added'>enough</transChange> root, it withered.<verse eID='Mark.4.6'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.7' sID='Mark.4.7'/>And other <transChange type='added'>seed</transChange> fell among the thorn plants, and the thorn plants came up and choked it, and it did not produce grain.<note>Literally “fruit,” describing here the grain harvested from the healthy plants; in contemporary English this would more naturally be expressed by terms like “grain” or “crop”</note><verse eID='Mark.4.7'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.8' sID='Mark.4.8'/>And other <transChange type='added'>seed</transChange> fell on the good soil, and produced grain,<note>Literally “fruit,” describing here the grain harvested from the healthy plants; in contemporary English this would more naturally be expressed by terms like “grain” or “crop”</note> coming up and increasing, and it bore <transChange type='added'>a crop</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note>—one thirty and one sixty and one a hundred <transChange type='added'>times as much</transChange>.<note>The phrase “<catchWord>times as much</catchWord>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note><verse eID='Mark.4.8'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.9' sID='Mark.4.9'/>And he said, “Whoever has ears to hear, let him hear!”<verse eID='Mark.4.9'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Reason for the Parables</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.4.10' sID='Mark.4.10'/>And when he was alone, those around him together with the twelve began asking<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began asking”)</note> him about the parables.<verse eID='Mark.4.10'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.11' sID='Mark.4.11'/>And he said to them, “To you has been granted the secret of the kingdom of God, but to those who are outside everything is in parables,<verse eID='Mark.4.11'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.12' sID='Mark.4.12'/>so that</p>
<lg>
<l level='1'>‘<seg type='x-idiom'>˻they may look closely˼</seg><note>Literally “seeing they may see”</note> and not perceive,</l>
<l level='2'>and <seg type='x-idiom'>˻they may listen carefully˼</seg><note>Literally “hearing they may hear”</note> and not understand,</l>
<l level='1'>lest they turn and it be forgiven them.’ ”<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Isa.6.9-Isa.6.10'>Isa 6:9–10</reference></note><verse eID='Mark.4.12'/></l>
</lg>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Parable of the Sower Interpreted</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.4.13' sID='Mark.4.13'/>And he said to them, “Do you not understand this parable? And how will you understand all the parables?<verse eID='Mark.4.13'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.14' sID='Mark.4.14'/>The sower sows the word.<verse eID='Mark.4.14'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.15' sID='Mark.4.15'/>And these are the ones beside the path where the word is sown, and whenever they hear <transChange type='added'>it</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> immediately Satan comes and takes away the word that was sown in them.<verse eID='Mark.4.15'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.16' sID='Mark.4.16'/>And these are the ones sown on the rocky ground, who whenever they hear the word immediately receive it with joy.<verse eID='Mark.4.16'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.17' sID='Mark.4.17'/>And they have no root in themselves, but are temporary. Then <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“comes”)</note> affliction or persecution comes because of the word, immediately they fall away.<verse eID='Mark.4.17'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.18' sID='Mark.4.18'/>And others are the ones sown among the thorn plants—these are the ones who hear the word,<verse eID='Mark.4.18'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.19' sID='Mark.4.19'/>and the cares of the world and the deceitfulness of wealth and the desires for other <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> come in <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“come in”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> choke the word and it becomes unproductive.<verse eID='Mark.4.19'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.20' sID='Mark.4.20'/>And those are the ones sown on the good soil, who hear the word and receive <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and bear fruit—one thirty and one sixty and one a hundred <transChange type='added'>times as much</transChange>.”<note>The phrase “<catchWord>times as much</catchWord>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note><verse eID='Mark.4.20'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Parable of the Lamp</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.4.21' sID='Mark.4.21'/>And he said to them, “Surely a lamp is not brought so that it may be put under a bushel basket or under a bed, <transChange type='added'>is it</transChange>?<note>The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase “<catchWord>is it</catchWord>”</note> <transChange type='added'>Is it</transChange> not<note>The negative construction in Greek anticipates a positive answer here</note> so that it may be put on a lampstand?<verse eID='Mark.4.21'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.22' sID='Mark.4.22'/>For nothing is secret except so that it may be revealed, nor has become hidden except so that it will come to light.<verse eID='Mark.4.22'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.23' sID='Mark.4.23'/>If anyone has ears to hear, let him hear!”<verse eID='Mark.4.23'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.24' sID='Mark.4.24'/>And he said to them, “Take care what you hear! With the measure by which you measure out, it will be measured out to you, and will be added to you.<verse eID='Mark.4.24'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.25' sID='Mark.4.25'/>For whoever has, <transChange type='added'>more</transChange> will be given to him, and whoever does not have, even what he has will be taken away from him.”<verse eID='Mark.4.25'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Parable of the Seed that Grows by Itself</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.4.26' sID='Mark.4.26'/>And he said, “The kingdom of God is like this: like a man scatters seed on the ground.<verse eID='Mark.4.26'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.27' sID='Mark.4.27'/>And he sleeps and gets up, night and day, and the seed sprouts and grows—<seg type='x-idiom'>˻he does not know how˼</seg>.<note>Literally “<catchWord>in such a way</catchWord> as he does not know”</note><verse eID='Mark.4.27'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.28' sID='Mark.4.28'/>By itself the soil produces a crop: first the grass, then the head of grain, then the full grain in the head.<verse eID='Mark.4.28'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.29' sID='Mark.4.29'/>But when the crop permits, he sends <transChange type='added'>in</transChange> the sickle right away, because the harvest has come.”<verse eID='Mark.4.29'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Parable of the Mustard Seed</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.4.30' sID='Mark.4.30'/>And he said, “With what can we compare the kingdom of God, or by what parable can we present it?<verse eID='Mark.4.30'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.31' sID='Mark.4.31'/><transChange type='added'>It is</transChange> like a mustard seed that when sown on the ground, <transChange type='added'>although it</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>although</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is”) which is understood as concessive</note> is the smallest of all the seeds that <transChange type='added'>are</transChange> on the ground,<verse eID='Mark.4.31'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.32' sID='Mark.4.32'/>but when it is sown it grows up and becomes the largest of all the garden herbs, and sends out large branches so that the birds of the sky are able to nest in its shade.”<verse eID='Mark.4.32'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.33' sID='Mark.4.33'/>And with many parables such as these he was speaking the word to them, as they were able to hear <transChange type='added'>it</transChange>.<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note><verse eID='Mark.4.33'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.34' sID='Mark.4.34'/>And he did not speak to them without a parable, but in private he explained everything to his own disciples.<verse eID='Mark.4.34'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Calming of a Storm</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.4.35' sID='Mark.4.35'/>And on that day, <transChange type='added'>when it</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> was evening, he said to them, “Let us cross over to the other side.”<verse eID='Mark.4.35'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.36' sID='Mark.4.36'/>And leaving the crowd, they took him along, as he was, in the boat. And other boats were with him.<verse eID='Mark.4.36'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.37' sID='Mark.4.37'/>And a great storm of wind developed, and the waves were breaking into the boat, so that the boat was already being filled <transChange type='added'>with water</transChange>.<note>The words “<catchWord>with water</catchWord>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note><verse eID='Mark.4.37'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.38' sID='Mark.4.38'/>And he was in the stern sleeping on the cushion, and they woke him up and said to him, “Teacher, is it not a concern to you that we are perishing?”<verse eID='Mark.4.38'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.39' sID='Mark.4.39'/>And he woke up <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“woke up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> rebuked the wind, and said to the sea, “Be quiet! Be silent!” And the wind abated and there was a great calm.<verse eID='Mark.4.39'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.40' sID='Mark.4.40'/>And he said to them, “Why are you fearful? Do you not yet have faith?”<verse eID='Mark.4.40'/> <verse osisID='Mark.4.41' sID='Mark.4.41'/>And <seg type='x-idiom'>˻they were terribly frightened˼</seg><note>Literally “they feared a great fear”</note> and began to say<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to say”)</note> to one another, “Who then is this, that even the wind and the sea obey him?”<verse eID='Mark.4.41'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
<chapter osisID='Mark.5'>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Demon-possessed Gerasene Healed</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.5.1' sID='Mark.5.1'/>And they came to the other side of the sea,<note>That is, the Sea of Galilee</note> to the region of the Gerasenes.<note>Most later manuscripts read "Gadarenes," while other manuscripts read “Gergesenes” here</note><verse eID='Mark.5.1'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.2' sID='Mark.5.2'/>And <transChange type='added'>as</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was getting out”)</note> he was getting out of the boat, immediately from the tombs a man with an unclean spirit went to meet him,<verse eID='Mark.5.2'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.3' sID='Mark.5.3'/>who <seg type='x-idiom'>˻lived˼</seg><note>Literally “had his dwelling”</note> among the tombs. And no one was able to bind him any longer, not even with a chain,<verse eID='Mark.5.3'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.4' sID='Mark.5.4'/>because he had often been bound with shackles and chains, and the chains had been torn apart by him, and the shackles had been shattered. And no one was strong <transChange type='added'>enough</transChange> to subdue him.<verse eID='Mark.5.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.5' sID='Mark.5.5'/>And during every night and day among the tombs and on the mountains he was crying out and cutting himself with stones.<verse eID='Mark.5.5'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.6' sID='Mark.5.6'/>And <transChange type='added'>when he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw Jesus from a distance, he ran and knelt down before him.<verse eID='Mark.5.6'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.7' sID='Mark.5.7'/>And crying out with a loud voice he said, “<seg type='x-idiom'>˻What have I to do with you˼</seg><note>Literally “what to me and to you”</note>, Jesus, Son of the Most High God? I implore you by God, do not torment me!”<verse eID='Mark.5.7'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.8' sID='Mark.5.8'/>(For he was saying to him, “Come out of the man, unclean spirit!”)<verse eID='Mark.5.8'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.9' sID='Mark.5.9'/>And he was asking him “<seg type='x-idiom'>˻What is your name˼</seg>?”<note>Literally “what name to you”</note> And he said to him, “My name <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> Legion, because we are many.”<verse eID='Mark.5.9'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.10' sID='Mark.5.10'/>And he was imploring him many <transChange type='added'>times</transChange> that he would not send them out of the region.<verse eID='Mark.5.10'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.11' sID='Mark.5.11'/>Now a large herd of pigs was there at the hill feeding,<verse eID='Mark.5.11'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.12' sID='Mark.5.12'/>and they implored him, saying, “Send us to the pigs so that we may enter into them.”<verse eID='Mark.5.12'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.13' sID='Mark.5.13'/>And he permitted them. And the unclean spirits came out <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> entered into the pigs, and the herd—about two thousand—rushed headlong down the steep slope into the sea and were drowned in the sea.<verse eID='Mark.5.13'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.14' sID='Mark.5.14'/>And their herdsmen fled and reported <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in the town and in the countryside, and they came to see what it was that had happened.<verse eID='Mark.5.14'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.15' sID='Mark.5.15'/>And they came to Jesus and saw the demon-possessed man sitting <transChange type='added'>there</transChange> clothed and in his right mind—the one who had had the legion—and they were afraid.<verse eID='Mark.5.15'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.16' sID='Mark.5.16'/>And those who had seen <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> described to them what had happened to the demon-possessed man, and about the pigs.<verse eID='Mark.5.16'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.17' sID='Mark.5.17'/>And they began to urge him to depart from their region.<verse eID='Mark.5.17'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.18' sID='Mark.5.18'/>And <transChange type='added'>as</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was getting”)</note> he was getting into the boat, the man who had been demon-possessed began to implore<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to implore”)</note> him that he could go with him.<verse eID='Mark.5.18'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.19' sID='Mark.5.19'/>And he did not permit him, but said to him, “Go to your home to your <transChange type='added'>people</transChange> and tell them all that the Lord has done for you, and <transChange type='added'>that</transChange> he has had mercy on you.”<verse eID='Mark.5.19'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.20' sID='Mark.5.20'/>And he went away and began to proclaim in the Decapolis all that Jesus had done for him, and they were all astonished.<verse eID='Mark.5.20'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Woman Healed and a Daughter Raised</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.5.21' sID='Mark.5.21'/>And <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had crossed over”)</note> Jesus had crossed over again in the boat to the other side, a large crowd gathered to him, and he was beside the sea.<verse eID='Mark.5.21'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.22' sID='Mark.5.22'/>And one of the rulers of the synagogue came—Jairus by name—and <transChange type='added'>when he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw him, he fell down at his feet.<verse eID='Mark.5.22'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.23' sID='Mark.5.23'/>And he was imploring him many <transChange type='added'>times</transChange>, saying, “My little daughter <seg type='x-idiom'>˻is at the point of death˼</seg>!<note>Literally “has finally”</note> Come, lay your<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands on her, so that she will get well and will live.”<verse eID='Mark.5.23'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.24' sID='Mark.5.24'/>And he went with him, and a large crowd was following him and pressing around him.<verse eID='Mark.5.24'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.5.25' sID='Mark.5.25'/>And <transChange type='added'>there was</transChange> a woman who was <seg type='x-idiom'>˻suffering from hemorrhages˼</seg><note>Literally “with a flow of blood”</note> twelve years.<verse eID='Mark.5.25'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.26' sID='Mark.5.26'/>And she had endured many <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> under many physicians, and had spent <seg type='x-idiom'>˻all that she had˼</seg><note>Literally “all with her”</note> and had received no <transChange type='added'>help</transChange> at all, but instead <seg type='x-idiom'>˻became worse˼</seg>.<note>Literally “came back for the worse”</note><verse eID='Mark.5.26'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.27' sID='Mark.5.27'/><transChange type='added'>When she</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard about Jesus, she came up in the crowd behind <transChange type='added'>him</transChange> <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> touched his cloak,<verse eID='Mark.5.27'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.28' sID='Mark.5.28'/>for she was saying, “If I touch just his clothing, I will be healed!”<verse eID='Mark.5.28'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.29' sID='Mark.5.29'/>And immediately her <seg type='x-idiom'>˻hemorrhage stopped˼</seg><note>Literally “flow of blood was dried up”</note> and she realized in her<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> body that she was healed of her<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> suffering.<verse eID='Mark.5.29'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.30' sID='Mark.5.30'/>And immediately Jesus, perceiving in himself <transChange type='added'>that</transChange> power had gone out from himself, turned around in the crowd <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“turned around”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Who touched my clothing?”<verse eID='Mark.5.30'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.31' sID='Mark.5.31'/>And his disciples said to him, “You see the crowd pressing upon you, and you say ‘Who touched me?’ ”<verse eID='Mark.5.31'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.32' sID='Mark.5.32'/>And he was looking around to see the one who had done this.<verse eID='Mark.5.32'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.33' sID='Mark.5.33'/>So the woman, frightened and trembling, knowing what had happened to her, came and fell down before him and told him the whole truth.<verse eID='Mark.5.33'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.34' sID='Mark.5.34'/>But he said to her, “Daughter, your faith has healed you. Go in peace and be well from your suffering.”<verse eID='Mark.5.34'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.5.35' sID='Mark.5.35'/><transChange type='added'>While</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>while</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“speaking”)</note> he was still speaking, they came from the synagogue ruler’s <transChange type='added'>house</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>house</catchWord>” is implied since the synagogue ruler himself is directly addressed (and therefore present) in the remainder of this verse</note> saying, “Your daughter has died. Why trouble the Teacher further?”<verse eID='Mark.5.35'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.36' sID='Mark.5.36'/>But Jesus, ignoring<note>Or “overhearing”</note> <seg type='x-idiom'>˻what was said˼</seg>,<note>Literally “the report that was spoken”</note> told the ruler of the synagogue, “Do not be afraid—only believe!”<verse eID='Mark.5.36'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.37' sID='Mark.5.37'/>And he did not allow anyone to follow along with him except Peter and James and John, the brother of James.<verse eID='Mark.5.37'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.38' sID='Mark.5.38'/>And they came to the house of the ruler of the synagogue and saw a commotion, and <transChange type='added'>people</transChange> weeping and wailing loudly.<verse eID='Mark.5.38'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.39' sID='Mark.5.39'/>And <transChange type='added'>when he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“entered”) which is understood as temporal</note> entered, he said to them, “Why are you agitated and weeping? The child is not dead, but is sleeping.”<verse eID='Mark.5.39'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.40' sID='Mark.5.40'/>And they began laughing<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began laughing”)</note> at him. But he sent <transChange type='added'>them</transChange> all out <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sent … out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> took along the father and mother of the child, and those <transChange type='added'>who were</transChange> with him, and went in to where the child was.<verse eID='Mark.5.40'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.41' sID='Mark.5.41'/>And taking hold of the child’s hand, he said to her, “<hi type='italic'>Talitha koum!</hi>” (which is translated, “Little girl, I say to you, get up!”),<verse eID='Mark.5.41'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.42' sID='Mark.5.42'/>and immediately the girl stood up and began walking around<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began walking around”)</note> (for she was twelve years old). And <seg type='x-idiom'>˻immediately they were utterly and completely astonished˼</seg>.<note>Literally “immediately they were astonished with great astonishment”</note><verse eID='Mark.5.42'/> <verse osisID='Mark.5.43' sID='Mark.5.43'/>And he commanded them strictly that no one should learn of this, and said to give her <transChange type='added'>something</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to eat.<verse eID='Mark.5.43'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
<chapter osisID='Mark.6'>
<div type='section'>
<title>Rejected at Nazareth</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.6.1' sID='Mark.6.1'/>And he went out from there and came to his hometown, and his disciples followed him.<verse eID='Mark.6.1'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.2' sID='Mark.6.2'/>And <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“came”)</note> the Sabbath came, he began to teach in the synagogue, and many who heard <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> were amazed, saying, “Where did this man <transChange type='added'>get</transChange> these <transChange type='added'>things</transChange>? And what <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> this wisdom that has been granted to this man, and the miracles such as these performed through his hands?<verse eID='Mark.6.2'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.3' sID='Mark.6.3'/>Is not this the carpenter, the son of Mary and brother of James and Joses and Judas and Simon? And are not his sisters here with us?” And they were offended by him.<verse eID='Mark.6.3'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.4' sID='Mark.6.4'/>And Jesus said to them, “A prophet is not without honor except in his hometown, and among his relatives, and in his <transChange type='added'>own</transChange> household.”<verse eID='Mark.6.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.5' sID='Mark.6.5'/>And he was not able to do any miracle in that place except to lay his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands on a few sick <transChange type='added'>people</transChange> <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“lay”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> heal <transChange type='added'>them</transChange>.<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note><verse eID='Mark.6.5'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.6' sID='Mark.6.6'/>And he was astonished because of their unbelief.</p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Twelve Commissioned and Sent Out</title>
<p>And he was going around among the villages teaching.<verse eID='Mark.6.6'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.7' sID='Mark.6.7'/>And he summoned the twelve and began to send them out two <transChange type='added'>by</transChange> two, and gave them authority over the unclean spirits.<verse eID='Mark.6.7'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.8' sID='Mark.6.8'/>And he commanded them that they take along nothing for the journey except only a staff—no bread, no traveler’s bag, no money in their<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> belts—<verse eID='Mark.6.8'/><verse osisID='Mark.6.9' sID='Mark.6.9'/>but to put on sandals and not to wear two tunics.<verse eID='Mark.6.9'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.10' sID='Mark.6.10'/>And he said to them, “Whenever you enter into a house, stay there until you depart from there.<verse eID='Mark.6.10'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.11' sID='Mark.6.11'/>And whatever place does not welcome you or listen to you, <transChange type='added'>as you</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“go out”) which is understood as temporal</note> go out from there, shake off the dust that is on your feet for a testimony against them.”<verse eID='Mark.6.11'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.12' sID='Mark.6.12'/>And they went out <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> proclaimed that <transChange type='added'>people</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>people</catchWord>” is supplied as the subject because a third-person pronoun (“they”) would be ambiguous</note> should repent.<verse eID='Mark.6.12'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.13' sID='Mark.6.13'/>And they were expelling many demons and anointing many sick <transChange type='added'>people</transChange> with olive oil and healing <transChange type='added'>them</transChange>.<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note><verse eID='Mark.6.13'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Herod Kills John the Baptist</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.6.14' sID='Mark.6.14'/>And King Herod heard <transChange type='added'>it</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> because his name had become known. And they were saying, “John, the one who baptizes, has been raised from the dead, and because of this these miraculous powers are at work in him.”<verse eID='Mark.6.14'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.15' sID='Mark.6.15'/>But others were saying, “He is Elijah,” and others were saying, “<transChange type='added'>He is</transChange> a prophet like one of the prophets.”<verse eID='Mark.6.15'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.16' sID='Mark.6.16'/>But <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> Herod heard <transChange type='added'>it</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he said, “John whom I beheaded—this one has been raised!”<verse eID='Mark.6.16'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.17' sID='Mark.6.17'/>For Herod himself had sent <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“had sent”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> arrested John and bound him in prison because of Herodias, the wife of Philip his brother, because he had married her.<verse eID='Mark.6.17'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.18' sID='Mark.6.18'/>For John had been saying to Herod, “It is not permitted for you to have your brother’s wife.”<verse eID='Mark.6.18'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.19' sID='Mark.6.19'/>So Herodias held a grudge against him and was wanting to kill him, and was not able <transChange type='added'>to do so</transChange>.<verse eID='Mark.6.19'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.20' sID='Mark.6.20'/>For Herod was afraid of John, <transChange type='added'>because he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>because</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“knew”) which is understood as causal</note> knew him <transChange type='added'>to be</transChange> a righteous and holy man and protected him. And <transChange type='added'>when he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participles (“came in” and “danced”) which are understood as temporal</note> listened to him, he was greatly perplexed, and <transChange type='added'>yet</transChange> he listened to him gladly.<verse eID='Mark.6.20'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.21' sID='Mark.6.21'/>And a suitable day came when Herod, on his birthday, gave a banquet for his courtiers and military tribunes and the most prominent <transChange type='added'>men</transChange> of Galilee.<verse eID='Mark.6.21'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.22' sID='Mark.6.22'/>And <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“listened to”) which is understood as temporal</note> his daughter Herodias<note>Other manuscripts read “the daughter of Herodias herself”</note> came in and danced, she pleased Herod and <seg type='x-idiom'>˻his dinner guests˼</seg>.<note>Literally “those reclining at table with <catchWord>him</catchWord>”</note> The king said to the girl, “Ask me <transChange type='added'>for</transChange> whatever you want, and I will give <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to you.”<verse eID='Mark.6.22'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.23' sID='Mark.6.23'/>And he swore to her at length,<note>A number of important manuscripts omit “at length”</note> “Anything whatever you ask me for I will give you, up to half my kingdom!”<verse eID='Mark.6.23'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.24' sID='Mark.6.24'/>And she went out <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to her mother, “What should I ask for?” And she said, “The head of John the baptizer.”<verse eID='Mark.6.24'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.25' sID='Mark.6.25'/>And she came in immediately with haste to the king <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came in”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> asked, saying, “I want you to give me the head of John the Baptist on a platter immediately.”<verse eID='Mark.6.25'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.26' sID='Mark.6.26'/>And <transChange type='added'>although he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>although</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as concessive</note> was deeply grieved, the king, because of his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> oaths and <seg type='x-idiom'>˻dinner guests˼</seg>,<note>Literally “those who were reclining at table”</note> did not want to refuse her.<verse eID='Mark.6.26'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.27' sID='Mark.6.27'/>And immediately the king sent an executioner <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sent”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> ordered <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to bring his head. And he went <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> beheaded him in the prison.<verse eID='Mark.6.27'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.28' sID='Mark.6.28'/>And he brought his head on a platter and gave it to the girl, and the girl gave it to her mother.<verse eID='Mark.6.28'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.29' sID='Mark.6.29'/>And <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> his disciples heard <transChange type='added'>this</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they came and took away his corpse and placed it in a tomb.<verse eID='Mark.6.29'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Feeding of Five Thousand</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.6.30' sID='Mark.6.30'/>And the apostles regathered to Jesus and reported to him everything that they had done and that they had taught.<verse eID='Mark.6.30'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.31' sID='Mark.6.31'/>And he said to them, “You yourselves come privately to an isolated place and rest for a short time.” For those <transChange type='added'>who were</transChange> coming and going were many, and they did not even have time to eat.<verse eID='Mark.6.31'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.32' sID='Mark.6.32'/>And they went away in the boat to an isolated place by themselves.<verse eID='Mark.6.32'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.33' sID='Mark.6.33'/>And many <transChange type='added'>people</transChange> saw them leaving and recognized <transChange type='added'>them</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and ran there together by land from all the towns, and arrived ahead of them.<verse eID='Mark.6.33'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.34' sID='Mark.6.34'/>And getting out <transChange type='added'>of the boat</transChange><note>The words “<catchWord>of the boat</catchWord>” are not in the Greek text but are implied by this verb, which refers to disembarking from a boat or ship</note> he saw the large crowd and had compassion on them, because they were like sheep <seg type='x-idiom'>˻without˼</seg><note>Literally “not having”</note> a shepherd, and he began to teach them many <transChange type='added'>things</transChange>.<verse eID='Mark.6.34'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.35' sID='Mark.6.35'/>And the hour had already become late <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came up”) which is understood as temporal</note> his disciples came up to him, saying, “The place is desolate and the hour <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> already late.<verse eID='Mark.6.35'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.36' sID='Mark.6.36'/>Send them away so that they can go into the surrounding farms and villages <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> purchase something to eat for themselves.”<verse eID='Mark.6.36'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.37' sID='Mark.6.37'/>But he answered <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “You give them <transChange type='added'>something</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to eat.” And they said to him, “Should we go <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> purchase bread for two hundred denarii and give <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to them to eat?”<verse eID='Mark.6.37'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.38' sID='Mark.6.38'/>And he said to them, “How many loaves do you have? Go look!” And <transChange type='added'>when they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“found out”) which is understood as temporal</note> found out, they said, “Five, and two fish.”<verse eID='Mark.6.38'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.39' sID='Mark.6.39'/>And he ordered them all to recline in groups on the green grass.<verse eID='Mark.6.39'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.40' sID='Mark.6.40'/>And they reclined in groups, by hundreds and by fifties.<verse eID='Mark.6.40'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.41' sID='Mark.6.41'/>And taking the five loaves and the two fish <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied in the translation because of English style</note> looking up to heaven, he gave thanks and broke the loaves and gave <transChange type='added'>them</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to his disciples so that they could set <transChange type='added'>them</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> before them. And he distributed the two fish to <transChange type='added'>them</transChange> all.<verse eID='Mark.6.41'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.42' sID='Mark.6.42'/>And they all ate and were satisfied.<verse eID='Mark.6.42'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.43' sID='Mark.6.43'/>And they picked up the broken pieces, twelve baskets full, and of the fish.<verse eID='Mark.6.43'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.44' sID='Mark.6.44'/>And those who ate the loaves were five thousand men.<verse eID='Mark.6.44'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus Walks on the Water</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.6.45' sID='Mark.6.45'/>And immediately he made his disciples get into the boat and go on ahead to the other side, to Bethsaida, while he himself dismissed the crowd.<verse eID='Mark.6.45'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.46' sID='Mark.6.46'/>And <transChange type='added'>after he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“went away”) which is understood as temporal</note> had said farewell to them, he went away to the mountain to pray.<verse eID='Mark.6.46'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.47' sID='Mark.6.47'/>And <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“came”)</note> evening came, the boat was in the middle of the sea and he <transChange type='added'>was</transChange> alone on the land.<verse eID='Mark.6.47'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.48' sID='Mark.6.48'/>And he saw them being beaten in their rowing<note>Or “being held up in their progress”</note> because the wind was against them. Around the fourth watch of the night he came to them, walking on the sea, and he was wanting to pass by them.<verse eID='Mark.6.48'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.49' sID='Mark.6.49'/>But <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> they saw him walking on the sea, they thought that it was a ghost, and they cried out.<verse eID='Mark.6.49'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.50' sID='Mark.6.50'/>For they all saw him and were terrified. But immediately he spoke with them and said to them, “Have courage, I am <transChange type='added'>he</transChange>! Do not be afraid!”<verse eID='Mark.6.50'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.51' sID='Mark.6.51'/>And he went up with them into the boat, and the wind abated. And <seg type='x-idiom'>˻they were extraordinarily˼</seg><note>Literally “exceedingly extremely”</note> astounded within themselves,<verse eID='Mark.6.51'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.52' sID='Mark.6.52'/>because they did not understand concerning the loaves, but their hearts were hardened.<verse eID='Mark.6.52'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Many Healed at Gennesaret</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.6.53' sID='Mark.6.53'/>And <transChange type='added'>after they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had crossed over”) which is understood as temporal</note> had crossed over, they came to land at Gennesaret and anchored <transChange type='added'>there</transChange>.<verse eID='Mark.6.53'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.54' sID='Mark.6.54'/>And <transChange type='added'>as</transChange> they were getting out of the boat, <transChange type='added'>people</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>people</catchWord>” is supplied as the subject of the verb because the third person pronoun “they” could be confused with the disciples getting out of the boat earlier in this verse</note> recognized him immediately.<verse eID='Mark.6.54'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.55' sID='Mark.6.55'/>They ran about <transChange type='added'>through</transChange> that whole region and began to carry around those <seg type='x-idiom'>˻who were sick˼</seg><note>Literally “who were having badly”</note> on stretchers, wherever they heard that he was.<verse eID='Mark.6.55'/> <verse osisID='Mark.6.56' sID='Mark.6.56'/>And wherever he would go, into villages or into towns or to farms, they would put those who were sick in the marketplaces and would implore him that if they could touch even the edge of his cloak. And all those who touched it were healed.<verse eID='Mark.6.56'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
<chapter osisID='Mark.7'>
<div type='section'>
<title>Human Traditions and God’s Commandments</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.7.1' sID='Mark.7.1'/>And the Pharisees and some of the scribes who had come from Jerusalem gathered to him.<verse eID='Mark.7.1'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.2' sID='Mark.7.2'/>And they saw that some of his disciples were eating their<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> bread with unclean—that is, unwashed—hands.<verse eID='Mark.7.2'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.3' sID='Mark.7.3'/>(For the Pharisees and all the Jews do not eat unless they wash their hands <seg type='x-idiom'>˻ritually˼</seg>,<note>Literally “with the fist”; although the exact meaning of the phrase is uncertain, there is general agreement it has to do with the ritual or ceremonial nature of the handwashing</note> <transChange type='added'>thus</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>thus</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“holding fast to”) which is understood as result</note> holding fast to the traditions of the elders.<verse eID='Mark.7.3'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.4' sID='Mark.7.4'/>And <transChange type='added'>when they come</transChange><note>The phrase “<catchWord>when they come</catchWord>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> from the marketplace, they do not eat unless they wash. And there are many other <transChange type='added'>traditions</transChange><note>The word “<catchWord>traditions</catchWord>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> which they have received <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“have received”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> hold fast to—<transChange type='added'>for example,</transChange><note>The phrase “<catchWord>for example</catchWord>” is not in the Greek text but is supplied as a clarification in the English translation</note> the washing of cups and pitchers and bronze kettles and dining couches.)<note>Several important manuscripts omit “and dining couches”</note><verse eID='Mark.7.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.5' sID='Mark.7.5'/>And the Pharisees and the scribes asked him, “Why do your disciples not live according to the tradition of the elders, but eat their<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> bread with unclean hands?”<verse eID='Mark.7.5'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.6' sID='Mark.7.6'/>So he said to them, “Isaiah prophesied correctly about you hypocrites, as it is written,</p>
<lg>
<l level='1'>‘This people honors me with their<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> lips,</l>
<l level='2'>but their heart is far, far away from me.<verse eID='Mark.7.6'/></l>
<l level='1'><verse osisID='Mark.7.7' sID='Mark.7.7'/>And they worship me in vain,</l>
<l level='2'>teaching <transChange type='added'>as</transChange> doctrines the commandments of men.’<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Isa.29.13'>Isa 29:13</reference></note><verse eID='Mark.7.7'/></l>
</lg>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.7.8' sID='Mark.7.8'/>Abandoning the commandment of God, you hold fast to the tradition of men.”<verse eID='Mark.7.8'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.7.9' sID='Mark.7.9'/>And he said to them, “You splendidly ignore the commandment of God so that you can maintain your tradition.<verse eID='Mark.7.9'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.10' sID='Mark.7.10'/>For Moses said, ‘Honor your father and your mother,’<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Exod.20.12'>Exod 20:12</reference>; <reference osisRef='Deut.5.16'>Deut 5:16</reference></note> and, ‘The one who speaks evil of father or mother <seg type='x-idiom'>˻must certainly die˼</seg><note>Literally “let him die the death”</note>.’<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Exod.21.17'>Exod 21:17</reference>; <reference osisRef='Lev.20.9'>Lev 20:9</reference></note><verse eID='Mark.7.10'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.11' sID='Mark.7.11'/>But you say, ‘If a man says to his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> father or to his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> mother, “Whatever <seg type='x-idiom'>˻benefit you would have received˼</seg><note>Literally “you would have been benefited”</note> from me <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> <hi type='italic'>corban</hi>”<note>A Hebrew term referring to something consecrated as a gift to God and thus not available for ordinary use</note> (that is, a gift <transChange type='added'>to God</transChange>),<verse eID='Mark.7.11'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.12' sID='Mark.7.12'/>you no longer permit him to do anything for his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> father or his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> mother,<verse eID='Mark.7.12'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.13' sID='Mark.7.13'/><transChange type='added'>thus</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>thus</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“making void”) which is understood as result</note> making void the word of God by your tradition that you have handed down, and you do many similar <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> such as this.”<verse eID='Mark.7.13'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Defilement from Within</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.7.14' sID='Mark.7.14'/>And summoning the crowd again, he said to them, “Listen to me, all <transChange type='added'>of you</transChange>, and understand:<verse eID='Mark.7.14'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.15' sID='Mark.7.15'/>There is nothing outside of a person that is able to defile him <transChange type='added'>by</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>by</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“going”) which is understood as means</note> going into him. But the things that go out of a person are the things that defile a person.”<note>Most later manuscripts add v. <reference osisRef='Mark.7.16'>16</reference>, “If anyone has ears to hear, let him hear.”</note><verse eID='Mark.7.15'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.17' sID='Mark.7.17'/>And when he entered into the house away from the crowd, his disciples asked him about the parable.<verse eID='Mark.7.17'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.18' sID='Mark.7.18'/>And he said to them, “So are you also without understanding? Do you not understand that everything <transChange type='added'>that is</transChange> outside that goes into a person <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> not able to defile him?<verse eID='Mark.7.18'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.19' sID='Mark.7.19'/>For it does not enter into his heart but into his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> stomach, and goes out into the latrine”—<transChange type='added'>thus</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>thus</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“declaring”) which is understood as result</note> declaring all foods clean.<verse eID='Mark.7.19'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.20' sID='Mark.7.20'/>And he said, “What comes out of a person, that defiles a person.<verse eID='Mark.7.20'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.21' sID='Mark.7.21'/>For from within, from the heart of people, come evil plans, sexual immoralities, thefts, murders,<verse eID='Mark.7.21'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.22' sID='Mark.7.22'/>adulteries, <transChange type='added'>acts of</transChange> greed, malicious <transChange type='added'>deeds</transChange>, deceit, licentiousness, <seg type='x-idiom'>˻envy˼</seg>,<note>Literally “the evil eye”</note> abusive speech, pride, foolishness.<verse eID='Mark.7.22'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.23' sID='Mark.7.23'/>All these evil <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> come from within and defile a person.”<verse eID='Mark.7.23'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Syrophoenician Woman’s Great Faith</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.7.24' sID='Mark.7.24'/>And from there he set out <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“set out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went to the region of Tyre. And <transChange type='added'>when he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“entered”) which is understood as temporal</note> entered into a house, he wanted no one to know, and <transChange type='added'>yet</transChange> he was not able to escape notice.<verse eID='Mark.7.24'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.25' sID='Mark.7.25'/>But immediately a woman whose young daughter was possessed by an unclean spirit, <transChange type='added'>when she</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard about him, came <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> fell down at his feet,<verse eID='Mark.7.25'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.26' sID='Mark.7.26'/>Now the woman was a Greek—a Syrophoenician by nationality—and she was asking him that he would expel the demon from her daughter.<verse eID='Mark.7.26'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.27' sID='Mark.7.27'/>And he said to her, “Let the children be satisfied first, for it is not right to take the children’s bread and throw <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the dogs!”<verse eID='Mark.7.27'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.28' sID='Mark.7.28'/>But she answered and said to him, “Lord, even the dogs under the table eat the children’s crumbs.”<verse eID='Mark.7.28'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.29' sID='Mark.7.29'/>And he said to her, “Because of this statement, go! The demon has gone out of your daughter.”<verse eID='Mark.7.29'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.30' sID='Mark.7.30'/>And <transChange type='added'>when she</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“went”) which is understood as temporal</note> went to her home, she found the child lying on the bed and the demon gone.<verse eID='Mark.7.30'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Man Deaf and Unable to Speak Healed</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.7.31' sID='Mark.7.31'/>And again he went away from the region of Tyre <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went away”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> came through Sidon to the Sea of Galilee, within the region of the Decapolis.<verse eID='Mark.7.31'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.32' sID='Mark.7.32'/>And they brought to him a man who was deaf and had difficulty speaking, and they were imploring him that he would place his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hand on him.<verse eID='Mark.7.32'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.33' sID='Mark.7.33'/>And he took him away from the crowd by himself <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took … away”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> put his fingers into his ears, and <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“spitting”) which is understood as temporal</note> spitting, he touched his tongue.<verse eID='Mark.7.33'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.34' sID='Mark.7.34'/>And looking up to heaven, he sighed and said to him, “<hi type='italic'>Ephphatha!</hi>” (that is, “Be opened!”).<verse eID='Mark.7.34'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.35' sID='Mark.7.35'/>And immediately his ears were opened and <seg type='x-idiom'>˻his difficulty in speaking was removed˼</seg><note>Literally “the bond of his tongue was loosened”</note> and he began to speak normally.<verse eID='Mark.7.35'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.36' sID='Mark.7.36'/>And he ordered them that they should say nothing, but as much as he ordered them <transChange type='added'>not to</transChange>, they proclaimed <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> even more instead.<verse eID='Mark.7.36'/> <verse osisID='Mark.7.37' sID='Mark.7.37'/>And they were amazed beyond all measure, saying, “He has done all <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> well! He even makes the deaf hear and the mute speak!”<verse eID='Mark.7.37'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
<chapter osisID='Mark.8'>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Feeding of Four Thousand</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.8.1' sID='Mark.8.1'/>In those days there was<note>Here the participle (“was”) is translated as a finite verb because of English style</note> again a large crowd, and they did not have<note>Here the participle (“have”) is translated as a finite verb because of English style</note> anything they could eat. Summoning the disciples, he said to them,<verse eID='Mark.8.1'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.2' sID='Mark.8.2'/>“I have compassion on the crowd, because they have remained with me three days already and do not have anything to eat.<verse eID='Mark.8.2'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.3' sID='Mark.8.3'/>And if I send them away hungry to their homes they will give out on the way, and some of them have come from far away.”<verse eID='Mark.8.3'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.4' sID='Mark.8.4'/>And his disciples answered him, “Where is anyone able to feed these <transChange type='added'>people</transChange> with bread here in the desert?”<verse eID='Mark.8.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.5' sID='Mark.8.5'/>And he asked them, “How many loaves do you have?” So they said, “Seven.”<verse eID='Mark.8.5'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.6' sID='Mark.8.6'/>And he commanded the crowd to recline for a meal on the ground, and taking the seven loaves, <transChange type='added'>after he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had given thanks”) which is understood as temporal</note> had given thanks he broke <transChange type='added'>them</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and began giving<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began giving”)</note> <transChange type='added'>them</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to his disciples so that they could set <transChange type='added'>them</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> before <transChange type='added'>them</transChange>.<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> And they set <transChange type='added'>them</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> before the crowd.<verse eID='Mark.8.6'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.7' sID='Mark.8.7'/>And they had a few small fish, and <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“giving thanks”) which is understood as temporal</note> giving thanks for them, he said to set these <transChange type='added'>before them</transChange> also.<verse eID='Mark.8.7'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.8' sID='Mark.8.8'/>And they ate and were satisfied, and they picked up the broken pieces that were left, seven baskets <transChange type='added'>full</transChange>.<verse eID='Mark.8.8'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.9' sID='Mark.8.9'/>Now there were about four thousand. And he sent them away.<verse eID='Mark.8.9'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.10' sID='Mark.8.10'/>And immediately he got into the boat with his disciples <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“got”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went to the district of Dalmanutha.<verse eID='Mark.8.10'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Pharisees Demand a Sign</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.8.11' sID='Mark.8.11'/>And the Pharisees came and began to argue with him, demanding from him a sign from heaven <transChange type='added'>in order to</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>in order to</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“test”) which is understood as purpose</note> test him.<verse eID='Mark.8.11'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.12' sID='Mark.8.12'/>And sighing deeply in his spirit, he said, “Why does this generation demand a sign? Truly I say to you, no sign will be given to this generation!”<verse eID='Mark.8.12'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.13' sID='Mark.8.13'/>And he left them, got into <transChange type='added'>the boat</transChange><note>Here the words “<catchWord>the boat</catchWord>” are not in the Greek text but must be supplied</note> again, <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participles (“left” and “got into”) have been translated as finite verbs</note> went to the other side.<verse eID='Mark.8.13'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Beware the Leaven of the Pharisees and Herod</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.8.14' sID='Mark.8.14'/>And they had forgotten to take bread, and except <transChange type='added'>for</transChange> one loaf, they did not have <transChange type='added'>any</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with them in the boat.<verse eID='Mark.8.14'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.15' sID='Mark.8.15'/>And he ordered them, saying, “Watch out! Beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and the leaven of Herod!”<verse eID='Mark.8.15'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.16' sID='Mark.8.16'/>And they began to discuss with one another that they had no bread.<verse eID='Mark.8.16'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.17' sID='Mark.8.17'/>And knowing <transChange type='added'>this</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he said to them, “Why are you discussing that you have no bread? Do you not yet perceive or understand? Have your hearts been hardened?<verse eID='Mark.8.17'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.18' sID='Mark.8.18'/><transChange type='added'>Although you</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>although</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have”) which is understood as concessive</note> have eyes, do you not see? And <transChange type='added'>although you</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>although</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“have”) which is understood as concessive</note> have ears, do you not hear? And do you not remember?<verse eID='Mark.8.18'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.19' sID='Mark.8.19'/>When I broke the five loaves for the five thousand how many baskets full of broken pieces did you pick up?” They said to him, “Twelve.”<verse eID='Mark.8.19'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.20' sID='Mark.8.20'/>“When <transChange type='added'>I broke</transChange><note>The words “<catchWord>I broke</catchWord>” are not in the Greek text, but are understood based on the previous verse</note> the seven <transChange type='added'>loaves</transChange><note>The word “<catchWord>loaves</catchWord>” is not in the Greek text, but is understood based on the previous verse</note> for the four thousand, how many baskets full of broken pieces did you pick up?” And they said to him, “Seven.”<verse eID='Mark.8.20'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.21' sID='Mark.8.21'/>And he said to them, “Do you not yet understand?”<verse eID='Mark.8.21'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Blind Man Healed at Bethsaida</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.8.22' sID='Mark.8.22'/>And they came to Bethsaida. And they brought to him a blind man and implored him that he would touch him.<verse eID='Mark.8.22'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.23' sID='Mark.8.23'/>And he took hold of the blind man’s hand <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took hold of”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> led him outside the village, and <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“spitting”) which is understood as temporal</note> spitting in his eyes, he placed his hands on him <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“placed”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> asked him, “Do you see anything?”<verse eID='Mark.8.23'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.24' sID='Mark.8.24'/>And looking up he said, “I see people, for I see <transChange type='added'>them</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> like trees walking around.”<verse eID='Mark.8.24'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.25' sID='Mark.8.25'/>Then he placed his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands on his eyes again, and he opened his eyes and was cured, and could see everything clearly.<verse eID='Mark.8.25'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.26' sID='Mark.8.26'/>And he sent him to his home, saying, “Do not even go into the village.”<verse eID='Mark.8.26'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Peter’s Confession at Caesarea Philippi</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.8.27' sID='Mark.8.27'/>And Jesus and his disciples went out to the villages of Caesarea Philippi, and on the way he asked his disciples, saying to them, “Who do people say <transChange type='added'>that</transChange> I am?”<verse eID='Mark.8.27'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.28' sID='Mark.8.28'/>And they told him, saying, “John the Baptist, and others Elijah, and others that <transChange type='added'>you are</transChange> one of the prophets.”<verse eID='Mark.8.28'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.29' sID='Mark.8.29'/>And he asked them, “But who do you say <transChange type='added'>that</transChange> I am?” Peter answered <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “You are the Christ!”<verse eID='Mark.8.29'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.30' sID='Mark.8.30'/>And he warned them that they should tell no one about him.<verse eID='Mark.8.30'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus Predicts His Death and Resurrection</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.8.31' sID='Mark.8.31'/>And he began to teach them that it was necessary <transChange type='added'>for</transChange> the Son of Man to suffer many <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> and to be rejected by the elders and the chief priests and the scribes, and to be killed, and after three days to rise.<verse eID='Mark.8.31'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.32' sID='Mark.8.32'/>And he was speaking openly <transChange type='added'>about</transChange> the subject, and Peter took him aside <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took … aside”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to rebuke him.<verse eID='Mark.8.32'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.33' sID='Mark.8.33'/>But turning around and seeing his disciples, he rebuked Peter and said, “Get behind me, Satan, because you are not setting your mind on the things of God, but the things of people!”<verse eID='Mark.8.33'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Taking Up One’s Cross to Follow Jesus</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.8.34' sID='Mark.8.34'/>And summoning the crowd together with his disciples, he said to them, “If anyone wants to follow after me, let him deny himself and take up his cross and follow me.<verse eID='Mark.8.34'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.35' sID='Mark.8.35'/>For whoever wants to save his life will lose it, but whoever loses his life on account of me and of the gospel will save it.<verse eID='Mark.8.35'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.36' sID='Mark.8.36'/>For what does it benefit a person to gain the whole world and forfeit his life?<verse eID='Mark.8.36'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.37' sID='Mark.8.37'/>For what can a person give in exchange for his life?<verse eID='Mark.8.37'/> <verse osisID='Mark.8.38' sID='Mark.8.38'/>For whoever is ashamed of me and my words in this adulterous and sinful generation, the Son of Man will also be ashamed of him when he comes in the glory of his Father with the holy angels.”<verse eID='Mark.8.38'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
<chapter osisID='Mark.9'>
<div type='section'>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.9.1' sID='Mark.9.1'/>And he said to them, “Truly I say to you, that there are some of those standing here who will never experience death until they see the kingdom of God having come with power.”<verse eID='Mark.9.1'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Transfiguration</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.9.2' sID='Mark.9.2'/>And after six days, Jesus took along Peter and James and John, and led them to a high mountain by themselves alone. And he was transfigured before them,<verse eID='Mark.9.2'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.3' sID='Mark.9.3'/>and his clothing became radiant—extremely white, like no cloth refiner on earth can <seg type='x-idiom'>˻make so white˼</seg>.<note>Literally “make white like this”</note><verse eID='Mark.9.3'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.4' sID='Mark.9.4'/>And Elijah appeared to them together with Moses, and they were talking with Jesus.<verse eID='Mark.9.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.5' sID='Mark.9.5'/>And Peter answered <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to Jesus, “Rabbi, it is good <transChange type='added'>that</transChange> we are here! And let us make three shelters, one for you and one for Moses and one for Elijah.”<verse eID='Mark.9.5'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.6' sID='Mark.9.6'/>(For he did not know what he should answer, because they were terrified.)<verse eID='Mark.9.6'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.7' sID='Mark.9.7'/>And a cloud came, overshadowing them, and a voice came from the cloud, “This is my beloved Son. Listen to him!”<verse eID='Mark.9.7'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.8' sID='Mark.9.8'/>And suddenly, looking around, they no longer saw anyone with them but Jesus alone.<verse eID='Mark.9.8'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.9.9' sID='Mark.9.9'/>And <transChange type='added'>as</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were coming down”)</note> they were coming down from the mountain, he ordered them that they should tell no one <transChange type='added'>the things</transChange> that they had seen, except when the Son of Man had risen from the dead.<verse eID='Mark.9.9'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.10' sID='Mark.9.10'/>And they kept the matter to themselves, discussing what this rising from the dead <seg type='x-idiom'>˻meant˼</seg>.<note>Literally “is”</note><verse eID='Mark.9.10'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.11' sID='Mark.9.11'/>And they asked him, saying, “<seg type='x-idiom'>˻Why do˼</seg><note>Literally “<catchWord>what is it</catchWord> that”</note> the scribes say that Elijah must come first?”<verse eID='Mark.9.11'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.12' sID='Mark.9.12'/>And he said to them, “Elijah indeed does come first <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“does come”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> restores all <transChange type='added'>things</transChange>. And how is it written concerning the Son of Man that he should suffer many <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> and be treated with contempt?<verse eID='Mark.9.12'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.13' sID='Mark.9.13'/>But I tell you that indeed Elijah has come, and they did to him whatever they wanted, just as it is written about him.”<verse eID='Mark.9.13'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Demon-possessed Boy Healed</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.9.14' sID='Mark.9.14'/>And <transChange type='added'>when they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> came to the disciples, they saw a large crowd around them and scribes arguing with them.<verse eID='Mark.9.14'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.15' sID='Mark.9.15'/>And immediately the whole crowd, <transChange type='added'>when they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw him, were amazed, and ran up to <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“ran up to”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> greeted him.<verse eID='Mark.9.15'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.16' sID='Mark.9.16'/>And he asked them, “What are you arguing <transChange type='added'>about</transChange> with them?”<verse eID='Mark.9.16'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.17' sID='Mark.9.17'/>And one <transChange type='added'>individual</transChange> from the crowd answered him, “Teacher, I brought to you my son who has <seg type='x-idiom'>˻a spirit that makes him mute˼</seg>.<note>Literally “a mute spirit”</note><verse eID='Mark.9.17'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.18' sID='Mark.9.18'/>And whenever it seizes him, it throws him down and he foams at the mouth and grinds his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> teeth and becomes paralyzed. And I told your disciples that they should expel it, and they were not able <transChange type='added'>to do so</transChange>.<note>The words “<catchWord>to do so</catchWord>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note><verse eID='Mark.9.18'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.19' sID='Mark.9.19'/>And he answered them <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “O unbelieving generation! <seg type='x-idiom'>˻How long˼</seg><note>Literally “until when”</note> will I be with you? <seg type='x-idiom'>˻How long˼</seg><note>Literally “until when”</note> must I put up with you? Bring him to me!”<verse eID='Mark.9.19'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.20' sID='Mark.9.20'/>And they brought him to him. And <transChange type='added'>when he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw him, the spirit immediately convulsed him, and falling on the ground, he began to roll around, foaming at the mouth.<verse eID='Mark.9.20'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.21' sID='Mark.9.21'/>And he asked his father how long it was since this had been happening to him. And he said, “From childhood.<verse eID='Mark.9.21'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.22' sID='Mark.9.22'/>And often it has thrown him both into fire and into water, in order that it could destroy him. But if you are able <transChange type='added'>to do</transChange> anything, have compassion on us <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied and the following participle (“have compassion”) has been translated as a finite verb and placed before the verb “help” in keeping with English style</note> help us!”<verse eID='Mark.9.22'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.23' sID='Mark.9.23'/>But Jesus said to him, “If you are able! All <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> <transChange type='added'>are</transChange> possible for the one who believes!”<verse eID='Mark.9.23'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.24' sID='Mark.9.24'/>Immediately the father of the child cried out <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“cried out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “I believe! Help my unbelief!”<verse eID='Mark.9.24'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.25' sID='Mark.9.25'/>Now <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus saw that a crowd was running together, he rebuked the unclean spirit, saying to it, “Mute and deaf spirit, I command you, come out of him, and enter into him no more!”<verse eID='Mark.9.25'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.26' sID='Mark.9.26'/>And it came out, screaming and convulsing <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> greatly, and he became as if <transChange type='added'>he were</transChange> dead, so that most <transChange type='added'>of them</transChange> said, “He has died!”<verse eID='Mark.9.26'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.27' sID='Mark.9.27'/>But Jesus took hold of his hand <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took hold of”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> raised him up, and he stood up.<verse eID='Mark.9.27'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.28' sID='Mark.9.28'/>And <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had entered”)</note> he had entered into the house, his disciples asked him privately, “Why were we not able to expel it?”<verse eID='Mark.9.28'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.29' sID='Mark.9.29'/>And he said to them, “This kind can come out by nothing except by prayer.”<note>Some manuscripts add “and fasting”</note><verse eID='Mark.9.29'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus Predicts His Death and Resurrection a Second Time</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.9.30' sID='Mark.9.30'/>And from there they went out <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> passed through Galilee. And he did not want anyone to know,<verse eID='Mark.9.30'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.31' sID='Mark.9.31'/>for he was teaching his disciples and was telling them, “The Son of Man is being betrayed into the hands of men, and they will kill him. And <transChange type='added'>when he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“is killed”) which is understood as temporal</note> is killed, after three days he will rise.”<verse eID='Mark.9.31'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.32' sID='Mark.9.32'/>But they did not understand the statement, and they were afraid to ask him.<verse eID='Mark.9.32'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Question About Who Is Greatest</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.9.33' sID='Mark.9.33'/>And they came to Capernaum. And <transChange type='added'>after he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as temporal</note> was in the house, he asked them, “What were you discussing on the way?”<verse eID='Mark.9.33'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.34' sID='Mark.9.34'/>But they were silent, because they had argued with one another on the way <transChange type='added'>about</transChange> who <transChange type='added'>was</transChange> greatest.<verse eID='Mark.9.34'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.35' sID='Mark.9.35'/>And he sat down <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sat down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> called the twelve and said to them, “If anyone wants to be first, he will be last of all and servant of all.”<verse eID='Mark.9.35'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.36' sID='Mark.9.36'/>And he took a young child <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“took”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> had him stand <seg type='x-idiom'>˻among them˼</seg>.<note>Literally “in the midst of them”</note> And taking him in his arms, he said to them,<verse eID='Mark.9.36'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.37' sID='Mark.9.37'/>“Whoever welcomes one of the young children such as these in my name welcomes me, and whoever welcomes me does not welcome me, but the one who sent me.”<verse eID='Mark.9.37'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Whoever Is Not Against Us Is for Us</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.9.38' sID='Mark.9.38'/>John said to him, “Teacher, we saw someone expelling demons in your name, and we tried to prevent him because he was not following us.”<verse eID='Mark.9.38'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.39' sID='Mark.9.39'/>But Jesus said, “Do not prevent him, because there is no one who does a miracle in my name and will be able soon afterward to speak evil of me.<verse eID='Mark.9.39'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.40' sID='Mark.9.40'/>For whoever is not against us is for us.<verse eID='Mark.9.40'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.41' sID='Mark.9.41'/>For whoever gives you a cup of water to drink in <transChange type='added'>my</transChange> name because you are Christ’s, truly I say to you that he will never lose his reward.<verse eID='Mark.9.41'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Temptations to Sin</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.9.42' sID='Mark.9.42'/>“And whoever causes one of these little ones who believe in me to sin, it is better for him if instead <seg type='x-idiom'>˻a large millstone˼</seg><note>Literally “a millstone of a donkey”</note> is placed around his neck and he is thrown into the sea.<verse eID='Mark.9.42'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.43' sID='Mark.9.43'/>And if your hand causes you to sin, cut it off! It is better <transChange type='added'>for</transChange> you to enter into life crippled than, having two hands, to go into hell—into the unquenchable fire!<note>Most later Greek manuscripts add v. <reference osisRef='Mark.9.44'>44</reference> after v. <reference osisRef='Mark.9.43'>43</reference>, “where their worm does not die and the fire is not extinguished” (identical to v. <reference osisRef='Mark.9.48'>48</reference>)</note><verse eID='Mark.9.43'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.45' sID='Mark.9.45'/>And if your foot causes you to sin, cut it off! It is better <transChange type='added'>for</transChange> you to enter into life lame than, having two feet, to be thrown into hell!<note>Most later Greek manuscripts add v. <reference osisRef='Mark.9.46'>46</reference> after v. <reference osisRef='Mark.9.45'>45</reference>, “where their worm does not die and the fire is not extinguished” (identical to v. <reference osisRef='Mark.9.48'>48</reference>)</note><verse eID='Mark.9.45'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.47' sID='Mark.9.47'/>And if your eye causes you to sin, tear it out! It is better <transChange type='added'>for</transChange> you to enter into the kingdom of God with one eye than, having two eyes, to be thrown into hell,<verse eID='Mark.9.47'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.48' sID='Mark.9.48'/>‘where their worm does not die and the fire is not extinguished.’<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Isa.66.24'>Isa 66:24</reference></note><verse eID='Mark.9.48'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.49' sID='Mark.9.49'/>For everyone will be salted with fire.<verse eID='Mark.9.49'/> <verse osisID='Mark.9.50' sID='Mark.9.50'/>Salt <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> good, but if the salt becomes deprived of its salt content, by what can you make it salty? Have salt among yourselves, and be at peace with one another.”<verse eID='Mark.9.50'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
<chapter osisID='Mark.10'>
<div type='section'>
<title>On Divorce</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.10.1' sID='Mark.10.1'/>And from there he set out <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“set out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> came to the region of Judea and the other side of the Jordan, and again crowds came together to him. And again, as he was accustomed <transChange type='added'>to do</transChange>,<note>The words “<catchWord>to do</catchWord>” are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> he began to teach<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to teach”)</note> them.<verse eID='Mark.10.1'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.2' sID='Mark.10.2'/>And Pharisees came up <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> asked him if it was permitted for a man to divorce <transChange type='added'>his</transChange><note>The pronoun “<catchWord>his</catchWord>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> wife, <transChange type='added'>in order to</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>in order to</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“test”) which is understood as purpose</note> test him.<verse eID='Mark.10.2'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.3' sID='Mark.10.3'/>And he answered <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “What did Moses command you?”<verse eID='Mark.10.3'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.4' sID='Mark.10.4'/>So they said, “Moses permitted <transChange type='added'>a man</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to write a certificate of divorce and to send <transChange type='added'>her</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> away.”<verse eID='Mark.10.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.5' sID='Mark.10.5'/>But Jesus said to them, “He wrote this commandment for you because of your hardness of heart.<verse eID='Mark.10.5'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.6' sID='Mark.10.6'/>But from the beginning of creation ‘he made them male and female.<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Gen.1.27'>Gen 1:27</reference>; <reference osisRef='Gen.5.2'>5:2</reference></note><verse eID='Mark.10.6'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.7' sID='Mark.10.7'/>Because of this a man will leave his father and mother and will be joined to his wife,<note>The earliest and most important manuscripts do not contain the phrase “and be joined to his wife”</note><verse eID='Mark.10.7'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.8' sID='Mark.10.8'/>and the two will become one flesh,’<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Gen.2.24'>Gen 2:24</reference></note> so that they are no longer two but one flesh.<verse eID='Mark.10.8'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.9' sID='Mark.10.9'/>Therefore what God has joined together, man must not separate.”<verse eID='Mark.10.9'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.10.10' sID='Mark.10.10'/>And in the house again the disciples began to ask<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to ask”)</note> him about this.<verse eID='Mark.10.10'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.11' sID='Mark.10.11'/>And he said to them, “Whoever divorces his wife and marries another commits adultery against her.<verse eID='Mark.10.11'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.12' sID='Mark.10.12'/>And if she divorces her husband <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“divorces”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> marries another, she commits adultery.”<verse eID='Mark.10.12'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Little Children Brought to Jesus</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.10.13' sID='Mark.10.13'/>And they were bringing young children to him so that he could touch them, but the disciples rebuked them.<verse eID='Mark.10.13'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.14' sID='Mark.10.14'/>But <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus saw <transChange type='added'>it</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> he was indignant, and said to them, “Let the young children come to me. Do not forbid them, <seg type='x-idiom'>˻for to such belongs˼</seg><note>Literally “for of such is”</note> the kingdom of God.<verse eID='Mark.10.14'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.15' sID='Mark.10.15'/>Truly I say to you, whoever does not welcome the kingdom of God like a young child will never enter into it.”<verse eID='Mark.10.15'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.16' sID='Mark.10.16'/>And <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“taking … into his arms”) which is understood as temporal</note> taking <transChange type='added'>them</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> into his arms, he blessed them, placing his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands on them.<verse eID='Mark.10.16'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Rich Young Man</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.10.17' sID='Mark.10.17'/>And <transChange type='added'>as</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was setting out”)</note> he was setting out on <transChange type='added'>his</transChange> way, one <transChange type='added'>individual</transChange> ran up and knelt down before him <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the two previous participles (“ran up” and “knelt down before”) have been translated as finite verbs</note> asked him, “Good Teacher, what must I do so that I will inherit eternal life?”<verse eID='Mark.10.17'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.18' sID='Mark.10.18'/>So Jesus said to him, “Why do you call me good? No one <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> good except God alone.<verse eID='Mark.10.18'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.19' sID='Mark.10.19'/>You know the commandments: ‘Do not murder, do not commit adultery, do not steal, do not give false testimony, do not defraud, honor your father and mother.’ ”<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Exod.20.12-Exod.20.16'>Exod 20:12–16</reference>; <reference osisRef='Deut.5.16-Deut.5.20'>Deut 5:16–20</reference>, except for “do not defraud” which is an allusion to <reference osisRef='Deut.24.14'>Deut 24:14</reference></note><verse eID='Mark.10.19'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.20' sID='Mark.10.20'/>And he said to him, “Teacher, all these I have observed from my youth.”<verse eID='Mark.10.20'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.21' sID='Mark.10.21'/>And Jesus, looking at him, loved him, and said to him, “You lack one <transChange type='added'>thing</transChange>: Go, sell all that you have, and give <transChange type='added'>the proceeds</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the poor—and you will have treasure in heaven—and come, follow me.”<verse eID='Mark.10.21'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.22' sID='Mark.10.22'/>But he looked gloomy at the statement <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“looked gloomy”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went away sorrowful, <seg type='x-idiom'>˻because he had˼</seg><note>Literally “because he was having”</note> many possessions.<verse eID='Mark.10.22'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.10.23' sID='Mark.10.23'/>And Jesus looked around <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“looked around”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to his disciples, “How <seg type='x-idiom'>˻difficult it is for˼</seg><note>Literally “with difficulty”</note> those who possess wealth to enter into the kingdom of God!”<verse eID='Mark.10.23'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.24' sID='Mark.10.24'/>And the disciples were astounded at his words. But Jesus answered <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them again, “Children, how difficult it is to enter into the kingdom of God!<verse eID='Mark.10.24'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.25' sID='Mark.10.25'/>It is easier <transChange type='added'>for</transChange> a camel to go through the eye of a needle than <transChange type='added'>for</transChange> a rich person to enter into the kingdom of God.”<verse eID='Mark.10.25'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.26' sID='Mark.10.26'/>And they were very astounded, saying to one another, “And who can be saved?”<verse eID='Mark.10.26'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.27' sID='Mark.10.27'/>Jesus looked at them <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“looked at”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “With human beings <transChange type='added'>it is</transChange> impossible, but not with God. For all <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> <transChange type='added'>are</transChange> possible with God.”<verse eID='Mark.10.27'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.28' sID='Mark.10.28'/>Peter began to say to him, “Behold, we have left everything and followed you.”<verse eID='Mark.10.28'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.29' sID='Mark.10.29'/>Jesus said, “Truly I say to you, there is no one who has left house or brothers or sisters or mother or father or children or fields on account of me and on account of the gospel<verse eID='Mark.10.29'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.30' sID='Mark.10.30'/><seg type='x-idiom'>˻who will not˼</seg><note>Literally “unless <catchWord>he will</catchWord> not”</note> receive a hundred times as much now in this time—houses and brothers and sisters and mothers and children and fields, together with persecutions—and in the age to come, eternal life.<verse eID='Mark.10.30'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.31' sID='Mark.10.31'/>But many <transChange type='added'>who are</transChange> first will be last, and the last first.”<verse eID='Mark.10.31'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus Predicts His Death and Resurrection a Third Time</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.10.32' sID='Mark.10.32'/>Now they were on the road going up to Jerusalem, and Jesus was going on ahead of them. And they were astounded, but those who were following <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> were afraid. And taking aside the twelve again, he began to tell them the things that were about to happen to him:<verse eID='Mark.10.32'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.33' sID='Mark.10.33'/>“Behold, we are going up to Jerusalem, and the Son of Man will be handed over to the chief priests and the scribes, and they will condemn him to death and will hand him over to the Gentiles.<verse eID='Mark.10.33'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.34' sID='Mark.10.34'/>And they will mock him and spit on him and flog him and kill <transChange type='added'>him</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and after three days he will rise.”<verse eID='Mark.10.34'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Request by James and John</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.10.35' sID='Mark.10.35'/>And James and John, the sons of Zebedee, came up to him <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the participle (“said”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> said to him, “Teacher, we want you to do for us whatever we ask you.”<verse eID='Mark.10.35'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.36' sID='Mark.10.36'/>And he said to them, “What do you want me <seg type='x-idiom'>˻to do˼</seg><note>Literally “that I do”</note> for you?”<verse eID='Mark.10.36'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.37' sID='Mark.10.37'/>So they said to him, “Grant to us that we may sit one at your right hand and one at <transChange type='added'>your</transChange> left in your glory.”<verse eID='Mark.10.37'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.38' sID='Mark.10.38'/>But Jesus said to them, “You do not know what you are asking! Are you able to drink the cup that I drink, or to be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with?”<verse eID='Mark.10.38'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.39' sID='Mark.10.39'/>And they said to him, “We are able.” So Jesus said to them, “You will drink the cup that I drink, and you will be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with,<verse eID='Mark.10.39'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.40' sID='Mark.10.40'/>but to sit at my right hand or at <transChange type='added'>my</transChange> left is not mine to grant, but <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> for those for whom it has been prepared.”<verse eID='Mark.10.40'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.41' sID='Mark.10.41'/>And <transChange type='added'>when they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <transChange type='added'>this</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> the ten began to be indignant about James and John.<verse eID='Mark.10.41'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.42' sID='Mark.10.42'/>And Jesus called them to himself <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“called … to himself”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “You know that those who are considered to rule over the Gentiles lord it over them, and their <transChange type='added'>people</transChange> in high positions exercise authority over them.<verse eID='Mark.10.42'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.43' sID='Mark.10.43'/>But it is not like this among you! But whoever wants to become great among you must be your servant,<verse eID='Mark.10.43'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.44' sID='Mark.10.44'/>and whoever wants to be most prominent among you must be the slave of all.<verse eID='Mark.10.44'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.45' sID='Mark.10.45'/>For even the Son of Man did not come to be served, but to serve, and to give his life <transChange type='added'>as</transChange> a ransom for many.”<verse eID='Mark.10.45'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Blind Man Healed at Jericho</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.10.46' sID='Mark.10.46'/>And they came to Jericho. And <transChange type='added'>as</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was setting out”)</note> he was setting out from Jericho along with his disciples and a large crowd, a blind beggar, Bartimaeus the son of Timaeus, was sitting beside the road.<verse eID='Mark.10.46'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.47' sID='Mark.10.47'/>And <transChange type='added'>when he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard that it was Jesus the Nazarene, he began to cry out and say, “Jesus, Son of David, have mercy on me!”<verse eID='Mark.10.47'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.48' sID='Mark.10.48'/>And many <transChange type='added'>people</transChange> warned him that he should be quiet. But he was crying out <seg type='x-idiom'>˻even more loudly˼</seg>,<note>Literally “by much more”</note> “Son of David, have mercy on me!”<verse eID='Mark.10.48'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.49' sID='Mark.10.49'/>And Jesus stopped <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stopped”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Call him.” And they called the blind man <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“called”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Have courage! Get up! He is calling you.”<verse eID='Mark.10.49'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.50' sID='Mark.10.50'/>And he threw off his cloak, jumped up, <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the two previous participles (“threw off” and “jumped up”) have been translated as finite verbs</note> came to Jesus.<verse eID='Mark.10.50'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.51' sID='Mark.10.51'/>And Jesus answered him <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “What do you want <seg type='x-idiom'>˻me to do˼</seg><note>Literally “that I do”</note> for you?” And the blind man said to him, “<hi type='italic'>Rabboni</hi>,<note>The Aramaic term is an elevated form of Rabbi</note> that I may regain <transChange type='added'>my</transChange> sight.”<verse eID='Mark.10.51'/> <verse osisID='Mark.10.52' sID='Mark.10.52'/>And Jesus said to him, “Go, your faith has healed you.” And immediately he regained <transChange type='added'>his</transChange> sight and began to follow<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to follow”)</note> him on the road.<verse eID='Mark.10.52'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
<chapter osisID='Mark.11'>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Triumphal Entry</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.11.1' sID='Mark.11.1'/>And when they came near to Jerusalem, to Bethphage and Bethany at the Mount of Olives, he sent two of his disciples<verse eID='Mark.11.1'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.2' sID='Mark.11.2'/>and said to them, “Go into the village before you, and right away <transChange type='added'>as you</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“enter”) which is understood as temporal</note> enter into it you will find a colt tied, on which no one <transChange type='added'>has</transChange> ever sat. Untie it and bring <transChange type='added'>it</transChange>.<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note><verse eID='Mark.11.2'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.3' sID='Mark.11.3'/>And if anyone says to you, ‘Why are you doing this?’ say, ‘The Lord has need of it, and will send it here again at once.’ ”<verse eID='Mark.11.3'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.4' sID='Mark.11.4'/>And they went away and found a colt tied at a door outside in the street, and they untied it.<verse eID='Mark.11.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.5' sID='Mark.11.5'/>And some of those who were standing there said to them, “What are you doing, untying the colt?”<verse eID='Mark.11.5'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.6' sID='Mark.11.6'/>So they told them, just as Jesus had said, and they allowed them <transChange type='added'>to take it</transChange>.<note>The phrase “<catchWord>to take it</catchWord>” is not in the Greek text, but is implied</note><verse eID='Mark.11.6'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.7' sID='Mark.11.7'/>And they brought the colt to Jesus and threw their cloaks over it, and he sat on it.<verse eID='Mark.11.7'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.8' sID='Mark.11.8'/>And many <transChange type='added'>people</transChange> spread their cloaks on the road, and others <transChange type='added'>spread</transChange><note>Here the verb “<catchWord>spread</catchWord>” is an understood repetition of the verb earlier in this verse</note> leafy branches <transChange type='added'>they</transChange><note>Here the participle “had cut” has been translated as a finite verb; it agrees in number, gender, and case with “others,” so “<catchWord>they</catchWord>’ has been supplied to indicate this</note> had cut from the fields.<verse eID='Mark.11.8'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.9' sID='Mark.11.9'/>And those who went ahead and those who were following were shouting,</p>
<lg>
<l level='1'>“Hosanna!</l>
<l level='1'>Blessed <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> the one who comes in the name of the Lord!<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Ps.118.25-Ps.118.26'>Ps 118:25–26</reference></note><verse eID='Mark.11.9'/></l>
<l level='1'><verse osisID='Mark.11.10' sID='Mark.11.10'/>Blessed <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> the coming kingdom of our father David!</l>
<l level='2'>Hosanna in the highest <transChange type='added'>heaven</transChange>!”<note>Here “heaven” is understood</note><verse eID='Mark.11.10'/></l>
</lg>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.11.11' sID='Mark.11.11'/>And he went into Jerusalem to the temple, and <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“looking around”) which is understood as temporal</note> looking around at everything, <transChange type='added'>because</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>because</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“was”) which is understood as causal</note> the hour was already evening, he went out to Bethany with the twelve.<verse eID='Mark.11.11'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Barren Fig Tree Cursed</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.11.12' sID='Mark.11.12'/>And on the next day <transChange type='added'>as</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were departing”)</note> they were departing from Bethany, he was hungry.<verse eID='Mark.11.12'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.13' sID='Mark.11.13'/>And <transChange type='added'>when he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw from a distance a fig tree that had leaves, he went <transChange type='added'>to see</transChange> if perhaps he would find anything on it. And <transChange type='added'>when he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came up”) which is understood as temporal</note> came up to it he found nothing except leaves, because it was not the season for figs.<verse eID='Mark.11.13'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.14' sID='Mark.11.14'/>And he responded <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“responded”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to it, “Let no one eat fruit from you any more <seg type='x-idiom'>˻forever˼</seg>!”<note>Literally “for the age”</note> And his disciples heard <transChange type='added'>it</transChange>.<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note><verse eID='Mark.11.14'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Cleansing of the Temple</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.11.15' sID='Mark.11.15'/>And they came to Jerusalem. And he entered into the temple <transChange type='added'>courts</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>courts</catchWord>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“entered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to drive out those who were selling and those who were buying in the temple <transChange type='added'>courts</transChange>,<note>Here “<catchWord>courts</catchWord>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and overturned the tables of the money changers and the chairs of those who were selling doves.<verse eID='Mark.11.15'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.16' sID='Mark.11.16'/>And he did not permit anyone to carry objects<note>Or “merchandise”</note> through the temple <transChange type='added'>courts</transChange>.<note>Here “<catchWord>courts</catchWord>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note><verse eID='Mark.11.16'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.17' sID='Mark.11.17'/>And he began to teach<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to teach”)</note> and was saying to them, “Is it not written,</p>
<lg>
<l level='1'>‘My house will be called a house of prayer</l>
<l level='2'>for all the nations,’<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Isa.56.7'>Isa 56:7</reference></note></l>
</lg>
<p>but you have made it a cave of robbers!”<verse eID='Mark.11.17'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.18' sID='Mark.11.18'/>And the chief priests and the scribes heard <transChange type='added'>it</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and began considering<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began considering”)</note> how they could destroy him. For they were afraid of him because the whole crowd was astounded by his teaching.<verse eID='Mark.11.18'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.19' sID='Mark.11.19'/>And when evening came they went out of the city.<verse eID='Mark.11.19'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Barren Fig Tree Withered</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.11.20' sID='Mark.11.20'/>And <transChange type='added'>as they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“passed by”) which is understood as temporal</note> passed by early in the morning, they saw the fig tree withered from the roots.<verse eID='Mark.11.20'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.21' sID='Mark.11.21'/>And Peter remembered <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“remembered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, “Rabbi, look! The fig tree that you cursed has withered!”<verse eID='Mark.11.21'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.22' sID='Mark.11.22'/>And Jesus answered <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “Have faith in God!<verse eID='Mark.11.22'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.23' sID='Mark.11.23'/>Truly I say to you that whoever says to this mountain, ‘Be lifted up and thrown into the sea!’ and does not doubt in his heart, but believes that what he says will happen, it will be <transChange type='added'>done</transChange> for him.<verse eID='Mark.11.23'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.24' sID='Mark.11.24'/>For this <transChange type='added'>reason</transChange> I say to you, whatever you pray and ask for, believe that you have received <transChange type='added'>it</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and it will be <transChange type='added'>done</transChange> for you.<verse eID='Mark.11.24'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.25' sID='Mark.11.25'/>And whenever you stand praying, if you have anything against anyone, forgive <transChange type='added'>him</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> so that your Father who <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> in heaven will also forgive you your sins.”<note>Most later Greek manuscripts add v. <reference osisRef='Mark.11.26'>26</reference> after v. <reference osisRef='Mark.11.25'>25</reference>, “But if you do not forgive, neither will your Father in heaven forgive your sins”</note><verse eID='Mark.11.25'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus’ Authority Challenged</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.11.27' sID='Mark.11.27'/>And they came again to Jerusalem. And <transChange type='added'>as</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was walking”)</note> he was walking in the temple <transChange type='added'>courts</transChange>,<note>Here “<catchWord>courts</catchWord>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> the chief priests and the scribes and the elders came up to him<verse eID='Mark.11.27'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.28' sID='Mark.11.28'/>and said to him, “By what authority are you doing these <transChange type='added'>things</transChange>, or who gave you this authority that you do these <transChange type='added'>things</transChange>?”<verse eID='Mark.11.28'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.29' sID='Mark.11.29'/>So Jesus said to them, “I will ask you one question. Answer me and I will tell you by what authority I am doing these <transChange type='added'>things</transChange>.<verse eID='Mark.11.29'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.30' sID='Mark.11.30'/>The baptism of John—was <transChange type='added'>it</transChange> from heaven or from men? Answer me!”<verse eID='Mark.11.30'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.31' sID='Mark.11.31'/>And they began to discuss<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to discuss”)</note> <transChange type='added'>this</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> with one another, saying, “If we say ‘From heaven,’ he will say, ‘Why then did you not believe him?’<verse eID='Mark.11.31'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.32' sID='Mark.11.32'/>But if we say, ‘From men’ ”—they were afraid of the crowd, because they all looked upon John <seg type='x-idiom'>˻as truly a prophet˼</seg>.<note>Literally “that he was truly a prophet”</note><verse eID='Mark.11.32'/> <verse osisID='Mark.11.33' sID='Mark.11.33'/>And they replied to Jesus saying, “We do not know.” And Jesus said to them, “Neither will I tell you by what authority I am doing these <transChange type='added'>things</transChange>.”<verse eID='Mark.11.33'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
<chapter osisID='Mark.12'>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Parable of the Tenant Farmers in the Vineyard</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.12.1' sID='Mark.12.1'/>And he began to speak to them in parables: “A man planted a vineyard, and put a fence <transChange type='added'>around it</transChange>, and dug a trough for the winepress, and built a watchtower, and leased it to tenant farmers, and went on a journey.<verse eID='Mark.12.1'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.2' sID='Mark.12.2'/>And he sent a slave to the tenant farmers at the proper time, so that he could collect <transChange type='added'>some</transChange> of the fruit of the vineyard from the tenant farmers.<verse eID='Mark.12.2'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.3' sID='Mark.12.3'/>And they seized him <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“seized”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> beat <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and sent <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> away empty-handed.<verse eID='Mark.12.3'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.4' sID='Mark.12.4'/>And again he sent to them another slave, and that one they struck on the head and dishonored.<verse eID='Mark.12.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.5' sID='Mark.12.5'/>And he sent another, and that one they killed. And <transChange type='added'>he sent</transChange><note>The words “<catchWord>he sent</catchWord>” are not in the Greek text, but are an implied repetition from earlier in the verse</note> many others, <transChange type='added'>some</transChange> of whom they beat and <transChange type='added'>some</transChange> of whom they killed.<verse eID='Mark.12.5'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.6' sID='Mark.12.6'/>He had one more, a beloved son. Last <transChange type='added'>of all</transChange> he sent him to them, saying, ‘They will respect my son.’<verse eID='Mark.12.6'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.7' sID='Mark.12.7'/>But those tenant farmers said to one another, ‘This is the heir. Come, let us kill him and the inheritance will be ours!’<verse eID='Mark.12.7'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.8' sID='Mark.12.8'/>And they seized <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“seized”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> killed him and threw him out of the vineyard.<verse eID='Mark.12.8'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.9' sID='Mark.12.9'/>What then will the owner of the vineyard do? He will come and destroy the tenant farmers and give the vineyard to others.<verse eID='Mark.12.9'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.10' sID='Mark.12.10'/>Have you not read this scripture:</p>
<lg>
<l level='1'>‘The stone which the builders rejected,</l>
<l level='2'>this has become <seg type='x-idiom'>˻the cornerstone˼</seg>.<note>Literally “the head of the corner”</note><verse eID='Mark.12.10'/></l>
<l level='1'><verse osisID='Mark.12.11' sID='Mark.12.11'/>This came about from the Lord,</l>
<l level='2'>and it is marvelous in our eyes’?”<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Ps.118.22-Ps.118.23'>Ps 118:22–23</reference></note><verse eID='Mark.12.11'/></l>
</lg>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.12.12' sID='Mark.12.12'/>And they were seeking to arrest him, and they were afraid of the crowd, because they knew that he had told the parable with reference to them. And they left him <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“left”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went away.<verse eID='Mark.12.12'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Paying Taxes to Caesar</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.12.13' sID='Mark.12.13'/>And they sent some of the Pharisees and the Herodians to him so that they could catch him unawares in a statement.<verse eID='Mark.12.13'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.14' sID='Mark.12.14'/>And <transChange type='added'>when they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“came”) which is understood as temporal</note> came, they said to him, “Teacher, we know that you are truthful and <seg type='x-idiom'>˻you do not care what anyone thinks˼</seg>,<note>Literally “it is not a care to you concerning anyone”</note> <seg type='x-idiom'>˻because you do not regard the opinion of people˼</seg><note>Literally “because you do not look at the face of men”</note> but teach the way of God in truth. Is it permitted to pay taxes to Caesar or not? Should we pay or should we not pay?”<verse eID='Mark.12.14'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.15' sID='Mark.12.15'/>But <transChange type='added'>because he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>because</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“knew”) which is understood as causal</note> knew their hypocrisy, he said to them, “Why are you testing me? Bring me a denarius so that I can look at <transChange type='added'>it</transChange>!”<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note><verse eID='Mark.12.15'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.16' sID='Mark.12.16'/>So they brought <transChange type='added'>one</transChange>.<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> And he said to them, “Whose image and inscription <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> this?” And they said to him, “Caesar’s.”<verse eID='Mark.12.16'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.17' sID='Mark.12.17'/>And Jesus said to them, “Give to Caesar the things of Caesar, and to God the things of God!” And they were utterly amazed at him.<verse eID='Mark.12.17'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Question About Marriage and the Resurrection</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.12.18' sID='Mark.12.18'/>And Sadducees—who say there is no resurrection—came up to him and began to ask<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to ask”)</note> him, saying,<verse eID='Mark.12.18'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.19' sID='Mark.12.19'/>“Teacher, Moses wrote for us that if someone’s brother dies and he leaves behind a wife and does not leave a child, that his brother should take the wife and <seg type='x-idiom'>˻father˼</seg><note>Literally “raise up”</note> descendants for his brother.<verse eID='Mark.12.19'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.20' sID='Mark.12.20'/>There were seven brothers, and the first took a wife. And <transChange type='added'>when he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“died”) which is understood as temporal</note> died, he did not leave descendants.<verse eID='Mark.12.20'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.21' sID='Mark.12.21'/>And the second took her, and he died without leaving descendants. And the third likewise.<verse eID='Mark.12.21'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.22' sID='Mark.12.22'/>And the seven did not leave descendants. Last of all the woman also died.<verse eID='Mark.12.22'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.23' sID='Mark.12.23'/>In the resurrection, when they rise, <seg type='x-idiom'>˻whose˼</seg><note>Literally “who of them”</note> wife will she be? For the seven had her <transChange type='added'>as</transChange> wife.<verse eID='Mark.12.23'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.24' sID='Mark.12.24'/>Jesus said to them, “Are you not deceived because of this, <transChange type='added'>because you</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>because</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“know”) which is understood as causal</note> do not know the scriptures or the power of God?<verse eID='Mark.12.24'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.25' sID='Mark.12.25'/>For when they rise from the dead, they neither marry nor are given in marriage, but are like angels in heaven.<verse eID='Mark.12.25'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.26' sID='Mark.12.26'/>Now concerning the dead, that they are raised, have you not read in the book of Moses <seg type='x-idiom'>˻in the passage about the bush˼</seg><note>Literally “at the bush”</note> how God spoke to him, saying, ‘I <transChange type='added'>am</transChange> the God of Abraham and the God of Isaac and the God of Jacob’?<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Exod.3.6'>Exod 3:6</reference></note><verse eID='Mark.12.26'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.27' sID='Mark.12.27'/>He is not God of the dead, but of the living. You are very much mistaken!”<verse eID='Mark.12.27'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Greatest Commandment</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.12.28' sID='Mark.12.28'/>And one of the scribes came up <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> heard them debating. <transChange type='added'>When he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw that he answered them well, he asked him, “Which commandment is the most important of all?”<verse eID='Mark.12.28'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.29' sID='Mark.12.29'/>Jesus answered, “The most important is, ‘Listen, Israel! The Lord our God, the Lord is one.<verse eID='Mark.12.29'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.30' sID='Mark.12.30'/>And you shall love the Lord your God from your whole heart and from your whole soul and from your whole mind and from your whole strength.’<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Deut.6.4-Deut.6.5'>Deut 6:4–5</reference>; <reference osisRef='Josh.22.5'>Josh 22:5</reference></note><verse eID='Mark.12.30'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.31' sID='Mark.12.31'/>The second <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> this: ‘You shall love your neighbor as yourself.’<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Lev.19.18'>Lev 19:18</reference></note> There is no other commandment greater than these.”<verse eID='Mark.12.31'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.32' sID='Mark.12.32'/>And the scribe said to him, “That is true, Teacher. You have said <seg type='x-idiom'>˻correctly˼</seg><note>Literally “in accordance with truth”</note> that he is one and there is no other except him.<verse eID='Mark.12.32'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.33' sID='Mark.12.33'/>And to love him from your<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> whole heart and from your<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> whole understanding and from your<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> whole strength, and to love your<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> neighbor as yourself, is much more than all whole burnt offerings and sacrifices.”<verse eID='Mark.12.33'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.34' sID='Mark.12.34'/>And Jesus, <transChange type='added'>when he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw that he had answered thoughtfully, said to him, “You are not far from the kingdom of God.” And no one dared to put a question to him any longer.<verse eID='Mark.12.34'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>David’s Son and Lord</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.12.35' sID='Mark.12.35'/>And continuing, Jesus said <transChange type='added'>while</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>while</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“teaching”) which is understood as temporal</note> teaching in the temple <transChange type='added'>courts</transChange>,<note>Here “<catchWord>courts</catchWord>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> “How can the scribes say that the Christ is David’s son?<verse eID='Mark.12.35'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.36' sID='Mark.12.36'/>David himself said by the Holy Spirit,</p>
<lg>
<l level='1'>‘The Lord said to my Lord,</l>
<l level='2'>“Sit at my right hand,</l>
<l level='1'>until I put your enemies</l>
<l level='2'>under your feet.” ’<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Ps.110.1'>Ps 110:1</reference></note><verse eID='Mark.12.36'/></l>
</lg>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.12.37' sID='Mark.12.37'/>David himself calls him ‘Lord,’ and how is he his son?” And the large crowd was listening to him gladly.<verse eID='Mark.12.37'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Warning to Beware of the Scribes</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.12.38' sID='Mark.12.38'/>And in his teaching he said, “Beware of the scribes, who like walking around in long robes and greetings in the marketplaces<verse eID='Mark.12.38'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.39' sID='Mark.12.39'/>and the best seats in the synagogues and the places of honor at banquets,<verse eID='Mark.12.39'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.40' sID='Mark.12.40'/>who devour the houses of widows and pray lengthy <transChange type='added'>prayers</transChange> for the sake of appearance. These will receive more severe condemnation!”<verse eID='Mark.12.40'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>A Poor Widow’s Offering</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.12.41' sID='Mark.12.41'/>And he sat down opposite the contribution box <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“sat down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> was observing how the crowd was putting coins into the contribution box. And many rich people were putting in many <transChange type='added'>coins</transChange>.<note>Although often translated “large sums,” the plural here suggests large numbers of individual coins, which would make an impressive noise</note><verse eID='Mark.12.41'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.42' sID='Mark.12.42'/>And one poor widow came <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> put in two small copper coins<note>This coin was the <hi type='italic'>lepton</hi>, worth 1/128 of a denarius</note> (that is, a penny).<note>This coin was the <hi type='italic'>quadrans</hi>, the smallest Roman coin, worth 2 <hi type='italic'>lepta</hi></note><verse eID='Mark.12.42'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.43' sID='Mark.12.43'/>And summoning his disciples, he said to them, “Truly I say to you that this poor widow put in more than all those who put <transChange type='added'>offerings</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> into the contribution box.<verse eID='Mark.12.43'/> <verse osisID='Mark.12.44' sID='Mark.12.44'/>For they all <seg type='x-idiom'>˻contributed˼</seg><note>Literally “put in”</note> out of their abundance, but she out of her poverty put in everything she had, her whole means of subsistence.”<verse eID='Mark.12.44'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
<chapter osisID='Mark.13'>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Destruction of the Temple Predicted</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.13.1' sID='Mark.13.1'/>And <transChange type='added'>as</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was going out”)</note> he was going out of the temple <transChange type='added'>courts</transChange>,<note>Here “<catchWord>courts</catchWord>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> one of his disciples said to him, “Teacher, look! What great stones and what wonderful buildings!”<verse eID='Mark.13.1'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.2' sID='Mark.13.2'/>And Jesus said to him, “Do you see these great buildings? Not <transChange type='added'>one</transChange> stone will be left here on <transChange type='added'>another</transChange> stone that will not be thrown down!”<verse eID='Mark.13.2'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Signs of the End of the Age</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.13.3' sID='Mark.13.3'/>And <transChange type='added'>as</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was sitting”)</note> he was sitting on the Mount of Olives opposite the temple, Peter and James and John and Andrew asked him privately,<verse eID='Mark.13.3'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.4' sID='Mark.13.4'/>“Tell us, when will these <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> happen, and what <transChange type='added'>will be</transChange> the sign when all these <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> are about to be accomplished?”<verse eID='Mark.13.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.5' sID='Mark.13.5'/>So Jesus began to say to them, “Watch out that no one deceives you!<verse eID='Mark.13.5'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.6' sID='Mark.13.6'/>Many will come in my name, saying, ‘I am <transChange type='added'>he</transChange>,’ and they will deceive many.<verse eID='Mark.13.6'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.7' sID='Mark.13.7'/>And when you hear about wars and rumors of wars, do not be alarmed. This must happen, but the end <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> not yet.<verse eID='Mark.13.7'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.8' sID='Mark.13.8'/>For nation will rise up against nation and kingdom against kingdom. There will be earthquakes in <transChange type='added'>various</transChange> places. There will be famines. These <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> <transChange type='added'>are</transChange> the beginning of birth pains.<verse eID='Mark.13.8'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Persecution of Disciples Predicted</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.13.9' sID='Mark.13.9'/>“But you, watch out for yourselves! They will hand you over to councils and you will be beaten in the synagogues and will have to stand before governors and kings because of me, for a witness to them.<verse eID='Mark.13.9'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.10' sID='Mark.13.10'/>And the gospel must first be proclaimed to all the nations.<note>Or “Gentiles”; the same Greek word can be translated “nations” or “Gentiles” depending on the context</note><verse eID='Mark.13.10'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.11' sID='Mark.13.11'/>And when they arrest you <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the participle (“hand you over”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> hand you over, do not be anxious beforehand what you should say, but whatever is given to you at that hour, say this. For you are not the ones who are speaking, but the Holy Spirit.<verse eID='Mark.13.11'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.12' sID='Mark.13.12'/>And brother will hand over brother to death, and a father <transChange type='added'>his</transChange><note>The word “<catchWord>his</catchWord>” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> child, and children will rise up against parents and have them put to death.<verse eID='Mark.13.12'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.13' sID='Mark.13.13'/>And you will be hated by all because of my name. But the one who endures to the end—this one will be saved.<verse eID='Mark.13.13'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Abomination of Desolation</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.13.14' sID='Mark.13.14'/>“But when you see the abomination of desolation standing where it should not be” (let the one who reads understand), “then those in Judea must flee to the mountains!<verse eID='Mark.13.14'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.15' sID='Mark.13.15'/>The one who is on his<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> housetop must not come down or go inside to take anything out of his house,<verse eID='Mark.13.15'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.16' sID='Mark.13.16'/>and the one who is in the field must not turn back to pick up his cloak.<verse eID='Mark.13.16'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.17' sID='Mark.13.17'/>And woe to those <seg type='x-idiom'>˻who are pregnant˼</seg><note>Literally “who have in the womb”</note> and to those who are nursing <transChange type='added'>their babies</transChange><note>The words “<catchWord>their babies</catchWord>” are not in the Greek text but are supplied as a necessary clarification</note> in those days!<verse eID='Mark.13.17'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.18' sID='Mark.13.18'/>But pray that it will not happen in winter.<verse eID='Mark.13.18'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.19' sID='Mark.13.19'/>For <transChange type='added'>in</transChange> those days there will be tribulation of such a kind as has not happened from the beginning of the creation that God created until now, and never will happen.<verse eID='Mark.13.19'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.20' sID='Mark.13.20'/>And if the Lord had not shortened the days, <seg type='x-idiom'>˻no human being would be saved˼</seg>.<note>Literally “every flesh would not be saved”</note> But for the sake of the elect, whom he chose, he has shortened the days.<verse eID='Mark.13.20'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.13.21' sID='Mark.13.21'/>“And at that time if anyone should say to you, “Behold, here <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> the Christ,’ ‘Behold, there <transChange type='added'>he is</transChange>,’ do not believe <transChange type='added'>him</transChange>!<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note><verse eID='Mark.13.21'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.22' sID='Mark.13.22'/>For false messiahs and false prophets will appear, and will produce signs and wonders in order to mislead, if possible, the elect.<verse eID='Mark.13.22'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.23' sID='Mark.13.23'/>But you, watch out! I have told you everything ahead of time!<verse eID='Mark.13.23'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Arrival of the Son of Man</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.13.24' sID='Mark.13.24'/>“But in those days, after that tribulation,</p>
<lg>
<l level='1'>‘the sun will be darkened</l>
<l level='2'>and the moon will not give its light,<verse eID='Mark.13.24'/></l>
<l level='1'><verse osisID='Mark.13.25' sID='Mark.13.25'/>and the stars will be falling from heaven,</l>
<l level='2'>and the powers in the heavens will be shaken.’<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Isa.13.10'>Isa 13:10</reference>; <reference osisRef='Isa.34.4'>34:4</reference></note><verse eID='Mark.13.25'/></l>
</lg>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.13.26' sID='Mark.13.26'/>And then they will see the Son of Man arriving in the clouds with great power and glory.<verse eID='Mark.13.26'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.27' sID='Mark.13.27'/>And then he will send out the angels, and will gather his elect together from the four winds, from the end of the earth to the end of heaven.<verse eID='Mark.13.27'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Parable of the Fig Tree</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.13.28' sID='Mark.13.28'/>“Now learn the parable from the fig tree: Whenever its branch has already become tender and puts forth its<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> leaves, you know that summer is near.<verse eID='Mark.13.28'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.29' sID='Mark.13.29'/>So also you, when you see these <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> happening, know<note>Or “you know”</note> that he is near, at the door.<verse eID='Mark.13.29'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.30' sID='Mark.13.30'/>Truly I say to you that this generation will never pass away until all these <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> take place!<verse eID='Mark.13.30'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.31' sID='Mark.13.31'/>Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will never pass away.<verse eID='Mark.13.31'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Unknown Day and Hour</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.13.32' sID='Mark.13.32'/>“But concerning that day or hour no one knows—not even the angels in heaven nor the Son—except the Father.<verse eID='Mark.13.32'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.33' sID='Mark.13.33'/>Watch out! Be alert, because you do not know when the time is!<verse eID='Mark.13.33'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.34' sID='Mark.13.34'/>It is like a man away on a journey, who left his house and gave his slaves authority—to each one his work—and to the doorkeeper he gave orders that he should be on the alert.<verse eID='Mark.13.34'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.35' sID='Mark.13.35'/>Therefore be on the alert, for you do not know when the master of the house is coming—whether in the evening, or at midnight, or when the rooster crows, or early in the morning—<verse eID='Mark.13.35'/><verse osisID='Mark.13.36' sID='Mark.13.36'/>lest he arrive suddenly <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“arrive”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> find you sleeping.<verse eID='Mark.13.36'/> <verse osisID='Mark.13.37' sID='Mark.13.37'/>And what I say to you, I say to everyone: Be on the alert!”<verse eID='Mark.13.37'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
<chapter osisID='Mark.14'>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Chief Priests and Scribes Plot to Kill Jesus</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.14.1' sID='Mark.14.1'/>Now after two days it was the Passover and the feast of Unleavened Bread, and the chief priests and the scribes were seeking how, <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arresting”) which is understood as temporal</note> arresting him by stealth, they could kill <transChange type='added'>him</transChange>.<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note><verse eID='Mark.14.1'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.2' sID='Mark.14.2'/>For they said, “Not at the feast, lest there be an uproar by the people.”<verse eID='Mark.14.2'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus’ Anointing at Bethany</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.14.3' sID='Mark.14.3'/>And <transChange type='added'>while</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>while</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> he was at Bethany in the house of Simon the leper, <transChange type='added'>as</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was reclining for a meal”)</note> he was reclining for a meal, a woman came holding an alabaster flask of very costly perfumed oil of genuine nard. <transChange type='added'>After</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“breaking”) which is understood as temporal</note> breaking the alabaster flask, she poured <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> out on his head.<verse eID='Mark.14.3'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.4' sID='Mark.14.4'/>But some were expressing indignation to one another:<note>Or perhaps “within themselves”</note> “Why has there been this waste of perfumed oil?<verse eID='Mark.14.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.5' sID='Mark.14.5'/>For this perfumed oil could have been sold for more than three hundred denarii and given to the poor!” And they began to scold<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to scold”)</note> her.<verse eID='Mark.14.5'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.6' sID='Mark.14.6'/>But Jesus said, “Leave her alone. Why do you cause trouble for her? She has done a good deed to me.<verse eID='Mark.14.6'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.7' sID='Mark.14.7'/>For the poor you always have with you, and you can do good for them whenever you want, but you do not always have me.<verse eID='Mark.14.7'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.8' sID='Mark.14.8'/>She has done what she could; <seg type='x-idiom'>˻she has anointed my body beforehand˼</seg><note>Literally “she has anticipated to anoint my body”</note> for burial.<verse eID='Mark.14.8'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.9' sID='Mark.14.9'/>And truly I say to you, wherever the gospel is proclaimed in the whole world, what she has done will also be told in memory of her.<verse eID='Mark.14.9'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Judas Arranges to Betray Jesus</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.14.10' sID='Mark.14.10'/>And Judas Iscariot, who <transChange type='added'>was</transChange> one of the twelve, went to the chief priests in order to betray him to them.<verse eID='Mark.14.10'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.11' sID='Mark.14.11'/>And <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> they heard <transChange type='added'>this</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> they were delighted, and promised to give him money. And he began seeking<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began seeking”)</note> how he could betray him conveniently.<verse eID='Mark.14.11'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus’ Final Passover with the Disciples</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.14.12' sID='Mark.14.12'/>And on the first day of the feast of Unleavened Bread, when they sacrificed the Passover lamb, his disciples said to him, “Where do you want us to go <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “and” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as an English infinitive</note> prepare, so that you can eat the Passover?”<verse eID='Mark.14.12'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.13' sID='Mark.14.13'/>And he sent two of his disciples and said to them, “Go into the city and a man carrying a jar of water will meet you. Follow him,<verse eID='Mark.14.13'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.14' sID='Mark.14.14'/>and wherever he enters, say to the master of the house, ‘The Teacher says, “Where is my guest room where I may eat the Passover with my disciples?” ’<verse eID='Mark.14.14'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.15' sID='Mark.14.15'/>And he will show you a large upstairs room furnished<note>Or perhaps “paved” or “panelled”</note> <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied in the translation because of English style</note> ready, and prepare for us there.”<verse eID='Mark.14.15'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.16' sID='Mark.14.16'/>And the disciples went out and came into the city and found <transChange type='added'>everything</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> just as he had told them, and they prepared the Passover.<verse eID='Mark.14.16'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.14.17' sID='Mark.14.17'/>And <transChange type='added'>when it</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> was evening, he arrived with the twelve.<verse eID='Mark.14.17'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.18' sID='Mark.14.18'/>And <transChange type='added'>while</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>while</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were reclining at table”)</note> they were reclining at table and eating, Jesus said, “Truly I say to you, that one of you who is eating with me will betray me.”<verse eID='Mark.14.18'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.19' sID='Mark.14.19'/>They began to be distressed and to say to him one by one, “Surely not I?”<note>The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note><verse eID='Mark.14.19'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.20' sID='Mark.14.20'/>But he said to them, “<transChange type='added'>It is</transChange> one of the twelve—the one who is dipping <transChange type='added'>bread</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> into the bowl with me.<verse eID='Mark.14.20'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.21' sID='Mark.14.21'/>For the Son of Man is going just as it is written about him, but woe to that man by whom the Son of Man is betrayed! <transChange type='added'>It would be</transChange> better for him if that man had not been born.”<verse eID='Mark.14.21'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Lord’s Supper</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.14.22' sID='Mark.14.22'/>And <transChange type='added'>while</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>while</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“were eating”)</note> they were eating, he took bread <transChange type='added'>and</transChange>,<note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied in the translation because of English style</note> <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“giving thanks”) which is understood as temporal</note> giving thanks, he broke <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and gave <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to them and said, “Take <transChange type='added'>it</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> this is my body.”<verse eID='Mark.14.22'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.23' sID='Mark.14.23'/>And <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“taking”) which is understood as temporal</note> taking the cup <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied in the translation because of English style</note> giving thanks, he gave <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to them, and they all drank from it.<verse eID='Mark.14.23'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.24' sID='Mark.14.24'/>And he said to them, “This is my blood of the covenant which is poured out for many.<verse eID='Mark.14.24'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.25' sID='Mark.14.25'/>Truly I say to you that I will never drink of the fruit of the vine any longer until that day when I drink it new in the kingdom of God.”<verse eID='Mark.14.25'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.26' sID='Mark.14.26'/>And <transChange type='added'>after they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had sung the hymn”) which is understood as temporal</note> had sung the hymn, they went out to the Mount of Olives.<verse eID='Mark.14.26'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus Predicts Peter’s Denial</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.14.27' sID='Mark.14.27'/>And Jesus said to them, “You will all fall away, because it is written,</p>
<lg>
<l level='1'>‘I will strike the shepherd</l>
<l level='2'>and the sheep will be scattered.’<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Zech.13.7'>Zech 13:7</reference></note><verse eID='Mark.14.27'/></l>
</lg>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.14.28' sID='Mark.14.28'/>But after I am raised, I will go ahead of you into Galilee.”<verse eID='Mark.14.28'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.29' sID='Mark.14.29'/>But Peter said to him, “Even if they all fall away, certainly I will not!”<verse eID='Mark.14.29'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.30' sID='Mark.14.30'/>And Jesus said to him, “Truly I say to you that today—this night—before the rooster crows twice, you will deny me three times!”<verse eID='Mark.14.30'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.31' sID='Mark.14.31'/>But he kept saying emphatically, “If it is necessary for me to die with you, I will never deny you!” And they all were saying the same <transChange type='added'>thing</transChange> also.<verse eID='Mark.14.31'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Prayer in Gethsemane</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.14.32' sID='Mark.14.32'/>And they came to a place <seg type='x-idiom'>˻named˼</seg><note>Literally “the name of which”</note> Gethsemane, and he said to his disciples, “Sit here while I pray.”<verse eID='Mark.14.32'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.33' sID='Mark.14.33'/>And he took along Peter and James and John with him, and he began to be distressed and troubled.<verse eID='Mark.14.33'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.34' sID='Mark.14.34'/>And he said to them, “My soul is deeply grieved, to the point of death. Remain here and stay awake.”<verse eID='Mark.14.34'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.35' sID='Mark.14.35'/>And going forward a little he fell to the ground and began to pray<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to pray”)</note> that, if it were possible, the hour would pass from him.<verse eID='Mark.14.35'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.36' sID='Mark.14.36'/>And he said, “Abba,<note>The word “Abba” means “father” in Aramaic</note> Father, all <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> <transChange type='added'>are</transChange> possible for you! Take away this cup from me! Yet not what I will, but what you <transChange type='added'>will</transChange>.”<note>Here the verb “<catchWord>will</catchWord>” is an understood repetition of the verb earlier in this verse</note><verse eID='Mark.14.36'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.37' sID='Mark.14.37'/>And he came and found them sleeping, and he said to Peter, “Simon, are you sleeping? Were you not able to stay awake one hour?<verse eID='Mark.14.37'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.38' sID='Mark.14.38'/>Stay awake and pray that you will not enter into temptation. The spirit <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> willing, but the flesh <transChange type='added'>is</transChange> weak!”<verse eID='Mark.14.38'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.39' sID='Mark.14.39'/>And again he went away <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went away”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> prayed, saying the same thing.<verse eID='Mark.14.39'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.40' sID='Mark.14.40'/>And again he came <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> found them sleeping, <seg type='x-idiom'>˻for they could not keep their eyes open˼</seg>,<note>Literally “for their eyes were weighed down”</note> and they did not know what to reply to him.<verse eID='Mark.14.40'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.41' sID='Mark.14.41'/>And he came the third <transChange type='added'>time</transChange> and said to them, “Are you still sleeping and resting? It is enough! The hour has come. Behold, the Son of Man is being betrayed into the hands of sinners.<verse eID='Mark.14.41'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.42' sID='Mark.14.42'/>Get up, let us go! Behold, the one who is betraying me is approaching!”<verse eID='Mark.14.42'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Betrayal and Arrest of Jesus</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.14.43' sID='Mark.14.43'/>And immediately, <transChange type='added'>while</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>while</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was … speaking”)</note> he was still speaking, Judas—one of the twelve—arrived, and with him a crowd with swords and clubs, from the chief priests and the scribes and the elders.<verse eID='Mark.14.43'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.44' sID='Mark.14.44'/>Now the one who was betraying him had given them a sign, saying, “<transChange type='added'>The one</transChange> whom I kiss—he is <transChange type='added'>the one</transChange>.<note>Here the predicate nominative (“<catchWord>the one</catchWord>”) is implied</note> Arrest him and lead <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> away under guard!”<verse eID='Mark.14.44'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.45' sID='Mark.14.45'/>And <transChange type='added'>when he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“arrived”) which is understood as temporal</note> arrived, he came up to him immediately <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “Rabbi,” and kissed him.<verse eID='Mark.14.45'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.46' sID='Mark.14.46'/>So they laid hands on him and arrested him.<verse eID='Mark.14.46'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.14.47' sID='Mark.14.47'/>But a certain one of the bystanders, drawing <transChange type='added'>his</transChange><note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> sword, struck the slave of the high priest and cut off his ear.<verse eID='Mark.14.47'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.48' sID='Mark.14.48'/>And Jesus answered <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to them, “Have you come out with swords and clubs, as against a robber, to arrest me?<verse eID='Mark.14.48'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.49' sID='Mark.14.49'/>Every day I was with you in the temple <transChange type='added'>courts</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>courts</catchWord>” is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> teaching, and you did not arrest me! But <transChange type='added'>this has happened</transChange><note>The phrase “<catchWord>this has happened</catchWord>” is not in the Greek text, but is understood and must be supplied in the translation because of English style; cf. the parallel in <reference osisRef='Matt.26.56'>Matt 26:56</reference></note> in order that the scriptures would be fulfilled.<verse eID='Mark.14.49'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.50' sID='Mark.14.50'/>And they all abandoned him <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“abandoned”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> fled.<verse eID='Mark.14.50'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.14.51' sID='Mark.14.51'/>And a certain young man was following him, clothed <transChange type='added'>only</transChange> in a linen cloth on <transChange type='added'>his</transChange> naked body. And they attempted to seize<note>Here the present tense is translated as a conative present (“attempted to”)</note> him,<verse eID='Mark.14.51'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.52' sID='Mark.14.52'/>but he left behind the linen cloth <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“left behind”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> fled naked.<verse eID='Mark.14.52'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus Before the Sanhedrin</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.14.53' sID='Mark.14.53'/>And they led Jesus away to the high priest, and all the chief priests and the elders and the scribes came together.<verse eID='Mark.14.53'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.54' sID='Mark.14.54'/>And Peter followed him from a distance, right inside, into the courtyard of the high priest. And he was sitting with the officers and warming himself by the fire.<verse eID='Mark.14.54'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.55' sID='Mark.14.55'/>Now the chief priests and the whole Sanhedrin were looking for testimony against Jesus in order to put him to death, and they did not find <transChange type='added'>it</transChange>.<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note><verse eID='Mark.14.55'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.56' sID='Mark.14.56'/>For many gave false testimony against him, and their<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> testimony was not consistent.<verse eID='Mark.14.56'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.57' sID='Mark.14.57'/>And some stood up <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stood up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to give false testimony<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to give false testimony”)</note> against him, saying,<verse eID='Mark.14.57'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.58' sID='Mark.14.58'/>“We heard him saying, ‘I will destroy this temple made by hands, and within three days I will build another not made by hands.”<verse eID='Mark.14.58'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.59' sID='Mark.14.59'/>And their testimony was not even consistent about this.<verse eID='Mark.14.59'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.60' sID='Mark.14.60'/>And the high priest stood up in the midst <transChange type='added'>of them</transChange> <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“stood up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> asked Jesus, saying, “Do you not reply anything? What are these <transChange type='added'>people</transChange> testifying against you?”<verse eID='Mark.14.60'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.61' sID='Mark.14.61'/>But he was silent and did not reply anything. Again the high priest asked him and said to him, “Are you the Christ, the Son of the Blessed One?”<verse eID='Mark.14.61'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.62' sID='Mark.14.62'/>And Jesus said, “I am, and you will see the Son of Man sitting at the right hand of the Power<note>An indirect way of referring to God</note> and coming with the clouds of heaven.”<verse eID='Mark.14.62'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.63' sID='Mark.14.63'/>And the high priest tore his clothes <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“tore”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “What further need do we have of witnesses?<verse eID='Mark.14.63'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.64' sID='Mark.14.64'/>You have heard the blasphemy! What <seg type='x-idiom'>˻do you think˼</seg>?”<note>Literally “does it seem to you”</note> And they all condemned him <seg type='x-idiom'>˻as deserving death˼</seg>.<note>Literally “to be deserving of death”</note><verse eID='Mark.14.64'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.65' sID='Mark.14.65'/>And some began to spit on him and to cover his face and to strike him with their fists, and to say to him “Prophesy!” And the officers received him with slaps in the face.<note>Or “with blows” (either meaning is possible here)</note><verse eID='Mark.14.65'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Peter Denies Jesus Three Times</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.14.66' sID='Mark.14.66'/>And <transChange type='added'>while</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>while</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> Peter was below in the courtyard, one of the female slaves of the high priest came up<verse eID='Mark.14.66'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.67' sID='Mark.14.67'/>And <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> she saw Peter warming himself, she looked intently at him <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“looked intently at”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “You also were with the Nazarene, Jesus.”<verse eID='Mark.14.67'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.68' sID='Mark.14.68'/>But he denied <transChange type='added'>it</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> saying, “I neither know nor understand what you mean!” And he went out into the gateway, and a rooster crowed.<note>Several important and early manuscripts lack the words “and a rooster crowed”</note><verse eID='Mark.14.68'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.69' sID='Mark.14.69'/>And the female slave, <transChange type='added'>when she</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> saw him, began to say again to the bystanders, “This man is one of them!”<verse eID='Mark.14.69'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.70' sID='Mark.14.70'/>But he denied <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> again. And after a little <transChange type='added'>while</transChange>, again the bystanders began to say<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to say”)</note> to Peter, “You really are <transChange type='added'>one</transChange> of them, because you also are a Galilean!”<verse eID='Mark.14.70'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.71' sID='Mark.14.71'/>And he began to curse and to swear with an oath, “I do not know this man whom you are talking about!”<verse eID='Mark.14.71'/> <verse osisID='Mark.14.72' sID='Mark.14.72'/>And immediately a rooster crowed for the second time. And Peter remembered the statement, how Jesus had said to him, “Before the rooster crows twice, you will deny me three times,” and throwing himself down, he began to weep.<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to weep”)</note><verse eID='Mark.14.72'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
<chapter osisID='Mark.15'>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus Taken to Pilate</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.15.1' sID='Mark.15.1'/>And as soon as morning <transChange type='added'>came</transChange>, <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“formulating”) which is understood as temporal</note> formulating a plan, the chief priests, with the elders and scribes and the whole Sanhedrin, tied up Jesus, led <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> away, and handed <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> over to Pilate.<verse eID='Mark.15.1'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.2' sID='Mark.15.2'/>And Pilate asked him, “Are you the king of the Jews?” And he answered him <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> said, “You say <transChange type='added'>so</transChange>.”<verse eID='Mark.15.2'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.3' sID='Mark.15.3'/>And the chief priests began to accuse<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here (“began to accuse”)</note> him <transChange type='added'>of</transChange> many <transChange type='added'>things</transChange>.<verse eID='Mark.15.3'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.4' sID='Mark.15.4'/>So Pilate asked him again, saying, “Do you not answer anything? See how many <transChange type='added'>charges</transChange><note>The word “charges” is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> they are bringing against you!”<verse eID='Mark.15.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.5' sID='Mark.15.5'/>But Jesus did not answer anything further, so that Pilate was astonished.<verse eID='Mark.15.5'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Pilate Releases Barabbas</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.15.6' sID='Mark.15.6'/>Now at each feast he customarily released<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as customary here (“customarily released”)</note> for them one prisoner whom they requested.<verse eID='Mark.15.6'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.7' sID='Mark.15.7'/>And the one named Barabbas<note>“Barabbas” means “son of the father” in Aramaic</note> was imprisoned with the rebels who had committed murder in the rebellion.<verse eID='Mark.15.7'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.8' sID='Mark.15.8'/>And the crowd came up <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came up”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to ask him to do as he customarily did<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as customary here (“customarily did”)</note> for them.<verse eID='Mark.15.8'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.9' sID='Mark.15.9'/>So Pilate answered them, saying, “Do you want me to release for you the king of the Jews?”<verse eID='Mark.15.9'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.10' sID='Mark.15.10'/>(For he realized that the chief priests had handed him over because of envy.)<verse eID='Mark.15.10'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.11' sID='Mark.15.11'/>But the chief priests incited the crowd so that he would release for them Barabbas<note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“answered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> instead.<verse eID='Mark.15.11'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.12' sID='Mark.15.12'/>So Pilate answered <transChange type='added'>and</transChange> said to them again, “Then what do you want me to do with <transChange type='added'>the one</transChange> whom you call the king of the Jews?”<verse eID='Mark.15.12'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.13' sID='Mark.15.13'/>And they shouted again, “Crucify him!”<verse eID='Mark.15.13'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.14' sID='Mark.15.14'/>And Pilate said to them, “Why? What evil has he done?” But they shouted even louder, “Crucify him!”<verse eID='Mark.15.14'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.15.15' sID='Mark.15.15'/>So Pilate, <transChange type='added'>because he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>because</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“wanted”) which is understood as causal</note> wanted <seg type='x-idiom'>˻to satisfy˼</seg><note>Literally “to make sufficient”</note> the crowd, released for them Barabbas. And <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“flogged”) which is understood as temporal</note> he had Jesus flogged, he handed <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> over so that he could be crucified.<verse eID='Mark.15.15'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus Is Mocked</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.15.16' sID='Mark.15.16'/>So the soldiers led him away into the palace (that is, the governor’s residence) and called together the whole cohort.<verse eID='Mark.15.16'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.17' sID='Mark.15.17'/>And they put a purple cloak on him, and <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“weaving”) which is understood as temporal</note> weaving a crown of thorns they placed <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on him.<verse eID='Mark.15.17'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.18' sID='Mark.15.18'/>And they began to greet him, “Hail, king of the Jews!”<verse eID='Mark.15.18'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.19' sID='Mark.15.19'/>And they repeatedly struck<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as iterative here (“repeatedly struck”)</note> him on the head with a reed, and were spitting on him, and <seg type='x-idiom'>˻they knelt down˼</seg><note>Literally “bending the knees”</note> <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“knelt down”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> did obeisance to him.<verse eID='Mark.15.19'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.20' sID='Mark.15.20'/>And when they had mocked him, they stripped him of the purple cloak and put his <transChange type='added'>own</transChange> clothes on him, and they led him out so that they could crucify him.<verse eID='Mark.15.20'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus Is Crucified</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.15.21' sID='Mark.15.21'/>And they forced a certain man who was passing by, Simon of Cyrene (the father of Alexander and Rufus), who was coming from the country, to carry his cross.<verse eID='Mark.15.21'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.22' sID='Mark.15.22'/>And they brought him to the place <hi type='italic'>Golgotha</hi> (which is translated “Place of a Skull”).<verse eID='Mark.15.22'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.23' sID='Mark.15.23'/>And they attempted to give<note>Here the imperfect tense is translated as a conative imperfect (“attempted to give”)</note> him wine mixed with myrrh, but he did not take it.<verse eID='Mark.15.23'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.24' sID='Mark.15.24'/>And they crucified him and divided his clothes among themselves<note>Here “among themselves” reflects the middle voice of the verb “divided”</note> <transChange type='added'>by</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>by</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“casting”) which is understood as means</note> casting lots for them <transChange type='added'>to see</transChange> who should take what.<verse eID='Mark.15.24'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.25' sID='Mark.15.25'/>Now it was the third hour when they crucified him.<verse eID='Mark.15.25'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.26' sID='Mark.15.26'/>And the inscription of the charge against him was written, “The king of the Jews.”<verse eID='Mark.15.26'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.27' sID='Mark.15.27'/>And with him they crucified two robbers, one on <transChange type='added'>his</transChange> right and one on <transChange type='added'>his</transChange> left.<note>Most later Greek manuscripts add v. <reference osisRef='Mark.15.28'>28</reference> (a quotation from <reference osisRef='Isa.53.12'>Isa 53:12</reference>) after v. <reference osisRef='Mark.15.27'>27</reference>, “And the scripture was fulfilled that says, ‘And he was counted with the lawless ones’ ”</note><verse eID='Mark.15.27'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.29' sID='Mark.15.29'/>And those who passed by reviled him, shaking their heads and saying, “Aha! The one who would destroy the temple and rebuild <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in three days,<verse eID='Mark.15.29'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.30' sID='Mark.15.30'/>save yourself <transChange type='added'>by</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>by</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“coming down”) which is understood as means</note> coming down from the cross!”<verse eID='Mark.15.30'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.31' sID='Mark.15.31'/>In the same way also the chief priests, along with the scribes, were mocking <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to one another, saying, “He saved others; he is not able to save himself!<verse eID='Mark.15.31'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.32' sID='Mark.15.32'/>Let the Christ, the king of Israel, come down now from the cross, so that we may see and believe! Even those who were crucified with him were reviling him.<verse eID='Mark.15.32'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus Dies on the Cross</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.15.33' sID='Mark.15.33'/>And <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“came”)</note> the sixth hour came, darkness came over the whole land until the ninth hour.<verse eID='Mark.15.33'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.34' sID='Mark.15.34'/>And at the ninth hour Jesus cried out with a loud voice, “<hi type='italic'>Eloi, Eloi, lema sabachthani?</hi>” (which is translated, “My God, my God, <seg type='x-idiom'>˻why˼</seg><note>Literally “for what <catchWord>reason</catchWord>”</note> have you forsaken me?”)<note>A quotation from <reference osisRef='Ps.22.1'>Ps 22:1</reference></note><verse eID='Mark.15.34'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.35' sID='Mark.15.35'/>And some of the bystanders, <transChange type='added'>when they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard <transChange type='added'>it</transChange>,<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> said, “Behold, he is summoning Elijah!”<verse eID='Mark.15.35'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.36' sID='Mark.15.36'/>And someone ran and filled a sponge with sour wine, put <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on a reed, <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the two previous participles (“ran” and “filled”) have been translated as finite verbs</note> gave <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to him to drink, saying, “Leave <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> alone! Let us see if Elijah is coming to take him down.”<verse eID='Mark.15.36'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.37' sID='Mark.15.37'/>But Jesus uttered a loud cry <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“uttered”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> expired.<verse eID='Mark.15.37'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.38' sID='Mark.15.38'/>And the curtain of the temple was torn in two from top to bottom.<verse eID='Mark.15.38'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.39' sID='Mark.15.39'/>And <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“saw”) which is understood as temporal</note> the centurion who was standing opposite him saw that he expired like this, he said, “Truly this man was God’s Son!”<verse eID='Mark.15.39'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.40' sID='Mark.15.40'/>And there were also women observing from a distance, among whom <transChange type='added'>were</transChange> Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James the younger<note>Or perhaps “the short,” referring to stature</note> and Joses,<note>This name appears in <reference osisRef='Matt.27.56'>Matt 27:56</reference> as “Joseph”</note> and Salome,<verse eID='Mark.15.40'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.41' sID='Mark.15.41'/>who used to follow<note>The imperfect tense has been translated as customary here (“used to follow”)</note> him and serve him when he was in Galilee, and many other <transChange type='added'>women</transChange> who went up with him to Jerusalem.<verse eID='Mark.15.41'/></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus Is Buried</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.15.42' sID='Mark.15.42'/>And <transChange type='added'>when it</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was”)</note> was already evening, since it was the day of preparation (that is, the day before the Sabbath),<verse eID='Mark.15.42'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.43' sID='Mark.15.43'/>Joseph of Arimathea, a prominent member of the council who was also himself looking forward to<note>Or “waiting for”</note> the kingdom of God, came acting courageously <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“came”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> went in to Pilate and asked for the body of Jesus.<verse eID='Mark.15.43'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.44' sID='Mark.15.44'/>And Pilate was surprised that he was already dead, and summoning the centurion, asked him whether he had died already.<verse eID='Mark.15.44'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.45' sID='Mark.15.45'/>And <transChange type='added'>when he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“learned of”) which is understood as temporal</note> learned of <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> from the centurion, he granted the corpse to Joseph.<verse eID='Mark.15.45'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.46' sID='Mark.15.46'/>And <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“purchasing”) which is understood as temporal</note> purchasing a linen cloth <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the participle (“taking...down”) has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> taking him down, he wrapped <transChange type='added'>him</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in the linen cloth and placed him in a tomb that had been cut from the rock. And he rolled a stone over the entrance of the tomb.<verse eID='Mark.15.46'/> <verse osisID='Mark.15.47' sID='Mark.15.47'/>Now Mary Magdalene and Mary the <transChange type='added'>mother</transChange> of Joses saw where he was placed.<verse eID='Mark.15.47'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
<chapter osisID='Mark.16'>
<div type='section'>
<title>Jesus Is Raised</title>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.16.1' sID='Mark.16.1'/>And <transChange type='added'>when</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was over”)</note> the Sabbath was over, Mary Magdalene, and Mary the <transChange type='added'>mother</transChange> of James, and Salome purchased fragrant spices so that they could go <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> anoint him.<verse eID='Mark.16.1'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.2' sID='Mark.16.2'/>And very early in the morning on the first <transChange type='added'>day</transChange> of the week they came to the tomb <transChange type='added'>after</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“had risen”)</note> the sun had risen.<verse eID='Mark.16.2'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.3' sID='Mark.16.3'/>And they were saying to one another, “Who will roll away the stone for us from the entrance of the tomb?”<verse eID='Mark.16.3'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.4' sID='Mark.16.4'/>And <transChange type='added'>when they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“looked up”) which is understood as temporal</note> looked up, they saw that the stone had been rolled away (for it was very large).<verse eID='Mark.16.4'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.5' sID='Mark.16.5'/>And <transChange type='added'>as they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“going”) which is understood as temporal</note> were going into the tomb, they saw a young man dressed in a white robe sitting on the right side, and they were alarmed.<verse eID='Mark.16.5'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.6' sID='Mark.16.6'/>But he said to them, “Do not be alarmed. You are looking for Jesus the Nazarene who was crucified. He has been raised, he is not here! See the place where they laid him!<verse eID='Mark.16.6'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.7' sID='Mark.16.7'/>But go, tell his disciples and Peter that he is going ahead of you to Galilee. You will see him there, just as he told you.”<verse eID='Mark.16.7'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.8' sID='Mark.16.8'/>And they went out <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> fled from the tomb, because trembling and amazement had seized them. And they said nothing to anyone, because they were afraid.<note>The Gospel of Mark ends at this point in some manuscripts, including two of the most important ones, while other manuscripts supply a shorter ending (sometimes included as part of v. <reference osisRef='Mark.16.8'>8</reference>), others supply the traditional longer ending (vv. <reference osisRef='Mark.16.9-Mark.16.20'>9–20</reference>), and still other manuscripts supply both the shorter ending and vv. <reference osisRef='Mark.16.9-Mark.16.20'>9–20</reference>; due to significant questions about the authenticity of these alternative endings, many scholars regard 16:8 as the last verse of the Gospel of Mark</note></p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Shorter Ending of Mark</title>
<p>〚So they promptly reported all the <transChange type='added'>things</transChange> they had been commanded to those around Peter. And after these <transChange type='added'>things</transChange>, Jesus himself also sent out through them from the east even as far as the west the holy and imperishable proclamation of eternal salvation. Amen.〛</p>
</div>
<div type='section'>
<title>The Longer Ending of Mark</title>
<p>〚<verse eID='Mark.16.8'/><verse osisID='Mark.16.9' sID='Mark.16.9'/>Now early on the first <transChange type='added'>day</transChange> of the week, <transChange type='added'>after he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“rose”) which is understood as temporal</note> rose, he appeared first to Mary Magdalene, from whom he had expelled seven demons.<verse eID='Mark.16.9'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.10' sID='Mark.16.10'/>She went out <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> announced <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to those who were with him <transChange type='added'>while they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>while</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were”) which is understood as temporal</note> were mourning and weeping.<verse eID='Mark.16.10'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.11' sID='Mark.16.11'/>And those, <transChange type='added'>when they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>when</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“heard”) which is understood as temporal</note> heard that he was alive and had been seen by her, refused to believe <transChange type='added'>it</transChange>.<note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note><verse eID='Mark.16.11'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.12' sID='Mark.16.12'/>And after these <transChange type='added'>things</transChange>, he appeared in a different form to two of them <transChange type='added'>as they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>as</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were walking”) which is understood as temporal</note> were walking, <transChange type='added'>while they</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>while</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were going out”) which is understood as temporal</note> were going out into the countryside.<verse eID='Mark.16.12'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.13' sID='Mark.16.13'/>And these went <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> reported <transChange type='added'>it</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the others, and they did not believe them.<verse eID='Mark.16.13'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.14' sID='Mark.16.14'/>And later, <transChange type='added'>while</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>while</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“were reclining at table”) which is understood as temporal</note> they were reclining at table, he appeared to the eleven. And he reprimanded their unbelief and hardness of heart, because they did not believe those who had seen him <transChange type='added'>after he</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>after</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the participle (“had been raised”) which is understood as temporal</note> had been raised.<verse eID='Mark.16.14'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.15' sID='Mark.16.15'/>And he said to them, “Go<note>As a participle of attendant circumstance this participle carries imperatival force picked up from the main verb (“preach”)</note> into all the world <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“go”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> preach the gospel to all creation.<verse eID='Mark.16.15'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.16' sID='Mark.16.16'/>The one who believes and is baptized will be saved, but the one who refuses to believe will be condemned.<verse eID='Mark.16.16'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.17' sID='Mark.16.17'/>And these signs will accompany those who believe: in my name they will expel demons, they will speak in new tongues,<verse eID='Mark.16.17'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.18' sID='Mark.16.18'/>and they will pick up snakes with their<note>Literally “the”; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands. And if they drink any deadly <transChange type='added'>poison</transChange> it will never hurt them; they will lay hands on the sick and <seg type='x-idiom'>˻they will get˼</seg><note>Literally “they will have”</note> well.”<verse eID='Mark.16.18'/></p>
<p><verse osisID='Mark.16.19' sID='Mark.16.19'/>Then the Lord Jesus, after <transChange type='added'>he</transChange> had spoken to them, was taken up into heaven and sat down at the right hand of God.<verse eID='Mark.16.19'/> <verse osisID='Mark.16.20' sID='Mark.16.20'/>And they went out <transChange type='added'>and</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>and</catchWord>” is supplied because the previous participle (“went out”) has been translated as a finite verb</note> proclaimed everywhere, <transChange type='added'>while</transChange><note>Here “<catchWord>while</catchWord>” is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle (“was working together with”)</note> the Lord was working together with <transChange type='added'>them</transChange><note>Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and confirming the message through the accompanying signs.〛<verse eID='Mark.16.20'/></p>
</div>
</chapter>
</div></osisText>
</osis>
