<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisIDWork='NSB' osisRefWork='Bible' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='NSB'>
        <title>New Simplified Bible</title>
        <contributor>xxx</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>The New Simplified Bible is not affiliated with any Bible publishing society or religious organization. It is not related to the publishing and preaching work of Jehovah's Witnesses and it is not endorsed by the Watch Tower Society.</description>
        <publisher>Jim Madsen, NSB</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>NSB</identifier>
        <source>http://www.geocities.com/simplifiedbible/index.html - the Word-Files</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>
used by Permission from Jim Madsen, NSB, 
when distribute them as long as they
are offered free of charge

New Simplified Bible
All Rights Reserved Worldwide
Copyright (c) 2003-2006

     </rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Eph'>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.1'>
        <title>(Writer: Paul) (60-61 C.E.) (Rome)</title>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.1'>Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through the will of God, to the holy ones who are at Ephesus and the faithful in Christ Jesus:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.2'>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.3'>Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ. He has blessed us with every spiritual blessing in the heavenly places through Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.4'>He chose us through him before the foundation of the world, that we should be holy and without blemish before him in love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.5'>He predetermined ordained us to adoption, as sons to himself through Jesus Christ, according to the kind intention of his will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.6'>This is to the praise of the glory of his kindness, with which he freely honored us, the loved ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.7'>In him we have our redemption through his blood, the forgiveness of our trespasses, according to the riches of his grace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.8'>He made this undeserved kindness abound toward us in all wisdom and prudence insight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.9'>He made known to us the secret of his will, according to his good pleasure and purpose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.10'>It was for an administration at the appointed time. This administration is to gather up all things in Christ, the things in heaven, and the things upon the earth. Yes in him!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.11'>We were assigned as heirs predetermined according to his purpose. He works all things according to his direction and will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.12'>We who were first to hope in Christ should serve to the praise of his glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.13'>You have heard the word of the truth in Christ. It is the good news about your salvation. You also believed and were sealed with the promised Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.14'>The Holy Spirit is a guarantee that we will receive our inheritance. This assures us that God will set us free to the praise of his glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.15'>For this cause I also, having heard of the faith in the Lord Jesus that is among you, and the love you show all the holy ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.16'>I continually give thanks for you in my prayers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.17'>May the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of glory, give you a spirit mental disposition of wisdom and revelation in the knowledge of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.18'>Have the eyes of your heart enlightened, that you may know the hope of his calling, the riches of his glorious inheritance in the holy ones,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.19'>and what the exceeding greatness of his power is toward us who believe, according to the operation of his mighty strength.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.20'>He operated in Christ, when he raised him from the dead, and made him to sit at his right hand in the heavenly places.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.21'>It is far above all governments and authority, power and dominion, and every name that is named, not only in this age but also in that which is to come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.22'>He God put all things in subjection under his feet, and made him head over all things to the congregation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.23'>which is his body, the fullness of him who fills accomplishescompletes all in all.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.2'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.1'>You were once dead because of your trespasses and sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.2'>You once walked according to the course of this world, according to the ruler of the power authority and jurisdiction of the air, the spirit that is now active in the sons of disobedience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.3'>We all once lived in the lust of our flesh, indulging the desires lusts of the flesh and of the mind. We were by nature children of anger and violent passion, like everyone else.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.4'>But God, being rich in mercy, because of his great love with which he loved us,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.5'>even when we were dead in our trespasses, made us alive together with Christ. For by grace loving-kindness you have been saved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.6'>God raised us up with him and made us to sit with him in the heavenly places, with Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.7'>So in the ages to come he, with Christ Jesus, might show the exceeding surpassingexceptional riches of his grace with kindness toward us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.8'>By grace Greek: charis, divine favor, loving-kindness you have been saved through faith. It is not from you. It is the gift from God!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.9'>It is not the result of works. So no man should boast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.10'>For we are his workmanship created with Christ Jesus for good works. God prepared these works in advance that we should walk in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.11'>Remember that you were once people of the nations in the flesh. You are called uncircumcision by that which is called circumcision, in the flesh, made by human hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.12'>You were separate from Christ at that time, alienated from the commonwealth of Israel. You were strangers from the covenants of the promise. You had no hope and were without God in the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.13'>You were once far off but now with Christ Jesus, the blood of Christ has brought you near.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.14'>For he is our peace, who made both Jews and Gentiles one, and broke down the middle barrier of partition.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.15'>Christ abolished in his flesh the enmity ill will, which the law of commandments contained in ordinances. That way he might create one new man, out of the two, with himself establishing peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.16'>So he reconciled them both in one body to God through the stake. He put to death the enmity antagonismhostility.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.17'>He came and preached peace to you who were far off, and peace to those who were near.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.18'>We both have access to the Father by one Spirit through him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.19'>So then you are no longer strangers and aliens. You are fellow citizens with the holy ones and of the household of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.20'>You are built upon the foundation of the apostles and prophets. Christ Jesus is the chief corner stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.21'>In him each building fits together and grows into a »holy Temple for Jehovah.« (Zechariah 6:12)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.22'>In Christ you are assembled together as a place for Gods Spirit to dwell.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.3'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.1'>For this cause I, Paul, am the prisoner of Christ Jesus on behalf of you people of the nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.2'>You have heard of the stewardship of Gods loving kindness that was given to me with you in view.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.3'>The secret was made known to me by revelation, just as I wrote before in few words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.4'>When you read this you can understand my insight into the secret of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.5'>It was not made known to other generations of the sons of men, as it has now been revealed to his holy apostles and prophets by the Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.6'>The Gentiles are fellow-heirs, and fellow-members of the body, and fellow-partakers of the promise in Christ Jesus through the good news.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.7'>I was made a minister, according to the gift of Gods grace that was given me according to the working of his power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.8'>To me, the very least of all the holy ones, was given grace loving divine influence to preach to the people of the nations the untraceable riches of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.9'>To make all men see what is the administration of the secret which for ages has been hidden in God who created all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.10'>It is the intent that now the manifold wisdom of God might be made known through the congregation and the rules and authorities in the heavenly places.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.11'>This is according to the eternal purpose determinationdesignarrangement that He carried out in Christ Jesus our Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.12'>We have boldness and access in confidence through our faith in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.13'>So I ask you not to lose heart at my tribulations for you, for they are your glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.14'>For this cause I bow my knees to the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.15'>Every family in heaven and on earth obtains its name from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.16'>That he would grant you, according to the riches of his glory, that you may be strengthened with power through his Spirit in the inward man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.17'>May Christ dwell in your hearts through faith to the end that you will be rooted and grounded in love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.18'>May you be able to comprehend with all the holy ones the breadth and length and height and depth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.19'>And may you know the love of Christ that surpasses knowledge. May you be filled with all the fullness of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.20'>Now to him that is able to do far more abundantly above all that we ask or think, according to the power that works in us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.21'>Glory be to him in the congregation and in Christ Jesus to all generations, forever and ever. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.4'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.1'>I therefore, the prisoner in the Lord, invite you to walk worthily of the calling with which you were called.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.2'>Walk with all lowliness and meekness, with longsuffering, putting up with one another in love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.3'>Diligently try to keep the unity oneness of the Spirit in the bond of peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.4'>There is one body, and one Spirit, even as you also were called in one hope of your calling.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.5'>There is one Lord, one faith, and one baptism.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.6'>There is one God and Father of all, who is over all, and through all, and in all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.7'>But unto each one of us grace was given according to the measure of the gift of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.8'>Therefore it says: »When he ascended on high, he led captives, and gave gifts to men anthropos: human beings.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.9'>(Now this, He ascended, what is it but that he also descended into the lower parts of the earth?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.10'>He that descended is the same also that ascended far above all the heavens, that he might fill all things.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.11'>He gave some to be apostles; and some, prophets; and some, evangelists; and some, shepherds and teachers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.12'>This is for the perfecting equippingpreparing of the holy ones, for the work of ministering, for the building up of the body of Christ:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.13'>until we all attain to the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, to a full-grown mature man, to the measure of the stature of the fullness of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.14'>We must no longer be children, tossed to and fro and carried about with every wind of doctrine, by the trickery of men, in craftiness, after the wiles of error.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.15'>By speaking the truth in love, we must grow up in all things to him. For he, Christ, is the head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.16'>The entire body is properly framed and fitted together through that which every joint supplies, according to the working in due measure of each individual part. It makes the body increase by building itself in love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.17'>This I say therefore, and testify affirm in the Lord, that you no longer walk as the nations also walk, in the vanity futilitydepravity of their mind thinking.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.18'>They are darkened blindedobscured in their understanding, alienated from the life of God, because of the ignorance that is in them, because of the hardening of their heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.19'>They are past feeling. They have given themselves over to loose conduct, to work all uncleanness with greediness a lust for more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.20'>But you did not learn Christ that way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.21'>You learned him and were taught by him just as truth is in Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.22'>You put away your former way coursebehaviorconversation of life, the old self that was corrupt with the lusts of deceit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.23'>You are renewed in the spirit vital principlesattitude of your mind understanding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.24'>Put on the new man, that in the likeness of God has been created in righteousness and holiness of the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.25'>Put away falsehood. Speak truth each one of you with his neighbor: for we are members belonging totogether with of one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.26'>Be angry and do not sin. Do not let the sun go down upon your anger rage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.27'>Do not give the devil an opportunity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.28'>He that steals must steal no more. Let him labor, working with his hands the thing that is good, that he may have something to give to someone in need.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.29'>Let no corrupt speech proceed out of your mouth. Speak what is good for understanding as the need may be, that it may give grace divine favor to those who hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.30'>Do not grieve the Holy Spirit of God, in which Greek: en hosin whichGreek: hos, he howherebywhich you were sealed to the day of release by ransom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.31'>Let all bitterness, and wrath, and anger, and screaming, and abusive speech, be put away removedexpiated from you, along with all malice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.32'>You should be kind to one another, tenderhearted, forgiving each other, even as God also forgave you through by means of Christ.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.5'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.1'>Therefore imitate God like beloved children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.2'>Walk in love, even as Christ also loved you, and gave himself up for us. He was an offering and a sacrifice to God for a sweet smelling odor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.3'>Fornication, and all uncleanness, or covetousness, must not even be mentioned among you, as is proper among holy ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.4'>Nor should there be filthiness, nor foolish talking, or jesting, which are not befitting but rather giving of thanks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.5'>For you know this with certainty, that no fornicator, no unclean person, no covetous man, who is an idolater, has any inheritance in the kingdom of Christ and of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.6'>Let no one deceive you with empty words. It is because of these things the wrath of God comes upon the sons of disobedience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.7'>Do not be partakers with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.8'>You were once darkness, but now you are light in the Lord. Walk livebe occupied as children of light</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.9'>for the fruit of the light lifespirit consists of all goodness and righteousness and truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.10'>Learn what is well pleasing to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.11'>Have no fellowship with the unfruitful works of darkness, but instead reprove exposeconvict them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.12'>For the things that are done by them in secret is a shame even to speak about.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.13'>But all things become visible when the light exposes them, for everything that becomes visible is light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.14'>For this reason it says: »Awake, sleeper, and arise from the dead, and Christ will shine on you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.15'>Be careful how you walk, not as unwise men but as wise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.16'>Make the most of your time redeem or ransom back time, because the days are evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.17'>Do not be foolish, but understand perceive what the will of Jehovah is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.18'>Do not get drunk with wine, for that is a public act of violence, but be filled with the Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.19'>Speak to one another in psalms and praise and spiritual songs, singing and making melody with your heart to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.20'>Always give thanks for all things in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ to God, even the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.21'>Be subject obedientsubordinate to one another in reverence of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.22'>Wives, be subject to your own husbands, as to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.23'>For the husband is the head of the wife, and Christ also is the head of the congregation, he being the savior of the body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.24'>The congregation is subject to Christ. Likewise let the wives also be to their husbands in everything.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.25'>Husbands love your wives, even as Christ also loved the congregation and gave himself up for it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.26'>This is so he might sanctify it, having cleansed it by the washing of water with the word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.27'>So he will be able to present the congregation to himself as a glorious congregation, not having spot or wrinkle or any such thing. It should be holy and without blemish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.28'>In this way husbands should love their wives as their own bodies. He that loves his own wife loves himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.29'>No man ever hated his own flesh; but nourishes and cherishes it, even as Christ also does the congregation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.30'>And we are members of his body!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.31'>For this reason a man will leave his father and mother, and will stick adherecleavebe joined to his wife. The two will become one flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.32'>This secret is great! I speak with regard to Christ and of the congregation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.33'>Each one of you should love his own wife even as himself. The wife should respect her husband.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.6'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.1'>Children, obey your parents in the Lord for this is right.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.2'>Honor your father and mother, which is the first commandment with promise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.3'>Then it will go well with you, and you may live long on the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.4'>Fathers, do not provoke your children to anger but nurture them in the discipline and instruction of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.5'>Servants, be obedient to those who according to the flesh are your masters, with fear and trembling, in sincerity of your heart, as to Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.6'>This should not be in the way of eye service, as men-pleasers; but as servants of Christ, doing the will of God from a complete heart;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.7'>with goodwill doing service, as to God, and not to men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.8'>You know that whatever good thing each person does, the same shall he receive again from God, whether he be slave or free.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.9'>You masters, do the same things to them. Do not threaten! You know that he who is both their Master and yours is in heaven. There is no favoritism with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.10'>Finally, be strong in the Lord, and in his mighty strength.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.11'>Put on the full armor every implement of God, that you may be able to stand against the cunning inventiveclever methods of the devil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.12'>Our struggle is not against flesh and blood, but against the rulers, against the powers, against the world forces of this darkness, against the spiritual forces of wickedness in heavenly places.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.13'>For that reason, take up the full armor of God, so that you will be able to resist in the evil day, having done everything, to stand firm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.14'>Stand firm therefore and gird your loins with truth. Put on the breastplate of righteousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.15'>Shod your feet with the preparation of the good news of peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.16'>Also take up the shield of faith, with which you will be able to quench all the fiery darts of the evil one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.17'>Take the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.18'>With prayer and supplication pray at all times in the Spirit. Watch with all perseverance and supplication for all the holy ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.19'>Pray on my behalf, that ability to speak may be given to me, to make known with boldness the secret of the good news.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.20'>I am an ambassador in chains who should speak boldly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.21'>That you also may know my affairs, how I do, Tychicus, the beloved brother and faithful minister in the Lord, will make known to you all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.22'>I have sent him to you for this very purpose, that you may know our state, and that he may comfort your hearts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.23'>Peace be to the brothers, and love with faith, from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.24'>Grace be with all who love our Lord Jesus Christ with an incorruptible sincereprincipledunending love.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>