<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisIDWork='NSB' osisRefWork='Bible' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='NSB'>
        <title>New Simplified Bible</title>
        <contributor>xxx</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>The New Simplified Bible is not affiliated with any Bible publishing society or religious organization. It is not related to the publishing and preaching work of Jehovah's Witnesses and it is not endorsed by the Watch Tower Society.</description>
        <publisher>Jim Madsen, NSB</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>NSB</identifier>
        <source>http://www.geocities.com/simplifiedbible/index.html - the Word-Files</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>
used by Permission from Jim Madsen, NSB, 
when distribute them as long as they
are offered free of charge

New Simplified Bible
All Rights Reserved Worldwide
Copyright (c) 2003-2006

     </rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Exod'>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.1'>
        <title>(Writer: Moses) (1512 B.C.E.)</title>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.1'>These are the names of the sons of Israel who came with their families and with Jacob to Egypt:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.2'>Reuben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.3'>Issachar, Zebulun, and Benjamin;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.4'>Dan and Naphtali and Gad and Asher.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.5'>Joseph was already in Egypt. The total number of Jacobs descendants was seventy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.6'>Joseph, all his brothers, and that entire generation died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.7'>The children of Israel had many children. They became so numerous and strong that the land was filled with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.8'>A new king, who knew nothing about Joseph, began to rule in Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.9'>He said to his people: »There are too many Israelites! They are stronger than we are.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.10'>»We must outsmart them or they will increase in number. If war breaks out they will leave the country and join our enemies to fight against us.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.11'>So the Egyptians put slave masters over them in order to oppress them through forced labor. They built Pithom and Rameses as supply storage cities for Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.12'>However the more the Israelites were oppressed, the more they increased in number and spread out. The Egyptians could not stand them any longer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.13'>They forced the Israelites to work hard as slaves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.14'>They made their lives bitter with backbreaking work in mortar and bricks and every kind of work in the fields. All the jobs the Egyptians gave them were brutally hard work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.15'>The king of Egypt spoke to the Hebrew midwives. Shiphrah and Puah were among them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.16'>He said: »When you help the Hebrew women give birth on the birth stool, if it is a son you shall put him to death. If it is a daughter, then she shall live.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.17'>The midwives respected God and did not do as the king of Egypt commanded them. They let the boys live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.18'>So the king of Egypt called for the midwives and said: »Why have you let the boys live?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.19'>The midwives replied to Pharaoh: »Because the Hebrew women are not as the Egyptian women. They are vigorous and give birth before the midwife can get to them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.20'>God was good to the midwives, and the people multiplied, and became very mighty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.21'>Because the midwives respected God, He established households for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.22'>Then Pharaoh commanded all his people: Every son who is born must be thrown into the Nile River. However, keep every daughter alive.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.2'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.1'>A man from Levis family married a Levite woman.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.2'>The woman became pregnant and bore a son. She saw how beautiful he was and hid him for three months.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.3'>When she could not hide him any longer, she took a basket made of papyrus reeds and coated it with tar and pitch. She put the baby in it and set it among the papyrus reeds near the bank of the Nile River.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.4'>The babys sister stood at a distance to see what would happen to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.5'>The kings daughter came to the river to bathe. Her servants walked along the bank. Suddenly she noticed the basket in the papyrus reeds and sent a slave woman to get it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.6'>She opened it and saw a baby boy. He was crying, and she felt sorry for him. »This is one of the Hebrew babies,« she said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.7'>His sister asked her: »Shall I go and call a Hebrew woman to nurse the baby for you?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.8'>»Please do,« she answered. So the girl went and brought the babys own mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.9'>Pharaohs daughter told her: »Take care of this child, and I will pay you. The babys mother carried him home and took care of him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.10'>When he was old enough, she took him to the kings daughter, who adopted him. She named him Moses because she said: »I pulled him out of the water.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.11'>After Moses had grown up, he went out to where his own people his brothers were hard at work. He saw an Egyptian beating one of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.12'>Moses looked around to see if anyone was watching. Then he killed the Egyptian and hid his body in the sand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.13'>The next day when Moses went out, he saw two Hebrews fighting. So he went to the man who started the fight and asked: »Why are you beating up one of your own people?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.14'>The man replied: »Who made you a prince or a judge over us? Are you intending to kill me as you killed the Egyptian?« Moses was afraid and said: »Surely the matter has become known.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.15'>When Pharaoh heard of this matter, he tried to kill Moses. But Moses fled from the presence of Pharaoh and settled in the land of Midian by a well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.16'>The priest of Midian had seven daughters. They came to draw water and filled the troughs to water their fathers flock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.17'>Then the shepherds came and drove them away. Moses stood up and helped them water their flock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.18'>When they returned to Reuel their father, he said, »Why have you come back so soon today?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.19'>They said: »An Egyptian delivered us out of the hand of the shepherds. He drew water for us and watered the flock.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.20'>He asked his daughters: »Where is he? Why have you left the man? Call him, that he may eat bread.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.21'>Moses was content to live with the man. He gave Moses his daughter Zipporah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.22'>She bore a son, and he called his name Gershom. For he said: »I have been a stranger in a strange land.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.23'>Time went by and the king of Egypt died. The Israelites still groaned because they were slaves. So they cried out, and their cries for help went up to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.24'>God heard their groaning. He remembered his promise to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.25'>God saw the Israelites being oppressed and was concerned about them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.3'>
        <title>MOSES CALLED</title>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.1'>One day Moses was taking care of the flock of his father-in-law Jethro, the priest of Midian. He led the flock across the desert to Sinai, the holy mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.2'>There the angel of Jehovah appeared to him in a flame of fire coming from the middle of a bush. Moses saw that the bush was on fire but that it was not burning up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.3'>»This is strange,« he thought. »Why is the bush not burning up? I will go closer and see.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.4'>Jehovah saw that Moses came closer. He called to him from the middle of the bush: »Moses! Moses!« Moses answered: »Yes, here I am.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.5'>God said: »Do not come any closer. Take off your sandals, because you are standing on holy ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.6'>»I am the God of your ancestors, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob.« Moses covered his face, because he was afraid to look at God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.7'>Jehovah said: »I have seen how my people are suffering as slaves in Egypt. I have heard them beg for my help because of the way they are being mistreated. I feel sorry for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.8'>»I have come down to rescue them from the Egyptians. I will bring my people out of Egypt into a country where there is good land, rich with milk and honey. I will give them the land where the Canaanites, Hittites, Amorites, Perizzites, Hivites, and Jebusites now live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.9'>»My people have begged for my help. I have seen how cruel the Egyptians are to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.10'>»Now go to Pharaoh! I am sending you to lead my people out of his country.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.11'>But Moses said: »Who am I to go to Pharaoh and lead your people out of Egypt?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.12'>God said: »I will be with you! This shall be the sign to you that it is I who have sent you: when you have brought the people out of Egypt, you shall worship God at this mountain.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.13'>Then Moses said to God: »Behold, I am going to the sons of Israel. I will say to them: The God of your fathers has sent me to you. Now they may ask me: What is His name? What shall I say to them?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.14'>God then said to Moses: »I exist and I WILL BE WHO I WILL BE.« You shall say to the sons of Israel: »I WILL BE, has sent me to you.« Hebrew: hayah, »I was, I am, I will be« gives evidence of Gods eternal existence</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.15'>God, further said to Moses: »You shall say to the sons of Israel: JEHOVAH, the God of your fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has sent me to you. JEHOVAH THIS IS MY NAME FOREVER! This is my memorial-name to all generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.16'>Go and gather the elders of Israel together and say to them: JEHOVAH, the God of your fathers, the God of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, has appeared to me. He said: »I am indeed concerned about you and what has been done to you in Egypt.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.17'>»So I said: I will bring you up out of the affliction of Egypt to the land of the Canaanite and the Hittite and the Amorite and the Perizzite and the Hivite and the Jebusite, to a land flowing with milk and honey.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.18'>»They will listen to what you say. You with the elders of Israel will approach the king of Egypt. You will say to him: Jehovah the God of the Hebrews, has met with us. So now, please, let us go a three days journey into the wilderness, that we may sacrifice to Jehovah our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.19'>»I know that the king of Egypt will not permit you to go, except under compulsion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.20'>»So I will stretch out my hand and strike Egypt with all my wonders that I will do in its midst. After that he will let you go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.21'>»I will grant this people favor in the sight of the Egyptians. When you go you will not go empty handed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.22'>»But every woman shall ask of her neighbor and the woman who lives in her house, articles of silver and articles of gold, and clothing. You will put them on your sons and daughters. Thus you will plunder the Egyptians.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.4'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.1'>Moses responded: »What if they will not believe me or listen to what I say? For they may say: Jehovah has not appeared to you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.2'>Jehovah asked him: »What is that in your hand?« He answered: »A shepherds staff.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.3'>Jehovah said: »Throw it on the ground.« When Moses threw it on the ground, it became a snake, and he ran away from it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.4'>Jehovah said to Moses: »Reach down and pick it up by the tail.« So Moses reached down and caught it. Suddenly it became a walking stick again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.5'>Jehovah said: »Do this to prove to the Israelites that Jehovah, the God of their ancestors, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, has appeared to you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.6'>Jehovah spoke to Moses again: »Put your hand inside your robe.« Moses obeyed. When he took his hand out, it was diseased, covered with white spots, like snow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.7'>Jehovah said: »Put your hand inside your robe again.« He did so, and when he took it out this time, it was healthy, just like the rest of his body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.8'>Jehovah said: »If they will not believe you or be convinced by the first sign, then this one will convince them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.9'>»If in spite of these two signs they still will not believe you, and if they refuse to listen to what you say, take some water from the Nile and pour it on the ground. The water will turn into blood.«</verse>
        <title>GOD TO TEACH MOSES WHAT TO SAY</title>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.10'>Moses said: »O Jehovah I am not a man of words. I have never been so, and am not now, even after what you have said to your servant. Talking is hard for me, and I am slow of tongue.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.11'>Jehovah said to him: »Who has made mans mouth? Or who makes him mute or deaf, or seeing or blind? Is it not I, Jehovah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.12'>»Now then go, and I, even I, will be with your mouth. I will teach you what you are to say.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.13'>But Moses said: »Please, Jehovah, send the message by whomever you will.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.14'>Then the anger of Jehovah burned against Moses, and He said: »Is there not your brother Aaron the Levite? I know that he speaks fluently. He is coming out to meet you. When he sees you, he will be glad in his heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.15'>»You are to speak to him and put the words in his mouth. I will be with your mouth and his mouth. I will teach you what you are to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.16'>Moreover, he shall speak for you to the people. He will be as a mouth for you and you will be as God to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.17'>»Take your staff in your hand with which you shall perform the signs.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.18'>Moses departed and returned to Jethro his father-in-law and said to him: »Please, let me go, that I may return to my brothers who are in Egypt, and see if they are still alive.« Jethro said to Moses: »Go in peace.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.19'>Jehovah said to Moses in Midian: »Go back to Egypt, for all the men who were seeking your life are dead.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.20'>So Moses took his wife and his sons and mounted them on a donkey and returned to the land of Egypt. Moses also took the staff of God in his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.21'>Jehovah said to Moses: »When you go back to Egypt see that you perform before Pharaoh all the wonders that I have put in your power. I will harden his heart so that he will not let the people go.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.22'>»Say to Pharaoh: Thus says Jehovah, Israel is my son, my firstborn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.23'>»So I said to you: Let My son go that he may serve me. But you have refused to let him go. Behold, I will kill your son, your firstborn.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.24'>Now it came about at the lodging place on the way that Jehovah met him and sought to put him to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.25'>Zipporah took a flint and cut off her sons foreskin and threw it at Moses feet. She said: »You are indeed a bridegroom of blood to me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.26'>So He let him alone. At that time she said: »You are a bridegroom of blood, because of the circumcision.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.27'>Jehovah said to Aaron: »Go to meet Moses in the wilderness.« So he went and met him at the mountain of God and kissed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.28'>Moses told Aaron all the words Jehovah sent him to tell Moses, and all the signs that he had commanded him to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.29'>Then Moses and Aaron went to Egypt and assembled all the elders of the people of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.30'>Aaron told them everything Jehovah had said to Moses. He also did the miraculous signs for the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.31'>The people believed them. When they heard that Jehovah was concerned about the people of Israel and that he had seen their misery, they knelt, bowed low and worshiped.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.5'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.1'>Moses and Aaron went to Pharaoh. They said: »Jehovah, the God of Israel, says: Let My people go that they may celebrate a feast to me in the wilderness.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.2'>But Pharaoh responded: »Who is Jehovah, that I should obey his voice to let Israel go? I do not know Jehovah, and besides, I will not let Israel go.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.3'>Then they said: »The God of the Hebrews met with us. Please, let us go on a three-day journey into the wilderness. Then we may sacrifice to Jehovah our God. Otherwise he will fall upon us with pestilence or with the sword.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.4'>The king of Egypt replied: »Moses and Aaron, why do you distract the people from their work? Get back to work!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.5'>Pharaoh added: »Look how many people there are in the land! Do you want them to quit working?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.6'>Pharaoh gave these orders to the slave drivers and foremen:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.7'>»Do not give the people any more straw to make bricks as you have been doing. Let them gather their own straw.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.8'>»Insist that they make the same number of bricks they were making before. Making fewer bricks will not be acceptable. They are lazy! That is why they are crying: Let us go offer sacrifices to our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.9'>»Make the work harder for these people so that they will be too busy to listen to lies.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.10'>The slave drivers and the Israelite foremen went out and said to the Israelites: »The king has said that he will not supply you with any more straw.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.11'>»He says that you must go and get it for yourselves wherever you can find it. You must still make the same number of bricks.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.12'>So the people went all over Egypt looking for straw.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.13'>The slave bosses were hard on them. They kept saying: »Each day you have to make as many bricks as you did when you were given straw.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.14'>The bosses beat the men in charge of the slaves and said: »Why did you not force the slaves to make as many bricks yesterday and today as they did before?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.15'>Finally, the men in charge of the slaves went to the king and asked: »Why are you treating us like this?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.16'>»No one brings us any straw. Yet we are still ordered to make the same number of bricks. We are beaten with whips, and your own people are to blame.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.17'>The king replied: »You are lazy. You are just lazy! That is why you keep asking me to let you go and sacrifice to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.18'>»Get back to work! You will not be given straw, but you must still make the same number of bricks.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.19'>The Israelite foremen realized they were in trouble when they were told: »Do not make fewer bricks each day than you are supposed to.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.20'>Leaving the Pharaoh, they found Moses and Aaron waiting for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.21'>They said: »May Jehovah see what you have done and judge you! You have made Pharaoh and his officials hate us. You have given them an excuse to kill us.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.22'>Moses went back to Jehovah and asked: »Why have you brought this trouble on your people? Why did you send me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.23'>»Ever since I went to Pharaoh to speak for you, he has treated your people cruelly, and you have done nothing at all to rescue your people.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.6'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.1'>Jehovah said to Moses: »Now you will see what I will do to Pharaoh. I will show him my power. He will let my people go! I will show him my power, and he will throw them out of his country.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.2'>God spoke further to Moses and said to him: »I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.3'>»I appeared to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, as God Almighty, but by my name, Jehovah, I did not make myself known to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.4'>»I also established my covenant with them, to give them the land of Canaan, the land in which they lived as foreigners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.5'>»Furthermore I have heard the groaning of the sons of Israel. This is because the Egyptians are holding them in bondage. I have remembered my covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.6'>»Tell the sons of Israel: I am Jehovah. I will bring you out from under the oppression of the Egyptians. I will free you from slavery! I will rescue you with my powerful arm and with mighty acts of judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.7'>»I will make you my people, and I will be your God. You will know that I am Jehovah your God. I brought you out from under the forced labor of the Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.8'>»I will bring you to the land I solemnly swore to give to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. I will give it to you as your own possession. I am Jehovah!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.9'>Moses reported this to the Israelites. But they would not listen to him. For they were so discouraged by their backbreaking work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.10'>Then Jehovah told Moses:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.11'>»Demand that Pharaoh king of Egypt let the sons of Israel go.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.12'>But Moses replied: »I am not a powerful speaker. If the sons of Israel will not listen to me, why should the king of Egypt?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.13'>Jehovah sent Aaron and Moses with a message for the sons of Israel and for the king. He also ordered Aaron and Moses to free the people from Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.14'>The following men were the heads of their fathers households: The sons of Reuben, Jacobs oldest son, were Hanoch, Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.15'>The sons of Simeon: Jemuel and Jamin and Ohad and Jachin and Zohar and Shaul the son of a Canaanite woman; these are the families of Simeon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.16'>These are the names of the sons of Levi according to their generations: Gershon and Kohath and Merari. Levi lived one hundred and thirty-seven years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.17'>The sons of Gershon: Libni and Shimei, according to their families.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.18'>The sons of Kohath: Amram and Izhar and Hebron and Uzziel. Kohath lived one hundred and thirty-three years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.19'>The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. These are the families of the Levites according to their generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.20'>Amram married his fathers sister Jochebed, and she bore him Aaron and Moses. Amram lived one hundred and thirty-seven years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.21'>The sons of Izhar: Korah and Nepheg and Zichri.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.22'>The sons of Uzziel: Mishael and Elzaphan and Sithri.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.23'>Aaron married Elisheba, the daughter of Amminadab, the sister of Nahshon, and she bore him Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.24'>The sons of Korah: Assir and Elkanah and Abiasaph; these are the families of the Korahites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.25'>Aarons son Eleazar married one of the daughters of Putiel, and she bore him Phinehas. These are the heads of the fathers households of the Levites according to their families.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.26'>It was the same Aaron and Moses to whom Jehovah said: »Bring out the sons of Israel from the land of Egypt according to their hosts.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.27'>They were the ones who spoke to Pharaoh king of Egypt about bringing out the sons of Israel from Egypt. It was the same Moses and Aaron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.28'>On the day when Jehovah spoke to Moses in the land of Egypt,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.29'>Jehovah said to Moses: »I am Jehovah! Speak to Pharaoh king of Egypt all that I speak to you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.30'>But Moses protested to Jehovah: »I am unskilled in speech. How then will Pharaoh listen to me?«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.7'>
        <title>TEN PLAGUES ON EGYPT</title>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.1'>Jehovah said to Moses: »See, I make you as God to Pharaoh, and your brother Aaron shall be your prophet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.2'>»You shall speak all that I command you. Your brother Aaron shall speak to Pharaoh that he let the sons of Israel go out of his land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.3'>»I will harden Pharaohs heart that I may multiply my signs and wonders in the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.4'>»Pharaoh will not listen to you. Then I will use my power to punish lay my hand upon Egypt severely. I will bring my people, the sons of Israel, out of Egypt in organized family groups.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.5'>»The Egyptians will know that I am Jehovah when I use my power against Egypt and bring the sons of Israel out of there.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.6'>Moses and Aaron did as Jehovah commanded them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.7'>Moses was eighty years old and Aaron was eighty-three when they talked to Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.8'>Jehovah said to Moses and Aaron:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.9'>»Pharaoh will say: Give me a sign to prove that God has sent you. Tell Aaron: Take your shepherds staff and throw it down in front of Pharaoh. It will become a large snake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.10'>Moses and Aaron went to Pharaoh. They did as Jehovah commanded. Aaron threw his staff down in front of Pharaoh and his officials. It became a large snake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.11'>Then Pharaoh sent for his wise men and sorcerers. These Egyptian magicians did the same thing using their magic spells.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.12'>Each of them threw his staff down. They all became large snakes. But Aarons staff swallowed theirs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.13'>Pharaoh continued to be stubborn. Just as Jehovah had predicted, he would not listen to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.14'>Jehovah said to Moses: »Pharaoh is being stubborn. He will not let my people go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.15'>»In the morning meet Pharaoh when he is on his way to the Nile. Wait for him on the bank of the river. Take the staff that turned into a snake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.16'>»Say to Pharaoh: Jehovah the God of the Hebrews sent me to tell you, Let my people go to worship me in the wilderness. So far you have not listened.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.17'>»Jehovah says: This is the way you will recognize that I am Jehovah: I will strike the Nile with this staff in my hand. The water will turn into blood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.18'>The fish in the Nile will die. The river will stink. The Egyptians will not be able to drink any water from the Nile.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.19'>Jehovah then spoke to Moses: »Tell Aaron, Take your staff and stretch out your hand over the waters of Egypt; its rivers, canals, ponds, and all its reservoirs. They will turn into blood. There will be blood everywhere in Egypt, even in the buckets of wood and stone pitchers.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.20'>Moses and Aaron did as Jehovah commanded. Aaron raised his staff and struck the Nile in front of Pharaoh and his officials. All the water in the river turned into blood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.21'>The fish in the Nile died. The river smelled bad. The Egyptians could not drink any water from the river. There was blood everywhere in Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.22'>But the Egyptian magicians did the same thing using their magic spells. So Pharaoh continued to be stubborn. He would not listen to Moses and Aaron, just as Jehovah predicted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.23'>Pharaoh turned and went back to his palace. This did not change his mind and heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.24'>All the Egyptians dug along the Nile for water to drink because they could not drink any of the water from the river.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.25'>Seven days passed after Jehovah struck the Nile.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.8'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.1'>Then Jehovah said to Moses: »Approach Pharaoh and say to him, Jehovah says: »Let My people go, that they may serve me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.2'>»»But if you refuse to let them go, behold, I will afflict your whole territory with frogs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.3'>»»The Nile will swarm with frogs. They will come up and go into your house and into your bedroom and on your bed. They will go into the houses of your servants and on your people, and into your ovens and into your kneading bowls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.4'>»»The frogs will come up on you and your people and all your servants.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.5'>Jehovah also said to Moses: »Say to Aaron, Stretch out your hand with your staff over the rivers, over the streams and over the pools. Make frogs come up on the land of Egypt.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.6'>»So Aaron stretched out his hand over the waters of Egypt. The frogs came up and covered the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.7'>»But the magicians used their secret powers to do the same thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.8'>»The king sent for Moses and Aaron and told them: If you ask Jehovah to take these frogs away from me and my people, I will let your people go and offer sacrifices to him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.9'>Moses answered: »You choose the time when I am to pray for the frogs to stop bothering you, your officials, and your people, and for them to leave your houses and be found only in the river.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.10'>The king replied: »Do it tomorrow!« »As you wish:« Moses agreed. »Then everyone will discover that there is no god like Jehovah!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.11'>»The frogs will no longer be found anywhere, except in the Nile.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.12'>Moses and Aaron left the palace. Moses begged Jehovah to do something about the frogs he had sent as punishment for the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.13'>Jehovah did as Moses asked. The frogs in the houses, the courtyards, and the fields died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.14'>The Egyptians piled them up in large mounds, until the land began to stink with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.15'>The king saw that the frogs were dead. He became stubborn again and, just as Jehovah had said, the king would not listen to Moses and Aaron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.16'>Jehovah said to Moses: »Tell Aaron, »Strike the ground with your stick. The dust will change into gnats in all of Egypt.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.17'>So Aaron struck the ground with his stick. The dust in Egypt was turned into gnats. They swarmed over the people and the animals.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.18'>The magicians tried to use their magic to make gnats appear, but they failed. There were gnats everywhere!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.19'>The magicians said to the king: »It is the finger of God!« God has done this! But the king was stubborn. Just as Jehovah predicted, the king would not listen to Moses and Aaron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.20'>Jehovah said to Moses: »Early tomorrow morning, go and meet the king as he goes to the river. Tell him that Jehovah says: Let my people go, so that they can serve me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.21'>»»I warn you that if you refuse, I will punish you by sending flies on you, your officials, and your people. The houses of the Egyptians will be full of flies. The ground will be covered with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.22'>»»At that same time I will cut off the land of Goshen where my people live. No swarms of flies shall be there. / Then you will know that I am Jehovah in the midst of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.23'>»»I will put a dividing line between my people and your people. This sign will happen tomorrow.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.24'>Jehovah did what he said. Dense swarms of flies came into Pharaohs palace and into the houses of his officials. All over Egypt the flies ruined everything.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.25'>Pharaoh called for Moses and Aaron. He said: »Go, sacrifice to your God here in this country.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.26'>Moses replied: »It is not right to do that. The sacrifices we offer to Jehovah our God are disgusting to Egyptians. If they see us offer sacrifices that they consider disgusting, will they not stone us to death?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.27'>»We need to travel three days into the desert to offer sacrifices to Jehovah our God, as he told us to do.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.28'>Pharaoh said: »I will let you go, but do not go far. You may offer sacrifices to Jehovah your God in the desert and pray for me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.29'>Moses answered: »As soon as I leave you, I will pray to Jehovah. Tomorrow the swarms of flies will go away from you, your officials, and your people. But you must stop tricking us by not letting the people go to offer sacrifices to Jehovah.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.30'>Moses left Pharaoh and prayed to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.31'>Jehovah did what Moses asked. The swarms of flies left Pharaoh, his officials, and his people. Not a single fly was left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.32'>Again Pharaoh was stubborn and did not let the people go.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.9'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.1'>Then Jehovah said to Moses: »Go to Pharaoh, and tell him, this is what Jehovah the God of the Hebrews says: Let my people go to serve me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.2'>»If you refuse to let them go and continue to hold them in slavery,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.3'>Jehovah will bring a terrible plague on your livestock, including your horses, donkeys, camels, cattle, sheep, and goats.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.4'>»»Jehovah will distinguish between Israels livestock and the livestock of the Egyptians. The animals belonging to the Israelites will not die.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.5'>Jehovah set a definite time: »I, Jehovah, choose tomorrow as the time when I will do this.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.6'>The next day Jehovah did as he had said. The Egyptians animals all died. Not one of the animals of the Israelites died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.7'>The king asked what had happened. He was told that none of the animals of the Israelites had died. He was stubborn and would not let the people go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.8'>Then Jehovah said to Moses and Aaron: »Take a few handfuls of ashes from a furnace. Moses is to throw them into the air in front of the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.9'>»They will spread out like fine dust over all the land of Egypt. They will produce boils that become open sores on the people and the animals.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.10'>They got some ashes and stood before the king. Moses threw them into the air. They produced boils that became open sores on the people and the animals.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.11'>The magicians were not able to appear before Moses, because they were covered with boils, like all the other Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.12'>Jehovah hardened the heart of Pharaoh and he did not listen to Moses and Aaron. Everything happened just as Jehovah had told Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.13'>Jehovah told Moses to get up early the next morning and say to the king: »God of the Hebrews commands you to let his people go, so they can serve him!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.14'>»If you do not, he will send his worst plagues to strike you, your officials, and everyone else in your country. Then you will find out that no one can oppose Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.15'>»He could already have sent a terrible disease and wiped you from the face of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.16'>»I have allowed you to remain, in order to show you my power and in order to proclaim my name through all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.17'>»Still you exalt yourself against my people by not letting them go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.18'>»At this time tomorrow, I will send a very heavy hail, such as has not been seen in Egypt from the day it was founded until now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.19'>»Bring your livestock and whatever you have in the field to safety. Every man and beast that is found in the field and is not brought home will die from the hail.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.20'>The ones among the servants of Pharaoh who respected the word of Jehovah made his servants and his livestock flee into the houses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.21'>He who paid no regard to the word of Jehovah left his servants and his livestock in the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.22'>Jehovah said to Moses: »Stretch out your hand toward the sky. Hail will fall on all the land of Egypt, on man and on beast and on every plant of the field, throughout the land of Egypt.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.23'>Moses stretched out his staff toward the sky. Then Jehovah sent thunder and hail, and fire ran down to the earth. Jehovah rained hail on the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.24'>It hailed, and lightning flashed while it hailed. This was the worst storm in all the land of Egypt since it had become a nation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.25'>All over Egypt the hail knocked down everything that was out in the open. It struck down people, animals, and every plant in the fields and destroyed every tree in the fields.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.26'>The region of Goshen, where the Israelites lived, was the only place where there was no hail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.27'>The king sent for Moses and Aaron and said: »This time I have sinned. Jehovah is in the right. My people and I are in the wrong.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.28'>»Pray to Jehovah! We have had enough of this thunder and hail! I promise to let you go. You do not have to stay here any longer.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.29'>Moses said to him: »As soon as I go out of the city, I will lift up my hands in prayer to Jehovah. The thunder will stop. There will be no more hail. Thus you may know that the earth belongs to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.30'>»But I know that you and your servants do not yet respect Jehovah God.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.31'>The flax and the barley were ruined, because the barley was ripe, and the flax was budding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.32'>But the wheat crops ripen later, and they were not damaged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.33'>Moses left the royal palace and the city. He lifted his arms in prayer to Jehovah. The thunder, hail, and drenching rain stopped.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.34'>The king realized that the storm was over. He disobeyed once more. He and his officials were so stubborn</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.35'>that he refused to let the Israelites go. This was exactly what Jehovah said would happen.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.10'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.1'>Jehovah told Moses: »Go back to the king. I have made him and his officials stubborn, so that I could work these signs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.2'>»I did this because I want you to tell your children and your grandchildren about the mighty things and the signs I have done in Egypt. Then all of you will know that I am Jehovah.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.3'>Moses and Aaron went to Pharaoh and said to him: »Thus says Jehovah, the God of the Hebrews, How long will you refuse to humble yourself before me? Let my people go, that they may serve me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.4'>»If you refuse to let my people go, behold, tomorrow I will bring locusts into your territory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.5'>»They shall cover the surface of the land. No one will be able to see the land. They will also eat the rest of what has escaped and is left to you from the hail. They will eat every tree that sprouts for you out of the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.6'>»Your houses shall be filled and the houses of all your servants and the houses of all the Egyptians. This is something neither your fathers nor your grandfathers have seen, from the day that they came upon the earth until this day. He turned and went out from Pharaoh.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.7'>Pharaohs servants said to him: »How long shall this man be a snare to us? Let the men go so that they may serve Jehovah their God. Do you not yet know that Egypt is destroyed?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.8'>Moses and Aaron were brought again to Pharaoh. He said to them: »Go! Serve Jehovah your God. Who are the ones that shall go?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.9'>Moses said: »We will go with our young and with our old, with our sons and with our daughters. We will go with our flocks and with our herds. We must hold a feast to Jehovah.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.10'>He said to them: »May Jehovah be with you, as I send you and your little ones away. Watch out for evil is before you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.11'>»Not so! You men go now and serve Jehovah. It is you who desired it.« So they were driven out from Pharaohs presence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.12'>Jehovah said to Moses: »Stretch out your hand over the land of Egypt for the locusts. Let them come up upon the land of Egypt and eat every herb of the land, all that the hail has left.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.13'>Moses held his staff over the land of Egypt. Jehovah made a wind from the east blow over the land all that day and all that night. By morning the east wind had brought the locusts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.14'>They invaded all of Egypt and landed all over the country in great swarms. Never before had there been so many locusts, nor would there ever be that many again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.15'>They covered all the ground until it was black with them. They ate all the plants and all the fruit on the trees that the hail had left. Nothing green was left on any tree or plant anywhere in Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.16'>Pharaoh quickly called for Moses and Aaron and said: »I have sinned against Jehovah your God and against you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.17'>»Please forgive my sin one more time. Pray to Jehovah your God to take this deadly plague away from me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.18'>Moses left Pharaoh and prayed to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.19'>Jehovah changed the wind to a very strong west wind. It picked up the locusts and blew them into the Red Sea. Not one locust was left anywhere in Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.20'>But Jehovah made the king stubborn. He did not let the Israelites go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.21'>Jehovah then said to Moses: »Raise your hand toward the sky. Darkness thick enough to be felt will cover the land of Egypt.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.22'>Moses raised his hand toward the sky. Total darkness fell throughout Egypt for three days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.23'>The Egyptians could not see each other. No one left his house during that time. The Israelites, however, had light where they were living.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.24'>The king called Moses. He said: »You may go and worship Jehovah. Even your women and children may go with you. But your sheep, goats, and cattle must stay here.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.25'>Moses answered: »Then you would have to provide us with animals for sacrifices and burnt offerings to offer to Jehovah our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.26'>»No, we will take our animals with us! Not one will be left behind. We must select the animals with which to worship Jehovah our God. We will not know what animals to sacrifice to him until we get there.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.27'>Jehovah made the king stubborn. He would not let them go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.28'>He said to Moses: »Get out of my sight! Do not let me ever see you again! On the day I do, you will die!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.29'>»You have spoken it!« Moses answered. »You will never see me again.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.11'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.1'>Jehovah said to Moses: »I will send only one more punishment plague on the king of Egypt and his people. After that he will let you leave. In fact, he will drive all of you out of here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.2'>»Speak to the people of Israel and tell all of them to ask their neighbors for gold and silver jewelry.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.3'>Jehovah made the Egyptians respect the Israelites. Indeed, the officials and all the people considered Moses to be a very great man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.4'>Moses approached the king. He said: »I have come to let you know what Jehovah is going to do. About midnight he will go through the land of Egypt,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.5'>and wherever he goes, the first-born son in every family will die. Your own son will die. So will the son of the lowest slave woman. Even the first-born males of cattle will die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.6'>»Everywhere in Egypt there will be loud crying. Nothing like this has ever happened before or will ever happen again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.7'>»But against any of the sons of Israel a dog will not even bark, whether against man or beast. This is so you may understand how Jehovah makes a distinction between Egypt and Israel.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.8'>All these your servants will come down to me and bow themselves before me. They will say: »Go out, you and all the people who follow you. Then I will go out.« He went out from Pharaoh in hot anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.9'>Then Jehovah said to Moses: »Pharaoh will not listen to you, so that my signs will be multiplied in the land of Egypt.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.10'>Moses and Aaron performed all these wonders before Pharaoh. Yet Jehovah hardened Pharaohs heart. He did not let the sons of Israel go out of his land.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.12'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.1'>Jehovah said to Moses and Aaron in the land of Egypt:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.2'>»This month shall be the beginning of months for you. It is to be the first month of the year to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.3'>»Tell the whole community of Israel: On the tenth day of this month each man must take a sheep for his family, one animal per household.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.4'>»A household may be too small to eat a whole animal. That household and the one next-door can share one animal. Choose your animal based on the number of people and what each person can eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.5'>»Your animal must be a one-year-old male that has no defects. You may choose a lamb or a young goat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.6'>»Take care of it until the fourteenth day of this month. Then at dusk, all the assembled people from the community of Israel must slaughter their animals.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.7'>»Some of the blood must be put on the two doorposts and above the door of each house where the animals are to be eaten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.8'>»That night the animals are to be roasted and eaten, together with bitter herbs greens and unleavened bread made without yeast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.9'>»Do not eat the meat raw or boiled. The entire animal, including its head, legs, and insides, must be roasted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.10'>»Eat what you want that night, and the next morning burn whatever is left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.11'>»Eat it in this manner: with your loins girded, your sandals on your feet, and your staff in your hand. Eat it in haste. It is Jehovahs Passover.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.12'>Jehovah said: »That night I will go through the land of Egypt. I will strike down all the firstborn in the land of Egypt, both man and beast. I will execute judgments against all the gods of Egypt! I am Jehovah!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.13'>»The blood will be a sign for you on the houses where you live. When I see the blood I will pass over you. No plague will befall you to destroy you when I strike the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.14'>»This day will be a memorial to you. You shall celebrate it as a feast to Jehovah. You are to celebrate it as a permanent ordinance throughout your generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.15'>»You will eat unleavened bread for seven days. The first day you shall remove leaven from your houses. Whoever eats anything leavened from the first day until the seventh day will be cut off from Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.16'>»You shall have a holy assembly on the first day. There should be another holy assembly on the seventh day. No work at all will be done on them, except what must be eaten by every person that alone may be prepared by you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.17'>»You shall also observe the Feast of Unleavened Bread. That was the day I brought your hosts out of the land of Egypt. Observe this day throughout your generations as a long lasting ordinance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.18'>»In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month at evening, you shall eat unleavened bread, until the twenty-first day of the month at evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.19'>»There shall be no leaven found in your houses for seven days. Whoever eats what is leavened shall be cut off from the congregation of Israel, whether he is an alien or a native of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.20'>»You shall not eat anything leavened. Eat unleavened bread in all your dwellings.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.21'>Moses called all the elders of Israel and said: »Take lambs according to your families and slay the Passover lamb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.22'>»Take a bunch of hyssop and dip it in the blood that is in the basin. Apply some of the blood that is in the basin to the lintel and the two doorposts. No one shall go outside the door of his house until morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.23'>»Jehovah will pass through to strike the Egyptians. When he sees the blood on the top and sides of the doorframe, Jehovah will pass over the door and will not allow the destroyer to come in to your houses to kill you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.24'>»You shall observe this event as an ordinance for you and your children from generation to generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.25'>»When you enter the land Jehovah will give you, as he has promised, you shall observe this rite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.26'>»When your children ask you: What does this rite mean to you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.27'>»You shall say: It is a Passover sacrifice to Jehovah who passed over the houses of the sons of Israel in Egypt when He killed the Egyptians, but spared our homes. The people bowed low and worshiped.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.28'>Then the sons of Israel did just as Jehovah had commanded Moses and Aaron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.29'>At midnight Jehovah killed every firstborn male in Egypt from the firstborn son of Pharaoh who ruled the land to the firstborn son of the prisoner in jail, and also every firstborn animal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.30'>Pharaoh, all his officials, and all the other Egyptians got up during the night. There was loud crying throughout Egypt because in every house someone had died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.31'>Pharaoh called for Moses and Aaron during the night. He said: »You and the Israelites must leave my people at once. Go serve Jehovah just as you requested.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.32'>»Take your flocks and herds, too, as you asked. Just go! And bless me, too!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.33'>The Egyptians begged the people to leave the country quickly. They said: »We will all be dead soon!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.34'>The people picked up their bread dough before it had risen. They carried it on their shoulders in bowls and wrapped up in their clothes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.35'>The sons of Israel did what Moses told them. They asked the Egyptians for gold and silver jewelry and for clothes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.36'>Jehovah made the Egyptians generous to the people. They gave them what they asked for. So the sons of Israel stripped Egypt of its wealth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.37'>The Israelites left Rameses to go to Succoth. There were about six hundred thousand men on foot, plus all the women and children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.38'>Many other people also went with them, along with large numbers of sheep, goats, and cattle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.39'>With the dough they had brought from Egypt, they baked round, flat bread. The dough had not risen because they had been thrown out of Egypt and had no time to prepare food for the trip.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.40'>The Israelites had been living in Egypt for four hundred and thirty years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.41'>After exactly four hundred and thirty years all of Jehovahs people left Egypt in organized family groups.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.42'>It is a night to be observed for Jehovah for having brought them out from the land of Egypt. This night is for Jehovah and should be observed by all the sons of Israel throughout their generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.43'>Jehovah said to Moses and Aaron: »This is the ordinance of the Passover: no foreigner is to eat of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.44'>»After you have circumcised your purchased slave he may eat of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.45'>»No foreigner visiting you may eat it. No hired worker may eat it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.46'>»The meal must be eaten inside one house. Never take any of the meat outside the house. Do not break any of the bones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.47'>»The entire community of Israel must celebrate the Passover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.48'>»The uncircumcised man may not eat it. If a foreigner has settled among you and wants to celebrate Passover to honor Jehovah, you must first circumcise all the males of his household. He is then to be treated like a native-born Israelite and may join in the festival.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.49'>»The same regulations apply to native-born Israelites and to foreigners who settle among you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.50'>All the Israelites obeyed. They did what Jehovah had commanded Moses and Aaron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.51'>On that day Jehovah brought the Israelite tribes out of Egypt.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.13'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.1'>Jehovah said to Moses:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.2'>»Consecrate appointsanctify all the first-born males to me. Every first-born male Israelite and every first-born male animal belongs to me!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.3'>Moses said to the people: »Remember this day in the month of Abib. It is the day Jehovahs mighty power rescued you from slavery in Egypt. Do not eat anything made with yeast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.4'>»You are going out this day in the month Abib.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.5'>»Jehovah shall bring you into the land of the Canaanites, and the Hittites, and the Amorites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites. He swore to your fathers to give you this land flowing with milk and honey. You shall observe this rite in this month.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.6'>»You must eat unleavened bread seven days. The seventh day will be a feast to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.7'>»Unleavened bread shall be eaten seven days. No leavened bread shall be seen with you or in all your borders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.8'>»On that day tell your children: We do this because of what Jehovah did for us when we left Egypt.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.9'>»This festival will be like a mark on your hand. It will be a reminder on your forehead that the teachings of Jehovah are always to be a part of your conversation! Jehovah used his mighty hand to bring you out of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.10'>»You must follow these rules every year at this time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.11'>»When Jehovah brings you to the land of the Canaanites and gives it to you, as he swore to you and your ancestors,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.12'>sacrifice every firstborn male offspring to Jehovah. The firstborn male offspring of each of your animals belongs to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.13'>»It will cost you a sheep or a goat to buy any firstborn donkey back from Jehovah. You must break the donkeys neck if you do not buy it back. You must also buy every firstborn son back from Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.14'>»In the future when your children ask you, What does this mean? tell them: Jehovah used his mighty hand to bring us out of slavery in Egypt.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.15'>»Pharaoh was too stubborn to let us go. Because of this every firstborn male in Egypt-human and animal was killed. This is why we sacrifice every firstborn male to Jehovah and buy every firstborn son back from Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.16'>»This festival will be like a mark on your hand and like a band on your forehead, because Jehovah used his mighty hand to bring us out of Egypt.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.17'>»When the king of Egypt let the people go God did not take them on the road that goes up the coast to Philistia, although it was the shortest way. God thought: I do not want the people to change their minds and return to Egypt when they see that they are going to have to fight.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.18'>He led them by way of the desert by the Red Sea. The Israelites were armed for battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.19'>Moses took the body of Joseph with him. Joseph made the Israelites solemnly promise to do so. Joseph said: When God rescues you, you must carry my body with you from this place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.20'>The Israelites left Sukkoth and camped at Etham on the edge of the desert.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.21'>Jehovah went in front of them in a pillar of cloud to show them the way during the day. He went in front of them in a pillar of fire to give them light, so that they could travel at night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.22'>The pillar of cloud was always in front of the people during the day, and the pillar of fire at night.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.14'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.1'>Jehovah said to Moses:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.2'>»Tell the Israelites to turn back and camp in front of Pi Hahiroth, between Migdol and the Red Sea, near Baal Zephon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.3'>»The king will think that the Israelites are wandering around in the country and are closed in by the desert.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.4'>»I will make him stubborn. He will pursue you. My victory over the king and his army will bring me honor. Then the Egyptians will know that I am Jehovah!« The Israelites did as they were told.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.5'>The king of Egypt was told that the people had escaped. He and his officials changed their minds and said: »What have we done? We have let the Israelites escape, and we have lost them as our slaves!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.6'>The king got his war chariot and army ready.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.7'>He commanded his officers in charge of his six hundred best chariots and all his other chariots to start after the Israelites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.8'>Jehovah made the king so stubborn that he went after them. The Israelites proudly went on their way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.9'>The kings horses and chariots and soldiers caught up with them while they were camping by the Red Sea near Pi-Hahiroth and Baal-Zephon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.10'>The Israelites saw the king coming with his army. They were frightened and begged Jehovah for help.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.11'>They also complained to Moses: Was there not enough room in Egypt to bury us? Is that why you brought us out here to die in the desert? Why did you bring us out of Egypt?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.12'>»Did we not say in Egypt: Leave us alone that we may serve the Egyptians? It would have been better for us to serve the Egyptians than to die in the desert.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.13'>But Moses said to the people: »Do not fear! Stand by and see the salvation of Jehovah. He will accomplish this for you today. The Egyptians whom you have seen today, you will never see them again forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.14'>»Jehovah will fight for you while you keep silent.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.15'>Jehovah said to Moses: »Why are you crying out to me? Tell the sons of Israel to go forward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.16'>»As for you, lift up your staff and stretch out your hand over the sea and divide it. The sons of Israel shall go through the midst of the sea on dry land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.17'>»I will harden the hearts of the Egyptians so that they will go in after them. I will be honored through Pharaoh and all his army, through his chariots and his horsemen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.18'>»Then the Egyptians will know that I am Jehovah, when I am honored through Pharaoh, through his chariots and his horsemen.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.19'>The angel of God, who had been going before the camp of Israel, moved and went behind them. The pillar of cloud moved from before them and stood behind them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.20'>So it came between the camp of Egypt and the camp of Israel. There was the cloud along with the darkness, yet it gave light at night. Thus the one did not come near the other all night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.21'>Moses stretched out his hand over the sea. Jehovah swept the sea back by a strong east wind all night and turned the sea into dry land. The waters were divided.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.22'>The Israelites went through the middle of the sea on dry ground. The water stood like a wall on their right and on their left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.23'>The Egyptians pursued them. Pharaohs horses, chariots, and cavalry followed them into the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.24'>Just before dawn, Jehovah looked down from the column of fire and smoke and threw the Egyptian camp into a panic.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.25'>He made the wheels of their chariots come off. They could hardly move. Then the Egyptians shouted: »Let us get out of here! Jehovah is fighting for Israel! He is against us!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.26'>Jehovah then said to Moses: »Hold out your hand over the sea, and the water will flow back over the Egyptians and their chariots and drivers.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.27'>Moses held out his hand over the sea. At daybreak the water returned to its normal level. The Egyptians tried to escape from the water. But Jehovah threw them into the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.28'>The water returned and covered the chariots, the drivers, and all the Egyptian army that had followed the Israelites into the sea. None of them were left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.29'>On the other hand, the Israelites walked through the sea on dry ground, with walls of water on both sides.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.30'>That day Jehovah saved the people of Israel from the Egyptians. The Israelites saw them lying dead on the seashore.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.31'>The Israelites saw the great power with which Jehovah had defeated the Egyptians. So they stood in awe of Jehovah. They had faith in Jehovah and in his servant Moses.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.15'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.1'>Moses and the Israelites sang this song to Jehovah: »I will sing to Jehovah, because he has won a glorious victory. He has thrown the horses and their riders into the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.2'>»Jehovah is my strong defender. He is the one who has saved me. He is my God, and I will praise him, my fathers God, and I will sing about his greatness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.3'>»Jehovah is His name, and he is a warrior!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.4'>»He threw the chariots and army of Egypts king into the Red Sea, and he drowned the best of the kings army.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.5'>»The depths have covered them. They sank to the bottom just like boulders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.6'>»With the tremendous force of your right arm, Jehovah, you crushed your enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.7'>»In the greatness of your excellence you overthrow those who rose up against you. You sent your wrath and consumed them like stubble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.8'>»With a blast from your nostrils, the water piled up. The waves stood up like a dam. The deep water thickened in the middle of the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.9'>»The enemy said: I will pursue them! I will catch them! I will divide the loot! I will take all I want! I will use my sword! I will take all they have!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.10'>»Your breath blew the sea over them. They sank like lead in the raging water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.11'>»Who among the gods is like you Jehovah? Who is like you, wonderful in holiness? Who can work wonders and mighty acts like yours?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.12'>»You stretched out your right hand, and the earth swallowed our enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.13'>»Using your powerful love, you rescued redeemed the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.14'>»Nations learned of this and trembled. The Philistines shook with horror.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.15'>»The sheiks chiefs of Edom were dismayed. The leaders of Moab are griped with fear. The inhabitants of Canaan are filled with fear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.16'>»Terror and dread fall upon them. By the greatness of your arm they are motionless as stone. Until your people pass over, O Jehovah, until the people pass over whom you have purchased.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.17'>»You will bring them and plant them on your own mountain, the place where you live, O Jehovah, the holy place that you built with your own hands, O Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.18'>»Jehovah will rule as king forever and ever.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.19'>When Pharaohs horses, chariots, and cavalry went into the sea, Jehovah made the water of the sea flow back over them. The Israelites had gone through the sea on dry ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.20'>The prophet Miriam, Aarons sister, took a tambourine in her hand. All the women, danced with tambourines, and followed her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.21'>Miriam sang to them: »Sing to Jehovah. He has won a glorious victory. He has thrown horses and their riders into the sea.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.22'>Moses led Israel away from the Red Sea into the desert of Shur. For three days they traveled in the desert without finding water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.23'>When they came to Marah, they could not drink the water because it tasted bitter. That is why the place was called Marah Bitter Place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.24'>The people complained about Moses. They asked: »What can we drink?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.25'>Moses cried out to Jehovah. Jehovah showed him a piece of wood. He threw it into the water, and the water became sweet. Jehovah presented laws and rules for them to live by. He tested them there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.26'>He said: »If you will listen carefully to Jehovah your God and do what he considers right, if you pay attention to his commands and obey all his laws, I will never make you suffer any of the diseases I made the Egyptians suffer. I am Jehovah, who heals you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.27'>Then they went to Elim. There were twelve springs and seventy palm trees. They camped there by the water.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.16'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.1'>The whole congregation of Israelites moved from Elim to the desert of Sin, which is between Elim and Sinai. This was on the fifteenth day of the second month after they left Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.2'>The entire congregation complained about Moses and Aaron in the desert.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.3'>The Israelites said to them: »If only Jehovah had allowed us die in Egypt! There we sat by our pots of meat and ate all the food we wanted! You brought us out into this desert to let us all starve to death!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.4'>Jehovah said to Moses: »I am going to cause food to rain down from the sky for all of you. The people must go out every day and gather enough for that day. In this way I can test them to find out if they will follow my instructions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.5'>»They are to bring in twice as much as usual and prepare it on the sixth day.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.6'>Moses and Aaron said to all the Israelites: »This evening you will know that it was Jehovah who brought you out of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.7'>»In the morning you will see the glory of Jehovahs presence. He hears your complaints against him. But what are we that you complain against us?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.8'>Moses said: »This will happen when Jehovah gives you meat to eat in the evening, and bread to eat in the morning. Jehovah hears your complaints against him. And what are we? Your complaints are not against us but against Jehovah.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.9'>Moses said to Aaron: »Say to all the congregation of the sons of Israel: Come near before Jehovah for he has heard your complaints.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.10'>Aaron was speaking to them, when everyone looked out toward the desert and saw the bright glory of Jehovah in a cloud.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.11'>Jehovah said to Moses:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.12'>»I have heard my people complain. I said to them: Each evening you will have meat and each morning they will have more than enough bread. Then you will know that I am Jehovah their God.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.13'>That evening many quails came and landed everywhere in the camp, and the next morning dew covered the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.14'>After the dew had gone, the desert was covered with thin flakes that looked like frost.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.15'>When the children of Israel saw, they said to one another: »What is this?« For they did not know what it was. Moses said to them: »This is the bread Jehovah has given you to eat.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.16'>This is what Jehovah has commanded: »Each man should gather according to what he can eat. You shall take two quarts for each person in your tent.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.17'>The sons of Israel did this. Some gathered much and some little.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.18'>They measured it. Those who gathered much did not have too much. Some who gathered less did not have too little. Each had gathered just what he needed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.19'>Moses said: »No one is to keep any of it for tomorrow.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.20'>Some of them did not listen to Moses and saved part of it. The next morning it was full of worms and smelled rotten. Moses was angry with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.21'>Every morning each one gathered as much as he needed. When the sun grew hot, what was left on the ground melted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.22'>The sixth day they gathered twice as much food, four quarts for each person. All the leaders of the congregation came and told Moses about it. (Mark 15:42)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.23'>Moses said: »Jehovah has commanded that tomorrow is a holy day of rest, dedicated to God. Bake today what you want to bake and boil what you want to boil. Whatever is left should be put aside and kept for tomorrow.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.24'>They kept what was left until the next day as Moses commanded. It did not spoil or get worms in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.25'>Moses said: »Eat this today, because today is the Sabbath, a day of rest dedicated to Jehovah. You will not find any food outside the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.26'>»You shall gather it for six days. But on the seventh day, the Sabbath, there shall be none.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.27'>Some of the people went out on the seventh day to gather. They did not find any.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.28'>Jehovah spoke to Moses: »How long do you refuse to keep my commandments and my instructions?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.29'>»Jehovah has given you the Sabbath. He gives you bread for two days on the sixth day. Remain every man in his place! Let no man go out of his place on the seventh day.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.30'>So the people rested on the seventh day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.31'>The house of Israel called its name manna. It was like coriander seed, white in color. It tasted like wafers made with honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.32'>Moses said: »This is what Jehovah has commanded: Let two quarts of it be kept throughout your generations. Then they may see the bread with which I fed you in the wilderness, when I brought you out of the land of Egypt.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.33'>Moses said to Aaron: »Take a jar, and put two quarts of manna in it. Place it before Jehovah, to be kept throughout your generations.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.34'>Aaron placed it before the Testimony, to be kept just as Jehovah commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.35'>The children of Israel ate the manna forty years, until they came to an inhabited land. They ate the manna until they came to the border of the land of Canaan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.36'>The standard dry measure used in Moses day equaled twenty quarts.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.17'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.1'>The entire congregation of Israelites left the desert of Sin and traveled from place to place as Jehovah commanded them. They camped at Rephidim, but there was no water for the people to drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.2'>So they complained to Moses about this: »Give us water to drink!« Moses said: »Why do you complain to me? Why do you test Jehovah?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.3'>The people were thirsty for water. They complained to Moses and asked: »Why did you bring us out of Egypt? Was it to make us, our children, and our livestock die of thirst?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.4'>Moses cried out to Jehovah: »What should I do with these people? They are almost ready to stone me!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.5'>Jehovah said to Moses: »Go in front of the people. Take the elders of Israel with you. Take your rod with which you struck the river, in your hand, and go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.6'>»Behold! I will stand before you there upon the rock in Horeb. Strike the rock and water will come out of it. Then the people may drink.« Moses did this in the sight of the elders of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.7'>He called the name of the place Massah, and Meribah, because of the complaining of the children of Israel, and because they tested Jehovah, saying: »Is Jehovah among us or not?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.8'>The Amalekites fought Israel at Rephidim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.9'>Moses said to Joshua: »Choose some of our men. Then fight the Amalekites. Tomorrow I will stand on top of the hill. I will hold in my hand the staff God told me to take along.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.10'>Joshua did as Moses told him. They fought the Amalekites, while Moses, Aaron, and Hur went to the top of the hill.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.11'>As long as Moses held up his hands, Israel would win, but as soon as he put his hands down, the Amalekites would start to win.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.12'>Finally, Moses was so tired that Aaron and Hur got a rock for him to sit on. They stood beside him and supported his arms in the same position until sunset.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.13'>That is how Joshua defeated the Amalekites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.14'>After the fight Jehovah said to Moses: »Write an account of this victory and read it to Joshua. I want the Amalekites to be forgotten forever.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.15'>Moses built an altar. He named it: »Jehovah Gives Me Victory.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.16'>Then Moses explained: »This is because I depended on Jehovah. But in future generations, Jehovah will have to fight the Amalekites again.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.18'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.1'>Jethro was the priest of Midian and the father-in-law of Moses. He heard what Jehovah God had done for Moses and his people, after rescuing them from Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.2'>Moses sent his wife Zipporah and her two sons to stay with Jethro. Jethro welcomed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.3'>Moses was still a foreigner in Midian when his first son was born. Moses said: »I will name him Gershom.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.4'>When his second son was born, Moses said: »I will name him Eliezer, because the God my father worshiped has saved me from the king of Egypt.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.5'>Jethro, Moses father-in-law brought Moses sons and wife to Moses in the desert. He was camped near the mountain of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.6'>Jethro sent word to Moses: »I am coming to visit you. I am bringing your wife and her two sons.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.7'>Moses went out to meet his father-in-law. Moses bowed with his face touching the ground and kissed Jethro. They asked each other how they were. Then they entered the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.8'>Moses told his father-in-law everything Jehovah had done to Pharaoh and the Egyptians for Israel. He talked about all the hardships they had on the way, and how Jehovah saved them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.9'>Jethro rejoiced over all the goodness Jehovah had done to Israel, in delivering them from the hand of the Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.10'>Jethro said: »Blessed be Jehovah who delivered you from the hand of the Egyptians and from the hand of Pharaoh. He delivered the people from under the domination of the Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.11'>»Now I know that Jehovah is greater than all the other gods. It was proven when they treated the people with contempt.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.12'>Jethro, Moses father-in-law, took a burnt offering and sacrifices for God, and Aaron came with all the elders of Israel to eat a meal with Moses father-in-law before God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.13'>The next day Moses settled disputes among the people. He was busy from morning till night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.14'>Jethro saw everything that Moses had to do. He asked: »What is all this that you are doing for the people? Why are you doing this all alone? There are people standing here from morning till night to consult you?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.15'>Moses answered: »They come here to find out what God wants them to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.16'>»They bring their complaints to me. I make decisions on the basis of Gods laws.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.17'>Jethro replied: »That is not a good way to do it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.18'>»You and your people will wear yourselves out. This is too much work for you. You cannot do it alone!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.19'>»Listen to the advice I give you. May God be with you! You must be the peoples representative to God and bring their disagreements to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.20'>»You must instruct them in the laws and the teachings. Show them how to live and tell them what to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.21'>»You should choose capable men from all the people. Find men who respect God. These must be men you can trust who hate corruption. Put them in charge of groups of thousands, hundreds, fifties and tens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.22'>»They must be the ones who usually settle disagreements among the people. They should bring all-important cases to you. But they should settle all minor cases themselves. Make it easier for yourself by letting them help you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.23'>»If you do this, as God commands, you will not wear yourself out. All these people can go home with their disputes settled.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.24'>Moses took Jethros advice</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.25'>and chose capable men from among all the Israelites. He appointed them as leaders of thousands, hundreds, fifties, and tens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.26'>They judged the people on a permanent basis. The difficult cases were taken to Moses but they decided the smaller disputes themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.27'>Moses said good-bye to Jethro, and Jethro went back home.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.19'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.1'>The Israelites arrived at the desert of Sinai in the third month after they left the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.2'>They traveled from Rephidim to the desert of Sinai. Israel camped in the wilderness at the foot of Mount Sinai.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.3'>Jehovah called Moses from the mountain. So Moses went up the mountain to God. Jehovah told him: »This is what you must say to the descendants of Jacob. Tell the Israelites:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.4'>You have seen what I did to Egypt and how I carried you on the wings of eagles and brought you to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.5'>If you will obey me and are faithful to the terms of my covenant, then out of all the nations you will be my own special possession, for all the earth is mine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.6'>You will be my kingdom of priests and my holy nation. These are the words you must speak to the children of Israel.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.7'>Moses went down the mountain and called for the elders of the people. He repeated to them all the words that Jehovah had commanded him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.8'>All the people answered together: »We will do everything Jehovah has said.« So Moses brought their answer back to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.9'>Jehovah said to Moses: »I will come to you in a thick cloud. The people will hear me speaking with you and will believe you from now on.« Moses gave Jehovah the peoples answer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.10'>Jehovah continued: »Go to the people and tell them to spend today and tomorrow purifying themselves for worship. They must wash their clothes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.11'>»They should be ready in three days. I will descend to Mount Sinai, where all of them can see me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.12'>»Warn the people that they are forbidden to touch any part of the mountain. Anyone who touches the mountain will be put to death,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.13'>with stones or arrows, and no one must touch the body of a person killed in this way. Even an animal that touches this mountain must be put to death. You may go up the mountain only after a signal is given on the trumpet.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.14'>Moses went down from the mountain to the people. He consecrated the people, and they washed their garments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.15'>He said to the people: »Get ready for the third day. Do not go near a woman for sexual intercourse.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.16'>On the morning of the third day there were thunder and lightning flashes and a thick cloud upon the mountain. A very loud trumpet sounded. It caused all the people in the camp to tremble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.17'>Moses brought the people out of the camp to meet God. They stood at the foot of the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.18'>Mount Sinai was all in smoke because Jehovah descended upon it in fire. Its smoke ascended like the smoke of a furnace. The whole mountain quaked violently!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.19'>The sound of the trumpet grew louder and louder. Moses spoke and God answered him with thunder.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.20'>Jehovah descended on the top of Mount Sinai. Jehovah called Moses to the top of the mountain. Moses climbed to the peak of Mount Sinai.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.21'>Jehovah spoke to Moses: »Go down and warn the people. They should not break through to gaze at Jehovah. Many of them would perish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.22'>»Let the priests who come near to Jehovah consecrate purify themselves, or else Jehovah will destroy them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.23'>Moses said to Jehovah: »The people cannot come up to Mount Sinai for you warned us. You said: Put limits around the mountain and set it apart as holy.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.24'>Jehovah replied to him: »You and Aaron come up to me. But do not let the priests and the people break through to come up to Jehovah, or he will destroy some of them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.25'>Moses returned to the people and told them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.20'>
        <title>TEN COMMANDMENTS</title>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.1'>God spoke all these words:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.2'>»I am Jehovah your God, who brought you out of slavery in Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.3'>»Do not have any other god.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.4'>»Do not make your own carved idols or statues that represent any creature in the sky, on the earth, or in the water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.5'>»Do not worship them or serve them. I, Jehovah your God, am a God demanding exclusive devotion. I do not tolerate rivals. I will not share your affection with any other god. I punish children for their parents sins to the third and fourth generation of those who hate me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.6'>»I show mercy loving kindness to thousands of generations of those who love me and obey my commandments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.7'>»Never use the name of Jehovah your God in a false and evil way. Jehovah will make sure that anyone who is false, evil, careless and vain with his name will be punished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.8'>»Remember the Sabbath day and keep it holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.9'>»You have six days to do all your work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.10'>»The seventh day is a Sabbath dedicated to Jehovah your God. Do not do any work, you or your son or your daughter, your male or your female servant or your cattle or your sojourner who stays with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.11'>»Jehovah made the heavens and the earth, the sea and all that is in them in six days. He rested on the seventh day. Therefore Jehovah blessed the Sabbath day and made it holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.12'>»Honor your father and your mother, that your days may be prolonged in the land Jehovah your God gives you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.13'>»Do not murder.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.14'>»Do not commit adultery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.15'>»Do not steal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.16'>»Do not lie accuse anyone falsely.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.17'>»Do not covet desire another mans house. Do not desire his wife, his slaves, his cattle, his donkeys, or anything else that he owns.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.18'>The people heard the thunder and the trumpet blast. They saw the lightning and the smoking mountain. They trembled with fear and stood at a distance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.19'>They said to Moses: »If you speak to us, we will listen. However, we are afraid that if God speaks to us, we will die.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.20'>Moses responded: »Do not be afraid. God has only come to test you and to inspire you to obey him, so that you will not sin.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.21'>But the people continued to stand at a distance. Only Moses went near the dark cloud where God was.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.22'>Jehovah commanded Moses to tell the Israelites: »You have seen how I have spoken to you from heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.23'>»Do not make for yourselves gods of silver or gold to be worshiped in addition to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.24'>»Make an altar of earth for me. Sacrifice your sheep and your cattle as offerings to be completely burned and as peace offerings. In every place that I set-aside for you to worship me, I will come to you and bless you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.25'>»If you make an altar of stone for me, do not build it out of cut stones. This is because when you use a chisel on stones, you make them unfit for my use.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.26'>»Do not build an altar for me with steps leading up to it. If you do, you will expose yourselves as you go up the steps.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.21'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.1'>»These are the ordinances you should set before them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.2'>»When you buy a Hebrew slave he will be your slave for six years. In the seventh year he may leave as a free man without paying for his freedom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.3'>»If he was single at the time you bought him he alone must be set free. If he was married at that time, both he and his wife must be given their freedom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.4'>»If his master gives him a wife, and she bears him sons or daughters, the wife and her children will belong to her master. He shall go out alone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.5'>»What if the slave loves his wife and children so much that he will not leave without them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.6'>»He must stand beside either the door or the doorpost at the place of worship. His owner will punch a small hole through one of his ears with a sharp metal rod. This makes him a slave for life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.7'>»When a man sells his daughter into slavery, she will not go free the way male slaves do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.8'>»If she does not please the master who has chosen her as a wife, he must let her be bought back by one of her close relatives. He has no right to sell her to foreigners, since he has treated her unfairly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.9'>»If a man buys a female slave to give to his son, he should treat her like a daughter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.10'>»If a man takes a second wife, he must continue to give his first wife the same amount of food and clothing and the same rights that she had before.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.11'>»If he fails to do any of these things, she should be given her freedom without cost.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.12'>»Death is the punishment for murder.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.13'>»If you did not intend to kill someone and I, Jehovah, let it happen anyway, you may run for safety to a place that I have set aside.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.14'>»If a man schemes and kills a man deliberately remove him from my altar and put him to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.15'>»He who strikes beats his father or his mother shall surely be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.16'>»Whoever kidnaps another person must be put to death regardless of whether he has sold the kidnapped person or still has him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.17'>»Anyone who curses his father or mother must be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.18'>»When men quarrel and one hits the other with a rock or with his fist and injures him so that he has to stay in bed you must do this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.19'>»If the injured man is able to stand up again and walk around outside with a cane, the one who hit him must not be punished. He must pay the injured man for the loss of his time and for all his medical expenses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.20'>»If a slave owner takes a stick and beats his slave, whether male or female, and the slave dies on the spot, the owner is to be punished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.21'>»If the slave lives a few days after the beating, you are not to be punished. After all, you have already lost the services of that slave who was your property.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.22'>»When a pregnant woman suffers a miscarriage as the result of an injury caused by someone who is fighting, if she is not badly hurt, the one who injured her must pay whatever fine her husband demands and the judges approve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.23'>»The payment will be for life if she is seriously injured,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.24'>eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.25'>»burn for burn, wound for wound, bruise for bruise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.26'>»If a man strikes the eye of his male or female slave, and destroys it, he shall let him go free because of his eye.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.27'>»If he knocks out a tooth of his male or female slave, he shall let him go free because of his tooth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.28'>»If an ox gores a man or a woman to death, the ox shall surely be stoned and its flesh shall not be eaten; but the owner of the ox shall go unpunished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.29'>»If an ox was previously in the habit of goring and its owner has been warned, yet he does not confine it and it kills a man or a woman, the ox shall be stoned and its owner also shall be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.30'>»If a ransom is demanded of him, then he shall give for the redemption of his life whatever is demanded of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.31'>»Whether it gores a son or a daughter, it shall be done to him according to the same rule.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.32'>»If the ox gores a male or female slave, the owner shall give his or her master thirty shekels of silver, and the ox shall be stoned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.33'>»If a man opens a pit, or digs a pit and does not cover it over, and an ox or a donkey falls into it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.34'>the owner of the pit shall make restitution. He will give money to its owner, and the dead animal shall become his.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.35'>»If one mans ox hurts anothers so that it dies, then they shall sell the live ox and divide its price equally. They should divide the dead ox.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.36'>»If it is known that the ox was previously in the habit of goring, yet its owner has not confined it, he shall surely pay ox for ox, and the dead animal shall become his.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.22'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.1'>»A man steals an ox or a sheep and slaughters it or sells it. He must pay five oxen for the ox and four sheep for the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.2'>»If the thief is caught while breaking in and is struck so that he dies, there will be no blood guiltiness on his account.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.3'>»But if it happens after sunrise, he is guilty of murder. A thief must make up for what he has stolen. If he is unable to do so, he should be sold as a slave to pay for what he stole.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.4'>»If the stolen animal is found alive in his possession, whether it is a bull, donkey, or a sheep, he must make up for the loss with double the amount.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.5'>»Someone lets his livestock graze in a field or a vineyard. They stray and graze in another persons field. He must make up for what the damaged field was expected to produce. If he lets them ruin the whole field with their grazing, he must make up from his own field for the loss with the best from his field and vineyard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.6'>»A fire starts and spreads into the underbrush so that it burns up stacked or standing grain or ruins a field. The person who started the fire must make up for the loss.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.7'>»Someone gives his neighbor silver or other valuables to keep for him. They are stolen from that persons house. If the thief is caught, he must make up for the loss with double the amount.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.8'>»If the thief is not caught, the owner of the house must be brought to God to find out whether or not he took his neighbors valuables.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.9'>»There is a dispute over the ownership of a bull, a donkey, a sheep, an article of clothing, and any other lost property which two people claim as their own. Both people must bring their case to God. The one whom God declares guilty must make up for his neighbors loss with double the amount.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.10'>»Someone gives his neighbor a donkey, a bull, a sheep, or any other kind of animal to keep for him, and it dies, is injured, or is captured in war, and there are no witnesses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.11'>»The case between them must be settled by swearing an oath to Jehovah that the neighbor did not take the other persons animal. The owner must accept the oath. The neighbor does not have to make up for the loss.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.12'>»However, if the animal was stolen from the neighbor, he must make up for the owners loss.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.13'>»If a wild animal killed the neighbors animal he must bring in the dead body of the wild animal as evidence. He does not have to make up for an animal that has been killed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.14'>»Whenever someone borrows an animal from his neighbor, and it is injured or dies while the owner is not present, the borrower must make up for the loss.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.15'>»If the owner is with the animal, the borrower does not have to make up for the loss. If it is rented, the rental fee covers the loss.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.16'>»When a man seduces a virgin who is not engaged to anyone and has sexual intercourse with her, he must pay the bride price and marry her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.17'>»If her father refuses to give her to him, he must pay an amount of money equal to the bride price for virgins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.18'>»Never allow a witch to live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.19'>»The person who has sexual intercourse with an animal must be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.20'>»The person who sacrifices to any god except Jehovah must be condemned and destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.21'>»Do not mistreat or oppress a foreigner. Remember that you were foreigners in Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.22'>»Do not mistreat any widow or orphan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.23'>»If you do, I, Jehovah, will answer them when they cry out to me for help,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.24'>and I will become angry and kill you in war. Your wives will become widows, and your children will be fatherless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.25'>»When you lend money to any of my people who are poor, do not act like a moneylender and require him to pay interest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.26'>»If you take someones cloak as a pledge that he will pay you, you must give it back to him before the sunsets,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.27'>for it is the only covering he has to keep him warm. What else can he sleep in? When he cries out to me for help, I will answer him because I am merciful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.28'>»Do not curse God. Do not curse a ruler of your people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.29'>»Do not delay the offering from your harvest and your vintage. Give the firstborn of your sons to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.30'>»Do the same with your oxen and with your sheep. Its mother may keep it for seven days. On the eighth day give it to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.31'>»You are to be my holy people. Do not eat any flesh torn to bits in the field. Throw it to the dogs.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.23'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.1'>»Do not spread false rumors. Do not help a guilty person by offering false testimony.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.2'>»Do not follow the majority to do wrong. Do not give testimony that perverts justice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.3'>»Do not show partiality to a poor man at his trial.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.4'>»If you see your enemys cow or donkey running loose, take it back to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.5'>»If your enemys donkey falls under its load, help him get the donkey to its feet again. Do not just walk away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.6'>»Do not deny justice to a poor person at his trial.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.7'>»Do not make false accusations. Do not put an innocent person to death. I will condemn anyone who does this evil thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.8'>»Do not accept a bribe, for a bribe makes the discerning blind to what is right and perverts the words of the righteous.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.9'>»Do not mistreat a foreigner. You know how it feels to be a foreigner. After all you were foreigners in Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.10'>»Plant your land and gather in what it produces for six years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.11'>»Let your land rest the seventh year. Do not harvest anything that grows on it. The poor may eat what grows there. The wild animals may have what is left. Do the same with your vineyards and your olive trees.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.12'>»Work six days a week. Do no work on the seventh day. Allow your slaves and the foreigners who work for you and even your animals to rest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.13'>»Listen to everything Jehovah has said to you. Do not pray to other gods! Do not even mention their names.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.14'>»Celebrate three festivals a year to honor me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.15'>»In the month of Abib, the month in which you left Egypt, celebrate the Festival of Unleavened Bread in the way that I commanded you. Do not eat any bread made with yeast during the seven days of this festival. Never come to worship me without bringing an offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.16'>»Celebrate the Harvest Festival when you begin to harvest your crops. Celebrate the Festival of Shelters in the autumn, when you gather the fruit from your vineyards and orchards.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.17'>»All your males should appear before Jehovah God three times a year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.18'>»Do not offer the blood of my sacrifice with leavened bread. Do not allow the fat of my feast to remain overnight until morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.19'>»Bring the choice first fruits of your soil into the house of Jehovah your God. Do not boil a young goat in the milk of its mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.20'>»I am going to send an angel before you to guard you along the way and to bring you into the place that I have prepared.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.21'>»Be on your guard before him and obey his voice. Do not be rebellious toward him. He will not pardon your transgression, since my name is in him. He has my honor, authority and character</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.22'>»If you truly obey his voice and do all that I say, then I will be an enemy to your enemies and an adversary to your adversaries.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.23'>»My messenger will go ahead of you. I will lead you to the land of the Amorites, Hittites, Perizzites, Canaanites, Hivites, and Jebusites. I will wipe them out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.24'>»Do not worship or serve their gods or follow their practices. You must destroy their gods and crush their sacred stones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.25'>»You must serve Jehovah your God! I will bless your food and water. I will take away all sickness from among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.26'>»No woman in your land will miscarry or be unable to have children. I will let you live a normal life span.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.27'>»I will send my terror ahead of you and throw any nation you meet into a panic. I will make all your enemies flee from you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.28'>»I will throw your enemies into panic! I will drive out the Hivites, the Canaanites, and the Hittites as you advance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.29'>»I will not drive them out within a years time. If I did, the land would become deserted. There would be too many wild animals for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.30'>»I will drive them a few at a time, until there are enough of you to take possession of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.31'>»I will make the borders of your land extend from the Gulf of Aqaba to the Mediterranean Sea and from the desert to the Euphrates River. I will give you power over the inhabitants of the land. You will drive them out as you advance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.32'>»Do not make any agreement with them or with their gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.33'>»Do not allow them to live in your land for they will make you sin against me. If you serve their gods it will be a snare to you.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.24'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.1'>Jehovah said to Moses: »You and Aaron, Nadab, Abihu, and seventy of Israels elders come up the mountain to me and worship at a distance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.2'>»Moses alone may come near Jehovah. The others may not. The people must not come along with Moses.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.3'>Moses told the people all Jehovahs words and legal decisions. Then all the people answered with one voice: »We will do everything Jehovah told us to do.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.4'>Moses wrote down all Jehovahs words. Early the next morning he built an altar at the foot of the mountain. He erected twelve sacred stones for the twelve tribes of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.5'>Moses sent young men to burn sacrifices to Jehovah. They sacrificed some cattle as peace offerings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.6'>Moses took half of the blood of the animals and put it in bowls. The other half he threw against the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.7'>He took the book of the covenant, in which Jehovahs commandments were written, and read it aloud to the people. They said: »We will obey Jehovah. We will do everything that he has commanded.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.8'>Moses took the blood from the bowls and sprinkled it on the people. Next, he told them: With this blood Jehovah makes his agreement with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.9'>Moses and Aaron, together with Nadab and Abihu and the seventy leaders, went up the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.10'>They saw the God of Israel. Under his feet was something that looked like a pavement made out of sapphire. It was as bright as the sky.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.11'>Even though these leaders of Israel saw God, he did not punish them. So they ate and drank.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.12'>Jehovah said to Moses: »Come up on the mountain and stay here for a while. I will give you the two stone tablets on which I have written the laws that my people must obey.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.13'>Moses and Joshua his assistant got ready. Moses started up the mountain to meet with God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.14'>He said to the elders: »Wait here for us until we return to you. Aaron and Hur are with you. Anyone with a legal matter should approach them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.15'>Moses went up to the mountain. The cloud covered the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.16'>The glory of Jehovah rested on Mount Sinai. The cloud covered it for six days. God called to Moses on the seventh day. He spoke from inside the cloud.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.17'>To the eyes of the Israelites the appearance of the glory of Jehovah was like a consuming fire on the top of the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.18'>Moses entered the midst of the cloud as he went up to the mountain. He was on the mountain forty days and forty nights.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.25'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.1'>Then Jehovah spoke to Moses. He said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.2'>»Tell the Israelites to choose something to give me as a special contribution. You must accept whatever contribution each person freely gives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.3'>»This is the type of contribution you will accept from them: gold, silver, and bronze,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.4'>violet, purple, and bright red yarns, fine linen, goats hair,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.5'>rams skins dyed red, fine leather, acacia wood,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.6'>olive oil for the lamps, spices balsam oil for the anointing oil and for the sweet-smelling incense,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.7'>onyx stones, and other precious stones to be set in the chief priests ephod and his breastplate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.8'>»Have them make a holy place sanctuary for me, and I will live among them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.9'>»Make the tent and all its furnishings exactly like the plans I show you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.10'>»Make a Box out of acacia wood, forty-five inches long, twenty-seven inches wide, and twenty-seven inches high.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.11'>»Cover it with pure gold inside and out and put a gold border all around it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.12'>»Make four carrying rings of gold for it and attach them to its four legs, with two rings on each side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.13'>»Make two poles of acacia wood. Cover them with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.14'>»Put them through the rings. Poles can be used to carry the chest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.15'>»Do not ever remove the poles from the rings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.16'>»I will give you the Ten Commandments written on two flat tablets. Put them inside the chest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.17'>»Cover the lid of the chest mercy seat with pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.18'>»Hammer out two winged cherubs of pure gold and fasten them to the lid at the ends of the chest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.19'>»Make one cherub at one end and one cherub at the other end. You shall make the cherubim of one piece with the chest at its two ends.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.20'>»The cherubim shall have their wings spread upward, covering the chest with their wings and facing one another. The faces of the cherubim are to be turned toward the chest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.21'>»After you put into the ark the words of my covenant that I will give you, place the throne of mercy on top.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.22'>»I will be above the throne of mercy between the angels whenever I meet with you. I will give you all my commandments for the Israelites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.23'>»Make a table of acacia wood thirty-six inches long, eighteen inches wide, and twenty-seven inches high.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.24'>»Cover it with pure gold. Put a gold molding around it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.25'>»Make a rim three inches wide around it. Put a gold molding around the rim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.26'>»Make four gold rings for it. Fasten them to the four corners where the four legs are.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.27'>»The rings are to be close to the rim. They are to hold the poles for carrying the table.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.28'>»Make the poles out of acacia wood. Cover them with gold and use them to carry the table.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.29'>»The plates and dishes for the table should be out of pure gold. Also make pitchers and bowls to be used for pouring wine offerings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.30'>»The table should be placed in front of the Covenant Box. There is always to be the sacred bread offered to me for the table.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.31'>»Make lamp stand of pure gold. Make its base and its shaft of hammered gold. Its decorative flowers, including buds and petals, are to form one piece with it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.32'>»Six branches shall extend from its sides, three from each side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.33'>»Three cups shall be shaped like almond blossoms in the one branch, a bulb and a flower, and three cups shaped like almond blossoms in the other branch. This should go on for six branches going out from the lamp stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.34'>»Four cups shaped like almond blossoms, its bulbs and its flowers should be in the lamp stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.35'>»A bulb shall be under each of the six pair of branches coming out of the lamp stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.36'>»Their bulbs and their branches shall be of one piece. All of it must be one piece of hammered work of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.37'>»Then make a total of seven lamps. Mount the lamps so that they shed light on the space in front of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.38'>»Its snuffers and fire holders trays must be of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.39'>»It shall be made from seventy-five pounds of pure gold, with all these utensils.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.40'>»See that you make them like the pattern for them that were shown to you on the mountain.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.26'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.1'>»Construct the tabernacle with ten curtains of fine twisted linen and blue and purple and scarlet material. Make them with cherubim, the work of a skillful workman.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.2'>»Each curtain will be forty-two feet long and six feet wide. All will be the same size.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.3'>»Five of the curtains must be sewn together. The other five must also be sewn together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.4'>»Make fifty violet loops along the edge of the end curtain in each set,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.5'>»Place the loops opposite each other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.6'>»Make fifty gold fasteners. Use them to link the two sets of curtains together so that the tent is a single unit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.7'>»Make eleven curtains of goats hair to form an outer tent over the inner tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.8'>»Each of the eleven curtains will be forty-five feet long and six feet wide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.9'>»Sew five of the curtains together into one set. Sew the remaining six into another set. Fold the sixth curtains in half to hang in front of the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.10'>»Fasten fifty loops along the edge of the end curtain in each set.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.11'>»Make fifty bronze fasteners. Put the fasteners through the loops to link the inner tent together as a single unit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.12'>»Hang the remaining curtain over the back of the inner tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.13'>»Eighteen inches will be left over on each side because of the length of the outer tents curtains. That should hang over each side in order to cover the inner tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.14'>»Make a cover of rams skins that have been dyed red for the outer tent. Place a cover made of fine leather over that.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.15'>»A framework out of acacia wood should be built for the inner tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.16'>»Each frame is to be fifteen feet long and twenty-seven inches wide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.17'>»It should have two identical pegs. Make all the frames for the inner tent the same way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.18'>»Make twenty frames for the south side of the inner tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.19'>»Provide forty silver sockets at the bottom of the twenty frames, two sockets at the bottom of each frame for the two pegs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.20'>»Prepare twenty frames for the north side of the inner tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.21'>»Also forty silver sockets, two at the bottom of each frame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.22'>»Prepare six frames for the far end, the west side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.23'>»There should be two frames for each of the corners at the far end of the inner tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.24'>»Fasten these together at the bottom and tightly at the top by a single ring. Both corner frames will be made this way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.25'>»There will be eight frames with sixteen silver sockets, two at the bottom of each frame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.26'>»Prepare crossbars out of acacia wood: five for the frames on one side of the inner tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.27'>»Also prepare five for those on the other side, and five for the frames on the far end of the inner tent, the west side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.28'>»The middle crossbar will run from one end to the other. It should be halfway up the frames.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.29'>»Cover the frames with gold. Make gold rings to hold the crossbars. Cover the crossbars with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.30'>»Erect the inner tent according to the plans you were shown on the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.31'>»Build a canopy of violet, purple, and bright red yarn. Creatively work an angel design of cherubim into fine linen yarn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.32'>»Hang it on four pillars of acacia overlaid with gold. Their hooks should also be of gold, on four sockets of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.33'>»Hang up the veil under the clasps. Bring in the Ark of the Covenant there within the veil. The veil shall serve for you as a partition between the holy place and the holy of holies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.34'>»Place the mercy seat on the Ark of the Covenant in the holy of holies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.35'>»Set the table outside the veil. Place the lamp stand opposite the table on the side of the tabernacle toward the south. Place the table on the north side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.36'>»Make a screen for the doorway of the tent of blue and purple and scarlet material and fine twisted linen, the work of a weaver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.37'>»Make five pillars of acacia for the screen and overlay them with gold. Their hooks should also be of gold. Cast five sockets of bronze for them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.27'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.1'>»Build the altar with acacia wood. It should be seven and one half feet square and four and one half feet tall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.2'>»Place a horn at each of its four corners. The four horns and the altar must be made out of one piece of wood covered with copper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.3'>»Make all the utensils for it out of copper: pots for taking away the altars ashes, also shovels, bowls, forks, and incense burners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.4'>»Make a grate for it out of copper mesh. Make a copper ring for each of the four corners of the grate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.5'>»Place the grate under the ledge of the altar so that it comes halfway up the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.6'>»Prepare poles out of acacia wood for the altar. Cover them with copper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.7'>»The poles should be put through the rings on both sides of the altar and used to carry it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.8'>»Make the altar out of boards so that it is hollow inside. It must be made just as you were shown on the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.9'>»Make a courtyard for the tent tabernacle. The south side of the courtyard toward the Negeb should be one hundred and fifty feet long and have curtains made out of fine linen yarn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.10'>»Hang on them twenty posts set in twenty copper bases. The hooks and bands on the posts should be made of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.11'>»The north side should be the same one hundred fifty feet long, with curtains on twenty posts set in twenty copper bases. The hooks and bands on the posts should be made of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.12'>»The courtyard on the west side should be seventy-five wide and have curtains hung on ten posts set in ten bases.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.13'>»On the east end, facing the rising sun, the courtyard should also be seventy-five feet wide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.14'>»One side of the entrance will be twenty-two and one half feet wide with curtains hung on three posts set in three bases.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.15'>»The other side will be the same.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.16'>»Use four more of these posts for the entrance. Hang on them an embroidered curtain of fine linen ten yards long and woven with blue, purple, and red wool.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.17'>»The curtains that surround the courtyard must be two and a half yards high and should be hung from the bronze posts with silver hooks and rods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.18'>»The courtyard should be one hundred and fifty feet long, seventy-five feet wide, and seven and one half feet high. The curtains should be made of fine linen yarn and with copper bases.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.19'>»Regardless of how they are used all the things for the tent must be made of copper. Even the pegs for the tent and the courtyard must be made of copper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.20'>»Command the Israelites that the lighting must be provided by pure virgin olive oil so that the lamps will not go out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.21'>»Keep the lamps lit in the tent of meeting outside the canopy where the words of my covenant are. Aaron and his descendants must keep the lamps lit in Jehovahs presence from evening until morning. This is a long lasting law among the Israelites for generations to come.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.28'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.1'>Jehovah continued: »Bring your brother Aaron and his sons Nadab, Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar to you from all the Israelites. They will serve me as priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.2'>»Make sacred clothes for your brother Aaron to give him dignity and honor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.3'>»Tell all the skilled men whom I have given this ability to make Aarons clothes. These clothes will set him apart as holy when he serves me as priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.4'>»The clothes they will make are as follows: a breastplate, an ephod and the robe that is worn with it, another specially woven linen robe, the chief priests turban, and a cloth belt. They will make these holy clothes for your brother Aaron and his sons so that they will be able to serve me as priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.5'>»Take the gold and blue thread and wool that is dyed bright read and the fine linen and</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.6'>»prepare the ephod with fine linen yarn. Embroider gold, violet, purple, and bright red yarn into the fabric.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.7'>»It should have two shoulder straps attached at the top corners so it can be fastened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.8'>»Make the belt that is attached to the ephod from the same fabric.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.9'>»Engrave the names of the sons of Israel on two onyx stones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.10'>»Engrave them in order of their birth. Place six names on each stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.11'>»Engrave the names of the sons of Israel on the two stones the same way a jeweler engraves a signet ring. Mount them in gold settings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.12'>»Then fasten them on the shoulder straps of the ephod as reminders of who the Israelites are. In this way Aaron will carry their names on his shoulders as a reminder in Jehovahs presence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.13'>»Make gold settings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.14'>»Also make two chains of pure gold. These gold chains should be twisted like ropes. Fasten these chains to the settings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.15'>»Prepare the breast piece for decision-making using a skilled craftsman. Make it like the ephod out of gold, violet, purple, and bright red yarn and out of fine linen yarn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.16'>»Fold it in half so it is nine inches square.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.17'>»Fasten four rows of precious stones on it. Put red quartz, topaz, and emerald in the first row.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.18'>»Place turquoise, sapphire, and crystal in the second row.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.19'>»In the third row put jacinth, agate, and amethyst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.20'>»In the fourth row put beryl, onyx, and gray quartz. Mount them in gold settings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.21'>»The stones represent the twelve sons of Israel, by name, each stone engraved like a signet ring with the name of one of the twelve tribes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.22'>»Make chains out of pure gold, twisted like ropes for the breastplate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.23'>»Make two gold rings for the breastplate. Attach them to the two top corners of the breastplate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.24'>»Fasten the two gold ropes to the rings at the top corners of the breastplate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.25'>»Fasten the other ends of the ropes to the two settings on the shoulder straps of the ephod so that the breastplate hangs in front of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.26'>»Make two gold rings, and connect them to the other two corners of the breastplate on the inside edge next to the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.27'>»Make two more gold rings, and fasten them to the bottom of the shoulder straps on the front of the ephod. This will be close to the seam just above the belt of the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.28'>»Then the breastplate should be fastened by its rings to the rings of the ephod with a violet cord. Attach it just above the belt of the ephod. This will hold the breastplate in place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.29'>»When Aaron goes into the holy place, he will carry the names of the sons of Israel over his heart as a continual reminder in Jehovahs presence. He must do this by wearing the breast piece for decision-making.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.30'>Put the Urim and Thummim into the breast piece for decision-making. They, too, will be over Aarons heart when he comes into Jehovahs presence. In this way when he is in Jehovahs presence, Aaron will always be carrying over his heart the means for determining Jehovahs decisions for the Israelites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.31'>»Make the robe that is worn with the ephod entirely of violet material.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.32'>»Provide an opening for the head in the center with a reinforced edge like a leather collar all around it to keep it from tearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.33'>»Along the hem of the robe weave pomegranates of blue, purple, and red wool with a gold bell between each of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.34'>»A gold bell should alternate with a pomegranate all around the hem of the robe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.35'>»Aaron should wear it when he serves as priest. The sound of the bells must be heard when he comes into and goes out of Jehovahs presence in the holy place so that he will not die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.36'>»Also make a plate of pure gold and engrave on it, like the engravings of a seal: Holy to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.37'>»Fasten it on a blue cord and on the turban. It should be at the front of the turban.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.38'>»It shall be on Aarons forehead. Aaron will take away the iniquity of the holy things that the sons of Israel consecrate. Concerning their holy gifts it will always be on his forehead that they may be accepted before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.39'>»Weave the tunic of checkered work of fine linen. Make a turban of fine linen and a sash, the work of a weaver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.40'>»Make linen robes, belts, and turbans for Aarons sons. These clothes will give them dignity and honor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.41'>»Dress your brother Aaron and his sons in these clothes and anoint them, ordain them, and set them apart to serve me as priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.42'>»Make linen undergarments to cover them down to their thighs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.43'>»Aaron and his sons must wear them when they go into the tent of meeting or when they come near the altar to serve as priests in the holy place. They will be blameless and will not die. This is a long lasting law for him and his descendants.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.29'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.1'>Jehovah also said: »This is what you must do in order to consecrate set Aaron and his sons apart to serve me as priests: Take a young bull that has no defects and two rams that have no defects.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.2'>»Use the best wheat flour to make some unleavened bread. Bake some with olive oil, some without it, and some in the form of thin cakes brushed with oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.3'>»Put them in a basket and offer them to me when you sacrifice the bull and the two rams.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.4'>»Bring Aaron and his sons to the entrance of the sacred tent of meeting and have them wash themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.5'>»Aaron should dress in the priestly shirt and robe under the sacred vest. Put on the vest, the breast piece, and the sash.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.6'>»Put on his turban with its narrow strip of engraved gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.7'>»Ordain him by pouring olive oil on his head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.8'>»Aarons sons should dress in their special shirts, caps and sashes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.9'>»Then ordain them, because they and their descendants will have a long lasting priesthood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.10'>»Lead the bull to the entrance of the sacred tent. Aaron and his sons will lay their hands on its head there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.11'>»Slaughter the bull near my altar in front of the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.12'>»Use a finger to smear some of its blood on each of the four corners of the altar. Pour out the rest of the blood on the ground next to the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.13'>»Take all the fat that covers the internal organs, the lobe of the liver, and the two kidneys with the fat on them, and burn them on the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.14'>»Burn the bulls meat, skin, and excrement outside the camp. It is an offering for sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.15'>»Take one of the rams and Aaron and his sons are to put their hands on its head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.16'>»Slaughter the ram. Take its blood and sprinkle it all around the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.17'>»Cut the ram in pieces. Wash its internal organs and its legs, and put them on top of the head and the other pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.18'>»Burn the whole ram on the altar. It is burnt offering to Jehovah. The odor of this offering pleases me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.19'>Take the other ram and Aaron and his sons are to put their hands on its head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.20'>»Kill it and take some of its blood and put it on the lobes of the right ears of Aaron and his sons, on the thumbs of their right hands and on the big toes of their right feet. Sprinkle the rest of the blood all around the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.21'>»Take some of the blood that is on the altar and some of the anointing oil, and sprinkle it on Aaron and his clothes and on his sons and their clothes. He, his sons, and their clothes will then be dedicated to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.22'>»Remove the rams fat, the fat tail, the fat covering the internal organs, the fat attached to the liver, the two kidneys with the fat on them, and the right thigh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.23'>»From the basket of bread which has been offered to me, take one loaf of each kind: one loaf made with olive oil and one made without it and one thin cake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.24'>»Put all this food in the hands of Aaron and his sons and have them dedicate it to me as a special gift.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.25'>»The meat and bread are to be placed on the altar and sent up in smoke with a smell before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.26'>»You may eat the choice breast from this second ram, but you must first lift them up to show that this meat is dedicated to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.27'>»You shall consecrate the breast of the wave offering and the thigh of the heave offering which was waved and which was offered from the ram of ordination, from the one that was for Aaron and from the one that was for his sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.28'>»It will be for Aaron and his sons as their long lasting portion from the sons of Israel. It is a heave offering. It will be a heave offering from the sons of Israel from the sacrifices of their peace offerings, even their heave offering to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.29'>»The holy garments of Aaron shall be for his sons after him. They may wear them when they are anointed and ordained.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.30'>»For seven days the one of his sons who is priest in his stead shall put them on when he enters the tent of meeting to minister in the holy place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.31'>»You shall take the ram of ordination and boil its flesh in a holy place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.32'>»Aaron and his sons shall eat the flesh of the ram and the bread that is in the basket, at the doorway of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.33'>»They shall eat those things used for their atonement and their ordination and consecration. A layman shall not eat them, because they are holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.34'>»If any of the flesh of ordination or any of the bread remains until morning it should be burned with fire. It should not be eaten because it is holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.35'>»Do to Aaron and to his sons all that I have commanded you. Ordain them for seven days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.36'>»Offer a bull as a sin offering for atonement each day. Purify the altar when you make atonement for it. Anoint it to consecrate it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.37'>»Make atonement for the altar and consecrate it for seven days. Then the altar shall be most holy, and whatever touches the altar shall be holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.38'>»Now this is what you shall offer on the altar: two one year old lambs each day, continuously.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.39'>»Offer one lamb in the morning and offer the other lamb at twilight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.40'>»Make an offering of eight cups of flour mixed with one quart of virgin olive oil with the first lamb. Offer one quart of wine for a drink offering with the other lamb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.41'>»You will offer the other lamb at twilight. Offer it with the same grain offering and the same drink offering as in the morning, for a soothing aroma, an offering by fire to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.42'>»It shall be a continual burnt offering throughout your generations at the doorway of the tent of meeting before Jehovah. That is where I will meet with you to speak to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.43'>»I will meet there with the sons of Israel, and it shall be consecrated by my glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.44'>»I will consecrate the tent of meeting and the altar. I will also consecrate Aaron and his sons to minister as priests to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.45'>»I will dwell among the sons of Israel and will be their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.46'>»They shall know that I am Jehovah their God who brought them out of the land of Egypt, that I might dwell among them. I am Jehovah their God!</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.30'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.1'>»Build an altar out of acacia wood for burning incense.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.2'>»Make it eighteen inches square and thirty-six inches high. The horns that extend out of it and the altar should be made out of one piece of wood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.3'>»Cover it all with pure gold, the top, the sides, and the horns. Put a gold molding around it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.4'>»Make two gold rings. Place them below the molding on opposite sides to hold the poles for carrying it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.5'>»Make the poles out of acacia wood. Cover them with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.6'>»Place the altar in front of the canopy that hangs over the ark containing the words of my covenant I will meet with you there in front of the throne of mercy that is on the ark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.7'>»Aaron must burn sweet incense on this altar every morning when he takes care of the lamps.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.8'>»When Aaron lights the lamps at dusk he must burn incense. An incense offering must burn smoke constantly in Jehovahs presence for generations to come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.9'>»Do not burn any unauthorized incense on this altar or any burnt offerings or grain offerings. Do not pour a wine offering on it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.10'>»Once a year Aaron must make atonement with Jehovah by putting blood on its horns. Once a year for generations to come blood from the offering must be placed on the altar to make atonement with Jehovah. It is most holy to Jehovah.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.11'>Jehovah again spoke to Moses:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.12'>»When you take a census of the people of Israel, each man is to pay me a price for his life. This to insure that no disaster will come on him while the census is being taken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.13'>»Everyone included in the census must pay the required amount of money. It should be weighed according to the official standard. Everyone must pay this as an offering to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.14'>»Every man being counted in the census who is twenty years old or older is to pay me this amount.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.15'>»The rich man is not to pay more. The poor man is not to pay less, when they pay this amount for their lives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.16'>»Collect this money from the people of Israel and spend it for the upkeep of the tent of meeting. This tax will be the payment for their lives. I will remember to protect them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.17'>Jehovah said to Moses:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.18'>»Make a copper basin with a bronze stand for washing. Put it between the tent of meeting and the altar, and fill it with water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.19'>»Aaron and his sons will use it for washing their hands and feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.20'>»Before they go into the tent of meeting, they must wash so that they will not die. Before they come near the altar to serve as priests and burn an offering by fire to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.21'>« They must wash their hands and feet, so that they will not die. This is a long lasting rule that they and their descendants are to observe.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.22'>Jehovah said to Moses:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.23'>»Take top quality spices: twelve pounds of liquid myrrh, six pounds of sweet-smelling cinnamon, six pounds of sweet-smelling cane,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.24'>and twelve pounds of cassia, according to the official standard. Add one gallon of olive oil,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.25'>and make sacred anointing oil, mixed like perfume.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.26'>»This is for dedicating the tent and chest,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.27'>the table with its equipment, the lamp stand with its equipment, the incense altar with all its utensils,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.28'>the altar for sacrifices, and the large bowl with its stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.29'>»You will make them so holy that anyone who even touches them will become holy when you dedicate them this way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.30'>»Sprinkle Aaron and his sons with this oil when you ordain them as my priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.31'>»Say this to the people of Israel: This oil must always be used in the ordination service of a priest. It is holy because it is dedicated to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.32'>»So treat it as holy! Do not use it for everyday purposes or mix any for yourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.33'>»If you do, you will no longer belong to Jehovahs people.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.34'>Jehovah said to Moses: »Take one part fragrant spices and two kinds of gum resin and aromatic mollusk shells, and mix them with one part pure frankincense.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.35'>»Have a perfumer make it into fragrant incense, seasoned with salt, pure and holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.36'>»Grind some of it into a fine powder. Put it in front of the ark containing the words of my covenant in the tent of meeting, where I will meet with you. You must treat it as most holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.37'>»Do not make any incense for yourselves using this formula. Treat it as holy to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.38'>»Anyone who prepares anything like it for his own enjoyment must be excluded from his people.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.31'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.1'>Jehovah said to Moses:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.2'>»I have called Bezalel, son of Uri and grandson of Hur, from the tribe of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.3'>»I filled him with the Spirit of God my power. I gave him understanding, skill, and ability for every kind of artistic work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.4'>»This is for planning skillful designs and working them in gold, silver, and copper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.5'>»It is also for cutting jewels to be set and for carving wood and for every other kind of artistic work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.6'>»I also appointed Oholiab, son of Ahisamach, from the tribe of Dan, to help him. I have given every craftsman the skill necessary to make what I have commanded you:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.7'>the tent of meeting, the ark containing the words of my covenant with the throne of mercy on it, and all the other furnishings for the tent,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.8'>the table and the dishes, the pure gold lamp stand and all its utensils, the altar for incense,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.9'>the altar for burnt offerings and all its accessories, the basin with its stand,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.10'>the special clothes the holy clothes for the priest Aaron and the clothes for his sons when they serve as priests,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.11'>the anointing oil, and the sweet incense for the holy place. They will make all these things as I commanded you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.12'>Jehovah also said to Moses:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.13'>»Speak to the people of Israel. Say: You must observe my Sabbaths. This is a sign between you and me throughout your generations that you may know that I am Jehovah, the one who sanctifies you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.14'>»You are to observe the Sabbath. It is holy to you. Everyone who profanes it will absolutely be put to death. Whoever does any work on it will be removed from his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.15'>»Work may be done for six days. The seventh day there is a Sabbath of complete rest. It is holy to Jehovah. Whoever does any work on the Sabbath day will definitely be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.16'>»The Israelites must observe the Sabbath and celebrate the Sabbath throughout their generations as a long lasting covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.17'>»It is a long lasting sign between the people of Israel and me for the reason that Jehovah made heaven and earth in six days. Then He ceased from work and was refreshed on the seventh day.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.18'>When God finished speaking to Moses on Mount Sinai, He gave him the two tablets of the testimony, tablets of stone, written by the finger of God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.32'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.1'>The people saw that Moses delayed coming down from the mountain. They gathered around Aaron. They said to him: »We do not know what has happened to Moses, the man who led us out of Egypt. Make gods to lead us.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.2'>Aaron replied: »Have your wives, sons, and daughters take off the gold earrings they are wearing. Bring them to me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.3'>The people took off their gold earrings and handed them to Aaron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.4'>After he worked on the gold with a tool, he made it into a statue of a calf. Then they said: »Israel, this is your god, who brought you out of Egypt.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.5'>Aaron built an altar in front of it when he saw what happened. Then he announced: »Tomorrow there will be a festival in Jehovahs honor.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.6'>Early the next day the people sacrificed burnt offerings and brought peace offerings. After that they sat down to a feast, which turned into an orgy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.7'>Jehovah said to Moses: »Go down there. Your people whom you brought out of Egypt have corrupted themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.8'>»They have already turned from the way I commanded them to live. They made a statue of a calf for themselves. They have bowed down to it and offered sacrifices to it. They said: »Israel, here is your god who brought you out of Egypt.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.9'>Jehovah added: »I have seen these people. They have an iron sinew stiff necked peopleare impossible to deal with.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.10'>»Now let me alone. Let my anger burn against them. I am so angry with them I am going to destroy them. Then I will make you into a great nation.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.11'>»But Moses pleaded with Jehovah his God. »Jehovah,« he said, »why are you so angry with your people? These are your people whom you brought out of Egypt using your great power and mighty hand!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.12'>»Do not let the Egyptians say: He was planning all along to kill them in the mountains and wipe them off the face of the earth. That is why he brought them out of our land. Do not be so angry. Reconsider your decision to bring this disaster on your people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.13'>»Remember your servants Abraham, Isaac, and Israel. You took an oath, swearing on yourself. You told them: I will make your descendants as numerous as the stars in the sky. I will give to your descendants all the land I spoke of. It will be their long lasting possession.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.14'>So Jehovah changed his mind and did not bring disaster on his people as he threatened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.15'>Moses went back down the mountain. He carried the two stone tablets with the commandments written on both sides.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.16'>God made the tablets and engraved the commandments on them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.17'>Joshua heard the people shouting and said to Moses: »I hear the sound of war in the camp.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.18'>Moses replied: »That does not sound like a shout of victory or a cry of defeat; it is the sound of singing.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.19'>Moses came close enough to the camp at the foot of the mountain to see the bull-calf and to see the people dancing. He became furious! He threw down the tablets he was carrying and broke them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.20'>He took the bull-calf that they had made, melted it, ground it into fine powder, and mixed it with water. Then he made the people of Israel drink it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.21'>Moses asked Aaron: »What did these people do to harm you? Why did you make them sin in this terrible way?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.22'>Aaron said, »Do not be angry with me. You know the people as well as I do. They are determined to do evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.23'>»They said to me: That man Moses led us out of Egypt, but now we do not know what has happened to him. Make us a god to lead us.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.24'>»Then I asked them to bring me their gold earrings. They took them off and gave them to me. I threw the gold into a fire, and out came this bull.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.25'>Moses saw that the people were naked. Aaron had made them naked to their shame among their enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.26'>Moses stood in the gate of the camp and said: »Who is on Jehovahs side? Come to me. All the sons of Levi came to him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.27'>He said to them, »Jehovah, the God of Israel says: Each man put his sword by his side. Go in and out from gate to gate throughout the camp. Kill each one his brother, and each one his neighbor, and each one his kindred.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.28'>The sons of Levi did according to the word of Moses. About three thousand men died that day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.29'>Moses said: »Today you are ordained as Jehovahs. God gave you a blessing today. Each of you fought with your own sons and brothers.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.30'>The next day Moses said to the people: »You have committed a serious sin. Now I will go up the mountain to Jehovah. Maybe I will be able to make a payment for your sin and make atonement with Jehovah for your sin.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.31'>So Moses went back to Jehovah and said: »These people have committed such a serious sin! They made a god out of gold for themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.32'>»Will you forgive their sin? If not, please wipe me out of the book you have written.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.33'>Jehovah answered Moses: »I will wipe out of my book whoever sins against me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.34'>»Now, go and lead the people to the place I told you about. My angel will go ahead of you. But on the day when I punish, I will punish them for their sin.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.35'>Jehovah killed people because they had Aaron make the calf.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.33'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.1'>Jehovah said to Moses: »You and the people you brought out of Egypt must leave this place. Go to the land I promised to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob with an oath, saying: I will give it to your descendants.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.2'>»I will send an angel ahead of you. I will force out the Canaanites, Amorites, Hittites, Perizzites, Hivites, and Jebusites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.3'>»Go to that land flowing with milk and honey. I will not be with you, because you are impossible to deal with. I would probably destroy you on the way.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.4'>The people heard this bad news and acted as if someone had died. No one wore any jewelry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.5'>Jehovah said to Moses: »Tell the Israelites: You are impossible to deal with. If I were with you, I might destroy you at any time. Take off your jewelry and I will decide what to do with you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.6'>The Israelites no longer wore their jewelry after they left Mount Horeb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.7'>Moses used to take a tent and set it up far outside the camp. He called it the tent of meeting. Anyone who was seeking Jehovahs will used to go outside the camp to the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.8'>Whenever Moses went out to the tent, all the people would rise and stand at the entrances to their tents and watch Moses until he went in.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.9'>After Moses entered, the pillar of cloud would come down and stay at the door of the Tent. Jehovah would speak to Moses from the cloud.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.10'>The people would bow down as soon they saw the pillar of cloud at the door of the Tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.11'>Jehovah would speak with Moses in person intimatelyface to face just as someone speaks with a friend. Moses would then return to the camp. But the young man who was his helper, Joshua son of Nun, stayed in the Tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.12'>Moses said to Jehovah: »It is true that you have told me to lead these people to that land, but you did not tell me whom you would send with me. You said that you know me well and are pleased with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.13'>If you are, tell me your plans, so that I may serve you and continue to please you. Remember also that you have chosen this nation to be your own.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.14'>Jehovah replied: »I will go with you and give you peace.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.15'>Moses said: »If you are not going with us, please do not make us leave this place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.16'>»If you do go with us, everyone will know that you are pleased with your people and with me. That way, we will be different from the rest of the people on earth.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.17'>Jehovah said to Moses: »I will do this thing of which you have spoken. You have found favor in my sight. I have known you by name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.18'>Then Moses said: Please show me your glory!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.19'>Jehovah said: »I will make all my goodness pass in front of you. I will call out my name, JEHOVAH. I will be kind to anyone I want to. I will be merciful to anyone I want to.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.20'>But he said: »You cannot see my face, because no one may see me and live.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.21'>Then Jehovah said: »Look, there is a place near me. Stand by this rocky cliff.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.22'>»When my glory passes by, I will put you in a crevice in the cliff and cover you with my hand until I have passed by.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.23'>»Then I will take my hand away, and you will see my back, but my face must not be seen.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.34'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.1'>Jehovah said to Moses: »Cut two more stone tablets like the first ones. I will write on them the words that were on the first tablets that you smashed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.2'>»Be ready in the morning. Come up on Mount Sinai and present yourself to me there on top of the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.3'>»No man may come with you or even be seen anywhere on the mountain. Even the flocks and herds may not graze in front of this mountain.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.4'>Moses cut two more stone tablets. Early the next morning he carried them up Mount Sinai, just as Jehovah commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.5'>Jehovah came down in a cloud and stood with him as Moses called upon the name of Jehovah!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.6'>Jehovah then passed in front of him and called out: »I, Jehovah, am a God who is full of compassion and pity. I am not easily angered and show great love and faithfulness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.7'>»I keep my promise for thousands of generations and forgive evil and sin. But I will not fail to punish children and grandchildren to the third and fourth generation for the sins of their fathers.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.8'>Moses hurried to bow low toward the earth and worship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.9'>He prayed: »Jehovah, if you really are pleased with me, I pray that you will go with us. It is true that these people are sinful and rebellious. However, please forgive our sin and let us be your people.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.10'>Jehovah said: »Behold! I offer a covenant promise to perform signs and miracles for you that have never been done in all the earth. Neighboring nations will stand in fear and know that I was the one who did these marvelous things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.11'>»I will force out the Amorites, the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites. You must do what I command you today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.12'>»Watch yourself that you make no covenant with the inhabitants of the land into which you are going. It will become a snare in your midst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.13'>»Instead tear down their altars and smash their sacred pillars and cut down their Asherim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.14'>»Do not worship any other god but Jehovah for his reputation is filled with zeal, and he is a God who demands exclusive devotion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.15'>Otherwise you might make a covenant with the inhabitants of the land. They would commit spiritual immorality fornication with their gods and sacrifice to their gods. Someone might invite you to eat of his sacrifice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.16'>»You might take some of his daughters for your sons, and his daughters might commit spiritual immorality fornication with their gods and cause your sons also to commit spiritual immorality with their gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.17'>»Do not make idol gods for yourself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.18'>»Celebrate the Festival of Unleavened Bread. As I commanded you, you must eat unleavened bread for seven days at the appointed time in the month of Abib. This is because in that month you came out of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.19'>»Every first male offspring is mine. The firstborn males of all your livestock, whether cattle, sheep, or goats are mine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.20'>»It will cost you a sheep or a goat to buy back the firstborn donkey. If you do not buy it back, then you must break the donkeys neck. You must buy back every firstborn of your sons. No one may come into my presence without an offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.21'>»You may work six days. On the seventh day you must not work. Even during the time of plowing or harvesting you must not work on this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.22'>»Celebrate the Festival of Weeks with the first grain from your wheat harvest. Celebrate the Festival of the Final Harvest at the end of the season.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.23'>»Three times a year all your men must come into the presence of the Sovereign Jehovah, the God of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.24'>»I will force nations out of your way and will expand your countrys borders. No one will want to take away your land while you are gone three times a year to Jehovahs festivals.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.25'>»Do not offer the blood of a sacrifice to me at the same time you offer anything containing yeast. No part of the sacrifice at the Passover festival should be left over in the morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.26'>»I am Jehovah your God! You must bring the first part of your harvest to the place of worship. Do not boil a young goat in its mothers milk.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.27'>Jehovah told Moses: »Put these laws in writing, as part of my agreement covenant with Israel.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.28'>Moses was there with Jehovah forty days and forty nights. He did not eat bread or drink water. He wrote on the tablets the words of the covenant, the Ten Commandments Ten Words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.29'>Moses came down from Mount Sinai. The two tablets of the testimony were in Moses hand as he came down from the mountain. Moses did not know that the skin of his face glowed because he spoke with God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.30'>Aaron and all the Israelites looked at Moses and saw his face glowing. They were afraid to come near him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.31'>Moses called to them. Aaron and all the leaders of the congregation came back to him. Then Moses spoke to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.32'>All the other Israelites came near him. He commanded them to do everything Jehovah told him on Mount Sinai.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.33'>Moses put a veil over his face when he finished speaking.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.34'>When Moses went into Jehovahs presence to speak with him, he took off the veil until he came out. When he came out and told the Israelites what he had been commanded,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.35'>they would see that Moses face was glowing. Moses would put the veil back on until he went in again to speak with Jehovah.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.35'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.1'>Moses assembled the whole Israelite congregation and said to them: »These are the things Jehovah commanded you to do:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.2'>»You may work for six days. The seventh day is a holy day of worship a Sabbath. It is a day when you do not work. It is dedicated to Jehovah. Whoever does any work on this day should be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.3'>»Do not light a fire in your homes on the Sabbath day.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.4'>Moses spoke to all the people of Israel: »This is what Jehovah has commanded:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.5'>Make an offering to Jehovah. Everyone who wishes to do so is to bring an offering of gold, silver, or copper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.6'>The offering could be of fine linen, blue, purple, and red wool; cloth made of goats hair;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.7'>rams skin dyed red, fine leather, acacia wood;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.8'>oil for the lamps, spices; balsam oil for the anointing oil and for the sweet incense.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.9'>The offering could also be carnelians and other jewels to be set in the High Priests ephod and in his breast piece.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.10'>All the skilled workers among you are to come and make everything that Jehovah commanded:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.11'>the Tent, its covering and its outer covering, its hooks and its frames, its crossbars, its posts, and its bases;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.12'>the Covenant Box, its poles, its lid, and the curtain to screen it off;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.13'>the table, its poles, and all its equipment; the bread offered to God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.14'>the lamp stand for the light and its equipment; the lamps with their oil;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.15'>the altar for burning incense and its poles; the anointing oil; the sweet incense; the curtain for the entrance of the Tent;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.16'>the altar on which to burn offerings, with its bronze grating attached, its poles, and all its equipment; the washbasin and its base;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.17'>the curtains for the enclosure, its posts and bases; the curtain for the entrance of the enclosure;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.18'>the Tent pegs and ropes for the Tent and the enclosure;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.19'>and the garments the priests are to wear when they serve in the Holy Place---the sacred clothes for Aaron the priest and for his sons.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.20'>Then the whole congregation of the people of Israel left Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.21'>Those who were willing and whose hearts moved them brought their contributions to Jehovah. The gifts were used to construct the tent of meeting, to pay other expenses, and to make the holy clothes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.22'>All willing, men and women alike, brought all kinds of gold jewelry: pins, brooches, earrings, signet rings, and pendants. They offered these gifts of gold to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.23'>Those who had violet, purple, or bright red yarn, fine linen, goats hair, rams skins dyed red, or fine leather brought them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.24'>Those who could give silver or copper brought it as their contribution to Jehovah. Those who had acacia wood that could be used in the construction brought it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.25'>All the skilled women brought fine linen thread and thread of blue, purple, and red wool, which they made.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.26'>They also made thread of goats hair.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.27'>The leaders brought different kinds of jewels to be sewn on the special clothes and the breast piece for the high priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.28'>And the spice and the oil for the light, and the holy anointing oil and the sweet perfume balsam oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.29'>The people of Israel, every man and woman whose hearts were willing, gave their offerings freely to Jehovah. This was for the work that Jehovah gave Moses orders to have done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.30'>Then Moses said to the sons of Israel: »Jehovah has called by name Bezalel son of Uri son of Hur of the tribe of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.31'>»He has filled him with the Spirit of God, in wisdom, in understanding and in knowledge and in all craftsmanship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.32'>»He is a master artist familiar with gold, silver, and copper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.33'>»He knows how to cut and set stones and how to work with wood. He is an expert in all trades.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.34'>»Jehovah also gave Bezalel and Oholiab, son of Ahisamach, from the tribe of Dan the ability to teach others.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.35'>»Jehovah made these men highly skilled in all trades. They can do the work of jewelers, carpenters, and designers. They know how to embroider violet, purple and bright red yarn on fine linen. They know how to weave yarn on a loom. They can do all kinds of trades. They are master artists.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.36'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.1'>Moses continued speaking: »Bezalel and Oholiab will do the work as Jehovah commanded. They will do this with the help of every other craftsman to whom Jehovah has given the necessary skills and talents. They will know how to do all the work for constructing the holy place.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.2'>Moses called Bezalel and Oholiab and every craftsman to whom Jehovah gave these skills and who was willing to come and do the work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.3'>Moses provided them with all the contributions the Israelites brought for the work of constructing the holy place. Plus, the people still kept bringing him voluntary freewill offerings every morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.4'>Then the skilled men who were doing the work went</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.5'>to Moses. They said: »The people are bringing more than is needed for the work Jehovah commanded to be done.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.6'>Moses sent a command throughout the camp, saying: »No one is to make any further contribution for the sacred Tent.« So the people did not bring any more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.7'>What had already been brought was sufficient to finish all the work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.8'>The most skilled men among those doing the work made the Tent of Jehovahs presence. They made it out of ten pieces of fine linen woven with blue, purple, and red wool and embroidered with figures of winged creatures.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.9'>Each curtain was forty-two feet long and six feet wide. They were all the same size.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.10'>Five of the curtains were sewn together. The other five were also sewn together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.11'>They made fifty violet loops along the edge of the end curtain in each set.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.12'>They placed the loops opposite sides of each other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.13'>They also made fifty gold fasteners. They used them to link the two sets of curtains together so that the inner tent was a single unit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.14'>Eleven curtains were made of goats hair to form an outer tent over the inner tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.15'>Each of the eleven curtains was forty-five feet long and six feet wide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.16'>Five of the curtains were sewn together into one set, and the remaining six into another set.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.17'>They made fifty loops along the edge of the end curtain in each set.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.18'>Fifty bronze fasteners were also made to link the inner tent together as a single unit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.19'>They made a cover out of rams skins that had been dyed red for the outer tent, and over that they put a cover made of fine leather.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.20'>A framework for the inner tent was made out of acacia wood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.21'>Each frame was fifteen feet long and twenty-seven inches wide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.22'>Each had two identical pegs. They made all the frames for the inner tent this same way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.23'>They made twenty frames for the south side of the inner tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.24'>Then they made forty silver sockets placed at the bottom of the twenty frames. There were two sockets at the bottom of each frame for the two pegs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.25'>Twenty frames were also made for the north side of the inner tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.26'>Forty silver sockets were prepared with two at the bottom of each frame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.27'>They made six frames for the far end, the west side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.28'>They made two frames for each of the corners at the far end of the inner tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.29'>They were held together at the bottom and held tightly at the top by a single ring. Both corner frames were made this way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.30'>There were eight frames with sixteen silver sockets. There were two at the bottom of each frame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.31'>They also made crossbars out of acacia wood. Five were for the frames on one side of the inner tent,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.32'>five were for those on the other side, and five were for the frames on the far side of the inner tent, the west side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.33'>The middle crossbar was made so that it ran from one end to the other, halfway up the frames.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.34'>They covered the frames with gold and made gold rings to hold the crossbars. They also covered the crossbars with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.35'>They made the canopy out of violet, purple, and bright red yarn and fine linen yarn. A cherubim angel design was creatively worked into the fabric.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.36'>Four posts of acacia wood were prepared for it. They covered them with gold. They made gold hooks for the posts. They cast four silver bases for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.37'>They made a screen out of fine linen yarn for the entrance to the outer tent. It was embroidered with violet, purple, and bright red yarn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.38'>They also made five posts with hooks for hanging the screen. They covered the tops of the posts and the bands with gold. The five bases for the posts were made of copper.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.37'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.1'>Bezalel made the ark out of acacia wood forty-five inches long, twenty-seven inches wide, and twenty-seven inches high.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.2'>He covered it with pure gold inside and out and put a gold molding around it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.3'>He cast four gold rings for its four feet, two rings on each side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.4'>The carrying poles he made with acacia wood. He covered them with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.5'>Then he put them through the rings that were on each side of the Ark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.6'>He made a lid of pure gold, forty-five inches long and twenty-seven inches wide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.7'>He made two cherubim of hammered gold,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.8'>one for each end of the lid. He made them so that they formed one piece with the lid, one cherub at each end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.9'>The cherubim had their wings spread upward. They covered the mercy seat with their wings. The faces of the cherubim were toward the mercy seat and toward each other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.10'>He made the table of acacia wood. It was thirty-six inches long and eighteen inches wide and twenty-seven inches high.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.11'>He covered it with pure gold, and made a gold molding that went all around it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.12'>The rim he made for it was a handbreadth all around. He also made gold molding all around it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.13'>He cast four gold rings for it and put the rings on the four corners that were on its four feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.14'>The rings were put close to the rim to hold the poles for carrying the table.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.15'>These poles were made out of acacia wood and were covered with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.16'>He made plates, dishes, bowls, and pitchers to be used for pouring wine offerings on the table. All of them were made out of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.17'>He made the lamp stand out of pure gold. The lamp stand, its base, and its shaft, as well as the flower cups, buds, and petals were hammered out of one piece of gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.18'>There were three branches on each of its two sides, for a total of six branches.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.19'>There were three decorative almond blossoms on each branch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.20'>And there were four on the lamp stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.21'>A blossom was placed where each pair of branches came out from the lamp stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.22'>The lamp stand, including its branches and decorative flowers, was made from a single piece of hammered pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.23'>He made seven its seven lamps including the snuffers and fire trays out of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.24'>The lamp stand and all the utensils were made out of seventy-five pounds of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.25'>He made an altar out of acacia wood for burning incense. It was eighteen inches square and thirty-six inches high. The horns and altar were made out of one piece of wood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.26'>All of it was covered with pure gold, the top, the sides, and the horns. He put a gold molding around it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.27'>He made two gold rings and put them below the molding on opposite sides to hold the poles for carrying it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.28'>Then the poles were made out of acacia wood and covered with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.29'>A perfumer made the holy oil to be used for anointing and for the pure, sweet incense.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.38'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.1'>He made the altar for burnt offerings out of acacia wood seven and one half feet square and four and one half feet high.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.2'>Then he placed a horn at each of its four corners. He made the four horns and the altar out of one piece of wood covered with copper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.3'>He also made all the equipment for the altar: the pans, the shovels, the bowls, the hooks, and the fire pans. All this equipment was made of copper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.4'>A copper grating was also made. It was placed under the rim of the altar, so that it reached halfway up the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.5'>A copper ring was attached beneath the ledge at the four corners to put the poles through.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.6'>After that he covered two acacia wood poles with copper and</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.7'>put them through the rings for carrying the altar, which was shaped like an open box.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.8'>He made the laver basin of copper with its base of copper, from the mirrors of the serving women who served at the doorway of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.9'>He made the courtyard. The south side curtains of the courtyard were fine twisted linen, one hundred and fifty feet long.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.10'>The courtyard had twenty pillars, and twenty sockets, made of copper. The hooks of the pillars and their bands were of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.11'>The north side was also one hundred and fifty feet long with twenty posts and twenty copper bases. The hooks and bands on the posts were made of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.12'>The west side was seventy-five feet long. It had curtains hung on ten posts set in ten bases. The hooks and bands on the posts were made of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.13'>The entrance was on the east side. The enclosure was also twenty-five yards wide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.14'>The curtains for the gate were twenty-two and one half feet long, with their three pillars and their three sockets,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.15'>There were seven and one half yards of curtains with three posts and three bases on each side of the entrance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.16'>The curtains around the courtyard were all made out of fine linen yarn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.17'>The bases for the posts were made of copper. The hooks and bands on the posts were made of silver. The tops of the posts were covered with silver. And the bands on all the posts of the courtyard were made of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.18'>The screen for the entrance to the courtyard was made of violet, purple, and bright red yarn embroidered on fabric made from fine linen yarn. It was thirty feet long and seven and one half feet high, just like the curtains of the courtyard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.19'>The screen hung on four posts set in four copper bases. The hooks and bands on the posts were made of silver. The tops of the posts were covered with silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.20'>The pegs for the tent and the surrounding courtyard were made of copper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.21'>This is the inventory of the tent, the Tent of Testimony. An inventory was ordered by Moses and carried out by the Levites under the direction of Ithamar, son of the priest Aaron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.22'>Bezalel, son of Uri and grandson of Hur, from the tribe of Judah, made everything Jehovah commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.23'>Bezalel was a jeweler, carpenter, designer, and he knew how to embroider violet, purple, and bright red yarn on fine linen. His assistant was Oholiab, son of Ahisamach, from the tribe of Dan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.24'>All the gold from the offerings presented to Jehovah used in building the holy place weighed over two thousand one hundred and ninety three pounds using the standard weight of the holy place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.25'>The silver collected when the census of the community was taken weighed seven thousand five hundred and forty four pounds using the standard weight of the holy place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.26'>This amounted to one-fifth of an ounce per person, for everyone counted who was at least twenty years old. There were six hundred and three thousand five hundred and fifty people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.27'>He used seven thousand five hundred pounds of silver to cast the one hundred bases for the holy place and the canopy. That came to seventy-five pounds per base.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.28'>Bezalel used forty-four pounds of silver to make the hooks and bands for the posts and the coverings for the tops of the posts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.29'>The offerings presented to Jehovah weighted five thousand three hundred and ten pounds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.30'>He used this to make the bases for the entrance to the tent of meeting, the copper altar with its copper grate and all its accessories,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.31'>the bases all around the courtyard, the bases for the entrance to the courtyard, all the pegs for the tent, and all the pegs for the surrounding courtyard.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.39'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.1'>From the violet, purple, and bright red yarn they made special clothes worn for official duties in the holy place. They also made the holy clothes for Aaron. They obeyed Jehovahs instructions to Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.2'>The ephod was made out of fine linen yarn and gold, violet, purple, and bright red yarn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.3'>The gold was hammered into thin sheets and cut up. They twisted the gold into threads, which they creatively worked into each strand of the violet, purple, and bright red yarn, and throughout the fine linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.4'>From this they made two shoulder straps for the ephod and attached them to its sides, so that it could be fastened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.5'>The finely woven belt, made of the same materials, was attached to the ephod so as to form one piece with it. This was as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.6'>They prepared the carnelians and mounted them in gold settings. They were skillfully engraved with the names of the twelve sons of Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.7'>They placed them on the shoulder straps of the ephod to represent the twelve tribes of Israel. Again, this was just as Jehovah commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.8'>The breast piece was made of the same materials as the ephod and with similar embroidery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.9'>It was square and folded double, nine inches long and nine inches wide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.10'>They mounted four rows of precious stones on it. Ruby was mounted on the first row along with topaz, and garnet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.11'>Included in the second row was an emerald, a sapphire, and a diamond.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.12'>The third row contained a turquoise, an agate, and an amethyst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.13'>The fourth row contained a beryl, a carnelian, and jasper. These were mounted in gold settings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.14'>Each of the twelve stones had engraved on it the name of one of the sons of Jacob, in order to represent the twelve tribes of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.15'>They made chains out of pure gold, twisted like ropes. These were for the breastplate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.16'>Two gold settings and two gold rings were prepared and attached, the two rings to the top two corners of the breast piece.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.17'>They fastened the two gold ropes to the rings at the top corners of the breastplate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.18'>They fastened the other ends of the ropes to the two settings on the shoulder straps of the ephod. The breastplate hung in front of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.19'>They made two gold rings and fastened them to the other two corners of the breast piece on the inside edge next to the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.20'>They made two more gold rings and fastened them to the bottom of the shoulder straps on the front of the ephod. This was close to the seam just above the belt of the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.21'>Finally they fastened the breast piece by its rings to the rings of the ephod with a violet cord. So the breast piece was attached just above the belt of the ephod and was held in place. They followed Jehovahs instructions to Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.22'>They made the robe that is worn with the ephod. It was woven entirely of violet yarn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.23'>The opening in the center of the robe had a finished edge, somewhat like a leather collar, all around it to keep it from tearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.24'>On the hem of the robe they made pomegranates of violet, purple, and bright red yarn, and fine yarn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.25'>Bells were made out of pure gold. They were fastened in between the pomegranates all around the hem of the robe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.26'>A gold bell alternated with a pomegranate all around the hem of the robe that is worn by Aaron when he served as priest. They followed Jehovahs instructions to Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.27'>They wove inner robes out of fine linen for Aaron and his sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.28'>They also made the chief priests turban and the other beautiful turbans out of fine linen. They made the undergarments and belt out of fine linen yarn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.29'>The belt was embroidered with violet, purple, and bright red yarn. They followed Jehovahs instructions to Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.30'>The flower-shaped medallion, the holy crown, was fashioned out of pure gold. The statement: HOLY TO JEHOVAH was engraved on it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.31'>They fastened a violet cord to it and tied it on top of the turban. They followed Jehovahs instructions to Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.32'>So all the work on the inner tent of the tent of meeting was now done. The Israelites obeyed all Jehovahs instructions to Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.33'>They brought everything to Moses: the inner tent, the outer tent and all its furnishings, the fasteners, frames, crossbars, posts, sockets,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.34'>the cover made of rams skins dyed red, the cover made of fine leather, the canopy over the Ark,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.35'>the Ark containing the words of Gods covenant with its poles and the throne of mercy,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.36'>the table with all the dishes, the bread of the presence,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.37'>the pure gold lamp stand with its lamps in a row and all its utensils, the olive oil for the lamps,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.38'>the gold altar, the anointing oil, the sweet incense, the screen for the entrance to the tent,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.39'>the copper altar with its copper grate, its poles, and all its accessories, the basin with its stand,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.40'>the curtains for the courtyard, the posts, bases, and screen for the entrance to the courtyard, the ropes and pegs, all the equipment needed for the service of the inner tent for tent of meeting;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.41'>the special clothes worn when serving as priests in the holy place, both the holy clothes for the priest Aaron and the clothes for his sons when serving as priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.42'>The Israelites did all the work according to Jehovahs instructions to Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.43'>Moses inspected all the work. He saw that they had followed Jehovahs instructions. So Moses blessed them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.40'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.1'>Jehovah said to Moses:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.2'>»Set up the tabernacle of the tent of meeting on the first day of the first month of the year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.3'>»Place the Ark containing the words of my covenant inside it, and hang the canopy over the ark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.4'>»Bring in the table and place the equipment on it. Also bring the lamp stand and set up the lamps on it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.5'>»Put the gold altar for burning incense in front of the Covenant Box and hang the curtain at the entrance of the Tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.6'>»Place the altar for burning offerings in front of the Tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.7'>»Set the washbasin between the Tabernacle and the altar and fill it with water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.8'>»Put up the surrounding enclosure and hang the curtain at its entrance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.9'>»Then dedicate the Tabernacle and all its equipment by anointing it with the sacred oil, and it will be holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.10'>»Dedicate the altar and all its equipment by anointing it, and it will be completely holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.11'>»Also dedicate the washbasin and its base in the same way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.12'>»Bring Aaron and his sons to the entrance of the Tabernacle, and have them take a ritual bath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.13'>»Dress Aaron in the priestly garments and anoint him. Consecrate him so that he can serve me as priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.14'>»Bring his sons and put the shirts on them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.15'>»Anoint them just as you anointed their father that they can serve me as priests. This anointing will make them priests for generations to come.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.16'>Moses did everything just as Jehovah commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.17'>The Tent of Jehovahs presence was set up on the first day of the first month of the second year after they left Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.18'>When Moses set up the tent, he put the sockets in place, put up the frames, inserted the crossbars, and set up the posts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.19'>He spread the outer tent over the inner tent and put the cover on top. Moses followed Jehovahs instructions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.20'>He took the words of Gods promise covenant and put them in the ark. He put the poles on the ark and placed the throne of mercy on top of the ark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.21'>Then he brought the ark into the tent and hung the canopy over it to mark off where the ark was. Moses followed Jehovahs instructions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.22'>Moses put the table in the tent of meeting on the north side of the tent outside the canopy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.23'>He arranged the bread on the table in Jehovahs presence, following Jehovahs instructions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.24'>He placed the lamp stand in the tent of meeting opposite the table, on the south side of the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.25'>He set the lighted lamps in Jehovahs presence, following Jehovahs instructions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.26'>Moses put the gold altar in the tent of meeting in front of the canopy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.27'>He burned sweet incense on it, following Jehovahs instructions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.28'>Then he put up the screen at the entrance to the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.29'>He put the altar for burnt offerings at the entrance to the tabernacle of the tent of meeting. He sacrificed burnt offerings and grain offerings on it. Moses followed Jehovahs instructions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.30'>He put the basin between the tent of meeting and the altar and put water in it for washing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.31'>Moses, Aaron, and his sons used this water to wash their hands and feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.32'>They washed whenever they went into the tent of meeting or whenever they approached the altar. Moses obeyed Jehovahs instructions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.33'>He set up the courtyard around the tent and the altar and put up the screen at the entrance to the courtyard. At last Moses finished the work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.34'>The column of smoke then covered the tent of meeting. The glory of Jehovah filled the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.35'>Moses could not go into the tent of meeting because the smoke settled on it and the glory of Jehovah filled the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.36'>In all their travels, when the column of smoke moved from the tent, the Israelites would break camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.37'>But if the column did not move, they would not break camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.38'>Jehovahs column of smoke stayed over the tent during the day. There was fire in the smoke at night. This way all the Israelites could see the column throughout their travels.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>