<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisIDWork='NSB' osisRefWork='Bible' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='NSB'>
        <title>New Simplified Bible</title>
        <contributor>xxx</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>The New Simplified Bible is not affiliated with any Bible publishing society or religious organization. It is not related to the publishing and preaching work of Jehovah's Witnesses and it is not endorsed by the Watch Tower Society.</description>
        <publisher>Jim Madsen, NSB</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>NSB</identifier>
        <source>http://www.geocities.com/simplifiedbible/index.html - the Word-Files</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>
used by Permission from Jim Madsen, NSB, 
when distribute them as long as they
are offered free of charge

New Simplified Bible
All Rights Reserved Worldwide
Copyright (c) 2003-2006

     </rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Jer'>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.1'>
        <title>(Writer: Jeremiah, means Jehovah Exalts) (580 B.C.E.)</title>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.1'>The words of Jeremiah, son of Hilkiah. He was one of the priests at Anathoth in the territory of Benjamin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.2'>Jehovah spoke his word to Jeremiah. This happened when King Josiah, son of Amon, was in his thirteenth year as king of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.3'>Jehovah also spoke when Jehoiakim, son of Josiah, was king of Judah. It was during the eleven years that Zedekiah, another son of Josiah, was king of Judah. Jehovah continued to speak to Jeremiah until the people of Jerusalem were taken away into captivity in the fifth month of the year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.4'>Jehovah spoke his word to me, Jeremiah, He said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.5'>»Before I formed you in the womb, I knew you. Before you were born, I set you apart for my holy purpose. I appointed you to be a prophet to the nations.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.6'>I, Jeremiah, said: »Lord Jehovah, I do not know how to speak. I am only a child!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.7'>Jehovah said to me: »Do not say, I am only a child. You must go wherever I send you. You must say whatever I command you to say.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.8'>»Do not be afraid of people. I am with you. I will rescue you,« says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.9'>Then Jehovah stretched out his hand and touched my mouth. Jehovah said to me: »I have put my words in your mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.10'>»Today I have appointed you in charge of nations and kingdoms. You will uproot and tear down. You will destroy and overthrow. You will build and plant.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.11'>Jehovah spoke his word to me again. He asked: »What do you see Jeremiah?« I answered: »I see a branch of an almond tree.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.12'>Jehovah said: »You are right. For I watch to make sure that my words come true.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.13'>Again Jehovah asked: »What do you see?« I answered: »I see a boiling pot, and its top is tilted away from the north.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.14'>Jehovah said to me: »Disaster will be poured out from the north on all those who live in the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.15'>»I am going to call every family and kingdom from the north, says Jehovah. They will come, and they will set up their thrones at the entrance of Jerusalem's gates. They will attack all the walls around the city and all the cities of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.16'>»I will pronounce judgment against my people because of all their wickedness. They abandoned me. They burned incense to other gods. They worshiped what their hands have made.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.17'>»Strengthen yourself, Jeremiah! Stand up, and say to them whatever I tell you to say. Do not be terrified in their presence, or I will make you even more terrified in their presence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.18'>»Today I have made you like a fortified city, an iron pillar, and a copper wall. You will be able to stand up to the whole land. You will be able to stand up to Judah's kings, its officials, its priests, and all the common people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.1.19'>»They will fight you but they will not defeat you. I am with you, and I will rescue you,« declares Jehovah.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.2'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.1'>Jehovah spoke his word to me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.2'>»Go and announce to Jerusalem, This is what Jehovah says: »I remember the unfailing loyalty of your youth, the love you had for me as a bride. I remember how you followed me into the desert, into a land that was not sown farmed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.3'>»»Israel was dedicated consecrated to Jehovah. It was the best part of the harvest. All who consumed it became guilty, and disaster struck them,« « says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.4'>Listen to the word of Jehovah, offspring of Jacob, all the families in the house of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.5'>Jehovah says: »What bad thing injustice did your fathers find in me that they went so far away from me? They followed worthless idols and became worthless lead astray themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.6'>»They did not ask: Where is Jehovah who brought us from Egypt? He led us through the desert, through a wasteland and its pits, a land of drought and the shadow of death. No one lives there or travels there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.7'>»I brought you into a fertile land to eat its fruit and its produce. You came and made my land unclean. You made my heritage disgusting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.8'>»The priests did not ask: Where is Jehovah? Those who deal with my Law did not know me. The rulers rebelled against me. The prophets prophesied in the name of Baal and followed things that could not help profit them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.9'>»That is why I will bring charges against you, proclaims Jehovah, and I will bring charges against your grandchildren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.10'>»Go over to the coasts of Cyprus Kittim, and see. Send someone to Kedar and observe closely. See if there has ever been such a thing as this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.11'>»Has any nation ever exchanged gods? Their gods are not really gods. Yet my people have exchanged their glory for something that does not help them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.12'>»Be horrified over this, heaven. Be terribly afraid,« declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.13'>»My people have done two things wrong: l They have abandoned me, the fountain source of living waters. They have dug their own cisterns, broken cisterns that cannot hold water. (Revelation 4:11)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.14'>»Are the people of Israel slaves? Were they born into slavery? Why, then, have they become someone's property?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.15'>»Young lions have roared at them. Young lions have turned the land into waste. The cities have been destroyed, without inhabitant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.16'>»Men from Noph Memphis, capital city of Egypt and Tahpanhes have shaved the crown of your head, Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.17'>»You have done this to yourself by abandoning Jehovah your God when he led you on his way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.18'>»Why are you going to Egypt to drink water from the Nile Shihor River? You will not gain anything by going to Assyria to drink water from the Euphrates River.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.19'>»Your own wickedness will correct you. Your apostasies unfaithful ways will punish you! You should know and see how evil and bitter it is for you when you abandon Jehovah your God! You do not respect reverence me,« says the Sovereign Lord Jehovah of Hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.20'>»Long ago you broke off your yoke, tore off your bonds, and said that you would not be a slave. You lay down and acted like a prostitute on every high hill and under every large tree.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.21'>»I planted you like a choice grapevine from the very best seed. Now you have turned against me and have become a wild vine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.22'>»If you wash with detergent and use a lot of soap, I would still see the stains from your wickedness,« says the Lord Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.23'>»How can you say, I have not been dishonored and have not gone after the Baal gods? »Look how you have behaved in the valley. Acknowledge what you have done. You are like a young camel that swiftly runs here and there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.24'>»You are like a wild donkey accustomed to the desert. You sniff at the wind while in heat. All who seek you will not get tired. They will find you during your monthly period.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.25'>»Do not run until your feet are bare and your throats are dry. But you say that it is useless. You love foreign gods and follow them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.26'>»As a thief feels ashamed when he is caught, so the nation of Israel will feel ashamed. Their kings, princes, priests, and prophets will also feel ashamed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.27'>»You call wood your father. You call stone your mother. You turned your backs, not your faces, to me. But when you are in trouble, you ask me to come and rescue you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.28'>»Where are the gods that you made for yourselves? Let them come and rescue you when you have trouble. You have as many gods as you have cities, Judah!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.29'>»Why do you complain about me? You have rebelled against me,« proclaims Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.30'>»I have punished your children without results. They did not respond to correction. You killed my prophets like a raging lion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.31'>»O you people of this generation consider the word of Jehovah! Have I been a wilderness, a land of thick darkness, for Israel? Why do my people say that they are free to wander around and no longer come to me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.32'>»A young woman cannot forget her jewelry or a bride her breastband sashgirdle. Yet, my people have forgotten me for countless days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.33'>»You carefully planned ways to look for love. You taught your ways to wicked women.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.34'>»You have bloodstains from innocent poor people on your clothes. You did not kill them for breaking in to your home.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.35'>»After all this you say: I am innocent. God will turn his anger from me. For I have not sinned.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.36'>»You change your mind so easily. You will be shamed by Egypt as you were shamed by Assyria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.2.37'>»You will also leave this place with your hands over your head, because Jehovah has rejected those you trust. They will not help you.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.3'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.1'>It is said: »If a man divorces his wife and she leaves him and marries another man, her first husband should not go back to her again.« The land would become completely polluted. »You have behaved like a prostitute who has many lovers. Now you want to come back to me!« Says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.2'>»Lift up your eyes to the bare hills and see. You have had sex with men in every place. You sat by the roadside waiting for them like a nomad in the desert. You have defiled corruptedprofaned the land with your prostitution and wickedness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.3'>»Accordingly the rain has been withheld, and there have been no spring showers. Yet, you have the unashamed conspicuousimpudent look of a prostitute, and you refuse to be ashamed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.4'>»Now you call to me. You say, Father! »You have been my friend ever since I was young.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.5'>»Will you hold a grudge forever? Will you always be angry? You have said and done all the evil things that you could.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.6'>During the reign of King Josiah, Jehovah asked me: »Did you see what unfaithful Israel did? She went up every high mountain and under every large tree, and she acted like a prostitute there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.7'>»I thought that after she had done all this she would come back to me. But she did not come back, and her treacherous unstableunreliablefalse sister Judah saw her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.8'>»Judah saw that I sent unfaithful Israel away because of her adultery and that I gave Israel her divorce papers. But treacherous Judah, her sister, was not afraid. She also acted like a prostitute.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.9'>»Because she was not concerned about her prostitution. She polluted the land and committed adultery with stone and wood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.10'>»Even after all this, Israel's treacherous sister Judah did not return to me with all her heart. She was deceitful,« says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.11'>Jehovah said to me: »Treacherous Judah was more reprehensible than unfaithful Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.12'>»Go and proclaim this message to the north: Come back, unfaithful Israel. It is Jehovah speaking. I will no longer frown on you because I am merciful, declares Jehovah. I will no longer be angry with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.13'>Admit that you have done wrong! You have rebelled against Jehovah your God. You have given yourself to foreign gods under every large tree. You have not obeyed me, says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.14'>Return, you disobedient people, proclaims Jehovah. I am your husband. I will take you, one from every city and two from every family, and bring you to Zion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.15'>»I will give you shepherds after my own heart. They will be shepherds who feed shepherdleadtend you with knowledge and understanding learningreasoninginsight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.16'>»In those days you will be fertile, and your population will increase in the land, says Jehovah. Men will no longer talk about the Ark of the Covenant of Jehovah. It will no longer come to mind. They will not remember it, miss it, or make another one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.17'>»At that time, they will call Jerusalem the throne of Jehovah. All nations will gather in Jerusalem because the name of Jehovah will be found there. They will no longer follow their own stubborn, evil ways.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.18'>»Then the nation of Judah will live with the nation of Israel. They will come together from the land of the north to the land that I gave their ancestors as their own inheritance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.19'>»I wanted to treat you like children and give you a pleasant land, the most beautiful property among the nations. I thought you would call me Father and not turn away from me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.20'>»But like a wife who is unfaithful to her husband, so you, O house of Israel, were unfaithful me,« says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.21'>A voice is heard on the bare hills. It is the crying and the pleading of the people of Israel. They are perverted and have forgotten Jehovah their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.22'>»Return you backsliding children, and I will forgive you for being unfaithful. See, we have come to you because you are Jehovah our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.23'>»Truly the sound from the hills and mountains is the noise of false worship. Truly Jehovah our God will be our salvation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.24'>»Ever since we were young, the shameful worship of Baal has taken everything our ancestors worked for, their flocks and herds, their sons and daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.3.25'>»We must lie down in our shame and let our humiliation cover us. Ever since we were young, we and our fathers have sinned against Jehovah our God. We have not obeyed Jehovah our God.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.4'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.1'>Jehovah says: »If you come back, Israel, if you come back to me, if you take your disgusting idols out of my sight and you do not stray from me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.2'>if you take the oath, as Jehovah lives in an honest, fair, and right way, then the nations will be blessed, and in him they will glory.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.3'>Jehovah says to the people of Judah and to Jerusalem: »Break up your unplowed fields, and do not plant among thorns.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.4'>»Be circumcised by Jehovah, and get rid of the foreskins of your hearts cleanse your hearts, people of Judah and inhabitants of Jerusalem. If you do not, my fury will blaze like a fire. It will burn, and no one will be able to put it out. This is because of the evil you do.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.5'>Report this message in Judah. Make it heard in Jerusalem. Say: »Blow the ram's horn throughout the land. Shout loudly and say: Assemble together! Let us go into the fortified cities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.6'>»Raise the flag to signal people to go to Zion. Take cover! Do not just stand there! I am bringing disaster and widespread destruction from the north.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.7'>»A lion has come out of its lair. A destroyer of nations has set out. He has left his place and is on his way to destroy your land. Your cities will be ruined. No one will live in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.8'>»Dress in sackcloth, beat your breasts mourn, and cry because Jehovahs burning anger has not turned back from us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.9'>»In that day,« declares Jehovah, »the king and the officials will lose their courage. The priests will be stunned. The prophets will be amazed and astonished.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.10'>I said, »Lord Jehovah, you have greatly deceived these people and Jerusalem. You said that everything would go well for them, but a sword is held at their throats threatens their lives.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.11'>Then it will be said to these people and to Jerusalem: »A hot wind from the heights will blow in the desert toward my people. It will not be a wind that winnows or cleanses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.12'>»It will be a stronger wind than that. It will come from me. Now, I will pass sentence on them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.13'>»The enemy comes up like clouds. His chariots are like a raging wind. His horses are swifter than eagles. How horable it will be for us! We will be destroyed!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.14'>»O Jerusalem, wash the evil from your heart so that you may be saved. How long will your wicked thoughts lodge within you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.15'>»A message is heard from Dan. A report of disaster comes from the mountains of Ephraim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.16'>»Warn the nations about this. Tell it to Jerusalem. Hostile troops are coming from a distant country. They shout battle cries against the cities of Judah.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.17'>»They surround Judah like men guarding a field, because Judah has rebelled against me,« declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.18'>»You brought this on yourself. This is your punishment. It is bitter. It breaks your heart.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.19'>O my anguish, my anguish! I writhe in pain. My heart pounds in side of me. My heart is pounding! I cannot keep quiet because I hear a ram's horn sounding the alarm for war.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.20'>Destruction upon destruction is proclaimed. The whole land is ruined. My tents are suddenly destroyed. Their curtains are torn in an instant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.21'>How long must I see the battle flag and hear the sound of rams' horns?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.22'>»My people are fools. They do not know me. They are stupid people. They do not understand. They are experts in doing wrong, and they do not know how to do good.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.23'>I see the earth. It is without form and empty. I see the sky. Its lights are gone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.24'>I see the mountains. They tremble and the hills sway.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.25'>I see that there are no people, and every bird has flown away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.26'>I see that the fertile land has become a desert. Its cities are torn down because of Jehovah and his burning anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.27'>Jehovah says: »The whole earth will be ruined, although I will not entirely destroy it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.28'>»The earth will mourn, and the sky will grow black. I have spoken, and I have determined it. I will not change my plans, and I will not turn back!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.29'>All the people in the city will flee at the sound of riders and archers. They will go off into the thickets and climb among the rocks. The entire city will be abandoned. No one will live in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.30'>You are going to be destroyed! What are you going to do? Why do you dress in scarlet crimson and put on gold jewelry? Why do you wear eye shadow? You are making yourself beautiful for nothing. Your lovers despise you. They want to kill you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.4.31'>I hear a woman in labor. I hear the woman cry with anguish as she gives birth to her first child. My people Zion gasp for breath. They stretch out their hands and say: »How horrible it is for us! My life is exhausted by the presence of murderers!«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.5'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.1'>People of Jerusalem, run through your streets! Look around and see for yourselves! Search the marketplaces! Can you find one person who does what is right and tries to be faithful to God? If you can, Jehovah will forgive Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.2'>Even though you claim to worship Jehovah, you do not mean what you say.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.3'>Jehovah looks for faithfulness. He struck you, but you paid no attention. He crushed you, but you refused to learn. You were stubborn and would not turn from your sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.4'>I thought: »These are only the poor and ignorant. They a foolish. They do not know what their God requires, what Jehovah wants them to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.5'>»I will go to the great men leaders and talk with them. Surely they know what their God requires, what Jehovah wants them to do. But all of them have rejected Jehovahs authority and refuse to obey him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.6'>That is why lions from the forest will kill them. Wolves from the desert will tear them to pieces, and leopards will prowl through their towns. If those people go out, they will be torn apart because their sins are numerous and time after time they have turned from God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.7'>Jehovah asked: Why should I forgive the sins of my people? They have abandoned me and have worshiped gods that are not real. I fed my people until they were full, but they committed adultery and spent their time with prostitutes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.8'>They were like well-fed stallions wild with desire, each lusting for his neighbor's wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.9'>»Why should I not punish the people of Judah?« Says Jehovah, »Should I take retribution vengeance?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.10'>»Go up through her vineyards and destroy them. But do not execute a complete destruction. Strip away her branches, for they are not Jehovahs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.11'>»The house of Israel and the house of Judah have dealt very treacherously with me,« says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.12'>They lied about Jehovah. They said: »It is not he, bad things will not happen to us. We will not see sword or famine.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.13'>»The prophets are as wind! The word is not in them. Thus it will be done to them!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.14'>Jehovah, the God of hosts says: »Because you have spoken this word and I am making my words fire in your mouth. This people are wood and will be consumed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.15'>»I am bringing a nation against you from afar, O house of Israel, declares Jehovah. It is an enduring nation. It is an ancient nation, a nation whose language you do not know. You cannot understand comprehendmake sense of what they say.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.16'>»Their quiver is like an open grave. All of them are mighty men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.17'>»They will devour your harvest and your food. They will devour your sons and your daughters. They will devour your flocks and your herds. They will devour your vines and your fig trees. They will demolish with the sword your fortified cities in which you trust.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.18'>»Yet even in those days, says Jehovah, I will not make you a complete destruction.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.19'>»They will ask: Why has Jehovah our God done all this to us? Answer them: »You have abandoned me and served foreign gods in your land. So you will serve foreigners in a land that is not yours.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.20'>»Declare this to the house of Jacob, and make this heard in Judah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.21'>»Hear this, you stupid and senseless people! You have eyes, but you cannot see. You have ears, but you cannot hear.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.22'>»Do you not reverence respect me?« Asks Jehovah. »Do you not tremble with awe in my presence? I made the sand a boundary for the sea, a permanent barrier it cannot cross. Although the waves toss continuously, they cannot break through. Although they roar, they cannot cross it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.23'>»These people are stubborn and rebellious. They have turned aside and departed from me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.24'>»They do not say in their hearts, to themselves: We should respect Jehovah our God. He sends rain at the right time, the autumn rain and the spring rain. He makes sure that we have harvest seasons.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.25'>»Your wickedness has turned these things away. Your sins have kept good things away from you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.26'>»Wicked men are found among my people. They lie in ambush like bird catchers. They set traps and catch men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.27'>»Like cages filled with birds, their houses are filled with deceit. That is why they become powerful and rich.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.28'>»They grow big and fat. Their evil deeds have no limits. They have no respect for the rights of others. They have no respect for the rights of orphans. But they still prosper. They do not defend the rights of the poor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.29'>»I will punish them for these things,« declares Jehovah. »I will punish these people!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.30'>»Something horrible and disgusting is happening in the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.5.31'>Prophets prophesy falsehoods. Priests rule under the prophets' directions, and my people love this. But what will you do when the end comes?«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.6'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.1'>Flee for safety people of Benjamin. Run from the midst of Jerusalem! Blow a rams horn in Tekoa and raise a signal over Beth-haccerem. Evil looks down from the north. There is great destruction.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.2'>I will destroy the beautiful and luxurious one, the daughter of Zion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.3'>Shepherds and their flocks will come to her. They will pitch their tents around her. They will pasture each in his place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.4'>Prepare for war against her. »Arise, and let us attack at noon.« »Woe to us, for the day declines is nearly over, for the shadows of the evening lengthen!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.5'>»Arise, and let us attack at night and destroy her palaces!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.6'>Jehovah of Hosts says: »Cut down trees and build up a siege against Jerusalem. This city should be punished, for there is only oppression in her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.7'>»As a well pours out its water, so Jerusalem pours out her wickedness. Violence and destruction are heard in her. Sickness and wounds are ever before me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.8'>»Be warned, O Jerusalem, I will be alienated from you. I will make you desolation, a land not inhabited.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.9'>Jehovah of Hosts says: »They will thoroughly glean as the vine the remnant of Israel. Pass your hand again like a grape gatherer over the baskets.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.10'>»To whom can I speak and give warning that they may hear? Their ears are closed and they cannot listen. Behold, the word of Jehovah has become a reproach to them. They have no delight in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.11'>I am full of the wrath of Jehovah. I am weary with holding it in. Pour it out on the children in the street and on the gathering of young men together. For both husband and wife will be taken, the aged and the very old.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.12'>»Their houses, their fields and their wives will be turned over to others. I will stretch out my hand extend my power against the inhabitants of the land,« declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.13'>»From the least of them even to the greatest of them, everyone is greedy for gain! From the prophet even to the priest everyone deals falsely!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.14'>»Superficially they have healed the brokenness of my people. They declare: Peace! Peace! »But there is no peace.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.15'>»Are they ashamed because of the abomination they have done? They are not even ashamed! Not at all! They do not even know how to blush. Therefore they will fall among those who fall. When I punish them, they will be cast down,« says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.16'>Jehovah says: »Stand by the way of life and see and ask for the ancient paths. Walk in the good way and you will find rest.« But you said: »We will not walk in it!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.17'>»I set watchmen over you. I said: Listen to the sound of the trumpet! But they said: We will not listen!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.18'>»Therefore hear, O nations, and know, O congregation, what is among them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.19'>»Hear, O earth: behold, I am bringing disaster on this people as the fruit of their plans. This is because they have not listened to my words, and have rejected my law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.20'>»What purpose does frankincense come to me from Sheba and the sweet cane from a distant land? Your burnt offerings are not acceptable and your sacrifices are not pleasing to me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.21'>Therefore, Jehovah says: »I am laying stumbling blocks before this people. They will stumble against them, Fathers and sons together; Neighbors and friends will perish.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.22'>Jehovah says: »Behold, a people is coming from the northland! A great nation will be aroused from the remote parts of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.23'>»They seize bow and spear. They are cruel and have no mercy. Their voice roars like the sea, and they ride on horses. They are arrayed as a man for the battle against you, O daughter of Zion!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.24'>We have heard the report! Our hands are limp. Anguish has seized us! We have pain like a woman in childbirth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.25'>Do not go out into the field. Do not walk on the road. The enemy has a sword and terror is on every side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.26'>O my people put on sackcloth and roll in ashes. Mourn as for an only son, a lamentation most bitter. For suddenly the destroyer will come upon us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.27'>»I have made you an assayer and a tester among my people. You will know and assay their course of life.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.28'>All of them are stubborn rebels. They go about telling false stories. They are copper and iron. They are all corrupt, all of them!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.29'>The bellows blow fiercely and the fire consumes the lead. The refining goes on in vain, but the wicked are not separated.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.6.30'>They call them rejected silver, for Jehovah has rejected them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.7'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.1'>This is the word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.2'>»Stand at the gate of Jehovahs house and proclaim there this word: Hear the word of Jehovah, all you of Judah who enter by these gates to worship Jehovah!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.3'>»Thus says Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel: »Amend make right your ways and your deeds, and I will let you dwell in this place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.4'>»»Do not trust in deceptive words. They say: This is the Temple of Jehovah, the Temple of Jehovah, and the Temple of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.5'>»»For if you truly amend your ways and your deeds, if you truly practice justice between a man and his neighbor,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.6'>if you do not oppress the alien, the orphan, or the widow, and do not shed innocent blood in this place, nor walk after other gods to your own ruin,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.7'>then I will let you dwell in this place, in the land I gave to your fathers from generation to generation and for a very long time.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.8'>»You are trusting in deceptive words that are of no value to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.9'>»Will you steal, murder, commit adultery, swear falsely, offer sacrifices to Baal and walk after other gods that you have not known?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.10'>»Then come and stand before me in this house. It is called by my name. You say, We are safe to do all these abominations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.11'>»Has this house, called by my name, become a den of robbers in your sight? Behold, I, even I, have seen it,« declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.12'>»But go to my place in Shiloh, where I made my name dwell from the beginning, and see what I did to it because of the wickedness of my people Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.13'>»For the reason that you did all these things,« says Jehovah, »I spoke to you. I rose up early and spoke. But you did not hear, and I called you but you did not answer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.14'>»Consider what I will do to the house that is called by my name. It is the house in which you trust. It is the place I gave you and your fathers, as I did to Shiloh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.15'>»I will cast you out of my sight, as I have cast out all your brothers, all the offspring of Ephraim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.16'>»As for you, do not pray for this people. Do not lift up cry or prayer for them, and do not intercede with me for I do not hear you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.17'>»Do you not see what they are doing in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.18'>»The children gather wood, and the fathers kindle the fire. The women knead dough to make cakes for the queen of heaven. They pour out drink offerings to other gods in order to spite me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.19'>»Do they spite me?« Asks Jehovah. »Is it not themselves they spite, to their own shame?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.20'>Therefore the Lord Jehovah says: »My anger and my wrath will be poured out on this place, on man and on beast, on the trees of the field and on the fruit of the ground. It will burn and not be quenched.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.21'>Thus says Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel: »Add your burnt offerings to your sacrifices and eat flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.22'>»For I did not speak to your fathers, or command them in the day that I brought them out of the land of Egypt, concerning burnt offerings and sacrifices.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.23'>»I gave them this command: Obey my voice, and I will be your God, and you will be my people. You will walk in all the way that I command you that it may be well with you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.24'>»Yet they did not obey or incline their ear. They walked in their own counsels and in the stubbornness of their evil heart. They went backward and not forward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.25'>»Since the day your fathers came out of the land of Egypt until this day, I have sent you all my servants the prophets, daily rising early and sending them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.26'>»Yet they did not listen to me or incline their ear. Instead they stiffened their neck became stubborn. They did more evil than their fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.27'>»You will speak all these words to them. But they will not listen to you. You will call them but they will not answer you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.28'>»You will say to them: This is the nation that did not obey the voice of Jehovah their God or accept correction. Truth has perished and truth has been removed from their mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.29'>Cut off your hair and cast it away. Take up a cry of sorrow and grief on the bare heights. Jehovah has rejected and forsaken the generation of his wrath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.30'>»The sons of Judah have done what is evil in my sight,« declares Jehovah. »They placed their detestable things in the house called by my name, to defile it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.31'>»They have built the high places of Topheth, which is in the valley of the son of Hinnom, to burn their sons and their daughters in the fire. I did not command this. I would never think of such a thing. It would not come from my heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.32'>»Days are coming, says Jehovah, when it will no longer be called Topheth, or the valley of the son of Hinnom Ben-hinnom, but the valley of the Slaughter. They will bury in Topheth because there is no other place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.33'>»The dead bodies of this people will be food for the birds of the sky and for the beasts of the earth. No one will frighten them away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.7.34'>»I will cause the voice of joy and the voice of gladness, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride to cease from the cities of Judah and from the streets of Jerusalem. The land will become a ruin.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.8'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.1'>Jehovah says: »At that time the bones of the kings and the leaders of Judah, the bones of the priests and the prophets, and the bones of the others who lived in Jerusalem will be taken out of their graves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.2'>»They will be spread out and exposed to the sun, the moon, and all the stars in the sky. These are the things that they had loved, served, gone after, sought, and worshiped. Their bones will not be gathered or buried, but they will become manure on the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.3'>»Then the few who remain from these wicked people will want to die rather than live where I will scatter them, declares Jehovah of Hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.4'>»Say to them: This is what Jehovah says: »When someone falls, he gets back up. When someone turns away from me, he returns.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.5'>»The people of Jerusalem turned away from me without ever returning. They still cling to deceit. They refuse to return.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.6'>»I paid attention and listened, but they were not honest. They do not turn away from their wickedness. They do not ask: What have we done? They go their own ways like horses charging into battle.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.7'>»Even storks know when it is time to return. Mourning doves, swallows swifts, and cranes know when it is time to migrate. But my people do not know that I, Jehovah, am urging them to return.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.8'>»How can you say you are wise and that you have Jehovahs Laws? The scribes have used their pens to spread falsehoods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.9'>»Wise people are put to shame, confused, and trapped. They have rejected the word of Jehovah. They do not really have any wisdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.10'>»So I will give their wives to other men. I will give their fields to new owners. From the least even to the greatest everyone is greedy for gain. From the prophet even to the priest everyone is deceitful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.11'>»They heal the brokenness of the daughter of my people superficially. They say: Peace! Peace! But there is no peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.12'>»Were they ashamed because of the abomination they had done? They certainly were not ashamed! And they did not know how to blush. For that reason they will fall among those who fall. At the time of their punishment they will be brought down,« Says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.13'>»I will surely snatch them away,« declares Jehovah. »There will be no grapes on the vine and no figs on the fig tree. The leaf will wither and what I have given them will pass away.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.14'>»Why are we sitting still? Assemble yourselves, and let us go into the fortified mother cities. Let us perish there, because Jehovah our God has doomed us. He has given us poisoned water to drink, for we have sinned against Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.15'>We waited for peace, but no good came. We waited for a time of healing, but all we got was terror!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.16'>From Dan is heard the snorting of his horses. At the sound of the neighing of his stallions the whole land quakes. For they come and devour the land and its fullness, the city and its inhabitants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.17'>»I am sending serpents against you, adders, for which there is no charm. They will bite you,« says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.18'>My sorrow is beyond healing, my heart is faint within me!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.19'>Behold, listen! The cry of the daughter of my people from a distant land: »Is Jehovah not in Zion? Is her King not within her?« »Why have they provoked me with their graven images, with foreign idols?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.20'>»Harvest is past, summer is ended, and we are not saved.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.21'>For the brokenness of the daughter of my people I am broken. I mourn and dismay has taken hold of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.8.22'>Is there no balm in Gilead? Is there no physician healer there? Why then has the health of the daughter of my people not been restored?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.9'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.1'>Oh that my head were waters and my eyes a fountain of tears. Then I might weep day and night for the slain of the daughter of my people!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.2'>I wish I had a dwelling in the desert. I would abandon my people and go away from them. They are all adulterers, an assembly of treacherous men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.3'>They bend their tongue like their bow. Lies and not truth prevail in the land. They move from evil to evil. »They do not know me,« says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.4'>»Let everyone be on guard against his neighbor. Do not trust any brother because every brother deals craftily cunningly, and every neighbor goes about as a slanderer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.5'>»Everyone deceives his neighbor and does not speak the truth. They have taught their tongue to speak lies. They wear themselves out committing sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.6'>»You live in the middle of deceit. Through deceit they refuse to know me,« says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.7'>Thus says Jehovah of Hosts: »Behold, I will refine them and assay them. What else can I do, because of the daughter of my people?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.8'>»Their tongue is a deadly arrow. It speaks deceit! With the mouth one speaks peace to his neighbor, but inwardly he sets an ambush for him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.9'>»I will punish them for these things,« declares Jehovah. »I will punish this nation and I will not be satisfied.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.10'>I will cry and weep for the mountains. I will sing a funeral song for the pastures in the wilderness. They are destroyed so that no one can travel through them. No one can hear the sound of cattle. Birds and cattle have fled. They are gone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.11'>I will make Jerusalem a heap of ruins. It will be a gathering place of jackals. I will make the cities of Judah desolation, without inhabitant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.12'>»Who is the wise man that may understand this? Who is he to whom the mouth of Jehovah has spoken? Let him declare it? Why is the land ruined, laid waste like a desert, so that no one passes through?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.13'>Jehovah said: »They have forsaken the Law I set before them. They have not obeyed my voice nor walked according to it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.14'>»They have walked after the stubbornness of their heart and after the Baals as their fathers taught them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.15'>»Therefore Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel says: Behold! I will feed this people with wormwood and give them poisoned water to drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.16'>I will scatter them among the nations, whom neither they nor their fathers have known. I will send the sword violence and warfare after them until I have annihilated them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.17'>»Jehovah of Hosts says: Consider the mourning women that they may come. Send for the wailing women that they may come!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.18'>Let them hurry and take up a wailing for us. Let our eyes shed tears and our eyelids flow with water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.19'>A voice of wailing is heard from Zion: »How we are ruined! We are put to great shame for we have left the land, because they have cast down our dwellings.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.20'>Listen to the word of Jehovah, you women, and open your ears to hear his words. Teach your daughters how to cry. Teach your neighbors funeral songs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.21'>Death has come through our windows and entered our palaces. Death has cut down the children in the streets and the young men in the market places.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.22'>»This is what Jehovah says: »Dead bodies will fall like manure on the field. They will be like grain that has been cut but not gathered.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.23'>This is what Jehovah says: »Do not let wise people brag about their wisdom. Do not let strong people brag about their strength. Do not let rich people brag about their riches.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.24'>»If they want to brag, instead let them advocate glorycelebrate that they understand and know me. They should advocate that I, Jehovah, act out of love, righteousness, and justice on the earth. This kind of celebration pleases me,« declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.25'>»The days are coming,« proclaims Jehovah, »when I will punish all who are circumcised only in the flesh. Yet they are not circumcised in the heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.9.26'>»I will punish Egypt, Judah, Edom, Ammon, and Moab. I will punish all who shave the hair on their foreheads or live in the desert. Even though all these nations are uncircumcised, all Israel has uncircumcised hearts.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.10'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.1'>Listen house of Israel, Hear the word Jehovah speaks to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.2'>This is what Jehovah says: »Do not learn the practices of the nations. Do not be frightened by the signs in the sky because they frighten the nations.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.3'>The peoples customs are erroneous and empty. It is wood cut from the forest. It is the work of the hands of a craftsman with a cutting tool.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.4'>»They decorate it with silver and with gold. They fasten it with nails and with hammers so that it will not tip over.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.5'>»They are like scarecrows in cucumber fields. They cannot speak. They must be carried, for they cannot walk! Do not fear them! For they can do no harm and they can do no good.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.6'>There is none like you, O Jehovah. You are great and your name is powerful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.7'>Who would not respect you, O King of the nations? It is your right! There is none like you among all the wise men of the nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.8'>They are very stupid and foolish. They teach vanity to a tree. Their idol is wood!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.9'>Beaten silver is brought from Tarshish, and gold from Uphaz. It is the work of a craftsman and of the hands of a goldsmith. Violet and purple are their clothing. They are all the work of skilled men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.10'>Jehovah is the true faithfulright God! He is the living God and the everlasting king. The earth quakes at his wrath. The nations cannot endure his indignation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.11'>You will say to the idolaters: »The gods that did not make the heavens and the earth will perish from the earth and from under the heavens.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.12'>He who made the earth by his power, and established the world by his wisdom; also stretched out the heavens by his understanding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.13'>He speaks, and the water in the sky produces a storm. He makes clouds rise from the ends of the earth. He makes lightning flash with the rain. He brings wind out of his storehouses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.14'>Every man is stupid lacking knowledge. Every goldsmith is put to shame by his idols. His molten images are deceitful. There is no breath in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.15'>They are worthless, a work of mockery. In the time of their punishment they will perish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.16'>Jacobs share is not like this. For he made everything! Israel is the tribe of his inheritance. Jehovah of Hosts is his name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.17'>Pick up your bundle from the ground, you who dwell under siege!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.18'>Jehovah says: »I am evicting the inhabitants of the land at this time. I will cause them distress that they may be found.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.19'>Oh, I am wounded! My wound is serious. Then I thought that this is my punishment, and I will bear it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.20'>My tent is destroyed. All the ropes are broken. My children have left me and have disappeared. There is no one to set up my tent again or put up my tent curtains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.21'>The shepherds are foolish. They do not look to Jehovah for help. That is why they will not succeed and all their flocks will be scattered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.22'>The report has arrived. Listen! An incredible uproar is coming from the land of the north. Its army will destroy Judah's cities and make them homes for jackals.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.23'>O Jehovah, I know that humans are not able to govern their own lives. Humans cannot administer their own steps.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.24'>Correct me, O Jehovah but please be fair. Do not correct me when you are angry. Otherwise, you will reduce me to nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.10.25'>Pour out your fury on the nations who do not know you and on people who do not worship you. They have devoured the descendants of Jacob. They have devoured them completely. They have destroyed their homes.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.11'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.1'>Jehovah said to me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.2'>»Listen to the terms of the covenant. Tell the people of Judah and of Jerusalem:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.3'>»Jehovah the God of Israel says, Cursed is everyone who does not obey the terms of this covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.4'>»It is the covenant I made with their ancestors when I brought them out of Egypt. Egypt was like an iron smelter furnace to them. I told them to obey me and to do everything that I commanded. I told them that if they obeyed, they would be my people and I would be their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.5'>»Then I would keep the promise I made to their ancestors that I would give them the rich and fertile land which they now have.» « I answered: « Amen Yes Jehovah.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.6'>Jehovah said to me: »Go to the cities of Judah and to the streets of Jerusalem. Proclaim my message there and tell the people: Listen to the terms of the covenant and obey them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.7'>»I solemnly warned your fathers in the day that I brought them up from the land of Egypt. Even to this day I persistently warned them, saying: Listen to my voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.8'>»Yet they did not obey or incline their ear pay attention. They walked, each one, in the stubbornness of his evil heart! Therefore I brought on them all the words of the covenant I commanded them to do. But they did not do it.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.9'>Jehovah said to me: »A conspiracy has been found among the men of Judah and among the inhabitants of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.10'>»They went back to the evil ways of their ancestors and refused to obey my words. They followed other gods and worshiped them. The nations of Israel and Judah have rejected the covenant that I made to their ancestors.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.11'>»Therefore Jehovah says: I am going to bring a disaster on them that they cannot escape. Although they will cry out to me, I will not listen to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.12'>»Then the cities of Judah and those who live in Jerusalem will cry to the gods to whom they have been sacrificing. But these gods will never rescue them in a time of distress.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.13'>»Judah, you have as many gods as you have cities. You have set up many altars in Jerusalem to sacrifice to Baal. You have as many detestable altars as there are streets in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.14'>»Jeremiah, do not pray for these people. Do not cry or pray for them. I will not listen when they call to me for help in times of trouble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.15'>»What right do these people I love have to be in my house when they do so many deceitful things? Can the meat from their sacrifices turn tragedy away from them? They exult celebrate when they do evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.16'>»Jehovah called you a large olive tree that has fine-looking fruit to look at. He will set fire to you with a mighty lightning storm, and your branches will be broken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.17'>»Jehovah of Hosts planted you. He has pronounced disaster on you. This is because of the evil things that Israel and Judah have done. They have made him infuriated by burning incense as an offering to Baal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.18'>Jehovah revealed their plot to me so that I would understand. He showed me what they were doing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.19'>I was like an unquestioning lamb brought to the slaughter. I did not know that they were plotting against me. They were saying: »Let us destroy the tree with its fruit. Let us cut Jeremiah off from this world of the living so that we will not be reminded of him anymore.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.20'>O Jehovah of Hosts, you are a fair judge. You test motives and thoughts. I want to see you take revenge on them. For that reason I presented my case to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.21'>This is what Jehovah says: »The people of Anathoth want to kill you. They say: Do not prophesy in the name of Jehovah, or we will kill you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.22'>This is what Jehovah of Hosts says: »I am going to punish them. The young men will die by the sword because of war. Their sons and daughters will die by famine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.11.23'>»I will bring disaster on the people of Anathoth. It will be a year of punishment. There will be no survivors.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.12'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.1'>Jehovah, if I argued my case with you, you would prove to be right. Indeed, I must question you about matters of justice. Why are the wicked so prosperous? Why do dishonest people succeed with impunity?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.2'>You plant them, and they take root. They grow and bear fruit. You are near their lips, but far from their mind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.3'>But, you know me, Jehovah. You see what I do and how in my heart I love you. Drag them away like sheep to be butchered. Guard them until it is time for them to be slaughtered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.4'>How long will our land be dry and the grass in every field be withered? Animals and birds are dying because of the wickedness of our people. These people say: »God does not see what we are doing.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.5'>Jehovah says: »Jeremiah, if you get tired racing against people, how can you race against horses? If you cannot even stand up in open country, how will you manage in the thicket by the Jordan?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.6'>»Even your relatives, members of your own family, have betrayed you. They join in the attacks against you. Do not trust them, even though they speak friendly words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.7'>Jehovah says: »I have abandoned Israel. I have rejected my chosen nation. I have given the people I love into the power of their enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.8'>»My chosen people have turned against me. Like a lion in the forest they have roared at me, and so I hate them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.9'>»My chosen people are like a bird attacked from all sides by hawks. Call the wild animals to come and join in the feast!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.10'>»Many foreign rulers have destroyed my vineyard. They trampled down my fields and turned my beautiful land into a desert.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.11'>»They made it a wasteland. It lies desolate before me. The whole land has become a desert, and no one cares.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.12'>»Across the entire desert highlands people have come to plunder. Jehovah has sent war to destroy the entire land. No one can live in peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.13'>»My people planted wheat. They gathered weeds! They worked hard and got nothing for it. Because of my fierce anger their crops have failed.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.14'>Jehovah says: »I have something to say about Israel's neighbors who have ruined the land I gave to my people Israel. I will take those wicked people away from their countries like an uprooted plant, and I will rescue Judah from them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.15'>»But after I have taken them away I will have mercy on them. I will bring each nation back to its own land and to its own country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.16'>»If with all their hearts they will accept the religion of my people and will swear: As Jehovah lives, as they once taught my people to swear by Baal, then they will also be a part of my people and will prosper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.12.17'>»However if any nation will not obey I will completely uproot it and destroy it.« I, Jehovah, have spoken.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.13'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.1'>Jehovah told me: »Go and buy a linen belt. Wear it on your hips for a while, but do not put it in any water.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.2'>So I bought a belt and put it on my hips.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.3'>Then Jehovah said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.4'>»Take off the linen belt. Go to the Euphrates River and hide the belt in a crack between some large rocks.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.5'>And that is what I did, just as Jehovah commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.6'>Some time later Jehovah said: »Go back and get the linen belt.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.7'>I went back and dug the belt out of the hiding place, but the cloth had rotted, and the linen belt was ruined. It was good for nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.8'>Then Jehovah said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.9'>»Jeremiah, I will use Babylon to destroy the pride of the people of Judah and Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.10'>»The people of Judah are evil and stubborn. They do not listen to me. They do whatever they want and even worship other gods. When I am finished with these people, they will be good for nothing, just like this linen belt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.11'>»This belt is tight around your waist, and that is how tightly I held onto the kingdoms of Israel and Judah. I wanted them to be my people. I wanted to make them famous, so that other nations would praise and honor me, but they refused to obey me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.12'>»Speak this word to them: Thus says Jehovah, the God of Israel, »Every jug is to be filled with wine. When they say to you, Do we not know that every jug is to be filled with wine?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.13'>»»Say to them: Jehovah says I am about to fill all the inhabitants of this land, the kings that sit for David on his throne, the priests, the prophets and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem with drunkenness!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.14'>»»I will dash them against each other, both the fathers and the sons together, declares Jehovah. I will not show pity nor be sorry nor have compassion so as not to destroy them.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.15'>Listen, give heed and do not be haughty arrogant. Jehovah has spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.16'>Give glory to Jehovah your God before he brings darkness and before your feet stumble on the dusky mountains. You hope for light. He makes it into deep darkness and turns it into gloom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.17'>If you will not listen, I will cry secretly over your arrogance. I will cry bitterly, and my eyes will flow with tears because Jehovahs flock will be taken captive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.18'>Say to the king and his mother: »Come down from your thrones, because your crowns have fallen off your heads.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.19'>The cities in the Negev will be locked up. There will be no one to reopen them. All the people of Judah will be taken away into captivity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.20'>»Look up, and see those who are coming from the north. Where is the flock that was given to you? Where are your beautiful sheep?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.21'>»What will you say when God makes the people you thought were your friends your new masters? Will pain grip you like a woman in labor?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.22'>»If you ask yourself: Why do these things happen to me? It is because you have so many sins. Your clothes have been torn off and your limbs are bare.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.23'>»Can Ethiopians change the color of their skin or leopards change their spots? Can you do good when you are taught to do wrong?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.24'>»I will scatter you like straw that is blown away by a desert wind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.25'>»This is your fate, the destiny I have planned for you,« proclaims Jehovah. »You have forgotten me and trusted in false gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.26'>»I will also tear off your clothes, and expose your shame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.13.27'>»I have seen you commit adultery and scream with delight. I have seen you act like a brazen prostitute on the hills and in the fields. How hideous it will be for you, Jerusalem! Will you ever be clean?«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.14'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.1'>Jehovah spoke his word about the drought to Jeremiah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.2'>Judah mourns and its gates collapse. The people of Judah are filled with bereavement as they sit on the ground. Their cry goes up from Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.3'>Important people send their assistants out for water. They do not find any water at the cisterns. They return with their containers empty. They cover their heads, because they are ashamed and dishonored.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.4'>There is no rain in the land and the ground is cracked. The farmers are disappointed. They cover their heads.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.5'>Even deer in the fields give birth and abandon their young because there is no grass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.6'>Wild donkeys stand on the bare hills. They sniff the wind like jackals. Their eyesight fails because they have no green plants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.7'>Do something, Jehovah, for the sake of your name, even though our iniquities testify against us. We have been unfaithful like apostates and have sinned against you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.8'>You are Israel's hope, its savior in times of trouble. Why are you like a stranger in the land, like a traveler who stays only one night?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.9'>Why are you like someone taken by surprise, like a mighty man who cannot help? You, O Jehovah, are among us. We are called by your name. Do not leave us!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.10'>This is what Jehovah says about these people: »They love to wander. They do not keep their feet where they belong. Therefore Jehovah is not happy with them. He will remember their crimes and punish their sins.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.11'>Jehovah said to me: »Do not pray for the good of these people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.12'>»Even if they go without food, I will not listen to their cries for help. Even if they sacrifice burnt offerings and grain offerings, I will not be pleased with them. But I will destroy these people with wars, famines, and plagues.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.13'>I said: »Alas, O Lord Jehovah, prophets are telling them: You will not see wars or famines, for I will give you lasting peace in this place.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.14'>Jehovah then told me: »These are the lies that the prophets are telling in my name: They claim that I sent them. They claim that I commanded them. They claim that I spoke to them. They even dreamed up visions to tell you. Their predictions are worthless! They are the products of their own imagination.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.15'>»I did not send these prophets. Yet, they prophesy in my name that there will be no wars or famines in this land. So this is what I, Jehovah, say about them: Wars and famines will bring an end to these prophets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.16'>»The people to whom they prophesy will be thrown out into the streets of Jerusalem. They will be victims of famines and wars. No one will bury them, their wives, their sons, or their daughters. I will pour on them the destruction that they deserve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.17'>»Say this to them: My eyes flow with tears day and night without stopping because my dear people will suffer massive destruction. It will be a very serious blow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.18'>»If I go to the field, I see those killed because of war. If I go to the city, I see those sick because of famine. Prophets and priests wander through a land they have not heard of.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.19'>Have you completely rejected Judah? Do you despise Zion? Why have you struck us so hard that we cannot heal? We hope for peace, but no good comes from it. We hope for a time of healing, but there's only terror.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.20'>O Jehovah, we recognize our wickedness and the wrongs done by our ancestors. We have sinned against you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.21'>For the sake of your name, do not despise us. Do not dishonor your glorious throne. Remember your promise to us. Do not break it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.14.22'>The valueless gods of the nations cannot make it rain. The skies cannot give showers by themselves. But you can, O Jehovah our God. We hope in you because you do all these things.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.15'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.1'>Jehovah said to me: »I would not feel sorry for these people, even if Moses and Samuel were standing in front of me. Send them away from my presence, and let them go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.2'>»When they ask you where they should go, say to them: This is what Jehovah says: Those who are to die will die. Those who are to die in wars will die in wars. Those who are to die in famines will die in famines. Those who are to die in captivity will die in captivity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.3'>»I will appoint over them four kinds of punishment, declares Jehovah. I will send swords to kill, dogs to drag away, and birds of the air and animals of the earth to devour and destroy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.4'>»I will make these people a horrifying shocking sight to all the kingdoms on the earth. This will happen because of what Judah's King Manasseh, son of Hezekiah, did in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.5'>»Who will take pity on you, Jerusalem? No one will mourn for you. No one will bother to ask how you are doing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.6'>»You left me, declares Jehovah. You turned your back on me. So I will stretch out my hand against you use my power against you and destroy you. I am tired of showing compassion to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.7'>»I will separate them with a winnowing shovel at the city gates. I will make them childless. I will destroy my people because they will not change their ways.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.8'>»Their widows will be more numerous than the grains of sand on the seashore. At noontime I will send a destroyer against the mothers of young men. I will suddenly bring anguish and terror to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.9'>»A mother who gives birth to seven sons will grow faint and breathe her last. She will die, ashamed and humiliated, while it is still daylight. I will put survivors from these people to death in the presence of their enemies, says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.10'>Sadness is mine! Why did my mother bring me into the world? I have to quarrel and argue with everyone in the whole earth. I have not lent any money or borrowed any; yet everyone curses me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.11'>Jehovah said: »I will certainly rescue you for a good. I will certainly make your enemies plead with you in times of evil and in times of distress.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.12'>»Can a man break iron, especially the iron from the north that is mixed with copper?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.13'>»Jehovah said to me: I will send enemies to carry away the wealth and treasures of my people. This will punish them for the sins they have committed throughout the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.14'>»I will make them serve their enemies in a land they know nothing about. My anger is like fire, and it will burn forever.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.15'>Then I said: »O Jehovah you understand. Remember me and help me. Let me have revenge on those who persecute me. Do not be so patient with them that they succeed in killing me. Remember that it is for your sake that I have suffered reproach.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.16'>»You spoke to me, and I listened to every word. I belong to you, Lord Jehovah. Your words filled my heart with joy and happiness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.17'>»I did not spend my time with other people laughing and having a good time. In obedience to your orders I stayed by myself and was filled with anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.18'>»Why do I suffer constant pain? Why is my wound incurable, refusing to be healed? Will you indeed be to me like a deceptive stream with water that is unreliable?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.19'>Therefore Jehovah says: »If you return I will restore you. You will stand before me. If you extract the precious from the worthless, you will become my spokesman. They for their part may turn to you. But you must not turn to them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.20'>»I will make you a fortified wall of copper to these people. Though they fight against you, they will not prevail over you. For I am with you to save you and deliver you, declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.15.21'>»I will deliver you from the hand of the wicked. I will redeem you from the grasp of the cruel.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.16'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.1'>The word of Jehovah also came to me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.2'>»You shall not take a wife for yourself nor have sons or daughters in this place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.3'>Jehovah says this about the sons and daughters born in this place, and about their mothers who bear them, and their fathers who begot them in this land:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.4'>»They will die of lethal diseases. They will not be mourned or buried. They will be as dung on the surface of the ground and die by sword and famine war and starvation. Their carcasses will become food for the birds of the sky and for the animals of the earth.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.5'>Jehovah says: »Do not enter a house of mourning, or go to lament or to console them. I have withdrawn my peace from this people,« declares Jehovah, »even my loving kindness and compassion.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.6'>»Both great and small men will die in this land. They will not be buried, they will not be lamented, nor will anyone gash himself or shave his head for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.7'>»Men will not break bread in mourning for them in order to comfort anyone for the dead. Nor will they give them a cup of consolation to drink for anyone's father or mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.8'>»Moreover you shall not go into a house of feasting to sit with them to eat and drink.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.9'>»This is what Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, says: I am going to put a stop to the sounds of joy and happiness and the sounds of brides and grooms in this place. This will happen in your lifetime, even as you watch.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.10'>»When you tell the people all these things, they will ask you: Why does Jehovah threaten us with all these disasters? What have we done wrong? How have we sinned against Jehovah our God?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.11'>»Tell them: It is because your ancestors abandoned me, says Jehovah. They followed other gods, served them, worshiped them, and abandoned me. They did not obey my law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.12'>»You have done worse than your ancestors. All of you are following your own stubborn, evil ways that keep you from listening obeying to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.13'>»Therefore I will throw you out of this land into a land that you and your ancestors have not heard of. There you will serve other gods day and night because I will no longer have pity on you.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.14'>»That is why the days are coming,« declares Jehovah, »when people will no longer begin an oath with: Jehovah brought the people of Israel out of Egypt and as Jehovah lives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.15'>»But they will say: Jehovah brought the people of Israel out of the land of the north and all the lands where he had scattered them. They will say this because I will bring them back to the land that I gave their fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.16'>»I am going to send for many fishermen,« says Jehovah, »and they will catch the people of Israel. After that, I will send for many hunters, and they will hunt for them on every mountain and hill and even in the cracks in the rocks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.17'>»I see everything that they do. They cannot hide anything from me. Their wickedness cannot be hidden; I can see it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.18'>»First, I will have them pay twice as much for their wickedness and their sin, because they have polluted my land. They have filled my property with the lifeless statues of their detestable and disgusting idols.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.19'>Jehovah is my strength and my fortress, my refuge in times of trouble. Nations come to you from the most distant parts of the world and say: Our ancestors have inherited lies, worthless and unprofitable gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.20'>Can people make gods for themselves? They are not really gods!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.16.21'>»That is what I will teach them. This time I will make my power and my strength known to them. THEN THEY WILL KNOW THAT MY NAME IS JEHOVAH.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.17'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.1'>Jehovah says: Judah's sin is written with an iron pen. It is engraved with a diamond point on the tablet of their hearts and on the horns strengthauthority of their altars.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.2'>Even their children remember their altars and their poles images dedicated to the goddess Asherah beside large trees on high hills</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.3'>and on mountains in the open country. I will turn your wealth and all your treasures into loot. I will do this because of your worship sites and your sin throughout all your territory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.4'>You will lose the inheritance that I gave you. I will make you serve your enemies in a land that you have not heard of. I will do this because you have stirred up the fire of my anger. It will burn for a very long time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.5'>This is what Jehovah says: »Cursed is the person who trusts humans, who makes flesh and blood his strength and whose heart turns away from Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.6'>»He will be like a bush in the desert and will not see when prosperity comes. He will live in stony wastes in the wilderness, a land of salt without inhabitant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.7'>»Blessed is the man who trusts in Jehovah, whose refuge and security confidence and hope is Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.8'>»For he will be like a tree planted by the water. It extends its roots by a stream and will not fear when the heat comes. Its leaves will be green. It will not be anxious in a year of drought nor cease to yield fruit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.9'>»The heart is more deceitful than all else and is desperately corrupt. Who can understand it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.10'>»I, Jehovah, search the heart and examine the mind inner man. I give to each man according to his ways, according to the results of his deeds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.11'>»A person who gets rich dishonestly is like a partridge that hatches eggs it did not lay. During his lifetime, he will lose his wealth. In the end, he will be a wicked fool.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.12'>From the very beginning our sanctuary was a glorious throne on high.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.13'>You will put to shame all that forsake you, O Jehovah, the hope of Israel. Those who turn away on earth will be written down, for they have forsaken Jehovah, the fountain of living water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.14'>Heal me, O Jehovah, and I will be healed! Save me and I will be saved! For you are my song of praise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.15'>Look, they keep saying to me: Where is the word of Jehovah? Let it come now!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.16'>I have not hurried away from being your shepherd. I have not longed for the day of destruction. You know what I used to say.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.17'>Do not cause me fear and anxiety. For you are my refuge in the day of disaster.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.18'>Let those who persecute me be put to shame. Do not let me be put to shame. Let them be dismayed, but let me not be dismayed. Bring on them a day of disaster. Crush them with twofold destruction!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.19'>Jehovah said to me: »Go and stand in the public gate, through which the kings of Judah come in and go out, as well as in all the gates of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.20'>Say to them: »Listen to the word of Jehovah, kings of Judah, and all Judah and all inhabitants of Jerusalem who come in through these gates:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.21'>»Jehovah says: Take heed for yourselves, and do not carry any load on the Sabbath day or bring anything in through the gates of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.22'>»You shall not bring a load out of your houses on the Sabbath day nor do any work. You should keep the Sabbath day holy, as I commanded your forefathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.23'>»Yet they did not listen or incline their ears. They stiffened their necks in order not to listen or take correction.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.24'>»But it will come about, if you listen attentively to me, declares Jehovah, to bring no load in through the gates of this city on the Sabbath day, but to keep the Sabbath day holy by doing no work on it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.25'>then there will come in through the gates of this city kings and princes sitting on the throne of David. They will ride in chariots and on horses, they and their princes, the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem. This city will be inhabited for a very long time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.26'>»They will come in from the cities of Judah and from the environs of Jerusalem, from the land of Benjamin, from the lowland, from the hill country and from the Negev. They will bring burnt offerings, sacrifices, grain offerings and incense. They will also bring sacrifices of thanksgiving to the house of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.17.27'>»If you do not listen to me to keep the Sabbath day holy by not carrying a load and coming in through the gates of Jerusalem on the Sabbath day, then I will kindle a fire in its gates and it will devour the palaces of Jerusalem. And it will not be quenched.« «</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.18'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.1'>Jehovah spoke his word to Jeremiah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.2'>»Go to the potter's house. There I will give you my message.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.3'>I went to the potter's house, and he was working there at his wheel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.4'>When a clay pot he was working on was ruined, he would rework it into a new clay pot the way he wanted to make it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.5'>Jehovah spoke his word to me. Jehovah asked:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.6'>»Nation of Israel, can I do with you as this potter does with clay?« Nation of Israel, »You are in my hands like the clay in the potter's hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.7'>»At one time I may threaten to tear up, break down, and destroy a nation or a kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.8'>»However if the nation that I threatened turns away from doing wrong. Then I will change my plans about the disaster I planned to do to it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.9'>»At another time I may promise to build and plant a nation or a kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.10'>»If that nation does what I consider evil and does not obey me I will change my mind about the good that I promised to do to it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.11'>»Now say to the people of Judah and to those who live in Jerusalem, This is what Jehovah says: I am going to prepare a disaster and make a plot against you. Turn from your evil ways, change your lives, and do good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.12'>»But they will answer, It is useless! We will live the way we want to. We will go our own stubborn, evil ways.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.13'>»This is what Jehovah says: Ask among the nations if anyone has ever heard anything like this. The people of Israel have done a very horrible thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.14'>»Does the snow of Lebanon forsake the rock of the open country? Or is the cold flowing water from a foreign land ever snatched away?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.15'>»My people have forgotten me. They burn incense to worthless gods and they have stumbled from their ways. They stray from the ancient paths to walk in pathways and not on a highway.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.16'>»They make their land desolation. It becomes an object of perpetual hissing. Everyone who passes by it will be astonished and shake his head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.17'>»Like an east wind I will scatter them before the enemy. I will show them my back and not my face in the day of their calamity.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.18'>Then they said: »Come and let us devise plans against Jeremiah. Surely the law is not going to be lost to the priest, nor counsel to the wise man, nor the divine word to the prophet! Come on and let us strike him with our tongue, and let us pay no attention to any of his words.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.19'>Do pay close attention to me, O Jehovah! Listen to what my opponents are saying!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.20'>Should good be repaid with evil? For they have dug a pit for me. Remember how I stood before you to speak good on their behalf. I tried to turn away your wrath from them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.21'>Therefore, give their children over to famine and deliver them up to the power of the sword. Let their wives become childless and widowed. Let their men also be smitten to death and their young men struck down by the sword in battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.22'>Let an outcry be heard from their houses when you suddenly bring raiders upon them. For they have dug a pit to capture me and hidden snares for my feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.18.23'>Yet You, O Jehovah, know all their deadly designs against me. Do not forgive their iniquity or blot out their sin from your sight. But may they be overthrown before you. Deal with them in the time of your anger!</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.19'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.19.1'>Jehovah says: Go and buy a potter's earthenware jar, and take some of the elders of the people and some of the senior priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.19.2'>Then go out to the valley of Ben-hinnom Hinnom Valley, which is by the entrance of the potsherd gate, and proclaim there the words that I tell you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.19.3'>Say: »Hear the word of Jehovah, O kings of Judah and inhabitants of Jerusalem: thus says Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, »»Behold I am about to bring adversity upon this place. The ears of everyone who hears of it will quiver with fear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.19.4'>»»This is because they have forsaken me. They have made this an alien place and have burned sacrifices in it to other gods. These are gods that neither they nor their forefathers nor the kings of Judah had ever known. They have filled this place with the blood of the blameless innocent.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.19.5'>»They have built the high places of Baal to burn their sons in the fire as burnt offerings to Baal. This is not something I commanded or spoke of, nor did it ever enter my mind heartconscience.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.19.6'>»»Therefore days are coming, declares Jehovah, when this place will no longer be called Topheth or the valley of Ben-hinnom, but rather the valley of Slaughter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.19.7'>»I will make void the counsel of Judah and Jerusalem in this place. I will cause them to fall by the sword before their enemies and by the hand of those who seek their life. I will give their carcasses as food for the birds of the sky and the animals of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.19.8'>»I will also make this city a desolation and an object of hissing. Everyone who passes by it will be astonished and hiss because of all its disasters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.19.9'>»I will make them eat the flesh of their sons and the flesh of their daughters, and they will eat one another's flesh in the siege and in the distress with which their enemies and those who seek their life will cause them.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.19.10'>»Then you are to break the jar in the sight of the men who accompany you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.19.11'>»Say to them: Jehovah of Hosts says: »Like this I will break this people and this city. It is just like one breaks a potter's vessel that cannot again be repaired. They will bury in Topheth because there is no other place for burial.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.19.12'>»This is how I will treat this place and its inhabitants,declares Jehovah, I will make this city like Topheth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.19.13'>»The houses of Jerusalem and the houses of the kings of Judah will be defiled like Topheth. They burned sacrifices to the heavenly hosts and poured out drink offerings to other gods on the rooftops of all of their houses.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.19.14'>Then Jeremiah came from Topheth, where Jehovah had sent him to prophesy. He stood in the court of Jehovahs house and said to all the people:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.19.15'>»Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel says: I am about to bring on this city and all its towns the entire disaster that I have declared against it. This is because they have stiffened their necks vigorously resisted so as not to heed my words.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.20'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.1'>Pashhur the priest, son of Immer, who was chief officer in the house of Jehovah, heard Jeremiah prophesying these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.2'>Pashhur had Jeremiah the prophet beaten and put him in the stocks that were at the upper Benjamin Gate, which was by the house of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.3'>The next day Pashhur released Jeremiah from the stocks. Jeremiah said to him: »Pashhur is not the name Jehovah has called you. He has called you Magor-missabib.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.4'>»For Jehovah says: Behold, I am going to make you a terror to yourself and to all your friends. They will fall by the sword of their enemies while you watch. I will hand over all Judah to the hand control of the king of Babylon. He will carry them away as exiles to Babylon and will slay them with the sword.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.5'>»I will also hand over all the wealth of this city, all its produce and all its costly things. I will even give all the treasures of the kings of Judah to the hand of their enemies. They will plunder them and take them away to Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.6'>»You, Pashhur, and all who live in your house will go into captivity. You will enter Babylon, and there you will die and be buried, you and all your friends to whom you have falsely prophesied.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.7'>O Jehovah, You have deceived me. I was deceived! You have overcome me and prevailed. I have become a laughingstock all day long; everyone mocks me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.8'>Each time I speak, I cry aloud. I proclaim violence and destruction! For me the word of Jehovah has resulted in reproach and derision all day long.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.9'>But if I say: »I will not remember him or speak anymore in his name,« then in my heart it becomes like a burning fire shut up in my bones. I am weary of holding it in. I cannot endure it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.10'>For I have heard the whispering of many: »Terror on every side! Denounce him; yes, let us denounce him!« All my trusted friends are watching for my fall. They say: »Perhaps he will be deceived, so that we may prevail against him and take our revenge on him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.11'>Jehovah is with me like a powerful champion. Therefore my persecutors will stumble and not prevail. They will be utterly ashamed! They have failed with an everlasting disgrace that will not be forgotten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.12'>Yet, O Jehovah of Hosts you test the righteous. You see the mind and the heart. Let me see your vengeance on them for to you I have revealed my cause.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.13'>Sing to Jehovah, praise Jehovah! He has delivered the needy one from the hand domination of evildoers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.14'>Cursed is the day when I was born. Let the day not be blessed when my mother bore me!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.15'>Cursed is the man who brought the news to my father, saying: »A baby boy has been born to you!« He made him very happy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.16'>But let that man be like the cities Jehovah overthrew without relenting. Let him hear an outcry in the morning and a shout of alarm at noon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.17'>He did not kill me before birth, so that my mother would have been my grave, and her womb ever pregnant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.20.18'>Why did I ever come forth from the womb to look on trouble and sorrow? My days have been spent in shame!</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.21'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.21.1'>This is the word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah. King Zedekiah sent to him Pashhur the son of Malchijah, and Zephaniah the priest, the son of Maaseiah. The king said to Jeremiah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.21.2'>»Please inquire of Jehovah on our behalf. Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon is warring against us. Perhaps Jehovah will deal with us with all his wonderful acts, so that the enemy will withdraw from us.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.21.3'>Jeremiah responded to them: »Say the following Zedekiah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.21.4'>Jehovah the God of Israel says: »Behold, I am about to turn back the weapons of war you control. The weapons you use to make war against the king of Babylon and the Chaldeans who besiege you outside the wall. I will gather them into the center of this city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.21.5'>»I will war against you with an outstretched hand and a mighty arm with my great power. I will extend my anger, wrath and great indignation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.21.6'>»I will also strike down the inhabitants of this city, both man and beast. They will die of a great pestilence.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.21.7'>»»Afterwards,« declares Jehovah: »I will hand over Judah's King Zedekiah, his officials, the people, and everyone else in this city who survives the plague, war, and famine. They will be handed over to King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon and to their enemies who want to kill them. Nebuchadnezzar will kill them with swords. He will not spare them, show them compassion, or care for them.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.21.8'>»Also say to this people, Jehovah says: »Behold, I set before you the way of life and the way of death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.21.9'>»He who dwells in this city will die by the sword and by famine and by pestilence. He who goes out and surrenders to the Chaldeans who are besieging you will live. He will have his own life as booty.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.21.10'>»»For I have set my face against this city for harm and not for good, declares Jehovah. It will be surrendered to the king of Babylon and he will burn it with fire.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.21.11'>»Then say to the household of the king of Judah: Hear the word of Jehovah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.21.12'>»O house of David, Jehovah says: »Administer justice every morning. Deliver the person who has been robbed from the power of his oppressor. That way I may not have to offer my wrath like fire and burn with none to extinguish it, because of the evil of your deeds.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.21.13'>»I am against you, O valley dweller, O rocky plain, declares Jehovah. You men say: »Who will come down against us? Or who will enter into our habitations?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.21.14'>»But I will punish you according to the results of your deeds, declares Jehovah. I will kindle a fire in its forest that will devour all its environs.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.22'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.1'>This is what Jehovah says: »Go to the palace of the king of Judah, and speak this message there:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.2'>»Listen to the word of Jehovah, you officials, you people who come into these gates, and you, king of Judah, the one sitting on David's throne.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.3'>This is what Jehovah says: »Judge fairly, and do what is right. Rescue those who have been robbed from those who oppress them. Do not mistreat foreigners, orphans, or widows, and do not oppress them. Do not kill innocent people in this place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.4'>»If you do what I say, then the kings who sit on David's throne will ride through the gates of this palace in chariots and on horses along with their officials and their people.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.5'>»But if you do not do what I say, I will take an oath on myself, declares Jehovah, this palace will become a pile of rubble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.6'>»Jehovah says concerning the house of the king of Judah: You are like Gilead to me, like the summit of Lebanon. Most assuredly I will make you like a wilderness, like cities that are not inhabited.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.7'>»I will set apart destroyers against you, each with his weapons. They will cut down your choicest cedars and throw them on the fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.8'>»Many nations will pass by this city. They will say to one another: Why has Jehovah done thus to this great city?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.9'>»They will answer: Because they abandoned the covenant of Jehovah their God and bowed down to other gods and served them.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.10'>»Do not weep for the dead or mourn for him. Weep continually for the one who goes away. For he will never return or see his native land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.11'>»This is what Jehovah says about King Josiah's son Shallum, who succeeded his father as king of Judah and left this place: He will never come back here again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.12'>»He will die in the place where they led him captive. He will not see this land again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.13'>»Woe to him who builds his house without righteousness and his upper rooms without justice. Woe to him who uses his neighbor's services without pay and does not give him his wages.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.14'>»Woe to him who says: I will build myself a roomy house with spacious upper rooms, and cut out its windows. I will panel it with cedar and paint it bright red vermilion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.15'>Do you become a king because you are competing in cedar? Did not your father eat and drink and do justice and righteousness? Then it was well with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.16'>He pled the cause of the afflicted and needy. Then it was well. »Is that not what it means to know me?« Says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.17'>»Your eyes and your heart are intent only upon your own dishonest gain. You are shedding innocent blood and on practicing oppression and extortion.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.18'>Therefore Jehovah tells us about Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah: »They will not cry for him: Alas, my brother! And, Alas, sister! They will not mourn him: Alas for the master! And, »Alas for his splendor!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.19'>He will be buried with a donkey's burial. He will be dragged off and thrown out beyond the gates of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.20'>»Go up to Lebanon and cry out! Lift up your voice in Bashan. Cry out also from Abarim, for all your lovers have been crushed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.21'>I spoke to you in your prosperity. But you said: I will not listen! This has been your practice from your youth, that you have not obeyed my voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.22'>»The wind will sweep away all your shepherds. Your lovers will go into captivity. Then you will surely be ashamed and humiliated because of all your wickedness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.23'>»You who dwell in Lebanon nested in the cedars. How you will groan when pangs come upon you, Pain like a woman in childbirth!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.24'>»As I live, says Jehovah, even though Coniah the son of Jehoiakim king of Judah were a signet ring on my right hand, yet I would pull you off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.25'>»As I live,« says Jehovah, »I will hand you over to those who want to kill you, those you fear, King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon and the Babylonians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.26'>»I will throw you and your mother into another land. You were not born there, but you will die there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.27'>»You will want to return to this land, but you will not be allowed to come home.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.28'>»This Jehoiakin is like a rejected and broken pot that no one wants. Is that why he and his descendants will be thrown out and cast into another land they have never heard of?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.29'>»O land, land, land! Hear the word of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.22.30'>»This is what Jehovah says: Write this about Jehoiakin: »He will be childless. He will not prosper in his lifetime. None of his descendants will succeed him as king. They will not sit on David's throne and rule Judah again.« «</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.23'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.1'>»Woe to the shepherds who are destroying and scattering the sheep of my pasture!« Says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.2'>This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says concerning the shepherds who are tending my people: »You have scattered my flock and driven them away. You have not attended to them. I am about to attend to you for the evil of your deeds,« says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.3'>»Then I will gather the remnant of my flock out of all the countries where I have driven them and bring them back to their pasture. Then they will be fruitful and multiply.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.4'>»I will also raise up shepherds over them who will tend them. They will not be afraid any longer, nor be terrified, nor will any be missing, proclaims Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.5'>»The days are coming,« declares Jehovah, »when I will raise up for David a righteous Branch. He will reign as king and act wisely and do justice and righteousness in the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.6'>»In His days Judah will be saved. Israel will dwell securely. This is his name by which he will be called, Jehovah Is Our Righteousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.7'>»Therefore the days are coming,« declares Jehovah, »when they will no longer say, As Jehovah lives, the one who brought up the sons of Israel from the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.8'>»Instead, Jehovah lives, the one who brought up and led back the descendants of the household of Israel from the northland and from all the countries where I had driven them. Then they will live on their own soil.«</verse>
        <title>CONCERNING THE PROPHETS</title>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.9'>My heart is broken within me. All my bones tremble! I have become like a drunken man, even like a man overcome with wine. This is because of Jehovah and because of his holy words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.10'>The land is full of adulterers! The land mourns because of the curse. The pastures of the wilderness have dried up. Their course also is evil and their might is not right.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.11'>»The prophets and priests are godless. Even in my Temple I have found them doing evil,« declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.12'>»That is why their own way will become like a slippery path in the dark. They will be chased away, and they will fall down in the dark. I will bring disaster on them. It is time for them to be punished,« proclaims Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.13'>»Say this about the prophets of Samaria: I saw something disgusting. The prophets of Samaria prophesied by Baal and led my people Israel astray.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.14'>»Say this about the prophets of Jerusalem: I see something horrible. The prophets of Jerusalem commit adultery and live a lie. They support those who do evil so that no one turns back from his wickedness. They are all like Sodom to me, and those who live in Jerusalem are like Gomorrah.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.15'>This is what Jehovah of Hosts says about the prophets: »I will give them wormwood to eat and poison to drink. The prophets of Jerusalem have spread godlessness throughout the land.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.16'>This is what Jehovah of Hosts says: »Do not listen to what the prophets are saying to you. They fill you with false hope. They speak about visions that they dreamed up. These visions are not from Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.17'>»They keep saying to those who despise me, Jehovah says: Everything will go well for you. They tell all who live by their own stubborn ways: Nothing bad will happen to you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.18'>Who is in Jehovahs inner circle and sees and hears his word? Who pays attention and listens to his word?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.19'>The storm of Jehovah vents his wrath. A whirling tempest will swirl down on the head of the wicked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.20'>The anger of Jehovah will not turn back until he has performed and carried out the purposes intent of his heart. In the last days you will clearly understand it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.21'>»I did not send these prophets, but they ran. I did not speak to them, but they prophesied.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.22'>»If they had stood in my council they would have announced my words to my people. They would have turned them back from their evil way and from the evil of their deeds.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.23'>»I am a God who is near,« declares Jehovah. »I am not a God far off!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.24'>»Can a man hide himself in hiding places so I do not see him?« asks Jehovah. »Do I not fill the heavens and the earth?« Declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.25'>»I have heard what the prophets have said who prophesy falsely in my name. They say: I had a dream! I had a dream!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.26'>»How long? Is there anything in the hearts of the prophets, who prophesy falsehood, even these prophets of the deception of their own heart?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.27'>»They think the dreams they tell will make my people forget my name, just as their ancestors forgot my name and turned to Baal worship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.28'>»The prophet who has had a dream should say it is only a dream. The prophet who has heard my message should proclaim that message faithfully.« »What good is chaff compared with wheat?« Says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.29'>»My message is like a fire and like a hammer that breaks rocks in pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.30'>»I am against those prophets who take each other's words and proclaim them as my message.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.31'>»I am also against those prophets,« says Jehovah, »They speak their own words and claim they came from me!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.32'>»Listen to what I, Jehovah, say! I am against the prophets who tell their dreams that are full of lies. They tell these dreams and lead my people astray with their lies and their boasting. I did not send them or order them to go. They are of no help at all to the people. I Jehovah have spoken!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.33'>Jehovah said to me: »Jeremiah, when one of my people or a prophet or a priest asks you, what is Jehovahs message? You are to say: You are a burden to Jehovah, and he is going to get rid of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.34'>»If any of my people or a prophet or a priest even uses the words: Jehovahs infallable utterance, I will punish them and their families.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.35'>»Each one of you should ask your friends and your relatives: What answer has Jehovah given? What has Jehovah said?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.36'>»So you must no longer use the words: Jehovahs infallable utterance, because if any of you do, I will make my message a real utterance to you. The people have perverted the words of their God, the living God, the Lord Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.37'>»Jeremiah, ask the prophets: What answer did Jehovah give you? What did Jehovah say?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.38'>»If you disobey my command and use the words: Jehovahs utterance, then hear this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.39'>»»I will certainly pick you up and throw you far away from me, both you and the city that I gave to you and your ancestors.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.23.40'>»»I will bring on you everlasting shame and disgrace that will never be forgotten.« «</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.24'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.24.1'>Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon carried away captive Jeconiah son of Jehoiakim, king of Judah, and the officials of Judah. He also captured the craftsmen and smiths from Jerusalem and brought them to Babylon. Then Jehovah showed me two baskets of figs set before the Temple of Jehovah!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.24.2'>One basket had very good figs, like first-ripe figs, and the other basket had very bad figs that could not be eaten because they were rotten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.24.3'>Then Jehovah said to me: »What do you see, Jeremiah?« I said: »Figs. The good figs are very good. The bad figs are very bad. They cannot be eaten because they are rotten.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.24.4'>The word of Jehovah came to me, He said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.24.5'>»Jehovah the God of Israel says: Like these good figs, so I will regard the captives of Judah as good. I have sent them out of this place into the land of the Chaldeans.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.24.6'>»I will watch over them for their good, and I will bring them to this land again. I will build them up and not overthrow them. I will plant them and not uproot them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.24.7'>»I will give them a heart willdesire to know me. I am Jehovah! They will be my people, and I will be their God! They will return to me with their whole heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.24.8'>»Like the bad figs that cannot be eaten because they are rotten,« says Jehovah, »so I will abandon Zedekiah king of Judah and his officials, and the remnant of Jerusalem who remain in this land and the ones who dwell in the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.24.9'>»»I will make them a horrifying sight to all the kingdoms of the earth. They will be a disgrace and an example. They will become something ridiculed and cursed wherever I scatter them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.24.10'>»»I will send wars, famines, and plagues until they disappear from the land that I gave to them and their ancestors.« «</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.25'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.1'>Jehovah spoke his word to Jeremiah about all the people of Judah when Jehoiakim, son of Josiah, was in his fourth year as king. This was the first year that Nebuchadnezzar was king of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.2'>The prophet Jeremiah spoke to all the people of Judah and to everyone who lived in Jerusalem. He said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.3'>»Jehovah continued to speak his word to me for twenty-three years. This covered the time from when Josiah, son of Amon, was in his thirteenth year as king of Judah until today. I have spoken to you again and again, but you have not listened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.4'>»Jehovah has sent all his servants the prophets to you. Yet, you have not listened or paid attention to them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.5'>The prophets said: »Turn from your evil ways and the evil you have done, and live in the land that Jehovah permanently gave to you and your ancestors.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.6'>»Do not follow other gods to serve and worship them. Do not make me furious about the idols your hands have shaped. Then I will not harm you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.7'>»You have not listened to me, declares Jehovah. You have made me furious about the idols your hands have shaped. You have brought harm upon yourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.8'>»This is what Jehovah of Hosts says: »You did not listen to my words,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.9'>so I am going to send for all the families from the north. I will also send for my servant King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon,« says Jehovah. »I will bring the families from the north to attack this land, its people, and all these surrounding nations. I am going to destroy them and turn them into something terrible, something ridiculed, and something permanently ruined.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.10'>»I will take from them the sounds of joy and happiness, the sounds of brides and grooms, the sound of mills, and the light of lamps.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.11'>»This whole land will be ruined and become a wasteland. These nations will serve the king of Babylon for seventy years.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.12'>»When the seventy years are over, I will punish the king of Babylon and that nation for their crimes, declares Jehovah. I will turn Babylon into a permanent wasteland.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.13'>»I will bring on that land all the disasters I threatened to do to it, everything that Jeremiah prophesied against all the nations, everything written in this book.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.14'>»Many nations and great kings will make slaves of the people of Babylon. I will pay them back for what they have done.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.15'>»This is what Jehovah the God of Israel said to me: Take from my hand this cup filled with the wine of my fury, and make all the nations to whom I am sending you drink from it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.16'>»When they drink from it, they will stagger and go insane because of the wars that I am going to send them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.17'>So I took the cup from Jehovahs hand. I made all the nations to whom Jehovah sent me drink from it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.18'>Jerusalem and the cities of Judah as well as its kings and officials drank from it. When they drank from it, they became wastelands and ruins, something ridiculed and cursed, until today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.19'>I also made these people drink from it: Pharaoh king of Egypt, his servants, officials, all his people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.20'>and all the foreign people living among them; all the kings of the land of Uz; all the kings of Philistia, those from the cities of Ashkelon, Gaza, and Ekron, and the people left in Ashdod;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.21'>Edom, Moab, and the people of Ammon;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.22'>all the kings of Tyre and Sidon, and the kings on the seacoast;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.23'>Dedan, Tema, Buz, and all who shave the hair on their foreheads;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.24'>all the kings of Arabia, and all the kings of the foreign people living in the desert;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.25'>all the kings of Zimri, all the kings of Elam, and all the kings of Media;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.26'>all the kings of the north, near and far, one after another-all the kingdoms of the earth. Last of all, the king of Sheshach will drink from the cup.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.27'>»Jehovah said: Say to them, This is what Jehovah of Hosts, »the God of Israel, says: Drink, get drunk, vomit, fall down, and do not get up because of the wars that I am going to send you.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.28'>»If they refuse to take the cup from your hand and drink from it, say to them: This is what Jehovah of Hosts says: »You must drink from it!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.29'>»I am going to bring disaster on the city that is named after me. Do you think you will go unpunished? You will not go unpunished! I am declaring war on all those who live on earth, declares Jehovah of Hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.30'>»That is why you will prophecy all these things to them and say: Jehovah roars from above. He thunders from his holy dwelling place. He roars against his land. He shouts like those who stomp grapes. He shouts against all those who live on earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.31'>»The sound is echoing to the ends of the earth because Jehovah has brought charges against the nations. He will judge all humans. He will kill the wicked, declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.32'>»This is what Jehovah of Hosts says: Disaster is spreading from nation to nation. A great storm is brewing from the distant corners of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.33'>»On that day those killed by Jehovah will stretch from one end of the earth to the other. They will not be mourned, taken away, or buried. They will become like manure on the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.34'>»Mourn, you shepherds, and cry. Roll in the dust, you leaders of the flock. The time has come for you to be slaughtered. The time has come for you to be scattered, and you will break like fine pottery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.35'>»There will be no place for the shepherds to flee, no escape for the leaders of the flock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.36'>»The shepherds are crying and the leaders of the flock are mourning because Jehovah is stripping their pasture.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.37'>»The peaceful pastures are destroyed by Jehovahs burning anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.25.38'>»He has left his lair like a lion. Their land has been ruined because of the heat of the oppressor, because of the fury of his anger.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.26'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.1'>Shortly after Jehoiakim son of Josiah became king of Judah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.2'>Jehovah said to me: »Stand in the court of the Temple and proclaim all I have commanded you to say to the people who come from the towns of Judah to worship there. Do not omit anything.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.3'>»Perhaps the people will listen and give up their evil ways. If they do I will change my mind about the destruction I plan to bring on them for all their wicked deeds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.4'>»Jehovah told me to say to the people: I Jehovah said that you must obey me by following the teaching that I gave you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.5'>»»You are to pay attention to the words of my servants, the prophets, whom I kept sending to you. You have never obeyed what they said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.6'>If you continue to disobey I will do to this Temple what I did to Shiloh, and all the nations of the world will use the name of this city as a curse.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.7'>The priests, the prophets, and all the people heard me saying these things in the Temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.8'>As soon as I had finished saying all that Jehovah commanded me to say, they grabbed me and shouted: »You ought to be killed for this!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.9'>»Why have you said in Jehovahs name that this Temple will become like Shiloh and that this city will be destroyed and no one will live in it?« Then the people crowded around me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.10'>When the leaders of Judah heard what had happened, they hurried from the royal palace to the Temple and took their places at the New Gate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.11'>The priests and the prophets said to the leaders and to the people: »This man deserves to be sentenced to death because he has spoken against our city. You heard him with your own ears.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.12'>Then I Jeremiah said: »Jehovah sent me to proclaim everything that you heard me say against this Temple and against this city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.13'>»You must change the way you are living and the things you are doing. You must obey Jehovah your God. If you do, he will change his mind about the destruction that he said he would bring on you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.14'>»I am in your hand power! Do with me whatever you think is fair and right.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.15'>»But if you put me to death, you and everyone else in Jerusalem will be guilty of murdering an innocent man. This is because everything I spoke came from Jehovah.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.16'>The judges and the other people told the priests and prophets: »Since Jeremiah only told us what Jehovah our God had said, we do not think he deserves to die.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.17'>Then some of the leaders from other towns stepped forward. They told the crowd:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.18'>»Years ago when Hezekiah was king of Judah, a prophet named Micah from the town of Moresheth said: Jehovah of Hosts says, »Jerusalem will be plowed under and left in ruins. Thorns will cover the mountain where the Temple now stands.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.19'>Then the leaders continued: »No one put Micah to death for saying that. Instead, King Hezekiah prayed to Jehovah with reverence and trembling and asked him to have mercy. Then Jehovah decided not to destroy Jerusalem, even though he had already said he would. People of Judah, if Jeremiah is killed we will bring a terrible disaster on ourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.20'>»There was another man prophesying in the name of Jehovah. His name was Uriah, son of Shemaiah, from Kiriath Jearim. He prophesied against this city and this land as Jeremiah did.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.21'>»When King Jehoiakim and all his personal troops and officials heard what Uriah said the king wanted to put him to death. But Uriah heard about it and fled in fear to Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.22'>»King Jehoiakim sent soldiers to Egypt: Elnathan son of Achbor and other soldiers along with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.23'>»They brought Uriah from Egypt and took him to King Jehoiakim. The king executed Uriah and threw his body into the burial ground for the common people.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.26.24'>Ahikam, son of Shaphan, supported Jeremiah. So Jeremiah was not handed over to the people to be put to death.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.27'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.1'>Jehovah spoke his word to Jeremiah when Zedekiah, son of King Josiah of Judah, began to rule.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.2'>This is what Jehovah said to me: »Make leather straps and a wooden yoke, and strap the yoke on your neck.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.3'>»Then send messages to the kings of Edom, Moab, Ammon, Tyre, and Sidon, with messengers who have come to King Zedekiah of Judah in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.4'>»Give them an order for their masters: This is what Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, says: Say this to your masters,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.5'>»I used my great strength and my powerful arm to make the earth along with the people and the animals on it. I give it to anyone I please.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.6'>»Now I have handed all these countries over to my servant King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon. I have even made wild animals serve him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.7'>»All nations will serve him, his son, and his grandson until Babylon is defeated. Then many nations and great kings will make him their slave.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.8'>»Suppose nations or kingdoms will not serve or surrender to King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon. I will punish those nations by wars, famines, and plagues, until I have put an end to them by Nebuchadnezzar's power,« says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.9'>»Do not listen to prophets, mediums, and interpreters of dreams, fortunetellers, or sorcerers who tell you, You will never serve the king of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.10'>»They prophesy lies to you. They will cause you to be taken far from your lands. I will scatter you, and you will die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.11'>»If a nation surrender to the king of Babylon and serve him I will let it stay in its own land. People will farm the land and live on it,« says Jehovah.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.12'>I spoke the same message to King Zedekiah of Judah: »Surrender to the king of Babylon, serve him and his people, and you will stay alive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.13'>»Why should you and your people die in wars, famines, and plagues? Jehovah has threatened the nations that do not serve the king of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.14'>»Do not listen to the prophets who tell you, You will never serve the king of Babylon. They prophesy lies to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.15'>»I did not send them,« declares Jehovah. »They prophesy lies in my name. So I will scatter you, and you and the prophets will die.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.16'>I also spoke this message to the priests and all the people. This is what Jehovah said to me: »Do not listen to the prophets who tell you that the utensils of Jehovahs Temple will be brought back from Babylon soon. They prophesy lies to you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.17'>»Do not listen to them. Instead, serve the king of Babylon, and live. Why should this city be turned into rubble?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.18'>»If they are prophets and Jehovah is speaking to them, they should beg Jehovah of Hosts not to allow the utensils that are left in Jehovahs Temple, in the royal palace of Judah, and in Jerusalem to be taken away to Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.19'>»Jehovah of Host reports concerning the pillars, concerning the sea, concerning the stands and concerning the rest of the vessels that are left in this city,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.20'>which Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon did not take when he carried into exile Jeconiah the son of Jehoiakim, king of Judah, from Jerusalem to Babylon, and all the nobles of Judah and Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.21'>»Thus says Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, concerning the vessels that are left in the House of Jehovah and in the house of the king of Judah and in Jerusalem,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.27.22'>»They will be carried to Babylon and they will be there until the day I visit them,« declares Jehovah. »Then I will bring them back and restore them to this place.« «</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.28'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.1'>That same year, in the fifth month of the fourth year that Zedekiah was king, Hananiah son of Azzur, a prophet from the town of Gibeon, spoke to me in the Temple. In the presence of the priests and of the people he told me</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.2'>that the Lord Jehovah, the God of Israel, said: »I have broken the power of the king of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.3'>»Within two years I will bring back to this place all the temple treasures that King Nebuchadnezzar took to Babylon.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.4'>»I will also bring back the king of Judah, Jehoiachin son of Jehoiakim, along with all of the people of Judah who went into exile in Babylon. I will break the power of the king of Babylon. I Jehovah have spoken!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.5'>In the presence of the priests and of all the people who were standing in the Temple, I said to Hananiah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.6'>»Amen! I hope Jehovah will do this! I certainly hope he will make the prophecy come true and will bring back from Babylon all the Temple treasures and all the people who were taken away as prisoners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.7'>»But listen to what I say to you and to the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.8'>»The prophets who spoke long ago before my time and yours predicted that war, starvation, and disease would come to many nations and powerful kingdoms.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.9'>»A prophet who predicts peace can only be recognized as a prophet whom Jehovah has truly sent when that prophet's predictions come true.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.10'>Hananiah took the yoke off my neck and broke it in pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.11'>He said in the presence of all the people: »Jehovah said that this is how he will break the yoke that King Nebuchadnezzar has put on the neck of all the nations. He will do this within two years.« Then I left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.12'>Some time after this Jehovah told me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.13'>»Go and tell Hananiah: Jehovah has said, »You may be able to break a wooden yoke, but he will replace it with an iron yoke.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.14'>»The Lord Jehovah, the God of Israel, said: He will put an iron yoke on all these nations and that they will serve King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon. Jehovah said that he would make even the wild animals serve Nebuchadnezzar.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.15'>Then Jeremiah the prophet told the prophet Hananiah: »Listen, Hananiah! Jehovah did not send you. You are making these people believe a lie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.16'>»Because of this, Jehovah says: I am going to get rid of you. Before this year is over you will die because you have told the people to rebel against Jehovah.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.28.17'>Hananiah died in the seventh month of that same year.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.29'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.1'>The prophet Jeremiah sent a letter from Jerusalem to the rest of the leaders among the captives. He also sent it to the priests, the prophets, and all the people that Nebuchadnezzar took away as captives from Jerusalem to Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.2'>This was after King Jehoiakin and his mother, the court officials, the leaders of Judah and Jerusalem, the craftsmen, and metal workers left Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.3'>He sent the letter with Shaphan's son Elasah and Hilkiah's son Gemariah, whom King Zedekiah of Judah had sent to King Nebuchadnezzar in Babylon. The letter said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.4'>»This is what Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, says to all those who were taken captive from Jerusalem to Babylon:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.5'>Build houses and live in them. Plant gardens and eat what they produce.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.6'>Get married and have sons and daughters. Find wives for your sons and let your daughters get married so they can have sons and daughters. Grow in number there and do not decrease.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.7'>Work for the good of the city where I have taken you as captives. Pray to Jehovah for that city. When it prospers, you will also prosper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.8'>»This is what Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, says: Do not let the prophets or the mediums among you trick you. Do not even listen to your own dreams.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.9'>These people prophesy lies to you in my name. I did not send them, declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.10'>»This is what Jehovah says: When Babylon's seventy years are over I will come to you. I will keep my promise to you and bring you back to this place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.11'>I know the plans that I have for you, says Jehovah. They are plans for peace and not disaster. They are plans to give you a future filled with hope.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.12'>Then you will call to me. You will come and pray to me and I will hear you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.13'>When you look for me, you will find me. When you wholeheartedly seek me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.14'>I will let you find me, declares Jehovah. I will bring you back from captivity. I will gather you from all the nations and places where I have scattered you, declares Jehovah. I will bring you back from the place where you are being held captive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.15'>»You said, Jehovah gave us prophets in Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.16'>»This is what Jehovah says about the king who sits on David's throne. And this is what he says about all the people who live in this city, the people who are your relatives and who were not taken away as captives:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.17'>Jehovah of Hosts says: »I am going to send them wars, famines, and plagues. These people are like rotten figs to me, figs that are so bad that they cannot be eaten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.18'>»I will chase them with wars, famines, and plagues. I will make them a terror to all the kingdoms on the earth. They will become something cursed, ridiculed, and hissed at, and they will be a disgrace among all the nations where I scatter them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.19'>They did not listen to me, says Jehovah. I sent them my servants the prophets again and again, but they refused to listen, says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.20'>»Therefore listen to the word of Jehovah, all you captives who were sent away from Jerusalem to Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.21'>»This is what Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, says about Kolaiah's son Ahab and about Maaseiah's son Zedekiah, who prophesy lies to you in my name: I am going to hand them over to King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon. I will kill them as you watch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.22'>Because of them, all the captives from Judah who are in Babylon will use this curse: »May Jehovah curse you as he cursed Zedekiah and Ahab, whom the king of Babylon burned to death.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.23'>They have done scandalous and disgraceful things in Israel. They committed adultery with their neighbors' wives and spoke lies in my name. I did not command them to do this. »»I know what they have done. I am a witness,« says Jehovah.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.24'>Jehovah says: »Say to Shemaiah from Nehelam,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.25'>This is what Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, says: »You sent letters in your own name to all the people who are in Jerusalem, to the priest Zephaniah, son of Maaseiah, and to all the priests. These letters said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.26'>Jehovah made you priest instead of Jehoiada so that there would be officials for Jehovahs temple. You should put every madman who acts like a prophet in prison and in shackles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.27'>Why have you not arrested Jeremiah from Anathoth? After all, he acts like a prophet among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.28'>That is why Jeremiah sent this message to us in Babylon: You will be captives a long time. Build houses, and live in them. Plant gardens, and eat what they produce,--« «»</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.29'>The priest Zephaniah read this letter to the prophet Jeremiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.30'>Then Jehovah spoke his word to Jeremiah. He said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.31'>»Send this message to all the captives. This is what Jehovah says about Shemaiah from Nehelam: »Shemaiah prophesied to you, but I did not send him. He has made you believe a lie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.29.32'>»Jehovah says: I will punish Shemaiah from Nehelam. I will also punish his descendants. No one from his family will be left alive. He will not see the blessings that I am going to send my people, declares Jehovah, because he has encouraged rebellion against Jehovah.« «</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.30'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.1'>Jehovah spoke his word to Jeremiah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.2'>This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: »Write in a book everything that I tell you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.3'>»The days are coming,« says Jehovah, »when I will bring my people Israel and Judah back from captivity. I will bring them back to the land that I gave their ancestors, and they will take possession of it.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.4'>These are the words Jehovah spoke about Israel and Judah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.5'>Jehovah said: »We hear cries of fear. We hear cries of panic. But we do not hear cries of peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.6'>»Ask now and see: Can a man give birth to a child? Why, then, do I see every strong man holding his stomach in pain like a woman giving birth to a child? Why has every face turned pale?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.7'>»How terrible that day will be! There will be no other day like it. It will be a time of calamity for the descendants of Jacob, but they will be rescued from it.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.8'>»On that day,« declares Jehovah of Hosts, »I will break the yokes off your necks and tear off your ropes. Foreigners will no longer make you serve them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.9'>»You will serve Jehovah your God and David your king. I will establish him for you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.10'>»Do not be afraid, my servant Jacob,« proclaims Jehovah. »Do not be terrified, Israel. I am going to rescue you from a faraway place. I am going to rescue your descendants from where they are captives. The descendants of Jacob will again have peace and security, and no one will frighten them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.11'>»I am with you. I will rescue you,« declares Jehovah. »I will completely destroy all the nations where I scattered you, but I will not completely destroy you. I will correct you with justice. I will not let you go entirely unpunished.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.12'>This is what Jehovah says: »Your wound is incurable. Your injury is beyond healing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.13'>»No one argues that you should be healed. But no medicine will heal you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.14'>»All your lovers have forgotten you, and they do not want you anymore. I have punished you as an enemy would. I have corrected you as a cruel person would. You are very wicked, and you have many sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.15'>»Why do you cry about your wound, your injury that cannot be cured? I have done this to you. You are very wicked, and you have many sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.16'>»That is why everyone who devours you will be devoured, and all your enemies will be taken away as captives. Those who looted you will be looted. Those who stole from you in war will have things stolen from them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.17'>»I will restore your health and heal your wounds,« proclaims Jehovah. »People call you an outcast: Zion, no one cares for you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.18'>»This is what Jehovah says: »I am going to bring the captives back to Jacob's tents and show compassion on their homes. Cities will be built on the ruins, and fortified palaces will be built in their rightful place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.19'>»The people who live there will sing songs of praise. The sound of laughter will be heard from there. I will make them numerous, and their number will not decrease. I will bring them honor, and they will not be considered unimportant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.20'>»Their children will be like they were long ago. Their community will be established in my presence, and I will punish everyone who oppresses them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.21'>»Their leader will be someone from their own people. Their ruler will come from among them. I will bring him near, and he will come close to me. Who would dare to come near me?« Declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.22'>»You will be my people, and I will be your God.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.23'>The storm of Jehovah will come with his anger. Like a driving wind, it will swirl down on the heads of the wicked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.30.24'>Jehovahs burning rage will not turn back until he has done everything he intends to do. You will understand this clearly in the last days.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.31'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.1'>Jehovah proclaims: »At that time I will be the God of all the families of Israel, and they will be my people.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.2'>Jehovah says: »The people who survived the sword war found favor in the wilderness. Israel went to find its rest.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.3'>Jehovah appeared to him from afar, saying: »I have loved you with an everlasting love. Therefore I have drawn you with loving-kindness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.4'>»I will build you and you will be rebuilt, O virgin of Israel! You will take up your tambourines and go to the dances of the merrymakers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.5'>»You will plant vineyards on the hills of Samaria. The planters will plant and will enjoy them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.6'>»There will be a day when watchmen on the hills of Ephraim call out: Arise, and let us go up to Zion, to Jehovah our God.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.7'>Jehovah says: »Sing aloud with gladness for Jacob, and shout among the chief of the nations.« Proclaim! Give praise and say, O Jehovah, save your people, the remnant of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.8'>I am bringing them from the North Country. I will gather them from the remote parts of the earth. Among them are the blind and the lame, the woman with child and she who is in labor with child. As a great company they will return here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.9'>With weeping they will come. By supplication I will lead them. I will make them walk by streams of waters on a straight path in which they will not stumble. For I am a father to Israel and Ephraim is my firstborn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.10'>Hear the word of Jehovah, O nations. Declare in the coastlands afar off. Say: »He who scattered Israel will gather him and keep him as a shepherd keeps his flock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.11'>»Jehovah will free the descendants of Jacob and reclaim them from those who are stronger than they are.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.12'>»They will come and shout for joy on top of Mount Zion. They will stream to it to enjoy Jehovahs blessings: fresh grain, new wine, olive oil, lambs and calves. Their lives will be like well-watered gardens, and they will never suffer again.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.13'>»Then young women will rejoice and dance along with young men and old men. I will turn their mourning into joy. I will comfort them. I will replace their sorrow with joy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.14'>»I will satisfy the priests with rich food. My people will be filled with my blessings,« proclaims Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.15'>»This is what Jehovah says: A sound is heard in Ramah, the sound of crying in bitter grief. Rachel is crying for her children. She refuses to be comforted, because they are dead.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.16'>This is what Jehovah says: »Stop your crying, and wipe away your tears. You will be rewarded for your work, declares Jehovah. You will return from the land of the enemy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.17'>»Your future is filled with hope, says Jehovah. Your children will return to their own territory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.18'>»I hear the people of Israel say in grief, Jehovah, we were like an untamed animal, but you taught us to obey. Bring us back for we are ready to return to you, Jehovah our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.19'>»We turned away from you. But soon we wanted to return. After you had punished us we hung our heads in grief. We were ashamed and disgraced because we sinned when we were young.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.20'>»Ephraim, O Ephraim my dear delightful son! Indeed, as often as I have spoken against him, I certainly still remember him. My heart yearns for him. I will surely have mercy on him,« declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.21'>»Set up road marks. Place guideposts! Direct your mind to the highway, the way by which you went. Return, O virgin of Israel. Return to these your cities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.22'>»How long will you go here and there, O faithless daughter? For Jehovah has created a new thing in the earth. A woman will protect a man.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.23'>Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel says: »Once again they will speak this word in the land of Judah and in its cities when I restore their prosperity. They will say: Jehovah bless you, O abode of righteousness, O holy mountain!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.24'>»Judah and all its cities will dwell together in it, the farmer and the shepherds with the flocks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.25'>»For I satisfy the weary ones and refresh everyone filled with sorrow.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.26'>At this, I woke up and looked around. My sleep had been pleasant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.27'>Jehovah says: »The time is coming when I will plant the nations of Israel and Judah with people and animals.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.28'>»I watched over them to uproot them and tear them down, to ruin and hurt them. Now I will watch over them to build them up. I will plant them,« says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.29'>»When that time comes people will no longer say: The fathers have eaten sour grapes, and their childrens teeth are set on edge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.30'>»Each person will die for his own sin. Whoever eats sour grapes will have his own teeth set on edge.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.31'>»The time is coming,« proclaims Jehovah, »when I will make a new covenant with the house of Israel and with the house of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.32'>»It will not be like the promise that I made to their ancestors when I took them by the hand and brought them out of Egypt. They rejected that promise, although I was a husband to them,« says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.33'>»This is the covenant agreement that I will make with Israel after those days,« declares Jehovah. »I will put my teachings Law inside them. I will write those teachings Law on their hearts innermanmindwillconscienceunderstanding. I will be their God, and they will be my people.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.34'>»No longer will each person teach his neighbors or his relatives by saying: Know Jehovah. »All of them, from the least important to the most important, will know me,« declares Jehovah. »I will forgive their wickedness and I will no longer hold remember their sins against them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.35'>Jehovah provides the sun to be a light during the day. He orders the moon and stars to be lights during the night. He stirs up the sea so that its waves roar. His name is Jehovah of Hosts. This is what Jehovah says:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.36'>»Only if this covenant is removed,« declares Jehovah, »will Israel's descendants stop being a nation in my presence.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.37'>This is what Jehovah says: »If the heavens could be measured or the foundations of the earth could be searched, I would reject all of Israel's descendants because of everything that they have done, declares Jehovah.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.38'>»The time is coming,« declares Jehovah, »when the city will be rebuilt for me from the Tower of Hananel to Corner Gate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.39'>»A measuring line will stretch from there straight to the Hill of Gareb, and then it will turn to Goah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.31.40'>»The whole valley is filled with its dead bodies and ashes. The entire area to the Kidron Valley, as far as the corner of Horse Gate in the east, will be holy to Jehovah. It will never be uprooted or torn down again.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.32'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.1'>Jehovah spoke his word to Jeremiah during Zedekiah's tenth year as king of Judah. This was Nebuchadnezzar's eighteenth year as king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.2'>At that time the army of the king of Babylon was blockading Jerusalem. The prophet Jeremiah was locked up in the courtyard of the prison. This prison was in the palace of the king of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.3'>When King Zedekiah of Judah locked up Jeremiah, Zedekiah asked him: »Why are you prophesying? You are saying, this is what Jehovah says: »I am going to hand this city over to the king of Babylon, and he will capture it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.4'>»King Zedekiah of Judah will not escape from the Babylonians. He will certainly be handed over to the king of Babylon. He will talk to Nebuchadnezzar in person and look him in the eye.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.5'>»Nebuchadnezzar will take Zedekiah to Babylon, and Zedekiah will stay there until I deal with him,« declares Jehovah. »When you fight the Babylonians, you will not win.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.6'>Jeremiah said: »The word of Jehovah came to me. He said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.7'>Hanamel the son of Shallum your uncle is coming to you. He says: »Buy for yourself my field at Anathoth, for you have the right of redemption to buy it.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.8'>»Then Hanamel my uncle's son came to me in the court of the guard according to the word of Jehovah and said to me: Buy my field, please, that is at Anathoth, which is in the land of Benjamin. You have the right of possession and the redemption is yours;. Buy it for yourself. »Then I knew that this was the word of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.9'>»I bought the field at Anathoth from Hanamel my uncle's son. I weighed out the silver for him, seventeen shekels of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.10'>»I signed and sealed the deed, and called in witnesses, and weighed out the silver on the scales.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.11'>»I took the deeds of purchase, both the sealed copy containing the terms and conditions and the open copy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.12'>»I gave the deed of purchase to Baruch the son of Neriah, the son of Mahseiah, in the sight of Hanamel my uncle's son and in the sight of the witnesses who signed the deed of purchase, before all the Jews who were sitting in the court of the guard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.13'>»I commanded Baruch in their presence, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.14'>Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel says: »Take these deeds, this sealed deed of purchase and this open deed, and put them in an earthenware jar, that they may be preserved a long time.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.15'>Jehovah of Host, the God of Israel says: »Houses and fields and vineyards will again be bought in this land.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.16'>»After I had given the deed of purchase to Baruch the son of Neriah I prayed to Jehovah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.17'>Ah Lord Jehovah! You have made the heavens and the earth by your great power and by your outstretched arm! Nothing is too difficult for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.18'>»You show loving kindness to thousands, but repay the iniquity of fathers into the bosom of their children after them. O great and mighty God. Jehovah of Hosts is his name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.19'>»You are great in counsel and mighty in deed. Your eyes are open to all the ways of the sons of men. You give to everyone according to his ways and according to the fruit of his deeds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.20'>»You set signs and wonders in the land of Egypt. Even to this day both in Israel and among mankind you have made a name for yourself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.21'>»You brought your people Israel out of the land of Egypt using signs and wonders. You did this with a strong hand, with an outstretched arm and with great terror.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.22'>»You gave them this land. You swore to their forefathers to give them a land flowing with milk and honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.23'>»They came in and took possession of it. But they did not obey your voice or walk in your Law. They have done nothing of all that you commanded them to do. Therefore you made this calamity come upon them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.24'>»The siege ramps have reached the city to take it. The city is given into the hand of the Chaldeans who fight against it, because of the sword, the famine and the pestilence. You brought all this disaster on them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.25'>»Yet you, Lord Jehovah, told me to buy a field with money and get witnesses to confirm it, although the city was handed over to the Babylonians.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.26'>Jehovah continued to speak his word to Jeremiah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.27'>»Behold! I am Jehovah the God of all humanity. Nothing is too hard for me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.28'>»This is what Jehovah says: I am going to hand this city over to the Babylonians and King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon. They will capture it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.29'>The Babylonians who are attacking this city will break in, set this city on fire, and burn it down. They will burn down the houses of people who made me furious by going up to the roofs to burn incense to Baal and to pour out wine offerings to other gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.30'>»Ever since they were young, the people of Israel and Judah have done what I consider evil. The people of Israel have made me furious by what they have done, says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.31'>The people in this city have made me so angry and furious from the day they built it to this day. So now I must remove this city from my presence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.32'>The people of Israel and Judah have made me furious because they are evil. The people, their kings and officials, their priests and prophets, and the Judeans and those who live in Jerusalem</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.33'>have turned their backs, not their faces to me. I taught them again and again, but they refused to listen and learn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.34'>They set up their detestable idols in the Temple that is called by my name, and they dishonored it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.35'>In the valley of Ben Hinnom they built worship sites for Baal to sacrifice their sons and daughters to Molech. I did not ask them to do this. It never entered my heart mind. I did not make Judah sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.36'>»You have said this about the city: Because of wars, famines, and plagues it will be handed over to the king of Babylon. Jehovah the God of Israel says:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.37'>I am going to gather the people from all the lands where I scattered them in my anger, fury, and terrifying wrath. I will bring them back to this place and make them live here securely.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.38'>»They will be my people, and I will be their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.39'>»I will give them the same attitude and the same purpose so that they will respect and reverence me as long as they live. This will be for their good and for the good of their children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.40'>»I will make an eternal promise to them that I will never stop blessing them. I will make them respect me so that they will never turn away from me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.41'>»I will enjoy blessing them. With all my heart and all my being I will faithfully plant them in this land.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.42'>»This is what Jehovah says: As I brought all these disasters on these people, so I will bring on them all these blessings that I have promised them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.43'>»Fields will be bought in this land of which you say: It is desolation, without man or beast; it is given into the hand of the Chaldeans.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.32.44'>»Men will buy fields for money, sign and seal deeds, and call in witnesses in the land of Benjamin, in the environs of Jerusalem, in the cities of Judah, in the cities of the hill country, in the cities of the lowland and in the cities of the Negev. I will restore their prosperity,« declares Jehovah.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.33'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.1'>The word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah the second time, while he was still confined in the court of the guard:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.2'>»Jehovah is the maker of the earth. Jehovah is the one who formed and established it. Jehovah is His name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.3'>Call to me and I will answer you. I will tell you grand and impressive things, things you do not know.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.4'>»The houses in this city and the palaces of the kings of Judah have been torn down. They are used against the dirt ramps and weapons of the Babylonians. This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says about this:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.5'>»The people of Israel fought the Babylonians. Now their houses are filled with the bodies of their own people I killed in my anger and my fury. I will hide my face from this city because of its wickedness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.6'>»However I will heal this city and restore it to health. I will heal its people, and I will give them peace and security.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.7'>»I will restore Judah and Israel and rebuild them as they were before.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.8'>»I will cleanse them from all the sins that they have committed against me. I will forgive them for all the sins that they have committed against me and for rebelling against me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.9'>»Jerusalem will be my source of joy, praise, and honor. All the nations on earth will hear about all the blessings that I will give to Jerusalem. They will be afraid and tremble because of all the prosperity that I will provide for it.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.10'>»This is what Jehovah says: You have said that this place is ruined and that no people or animals live in it. It is true! The cities of Judah and the streets of Jerusalem are deserted. No people or animals live there. But once again you will hear,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.11'>»Yes, you will hear the sounds of joy and happiness and the sounds of brides and grooms. You will hear those who bring thank offerings to Jehovahs Temple.«  »They will say: Give thanks to Jehovah of Hosts because Jehovah is good, because his mercy endures forever. I will restore the prosperity of the land to what they were before,«  says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.12'>»Jehovah of Hosts said: In this land that is like a desert and where no people or animals live, there will once again be pastures where shepherds can take their sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.13'>»In mountain towns, in the foothills, and in southern Judah, in the territory of Benjamin, in the villages around Jerusalem, and in the towns of Judah, shepherds will once again count their sheep. I Jehovah have spoken.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.14'>»Jehovah said: The time is coming when I will fulfill the promise that I made to the people of Israel and Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.15'>»At that time I will choose as king a righteous descendant of David. That king will do what is right and just throughout the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.16'>»The people of Judah and of Jerusalem will be rescued and will live in safety. The city will be called Jehovah is Our Righteousness.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.17'>»I Jehovah promise that there will always be a descendant of David to be king of Israel</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.18'>and that there will always be priests from the tribe of Levi to serve me and to offer burnt offerings, grain offerings, and sacrifices.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.19'>Jehovah continued to speak to me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.20'>»If you break my covenant of the day and my covenant of the night, so that day and night will not be at their appointed time,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.21'>then my covenant may also be broken with David my servant so that he will not have a son to reign on his throne, with the Levitical priests as my ministers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.22'>»I will increase the descendants of my servant David and the Levites who serve me in the same way as the stars of heaven that cannot be counted and the sand on the seashore that cannot be measured.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.23'>The word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.24'>»Have you not observed what this people have said. They say, The two families Jehovah chose, he has rejected? Thus they despise my people, no longer are they as a nation in their sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.25'>»Jehovah says: If My covenant for day and night do not stand and I have not established the fixed patterns of heaven and earth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.33.26'>then I would reject the descendants of Jacob and David my servant. And I would not take from his descendants rulers over the descendants of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. But I will restore their prosperity and will show them love and compassion.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.34'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.1'>Jehovah spoke his word to Jeremiah when King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon, his entire army, and all the kingdoms and people that he ruled were attacking Jerusalem and all its cities. This is what he said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.2'>»This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: Go to King Zedekiah of Judah, and tell him, Jehovah says: »I am going to hand this city over to the king of Babylon. He will burn it down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.3'>»You will not escape from him. You will certainly be captured and handed over to him. You will see the king of Babylon with your own eyes, and he will talk to you face to face. Then you will go to Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.4'>»Listen to the word of Jehovah, King Zedekiah of Judah. This is what Jehovah says about you: You will not die in war.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.5'>You will die peacefully. People will burn funeral fires for you as they did for your ancestors, the kings who lived before you. They will say: »Oh, master, as they mourn for you. I have spoken my word, declares Jehovah.« « «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.6'>The prophet Jeremiah told all these things to King Zedekiah of Judah in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.7'>He did this when the army of the king of Babylon was attacking Jerusalem and the cities of Lachish and Azekah. These were the only fortified cities of Judah that were left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.8'>Jehovah spoke his word to Jeremiah after King Zedekiah and all the people in Jerusalem promised to free their slaves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.9'>Everyone was supposed to free his Hebrew slaves, both male and female. No one was supposed to keep another Jew as a slave.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.10'>All the officials and all the people agreed and promised to free their male and female slaves and not to keep them as slaves anymore. So they set them free.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.11'>Later they changed their minds and took back the men and women they had freed and made them their slaves again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.12'>Jehovah continued to speak his word to Jeremiah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.13'>»This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: I put a condition on the covenant I made to your ancestors when I brought them from Egypt, where they were slaves. I said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.14'>»Every seven years each of you must free any Hebrews who sold themselves to you. When they have served you for six years, you must set them free. But your ancestors refused to obey me or listen to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.15'>»You changed and did what I consider right. You agreed to free your neighbors, and you made a covenant in my presence, in the Temple that is called by my name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.16'>»Now you have changed again and dishonored me. You brought back the male and females slaves that you had set free to live their own lives. You have forced them to be your male and female slaves again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.17'>»This is what Jehovah says: You did not obey me. You have not freed your relatives and neighbors. Now I am going to free you, declares Jehovah. I will free you to die in wars, plagues, and famines. I will make all the kingdoms of the world horrified at the thought of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.18'>I will hand over the people who have rejected my covenant. They have not kept the terms of the covenant they made in my presence when they cut a calf in two and passed between its pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.19'>I will hand over the officials of Judah and Jerusalem, the palace officials, the priests, and all the common people who passed between the pieces of the calf.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.20'>I will hand them over to their enemies who want to kill them. Their corpses will be food for birds and wild animals.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.21'>I will hand King Zedekiah of Judah and his officials over to their enemies who want to kill them and to the army of the king of Babylon, the army that has withdrawn from you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.34.22'>»I am going to give a command, declares Jehovah. I will bring that army back to this city to attack it, capture it, and burn it down. I will destroy the cities of Judah so that no one will live there.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.35'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.1'>This is the word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah, in the days of Jehoiakim, the son of Josiah, king of Judah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.2'>»Go into the house of the Rechabites and talk to them. Take them into the House of Jehovah, into one of the rooms, and give them wine.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.3'>I took Jaazaniah, the son of Jeremiah, the son of Habazziniah, and his brothers and all his sons and all the Rechabites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.4'>I took them into the House of Jehovah, into the room of the sons of Hanan, the son of Igdaliah, the man of God. This was near the rulers' room, over the room of Maaseiah, the son of Shallum, the keeper of the door.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.5'>I set out some large bowls full of wine together with some cups. Then I said to the Rechabites: »Have some wine!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.6'>But they answered: »No! The ancestor of our clan, Jonadab son of Rechab, made a rule that we must obey. He said: Do not ever drink wine</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.7'>or build houses or plant crops and vineyards. Instead, you must always live in tents and move from place to place. If you obey this command, you will live a long time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.8'>»We have obeyed all the instructions that Jonadab gave us. We never drink wine, and neither do our wives, our sons, or our daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.9'>»We do not build houses for homes for we live in tents. We own no vineyards, fields, or grain. We have fully obeyed everything that our ancestor Jonadab commanded us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.10'>»We live in tents, and we have obeyed everything our ancestor Jonadab ordered us to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.11'>»But when King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon invaded this land, we said: Let's go to Jerusalem to escape the Babylonian and Aramean armies. That is why we are living in Jerusalem.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.12'>Then Jehovah spoke his word to Jeremiah. He said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.13'>»This is what Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, says: Tell the people of Judah and those who live in Jerusalem, Will you ever learn your lesson and obey my words?« Declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.14'>»Jonadab, Rechab's son, ordered his descendants not to drink wine. This order has been carried out. His descendants have not drunk any wine to this day, because they have obeyed their ancestor's order. I have spoken to you again and again, but you have refused to listen to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.15'>»I have sent all my servants the prophets to you again and again. They said: Turn from your evil ways, do what is right, and do not follow other gods in order to serve them. Then you will live in the land that I gave you and your ancestors. However, you refused to listen to me or obey me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.16'>»The descendants of Jonadab, Rechab's son, have carried out the orders of their ancestor, but you refuse to listen to me.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.17'>»This is what Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, says: I am going to bring on Judah and on all those who live in Jerusalem all the disasters that I threatened. I have spoken to them, but they did not listen. I called to them, but they did not answer.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.18'>Then Jeremiah said to the family of Rechab: »This is what Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, says: You obeyed the order of your ancestor Jonadab, followed all his instructions, and did exactly what he told you to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.35.19'>So this is what Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, says: »A descendant of Jonadab, Rechab's son, will always serve me.« «</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.36'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.1'>In the fourth year of the reign of Jehoiakim, son of King Josiah of Judah, Jehovah spoke his word to Jeremiah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.2'>»Take a scroll, and write on it everything that I have dictated to you about Israel, Judah, and all the other nations from the time I spoke to you during the reign of Josiah until today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.3'>»Maybe the nation of Judah will hear about all the disasters that I devise to bring on them, and they will turn from their wicked ways. Then I will forgive their wickedness and their sins.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.4'>Then Jeremiah called Baruch, son of Neriah. Jeremiah dictated everything that Jehovah told him. Baruch wrote it all down on a scroll.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.5'>Jeremiah told Baruch: »I am no longer allowed to go to Jehovahs Temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.6'>»On a day of fasting, you must read from the scroll Jehovahs message that you wrote as I dictated. You must read it to the people in Jehovahs Temple. You must also read it to all the people of Judah when they come from their cities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.7'>»Maybe their prayers will come into Jehovahs presence, and they will turn from their evil ways. Jehovah has threatened these people with his terrifying anger and fury.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.8'>Baruch, son of Neriah, did as the prophet Jeremiah commanded him. In Jehovahs Temple he read from the scroll everything that Jehovah had said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.9'>In the ninth month of the fifth year of the reign of Jehoiakim, son of King Josiah of Judah, a time for fasting was called. It was a time for all the people in Jerusalem and for everyone who was coming from any city in Judah to Jerusalem to fast in Jehovahs presence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.10'>Then Baruch read the scroll containing the words of Jeremiah. Baruch read it to all the people in Jehovahs temple in the room of the scribe Gemariah, son of Shaphan, in the upper courtyard at the entrance of New Gate of Jehovahs Temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.11'>Micaiah, who was the son of Gemariah and the grandson of Shaphan, heard Baruch read from the scroll everything Jehovah had said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.12'>Then he went down to the scribe's room in the king's palace where all the scribes were sitting. The scribe Elishama, Delaiah son of Shemaiah, Elnathan son of Achbor, Gemariah son of Shaphan, Zedekiah son of Hananiah, and all the other officials were there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.13'>Micaiah told them everything he heard Baruch read from the scroll publicly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.14'>Then all the officials sent Jehudi, who was the son of Nethaniah, the grandson of Shelemiah, and the great-grandson of Cushi, to Baruch. Jehudi said to Baruch: »Bring the scroll that you read publicly, and come with me.« Baruch, son of Neriah, took the scroll and went with him to see the officers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.15'>They said to Baruch: »Please sit down, and read it to us.« So Baruch read it to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.16'>When they heard everything, they turned to each other in terror. They said to Baruch: »We must tell the king everything.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.17'>They asked Baruch: »Please tell us how you wrote all this. Did Jeremiah dictate it to you?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.18'>Baruch answered: »He dictated everything to me, and I wrote it on the scroll in ink.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.19'>The officials said to Baruch: »You and Jeremiah must hide. Do not let anyone know where you are.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.20'>After they put the scroll in the side room of the scribe Elishama, they went to the king in the courtyard and told him everything.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.21'>Then the king sent Jehudi to get the scroll. He took the scroll from the side room of the scribe Elishama. Jehudi read it to the king and all the officials standing by the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.22'>It was the ninth month, and the king was in his winter house sitting in front of the fire in the fireplace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.23'>As Jehudi read three or four columns, the king would cut them off with a scribe's knife and throw them into the fire in the fireplace. He did this until the whole scroll was burned up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.24'>The king and all his attendants did not show any fear or tear their clothes in fear when they heard everything being read.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.25'>Even when Elnathan, Delaiah, and Gemariah urged the king not to burn the scroll, he refused to listen to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.26'>The king commanded Jerahmeel the king's son, Seraiah son of Azriel, and Shelemiah son of Abdeel to arrest the scribe Baruch and the prophet Jeremiah. But Jehovah had hidden Baruch and Jeremiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.27'>After the king burned up the scroll that Baruch had written and that Jeremiah had dictated, Jehovah spoke his word to Jeremiah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.28'>»Take another scroll, and write on it everything that was written on the scroll that King Jehoiakim of Judah burned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.29'>»Say about King Jehoiakim of Judah: This is what Jehovah says: You burned this scroll, and you asked Jeremiah: »Why did you write that the king of Babylon would certainly come to destroy this land and take away people and animals?« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.30'>»This is what Jehovah says about King Jehoiakim of Judah: He will have no one to sit on David's throne, and his own corpse will be thrown out and exposed to the heat of day and the cold of night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.31'>»»I will punish him, his descendants, and his attendants for their wickedness. They refused to listen. So I will bring on them, on those who live in Jerusalem, and on the people of Judah all the disasters that I have threatened.« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.36.32'>Jeremiah took another scroll and gave it to the scribe Baruch, son of Neriah. As Jeremiah dictated, Baruch wrote on it everything that was on the scroll that King Jehoiakim of Judah had burned. They added many similar messages.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.37'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.1'>King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon appointed Zedekiah, son of Josiah, to be king of Judah. Zedekiah succeeded Jehoiakin, son of Jehoiakim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.2'>Zedekiah, his administrators, and the common people did not listen to what Jehovah spoke through the prophet Jeremiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.3'>King Zedekiah sent Jehucal son of Shelemiah and the priest Zephaniah son of Maaseiah to the prophet Jeremiah. They asked him: »Please pray to Jehovah our God for us.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.4'>Jeremiah was still free to come and go among the people. The people of Jerusalem had not put him in prison yet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.5'>Pharaoh's army came from Egypt. When the Babylonians who were blockading Jerusalem heard this news, they retreated from Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.6'>Jehovah spoke his word to the prophet Jeremiah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.7'>»This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: Say this to the king of Judah, who sent you to get advice from me: »Pharaoh's army has come out to help you. But it will go back to Egypt, its own land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.8'>»Then the Babylonians will return. They will attack the city, capture it, and burn it down.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.9'>»Jehovah says: Do not deceive yourselves by thinking that the Babylonians will leave you. They will not leave you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.10'>»Even if you would defeat the entire Babylonian army so that they had only a few badly wounded men left in their tents, they would get up and burn down this city!« «</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.11'>The Babylonian army retreated from Jerusalem because Pharaoh's army was coming.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.12'>Jeremiah wanted to leave Jerusalem and go to the territory of Benjamin to take possession of his property there among the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.13'>When he came to Benjamin Gate, the captain of the guard there, whose name was Irijah, son of Shelemiah and grandson of Hananiah, arrested the prophet Jeremiah. He said: »You are deserting to the Babylonians!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.14'>Jeremiah answered: »That is not true! I am not deserting to the Babylonians.« But Irijah would not listen to him. Irijah arrested Jeremiah and took him to the officials.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.15'>The officials were so angry with Jeremiah that they beat him and put him in prison in the scribe Jonathan's house, which had been turned into a prison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.16'>Jeremiah went into a prison cell, and he stayed there a long time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.17'>Then King Zedekiah sent for Jeremiah, and the king asked him privately in the palace: »Is there any message from Jehovah? Jeremiah answered: Yes! There is a message from Jehovah. You will be handed over to the king of Babylon.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.18'>Then Jeremiah asked King Zedekiah: »What crime have I committed against you, your administrators, or these people? Why have you put me in prison?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.19'>»Where are the prophets who told you that the king of Babylon would not attack you and this land?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.20'>»Your Majesty, please listen, and accept my plea for mercy. Do not return me to the scribe Jonathan's house, or I will die there.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.37.21'>King Zedekiah gave the command to have Jeremiah put in the courtyard of the prison. He gave him a loaf of bread every day from the bakers' street until all the bread in the city was gone. So Jeremiah stayed in the courtyard of the prison.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.38'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.1'>Shephatiah son of Mattan, Gedaliah son of Pashhur, Jehucal son of Shelemiah, and Pashhur son of Malchiah heard what I was telling the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.2'>»Jehovah says: Whoever stays on in the city will die in war or of starvation or disease. But those who go out and surrender to the Babylonians will not be killed. They will at least escape with their life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.3'>»I also told them that Jehovah said: I am going to give the city to the Babylonian army, and they will capture it.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.4'>The officials went to the king and said: »This man must be put to death. By talking like this he is making the soldiers in the city lose their courage. He is doing the same thing to everyone else left in the city. He is not trying to help the people. He only wants to hurt them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.5'>King Zedekiah answered: »Very well, then, do what you want to with him. I cannot stop you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.6'>So they took me and let me down by ropes into Prince Malchiah's well, which was in the palace courtyard. There was no water in the well, only mud, and I sank down in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.7'>Ebedmelech the Ethiopian, a eunuch officer who worked in the royal palace, heard that they had put me in the well. At that time the king was holding court at the Benjamin Gate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.8'>So Ebedmelech went there and said to the king:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.9'>»Your Majesty, what these men have done is wrong. They have put Jeremiah in the well, where he is sure to die of starvation, since there is no more food in the city.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.10'>Then the king ordered Ebedmelech the Ethiopian, »Take with you three men and to pull him out of the well before he dies.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.11'>So Ebedmelech went with the men to the palace storeroom and got some worn-out clothing which he let down to me by ropes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.12'>He told me to put the rags under my arms, so that the ropes would not hurt me. I did this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.13'>So they pulled me up out of the well. After that I was kept in the courtyard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.14'>On another occasion King Zedekiah had me brought to him at the third entrance to the temple. He said: »I am going to ask you a question, and I want you to tell me the whole truth.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.15'>I answered: »If I tell you the truth, you will put me to death, and if I give you advice, you will not pay any attention.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.16'>So King Zedekiah promised me in secret: »I swear by the living God, the God who gave us life, that I will not put you to death or hand you over to the men who want to kill you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.17'>Then I told Zedekiah that Jehovah, the God of Israel said: »If you surrender to the king of Babylons officers, your life will be spared, and this city will not be burned down. Both you and your family will be spared.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.18'>»But if you do not surrender, then this city will be handed over to the Babylonians. They will burn it down, and you will not escape from them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.19'>The king answered: »I am afraid of our own people who have deserted to the Babylonians. I may be handed over to them and tortured.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.20'>I said: »You will not be handed over to them. I beg you to obey Jehovahs message. Then all will go well with you, and your life will be spared.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.21'>»Jehovah has shown me in a vision what will happen if you refuse to surrender.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.22'>»In it I saw all the women left in Judah's royal palace being led out to the king of Babylonia's officers. Listen to what they were saying as they went. The king's best friends misled him, they overruled him. And now that his feet have sunk in the mud, his friends have left him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.23'>Then I added: »All your women and children will be taken out to the Babylonians. You will not escape from them. You will be taken prisoner by the king of Babylonia. And this city will be burned to the ground.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.24'>Zedekiah replied: »Do not let anyone know about this conversation, and your life will not be in danger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.25'>»If the officials hear that I have talked with you, they will come and ask you what we said. They will promise not to put you to death if you tell them everything.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.26'>»Just tell them you were begging me not to send you back to prison to die there.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.27'>Then all the officials came and questioned me. I told them exactly what the king had told me to say. There was nothing else they could do, because no one had overheard the conversation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.38.28'>I was kept in the palace courtyard until the day Jerusalem was captured.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.39'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.1'>In the tenth month of the ninth year that Zedekiah was king of Judah, King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylonia came with his whole army and attacked Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.2'>On the ninth day of the fourth month of Zedekiah's eleventh year as king, the city walls were broken through.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.3'>When Jerusalem was captured, all the high officials of the king of Babylon came and took their places at the Middle Gate, including Nergal Sharezer, Samgar Nebo, Sarsechim, and another Nergal Sharezer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.4'>When King Zedekiah and all his soldiers saw what was happening, they tried to escape from the city during the night. They left by way of the royal garden, went through the gateway connecting the two walls, and escaped in the direction of the Jordan Valley.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.5'>But the Babylonian army pursued them and captured Zedekiah in the plains near Jericho. Then they took him to King Nebuchadnezzar, who was in the city of Riblah in the territory of Hamath, and there Nebuchadnezzar passed sentence on him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.6'>At Riblah he put Zedekiah's sons to death while Zedekiah was looking on, and he also had the officials of Judah executed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.7'>After that, he had Zedekiah's eyes put out and had him placed in chains to be taken to Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.8'>The Babylonians burned down the royal palace and the houses of the people and tore down the walls of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.9'>Finally Nebuzaradan, the commanding officer, took away as prisoners to Babylon the people who were left in the city, together with those who had deserted to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.10'>He left in the land of Judah some of the poorest people, who owned no property, and he gave them vineyards and fields.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.11'>But King Nebuchadnezzar commanded Nebuzaradan, the commanding officer, to give the following order:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.12'>Go and find Jeremiah and take good care of him. Do not harm him, but do for him whatever he wants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.13'>So Nebuzaradan, together with the high officials Nebushazban and Nergal Sharezer and all the other officers of the king of Babylon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.14'>had me brought from the palace courtyard. They put me under the care of Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam and grandson of Shaphan, who was to see that I got home safely. Thus I stayed there among the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.15'>While I was still imprisoned in the palace courtyard, Jehovah told me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.16'>»Tell Ebedmelech the Ethiopian that Jehovah, the God of Israel, said: Just as I said I would, I am going to bring upon this city destruction and not prosperity. When this happens, you will be there to see it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.17'>»I Jehovah will protect you, and you will not be handed over to the people you are afraid of.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.39.18'>»I will keep you safe, and you will not be put to death. You will escape with your life because you have put your trust in me. I Jehovah have spoken!«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.40'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.1'>Jehovah spoke his word to Jeremiah after Nebuzaradan, the captain of the guard, let him go at Ramah. Nebuzaradan found Jeremiah in chains along with the captives of Jerusalem and Judah who were being taken to Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.2'>The captain of the guard took Jeremiah aside and said to him: »Jehovah your God threatened to bring this disaster on this place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.3'>»He has carried out his threat. Jehovah did as he promised because you Israelites have sinned against him and refused to obey him. That is why this has happened to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.4'>»Today, I am removing the chains from your hands. If you would like to come with me to Babylon, come, and I will look after you. But if you do not want to come with me to Babylon, do not come. The whole land is yours. Go wherever you want.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.5'>If you wish to remain, then go back to Gedaliah, son of Ahikam and grandson of Shaphan, whom the king of Babylon appointed to govern the cities of Judah. Live among the people with him, or go anywhere you want. The captain of the guard gave Jeremiah some food and a present and let him go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.6'>Jeremiah went to Gedaliah, son of Ahikam, at Mizpah and lived with him among the people who were left in the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.7'>All the army commanders and their men who were in the field heard that the king of Babylon had appointed Gedaliah, son of Ahikam, to govern the country and some of the country's poorest men, women, and children who had not been taken away to Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.8'>These are the commanders who went with their men to Gedaliah at Mizpah: Ishmael son of Nethaniah, Johanan and Jonathan sons of Kareah, Seraiah son of Tanhumeth, the sons of Ephai from Netophah, and Jezaniah, who was the son of a man from Maacah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.9'>Gedaliah, son of Ahikam and grandson of Shaphan, swore an oath to them and their men. He said: »Do not be afraid to serve the Babylonians. Live in this country, serve the king of Babylon, and you will prosper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.10'>»I am going to live in Mizpah and represent you when the Babylonians come to us. Gather grapes, summer fruit, and olive oil, and put them in storage jars. Live in the cities you have taken over.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.11'>All the Jews who were in Moab, Ammon, Edom, and in all the other countries heard that the king of Babylon had left a few survivors in Judah and had appointed Gedaliah, son of Ahikam and grandson of Shaphan, to govern them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.12'>So all the Jews returned from all the places where they had been scattered. They came to Judah and to Gedaliah at Mizpah. They gathered a large harvest of grapes and summer fruit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.13'>Kareah's son Johanan and all the army commanders who were still in the country came to Gedaliah at Mizpah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.14'>They asked him: »Do you know that King Baalis of the Ammonites has sent Ishmael, Nethaniah's son, to kill you?« However, Gedaliah, son of Ahikam, did not believe them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.15'>Then Johanan, Kareah's son, secretly asked Gedaliah at Mizpah: »Let me kill Ishmael, Nethaniah's son. No one will know about it. Why should he kill you? All the Jews who have gathered around you would scatter. What is left of Judah would disappear.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.40.16'>Gedaliah, son of Ahikam, told Johanan, Kareah's son: »Do not do that! What you are saying about Ishmael is a lie.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.41'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.1'>In the seventh month Ishmael son of Nethaniah and grandson of Elishama, a descendant of the royal family and of the king's officers went with ten men to Gedaliah, son of Ahikam, at Mizpah. As they ate together at Mizpah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.2'>Ishmael, son of Nethaniah, and the ten men who were with him got up, drew their swords, and killed Gedaliah, son of Ahikam and grandson of Shaphan. So they assassinated the man whom the king of Babylon had appointed to govern the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.3'>Ishmael also killed all the Jews who were with Gedaliah at Mizpah as well as the Babylonian soldiers that he found there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.4'>The day after the murder of Gedaliah, before anyone knew about it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.5'>Eighty men arrived from Shechem, Shiloh, and Samaria. Their beards were shaved off, their clothes were torn, and cuts were on their bodies. They brought grain offerings and incense to Jehovahs Temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.6'>Ishmael, son of Nethaniah, left Mizpah to meet them. He was crying as he went. When he met them, he said to them: »Come to Gedaliah, son of Ahikam.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.7'>When they came into the city, Ishmael, son of Nethaniah, and his men slaughtered them and threw them into a cistern.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.8'>Ten men from the group pleaded with Ishmael: »Do not kill us! We have wheat, barley, olive oil, and honey hidden in the country.« So he left them alone and did not kill them along with the others.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.9'>The cistern where Ishmael threw all the bodies of the men he had killed was the same one that King Asa made as a part of his defense against King Baasha of Israel. Ishmael, son of Nethaniah, filled it with the bodies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.10'>Then Ishmael took captive the rest of the people who were at Mizpah. He captured the king's daughters and all the other people who had been left at Mizpah. They were the people whom Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard had put under the control of Gedaliah son of Ahikam. Ishmael son of Nethaniah took them captive and left for Ammon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.11'>When Kareah's son Johanan and all the army commanders who were with him heard about all the crimes Ishmael son of Nethaniah did,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.12'>they took all their men and went to fight Ishmael. They caught up with him at the large pool in Gibeon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.13'>When all the people who were with Ishmael saw Kareah's son Johanan and all the army commanders who were with him, they were glad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.14'>Then all the people Ishmael had taken captive at Mizpah turned and ran to Kareah's son Johanan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.15'>Ishmael and eight of his men escaped from Johanan and fled to Ammon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.16'>Then Kareah's son Johanan and all the army commanders who were with him brought back the rest of the people of Mizpah whom he had rescued from Ishmael, son of Nethaniah, after Ishmael had killed Gedaliah, son of Ahikam. Johanan brought back men, women, children, soldiers, and commanders from Gibeon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.17'>When they left Gibeon, they stayed near Bethlehem at Geruth Kimham on their way to Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.41.18'>They were afraid of the Babylonians because Ishmael had killed Gedaliah whom the king of Babylon had appointed to govern the land.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.42'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.1'>All the army leaders, including Johanan son of Kareah and Azariah son of Hoshaiah, came with people of every class.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.2'>They said to me: »Please do what we ask you! Pray to Jehovah our God for us. Pray for all of us who have survived. Once there were many of us. Now there are only a few of us left, as you can see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.3'>»Pray that Jehovah our God will show us the way we should go and what we should do.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.4'>I answered: »Very well, then. I will pray to Jehovah our God, just as you have asked. I will tell you what he says. I will not keep back anything from you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.5'>Then they said to me: »May Jehovah be a true and faithful witness against us if we do not obey all the commandments that Jehovah our God gives you for us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.6'>»Whether it pleases us or not, we will obey Jehovah our God, to whom we are asking you to pray. All will go well with us if we obey him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.7'>Ten days later Jehovah spoke to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.8'>I called together Johanan, all the army leaders who were with him, and all the other people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.9'>I said to them, »Jehovah, the God of Israel, to whom you sent me with your request said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.10'>If you are willing to go on living in this land I will build you up and not tear you down. I will plant you and not uproot you. The destruction I brought on you has caused me great sorrow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.11'>Stop being afraid of the king of Babylon. I am with you. I will rescue you from his power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.12'>For the reason that I am merciful, I will make him have mercy on you and let you go back home. I Jehovah have spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.13'>»If you say: »We will not stay in this land, and you disobey Jehovah your God.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.14'>Then you say: »We will go to Egypt, where we will not have to see war, hear the sound of a ram's horn, or be hungry. We will stay there.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.15'>Listen to the word of Jehovah, you people who are left in Judah. This is what Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, says: »Suppose you are determined to go to Egypt, and you go and live there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.16'>»Then the war that you fear will overtake you, and the hunger you dread will follow you, and you will die there in Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.17'>»All the people who are determined to go and live in Egypt will die either in war or of starvation or disease. Not one of them will survive, not one will escape the disaster that I am going to bring on them.« </verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.18'>»Jehovah, the God of Israel, says: Just as my anger and fury were poured out on the people of Jerusalem, so my fury will be poured out on you if you go to Egypt. You will be a horrifying sight. People will make fun of you and use your name as a curse. You will never see this place again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.19'>»Then I continued: Jehovah has told you people who are left in Judah not to go to Egypt. And so I warn you now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.20'>»You are making a fatal mistake. You asked me to pray to Jehovah our God for you, and you promised that you would do everything that he commands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.21'>»Now I have told you, but you are disobeying everything that Jehovah our God sent me to tell you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.42.22'>»So then, remember this: you will die in war or of starvation or disease in the land where you want to go and live.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.43'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.43.1'>As soon as Jeremiah, whom Jehovah their God had sent, had finished telling all the people all the words of Jehovah their God, that is, all these words,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.43.2'>Azariah the son of Hoshaiah, and Johanan the son of Kareah, and all the arrogant egotistical men said to Jeremiah: »You are telling a lie! Jehovah our God has not sent you to say: You are not to enter Egypt to reside there.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.43.3'>Baruch the son of Neriah is inciting you against us to give us over into the hand of the Chaldeans. They will put us to death or exile us to Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.43.4'>So Johanan the son of Kareah and all the commanders of the forces, and all the people, did not obey the voice of Jehovah and stay in the land of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.43.5'>But Johanan the son of Kareah and all the commanders of the forces took the entire remnant of Judah who had returned from all the nations to which they had been driven away, in order to reside in the land of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.43.6'>They took men, women, children, and the king's daughters. They took every person whom Nebuzaradan, the captain of the guard, had left with Gedaliah, son of Ahikam and grandson of Shaphan, including the prophet Jeremiah and Baruch, son of Neriah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.43.7'>They did not listen to Jehovah. They went to Egypt. They went as far as Tahpanhes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.43.8'>Then Jehovah spoke his word to Jeremiah in Tahpanhes. He said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.43.9'>»Take some large stones, and bury them under the brick pavement at the entrance to the Pharaoh's palace in Tahpanhes. Do this while the people of Judah watch you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.43.10'>»Say to them: This is what Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, says: I am going to send for my servant King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon. I will set his throne over these stones that I buried, and I will spread his royal canopy above them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.43.11'>»He will defeat Egypt. He will bring death to those who are supposed to die. He will capture those who are supposed to be captured. He will kill in battle those who are supposed to be killed in battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.43.12'>»He will set fire to the temples of Egypt's gods. He will burn down the temples and take their gods captive. Nebuchadnezzar will put on Egypt as his coat as a shepherd puts on his coat. He will leave Egypt peacefully.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.43.13'>»At Beth Shemesh he will break the monuments in Egypt and burn down the temples of Egypt's gods.« «</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.44'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.1'>Jehovah spoke to me concerning all the Israelites living in Egypt, in the cities of Migdol, Tahpanhes, and Memphis, and in the southern part of the country«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.2'>»Jehovah, the God of Israel, said: You have seen the destruction I brought on Jerusalem and all the other cities of Judah. Even now they are still in ruins, and no one lives in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.3'>»This is because their people had done evil and had made me angry. They offered sacrifices to other gods and served gods that neither they nor you nor your ancestors ever worshiped.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.4'>»I kept sending you my servants the prophets, who told you not to do this terrible thing that I hate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.5'>»But you would not listen or pay any attention. You would not give up your evil practice of sacrificing to other gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.6'>»I poured out my anger and fury on the towns of Judah and on the streets of Jerusalem. I set them on fire. They were left in ruins and became a horrifying sight, as they are today.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.7'>»I Jehovah, the God of Israel, says: Now ask why you are doing such an evil thing to yourselves. Do you want to bring destruction on men and women, children and babies, so that none of your people will be left?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.8'>»Why do you make me angry by worshiping idols and by sacrificing to other gods here in Egypt, where you have come to live? Are you doing this just to destroy yourselves, so that every nation on earth will make fun of you and use your name as a curse?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.9'>»Have you forgotten all the wicked things that have been done in the towns of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem by your ancestors, by the kings of Judah and their wives, and by you and your wives?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.10'>»You have not humbled yourselves to this very day. You have not honored me or lived according to all the laws that I gave you and your ancestors.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.11'>»I Jehovah, the God of Israel, will turn against you and destroy all Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.12'>»As for the people of Judah who are left and are determined to go and live in Egypt, I will see to it that all of them are destroyed. All of them, great and small will die in Egypt, either in war or of starvation. They will be a horrifying sight. People will make fun of them and use their name as a curse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.13'>»I will punish those who live in Egypt, just as I punished Jerusalem with the sword war, starvation, and disease.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.14'>»None of the people of Judah who are left and have come to Egypt to live will escape or survive. Not one of them will return to Judah, where they long to live once again. No one will return except a few refugees.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.15'>Then all the men who knew that their wives offered sacrifices to other gods, and all the women who were standing there, including the Israelites who lived in southern Egypt, a large crowd in all said to me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.16'>»We refuse to listen to what you have told us in the name of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.17'>»We will do everything that we said we would. We will offer sacrifices to our goddess, the Queen of Heaven, and we will pour out wine offerings to her, just as our ancestors, our king and our leaders, and we used to do in the towns of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem. Then we had plenty of food, we were prosperous, and had no troubles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.18'>»Ever since we stopped sacrificing to the Queen of Heaven and stopped pouring out wine offerings to her, we have had nothing, and our people have died in war and of starvation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.19'>»The women added: When we baked cakes shaped like the Queen of Heaven, offered sacrifices to her, and poured out wine offerings to her, our husbands approved of what we were doing.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.20'>Then I said to all the men and the women who had answered me in this way:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.21'>»About the sacrifices you and your ancestors, your kings and your leaders, and the people of the land offered in the towns of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem: do you think that Jehovah did not know about them or that he forgot them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.22'>»This very day your land lies in ruins and no one lives in it. It has become a horrifying sight. People use its name as a curse because Jehovah could no longer endure your wicked and evil practices.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.23'>»This present disaster has come on you because you offered sacrifices to other gods and sinned against Jehovah by not obeying all his commandments.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.24'>»I told all the people, especially the women, what Jehovah, the God of Israel, was saying to the people of Judah living in Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.25'>»Both you and your wives have made solemn promises to the Queen of Heaven. You promised that you would offer sacrifices to her and pour out wine offerings to her, and you have kept your promises. Very well, then! Keep your promises! Carry out your vows!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.26'>»But now listen to the vow that I, Jehovah, have made in my mighty name to all you in Judah and in Egypt: Never again will I let any of you use my name to make a vow by saying: »I swear by the living God, Jehovah!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.27'>»I will see to it that you will not prosper, but will be destroyed. All of you will die! You will die in war or of disease, until not one of you is left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.28'>»But a few of you will escape death and return from Egypt to Judah. Then the survivors will know whose words have come true, mine or theirs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.29'>»I Jehovah will give you proof that I will punish you in this place and that my promise to bring destruction on you will come true.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.44.30'>»Jehovah says, I will hand over King Hophra of Egypt to his enemies who want to kill him, just as I handed over King Zedekiah of Judah to King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon, who was his enemy and wanted to kill him.« «</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.45'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.45.1'>This is the message that the prophet Jeremiah spoke to Baruch, son of Neriah. Baruch wrote these things on a scroll book as Jeremiah dictated them during the fourth year that Jehoiakim, son of Josiah, was king of Judah. Jeremiah said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.45.2'>»This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says to you, Baruch:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.45.3'>You said: »I am so miserable! Jehovah has added grief to my pain. I am worn out from groaning. I cannot find any rest.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.45.4'>»Say this to Baruch: This is what Jehovah says: »I will tear down what I have built. I will uproot what I have planted throughout the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.45.5'>»Are you looking for great things for yourself? Do not look for them.« »I am going to bring disaster on all people!« Declares Jehovah, »But wherever you go I will let you escape with your life.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.46'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.1'>Jehovah spoke this message to the prophet Jeremiah about the nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.2'>This is the message about EGYPT, about the army of Pharaoh Neco, king of Egypt. King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon defeated his army at Carchemish along the Euphrates River during the fourth year that Jehoiakim, son of Josiah, was king of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.3'>»Get your large and small shields ready and advance into battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.4'>»Harness your horses. Mount up, you horsemen. Take your positions, and put on your helmets. Polish your spears. Put on your armor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.5'>»What do I see in them? They are terrified. They are retreating. Their warriors are defeated. They flee without looking back. Terror is all around them!« declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.6'>The infantry cannot flee. The warriors cannot escape. They stumble and fall in the north by the Euphrates River.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.7'>Who is this, rising like the Nile River, like streams that flow swiftly?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.8'>Egypt is like the rising Nile River, like a river quickly overflowing its banks. Egypt says: »I will rise. I will cover the earth. I will destroy cities and the people in them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.9'>Go into battle, you horsemen. Drive wildly, you chariot drivers. March into battle, you warriors, you warriors from Sudan and Put who carry shields, you warriors from Lydia who use bows and arrows.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.10'>That day belongs to Jehovah of Hosts. It is a day of vengeance when he will take revenge on his enemies. His sword will devour until it has had enough, and it will drink their blood until it is full. The Almighty Jehovah of Hosts will offer them as sacrifices in the north by the Euphrates River.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.11'>Go to Gilead, and get medicine, dear people of Egypt. You have used many medicines without results and cannot be cured.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.12'>The nations have heard of your shame. Your cry fills the earth. One warrior will stumble over another, and both will fall together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.13'>Jehovah spoke this message to the prophet Jeremiah about the coming of King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon, who will defeat Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.14'>»Tell this in Egypt. Announce this in Migdol. Make it known in Memphis and in Tahpanhes. Say: Take your positions, and get ready. Swords will kill those around you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.15'>»Why should your soldiers be cut down? They cannot stand because Jehovah will push them down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.16'>« They have repeatedly stumbled and now they have fallen. They say to each other: Get up! Let us go back to our people, to the land where we were born and escape our enemy's sword.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.17'>»There they will cry: Pharaoh, king of Egypt, is a big windbag. He has missed his chance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.18'>»As I live, declares the king, whose name is Jehovah of Hosts; someone who is like Mount Tabor among the mountains will come. Someone who is like Mount Carmel by the sea will come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.19'>»Pack your bags inhabitants of Egypt, because you will be taken away as captives. Memphis will become a dreary wasteland, a pile of rubble where no one lives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.20'>»Egypt is like a beautiful cow, but a horsefly distruction from the north will attack it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.21'>»Egypt's hired soldiers are like fattened calves. They will turn and run away together. They will not stand their ground. The day of destruction is coming. At that time they will be punished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.22'>»Egypt will hiss like a snake as it slithers away. Its enemies will come with full force. They will attack it with axes like those who chop wood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.23'>»They will cut down the forest, declares Jehovah, since Egypt cannot be found. They are more numerous than locusts. They cannot be counted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.24'>»The people of Egypt will be put to shame. They will be handed over to the people from the north.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.25'>»Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, says: I am going to punish Amon, who is the god of Thebes. I will also punish Pharaoh, Egypt, its gods, its kings, and whoever trusts Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.26'>»I will hand them over to those who want to kill them, to King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon and his officers. Afterward, they will live in peace as they did long ago,declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.27'>»Do not be afraid, my servant Jacob. Do not be terrified, Israel. I am going to rescue you and your descendants from a faraway land, from the land where you are captives. Then Jacob's descendants will again have undisturbed peace, and no one will make them afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.46.28'>»Do not be afraid, my servant Jacob,« declares Jehovah. »I am with you. I will completely destroy all the nations where I scattered you, but I will not completely destroy you. I will correct you with justice. I will not let you go entirely unpunished.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.47'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.47.1'>That which came as the word of Jehovah to Jeremiah the prophet concerning the PHILISTINES, before Pharaoh conquered Gaza.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.47.2'>Jehovah says: »Behold! Waters are going to rise from the north and become an overflowing torrent. They will overflow flood the land and all its fullness, the city and those who live in it and the men will cry out. Every inhabitant of the land will wail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.47.3'>»They will hear the sound of galloping warhorses, the rattling of enemy chariots, and the rumbling of their wheels. Fathers who lack courage abandon their children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.47.4'>The time has come to destroy all the Philistines, to cut off from Tyre and Sidon any Philistine who might have escaped to get help. Jehovah will destroy the Philistines and anyone who is left from the island of Crete.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.47.5'>»Gaza will shave its head in mourning. Ashkelon will be destroyed. How long will you cut yourselves, you people left on the plains?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.47.6'>»You cry out: Sword of Jehovah, how long will you keep on fighting? Go back into your sheath. Stay there and rest!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.47.7'>»How can the sword of Jehovah rest? Jehovah has ordered it to attack Ashkelon and the coast. He has assigned it to be there.« (Ezekiel 21:3, 30) (Revelation 19:15, 16)</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.48'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.1'>This is what the Lord Jehovah said about MOAB: »Pity the people of Nebo. Their town is destroyed! Kiriathaim is captured, its mighty fortress torn down, and its people put to shame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.2'>»The splendor of Moab is gone. The enemy has captured Heshbon and plot to destroy the nation of Moab. The town of Madmen will be silenced. Armies will march against it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.3'>»The people of Horonaim cry out: »Violence! Destruction!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.4'>Moab has been destroyed! Listen to the children crying.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.5'>Hear the sound of their sobs along the road up to Luhith, the cries of distress on the way down to Horonaim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.6'>»Quick, run for your lives!« They say. »Run like a wild desert donkey!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.7'>Moab, you trusted in your strength and your wealth, but now even you will be conquered. Your god Chemosh will go into exile, along with his princes and priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.8'>Not a town will escape the destruction. Both valley and plain will be ruined. I Jehovah have spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.9'>»Set up a tombstone for Moab. It will soon be destroyed. Its towns will be left in ruins, and no one will live there again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.10'>»Curse those who do not do Jehovahs work with all their heart! Curse those who do not slash and kill!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.11'>Jehovah said: »Moab has always lived secure and has never been taken into exile. Moab is like wine left to settle undisturbed and never poured from jar to jar. Its flavor has never been ruined, and it tastes as good as ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.12'>»So now, the time is coming when I will send people to pour Moab out like wine. They will empty its wine jars and break them in pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.13'>»Then the Moabites will be disillusioned with their god Chemosh. The same as the Israelites were disillusioned with Bethel, their trusted god.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.14'>»Men of Moab, why do you claim to be heroes, brave soldiers tested in war?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.15'>»Moab and its cities are destroyed. Its finest young men have been slaughtered. I am the king, the Lord Jehovah, and I have spoken!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.16'>»Moab's doom approaches. Its ruin is coming soon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.17'>»Mourn for that nation, you that live nearby, all of you that know its fame. Say: Its powerful rule has been broken. Its glory and might are no more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.18'>»You that live in Dibon come down from your place of honor and sit on the ground in the dust. Moab's destroyer is here and has left its forts in ruins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.19'>»You that live in Aroer stand by the road and wait. Ask those who are running away, say, What has happened?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.20'>»Moab has fallen, they will answer; weep for it because it is disgraced. Announce along the Arnon River that Moab is destroyed!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.21'>»Judgment has come on the cities of the plateau: on Holon, Jahzah, Mephaath,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.22'>»Dibon, Nebo, Beth Diblathaim,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.23'>»Kiriathaim, Bethgamul, Bethmeon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.24'>»Kerioth, and Bozrah. Judgment has come on all the cities of Moab, far and near.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.25'>»Moab's might has been crushed. Its power has been destroyed. I Jehovah have spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.26'>»Jehovah said: Make Moab drunk, because it has rebelled against me. Moab will roll in its own vomit and people will laugh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.27'>»Moab, remember how you made fun of the people of Israel? You treated them as though they had been caught with a gang of robbers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.28'>»You people who live in Moab, leave your towns! Go and live on the cliffs! Be like the dove that makes its nest in the sides of a ravine.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.29'>»Moab is very proud! I have heard how proud, arrogant, and conceited the people are, how much they think of themselves.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.30'>»Jehovah says: I know Moabs great pride, but it is of no use. Moabs bragging gains nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.31'>»I cry with sadness for Moab, yes for everyone in Moab. I moan for the people from the town of Kir-Hareseth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.32'>»I weep with the people of the town of Jazer. And what of the grapevines of the town of Sibmah? In the past your vines spread all the way to the sea, as far as the sea of Jazer. But the destroyer has taken over your fruit and grapes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.33'>« Joy and gladness are taken from the fruitful orchards and fields and from the land of Moab. I have stopped the flow of wine from the wine presses. No one walks on the grapes with shouts of joy. There are shouts, but they are not shouts of joy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.34'>»Their crying can be heard from Moabite towns. It can be heard from Heshbon to Elealeh and Jahaz, from Zoar as far away as Horonaim and Eglath Shelishiyah three year old heifer. Even the waters of Nimrim are dried up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.35'>»I will stop Moab from making burnt offerings at the places of worship. I will stop Moab from burning incense to their gods, says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.36'>»My heart cries sadly for Moab like a flute playing a funeral song. It cries like a flute for the people from Kir Hareseth. The money they made has all been taken away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.37'>»They have all shaved their heads and cut off their beards. They have all made gashes on their hands, and everyone is wearing sackcloth.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.38'>»People are weeping on every roof in Moab and in every public square. There is only sadness, because I have broken Moab like a jar no one wants, say Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.39'>Moab has been shattered! Cry out! Moab has been disgraced. It is in ruins and all the surrounding nations make fun of it. I Jehovah have spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.40'>»This is what Jehovah says: Look! Someone is coming like an eagle diving down from the sky and spreading its wings over Moab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.41'>»The towns of Moab will be captured. The strong walled cities will be defeated. Then Moabs warriors will be frightened like a woman who is giving birth.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.42'>»The nation of Moab will be destroyed. This is because they thought they were greater than Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.43'>»Fear, deep pits, and traps wait for you people of Moab, says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.44'>»People will run out of fear, but they will fall into the pits. Those who climb out of the pits will be caught in the traps. »I will bring the year of punishment to Moab,« says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.45'>Helpless people have run to find protection in Heshbon, the city that King Sihon once ruled, but it is in flames. It has burned up leaders of Moab and destroyed those proud people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.46'>»Pity the people of Moab! The people who worshiped Chemosh have been destroyed. Their sons and daughters have been taken away as prisoners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.48.47'>»In the future, however, I will make good things happen to Moab. It will be prosperous again, says Jehovah. As of now the judgement of Moab.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.49'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.1'>This is what Jehovah says about the people of AMMON: »Does Israel not have any children? Does it not have any heirs? Why has the god Milcom taken over the inheritance of Gad's descendants? Why do Milcom's people live in Gad's cities?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.2'>»That is why the days are coming, declares Jehovah, when I will sound the battle cry against Rabbah, where the people of Ammon live. It will become a pile of rubble. Its villages will be burned down. »Then Israel will take possession of its inheritance, says Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.3'>»Cry loudly, Heshbon, because Ai is destroyed. Cry, people of Rabbah, put on your sackcloth, and mourn. Run back and forth between the walls. Milcom will be taken away into captivity with its priests and officials.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.4'>Why do you brag about your valleys, your fertile valleys, you unfaithful people? You trust your treasures. You think: »Who would attack me?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.5'>»I will bring terror on you from all around,« proclaims Jehovah of Hosts. »Everyone will be scattered. No one will gather the refugees.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.6'>»Afterward, I will return the captives of Ammon, declares Jehovah.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.7'>This is what Jehovah of Hosts says about Edom: »Is there no longer any wisdom in Teman? Has wisdom disappeared from your people? Has their wisdom vanished?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.8'>»Turn and run, take cover in deep places inhabitants of Dedan. When I punish them, I will bring disaster on the descendants of Esau.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.9'>»If people come to pick your grapes, will they not leave a few grapes behind? If thieves come during the night, will they steal only until they have had enough?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.10'>»Yet, I will strip the descendants of Esau. I will find their hiding places. They will not be able to hide. Their children and relatives will be destroyed. None of their neighbors will say:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.11'>»Abandon your orphans, and I will keep them alive. Your widows can trust me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.12'>This is what Jehovah says: »If those who do not deserve to drink from the cup still drink from it, why should you go unpunished? You will not go unpunished. You must drink from it.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.13'>»I take an oath on myself,« says Jehovah, »that Bozrah will become a pile of rubble. It will become something horrifying, ridiculed, ruined, and cursed. All its cities will lie in ruins permanently.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.14'>I heard a message from Jehovah. A messenger was sent among the nations to say: »Assemble and attack Edom. Get ready for battle.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.15'>»Edom, I will make you the smallest of nations and despised among humanity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.16'>»You have frightened other people. Your arrogance has deceived you. You live on rocky cliffs and occupy the highest places in the hills. Even though you build your nest as high as an eagle, I will bring you down from there,« proclaims Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.17'>Jehovah said: »The destruction that will come on Edom will be so terrible that everyone who passes by will be shocked and terrified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.18'>»The same thing will happen to Edom that happened to Sodom and Gomorrah, when they and the nearby towns were destroyed. No one will ever live there again. I Jehovah have spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.19'>»Like a lion coming out of the thick woods along the Jordan River up to the green pastureland, I will come and make the Edomites run away suddenly from their country. Then the leader I choose will rule the nation. Who can be compared to me? Who would dare challenge me? What ruler could oppose me?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.20'>Hear that which I have determined against the people of Edom, and to what I intend to do to the people of the city of Teman. Even their children will be dragged off, and everyone will be horrified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.21'>When Edom falls, there will be such a noise that the entire earth will shake. The cries of alarm will be heard as far away as the Gulf of Aqaba.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.22'>The enemy will attack Bozrah like an eagle swooping down with outspread wings. On that day Edom's soldiers will be as frightened as a woman in labor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.23'>This is what Jehovah said about Damascus: The people in the cities of Hamath and Arpad are worried and troubled because they have heard bad news. Anxiety rolls over them like a sea, and they cannot rest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.24'>»The people of Damascus are weak and have fled in terror. They are in pain and misery like a woman in labor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.25'>»I once was pleased with your famous city. But now I warn you: Escape while you still can!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.26'>»Soon, even your best soldiers will lie dead in your streets. I the all-powerful Jehovah have spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.27'>»I will set fire to your city walls and burn down the fortresses King Benhadad built.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.28'>This is what Jehovah says about the Kedar tribe and the desert villages that were conquered by King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylonia: »Listen, you people of Kedar and the other tribes of the eastern desert. I have told Nebuchadnezzar to attack and destroy you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.29'>»His fearsome army will surround you. They will take your tents and possessions, your sheep and camels.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.30'>»Run and hide, you people of the desert who live in villages! Nebuchadnezzar has big plans for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.31'>»You have no city walls and no neighbors to help. You think you are safe. Therefore I told him to attack.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.32'>»Your camels and large herds will be yours no longer. People of the Arabian Desert, disaster will strike you from every side, and you will be scattered everywhere on earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.33'>»Hazor will be a place where only jackals live. It will become a permanent wasteland. No one will live there. No human will stay there.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.34'>Early in the rule of King Zedekiah of Judah, Jehovah spoke his word to the prophet Jeremiah about Elam.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.35'>»This is what Jehovah of Hosts says: I am going to break the bows of Elam's archers, the most important weapon of their strength.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.36'>»I will bring the four winds from the four corners of heaven against Elam and scatter its people in every direction. There will not be a nation where Elam's refugees will not go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.37'>»I will defeat the people of Elam in the presence of their enemies, in the presence of those who want to kill them. I will bring disaster with my burning anger, declares Jehovah. I will send armies after them until I put an end to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.38'>»I will set my throne in Elam and destroy its king and officials,declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.49.39'>»Afterward, I will return the captives of Elam,« declares Jehovah.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.50'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.1'>The word Jehovah spoke concerning BABYLON, the land of the Chaldeans, through Jeremiah the prophet:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.2'>»Declare and proclaim among the nations. Proclaim it and lift up a standard. Do not conceal it but say: Babylon has been captured. Bel has been put to shame. Marduk has been shattered! Her images have been put to shame and her idols have been shattered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.3'>»A nation has come up against her out of the north. It will make her land an object of horror. There will be no inhabitant in it. Both man and beast wander off. They have gone away!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.4'>»In those days and at that time,« declares Jehovah, »the sons of Israel will come. Both they and the sons of Judah will go along weeping as they go. They will seek Jehovah their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.5'>»They will ask for the way to Zion turning their faces in its direction. They will come to join themselves to Jehovah in an everlasting covenant that will not be forgotten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.6'>»My people have become lost sheep. Their shepherds have led them astray. They have made them turn aside on the mountains. They have gone along from mountain to hill and have forgotten their resting place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.7'>»All who came upon them have devoured them. Their adversaries said: We are not guilty. They have sinned against Jehovah who is the habitation of righteousness, Even Jehovah, the hope of their fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.8'>»Wander away from the midst of Babylon. Go forth from the land of the Chaldeans. Be also like male goats at the head of the flock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.9'>»I am going to stir up an alliance of strong nations from the north and bring it against Babylon. Those nations will take up positions against Babylon. Babylon will be captured from the north. Its enemy's arrows will be like skilled soldiers who don't come back empty-handed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.10'>»The Babylonians will become the prize. All who loot them will get everything they want,« declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.11'>»You are happy and excited. You have looted the people who belong to me. You dance around like calves on the grass and neigh like stallions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.12'>»But your mother will be greatly ashamed. The woman who gave birth to you will be disgraced. Babylon, you will be the least important nation. You will become a parched desert.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.13'>»No one will live in Babylon because of Jehovahs anger. It will be completely abandoned. Everyone who passes by Babylon will be horrified and hiss at all its wounds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.14'>»Take up your positions around Babylon, all you archers with bows. Shoot at it and do not save any arrows. For the people of Babylon have sinned against Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.15'>»Shout a war cry against them on every side. They will surrender. Their towers will fall and their walls will be torn down. Since this is Jehovahs vengeance, take revenge against them. Do to them what they did to others.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.16'>»Do not allow anyone in Babylon to plant or harvest. Everyone will turn to his own people and flee to his own homeland because of the enemies' swords.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.17'>»The people of Israel are like scattered sheep that lions have chased. The first to devour them was the king of Assyria. The last to gnaw at their bones was King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.18'>»This is what Jehovah of Hosts, the God of Israel, says: I am going to punish the king of Babylon and his land as I punished the king of Assyria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.19'>»I will bring the people of Israel back to their pastures. They will eat on Mount Carmel and Mount Bashan. They will eat until they are full on the mountains of Ephraim and Gilead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.20'>»In those days and at that time,« says Jehovah, »people will look for Israel's crimes, but they will find none. They will look for Judah's sins, but none will be found. I will forgive the faithful few whom I have spared.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.21'>»Attack the land of Merathaim and the people who live in Pekod. Claim them for me by killing them with a sword, says Jehovah. Do everything I commanded you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.22'>»The noise of battle and great destruction fills the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.23'>»The hammer of the whole earth is broken and shattered. See how desolate Babylon is of all the nations!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.24'>»I will set traps for you, Babylon. You will be caught, but you will not know it. You will be found and captured because you have opposed Jehovah.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.25'>Jehovah will open his armory and bring out the weapons of his fury, because Jehovah of Hosts has a job to do in the land of the Babylonians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.26'>Attack them from a distance, open their storehouses, pile up their corpses like piles of grain, claim them for me by destroying them, and do not leave anyone behind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.27'>Kill all their young bulls. Let them go to be slaughtered. How horrible it will be for them when their time has come, the time for them to be punished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.28'>Fugitives and refugees from Babylon are coming to Zion to tell about the vengeance of Jehovah our God, the vengeance for his temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.29'>»Call together the archers, the soldiers with bows, against Babylon. Set up blockades around it. Do not let anyone escape. Pay the people of Babylon back for what they have done. Do to them what they did to others. They have disobeyed Jehovah, the Holy One of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.30'>»That is why their young men will die in the streets, and all their soldiers will be silenced that day, declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.31'>»I am against you, you arrogant city, declares the Lord Jehovah of Hosts. »Your day has come, the time when I will punish you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.32'>»Those prideful people will stumble and fall, and there will be no one to help them get up. I will light a fire in their cities that will burn up everything around them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.33'>Jehovah of Hosts says: »All the people of Israel and Judah are oppressed. All their enemies have captured them. They refuse to let them go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.34'>»Their defender is strong. His name is Jehovah of Hosts. He will certainly take up their cause in order to bring rest to the land of Israel and unrest to the people who live in Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.35'>»A sword will kill the Babylonians and everyone who lives in Babylon,« declares Jehovah. »A sword will kill their officials and their wise men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.36'>»A sword will kill the false prophets. They will become fools. A sword will kill their soldiers and defeat them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.37'>»A sword will kill their horses, their chariots, and all the foreigners within their ranks. They will become women. A sword will destroy their treasures, and they will be looted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.38'>»A drought will diminish their water supply, and it will dry up. Babylon is a land of idols, statues that will go crazy with fear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.39'>»That is why desert animals will live with hyenas. Desert owls will also live there. It will no longer be inhabited or lived in for generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.40'>»Babylon will be like Sodom and Gomorrah, and their neighboring cities when I, God, destroyed them. No one will live there. No human will stay there, proclaims Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.41'>»People are going to come from the north. A great nation and many kings will rise from the ends of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.42'>»They will take hold of bows and spears. They will be cruel and have no compassion. They will sound like the sea when it roars. They will ride horses. They are ready for war, ready to attack you, people of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.43'>»The king of Babylon has heard reports about them, and he loses courage. Anguish will grip him as pain grips a woman in labor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.44'>»I will suddenly chase them from their places like a lion coming out of the jungle along the Jordan River into pastureland. I will appoint over Babylon whomever I choose. Who is like me? Who can challenge me? Is there any leader who can stand up to me?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.45'>Listen to what Jehovah is going to do against Babylon and the things he intends to do to the land of the Babylonians. He will surely drag away the little ones of the flock. He will surely destroy the pasture because of the Babylonians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.50.46'>The earth will quake at the news, »Babylon has been captured!« Its cry will be heard among the nations.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.51'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.1'>Jehovah says: »I am bringing a destructive wind against Babylon and its people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.2'>»I will send foreigners to destroy Babylon like a wind that blows straw away. When that day of destruction comes, they will attack from every side and leave the land bare.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.3'>»Do not give its soldiers time to shoot their arrows or to put on their armor. Do not spare the young men! Destroy the whole army!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.4'>»They will be wounded and die in the streets of their cities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.5'>I, the Lord Jehovah, have not abandoned Israel and Judah, even though they have sinned against me, the Holy One of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.6'>»Run away from Babylon! Run for your lives! Do not be killed because of Babylon's sin. I am now taking my revenge. I am punishing it as it deserves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.7'>»Babylon was like a gold cup in my hand, making the whole world drunk. The nations drank its wine and went out of their minds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.8'>»Babylon has suddenly fallen and is destroyed! Mourn over it! Get medicine for its wounds, and maybe it can be healed.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.9'>»Foreigners living there said: We tried to help Babylon, but it was too late. Let us leave now and go back home. God has punished Babylon with all his might and has destroyed it completely.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.10'>Jehovah says: »My people shout, Jehovah has shown that we are in the right. Let us go and tell the people in Jerusalem what Jehovah our God has done.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.11'>»Jehovah has stirred up the kings of Media, because he intends to destroy Babylon. That is how he will take revenge for the destruction of his Temple. The attacking officers command: Sharpen your arrows! Get your shields ready!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.12'>»Give the signal to attack Babylon's walls. Strengthen the guard! Post the sentries! Place troops in ambush! Jehovah has done what he said he would do to the people of Babylon.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.13'>»That country has many rivers and rich treasures. Yet its time is up, and its thread of life is cut.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.14'>Jehovah has sworn by his own life: »I will bring many men to attack Babylon like a swarm of locusts, and they will shout with victory.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.15'>Jehovah made the earth by his power. By his wisdom he created the world and stretched out the heavens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.16'>When He utters His voice, there is a tumult of waters in the heavens. He causes the clouds to ascend from the end of the earth. He makes lightning for the rain and brings forth the wind from his storehouses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.17'>All mankind is stupid and devoid of knowledge. Every goldsmith is put to shame by his idols. His molten images are deceitful, and there is no breath in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.18'>They are worthless, a work of mockery. In the time of their punishment they will perish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.19'>The portion of Jacob is not like these. He is the maker of all and of the tribe of his inheritance. Jehovah of Hosts is his name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.20'>He says: »You are my war-club, my weapon of war. I shatter nations with you and with you I destroy kingdoms.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.21'>»I will use you to crush horses and their riders. I will use you to crush chariots and their drivers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.22'>»I will use you to crush men and women. I will use you to crush the old and the young. I will use you to crush young men and women.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.23'>»I will use you to crush shepherds and their flocks. I will use you to crush farmers and their oxen. I will use you to crush governors and officials.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.24'>»In your presence I will pay back Babylon and all the people who live in Babylon for all the evil things that they did in Zion,« proclaims Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.25'>»I am against you, Babylon, you destructive mountain. You have destroyed the whole earth,« declares Jehovah. »I will use my power against you and roll you off the cliffs, and make you a scorched mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.26'>»People will not find any stones in you to use as a cornerstone. They will not find any stones in you to use for a foundation. You will become permanent ruins,« declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.27'>Raise your battle flag throughout the world. Blow the ram's horn among the nations. Prepare nations to attack Babylon. Tell the kingdoms of Ararat, Minni, and Ashkenaz to attack it. Appoint a commander to lead the attack. Bring up horses like a swarm of locusts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.28'>Prepare nations to attack Babylon. Prepare the king of the Medes, their governors, all their deputies, and all the countries that they rule.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.29'>The earth trembles and writhes in pain. Jehovah carries out his plans against Babylon to make Babylon a wasteland so that no one will live there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.30'>The warriors of Babylon have stopped fighting. They stay in their fortified cities. Their strength has failed. They have become women. Their buildings are set on fire. The bars across their gates are broken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.31'>Runners run to meet runners. Messengers follow messengers. They inform the king of Babylon that his entire city is captured.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.32'>The river crossings have been taken. The enemy has burned its marshes, and its soldiers are terrified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.33'>»I am the All-Powerful Jehovah, the God of Israel, and I make this promise: Soon Babylon will be leveled and packed down like a threshing place at harvest time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.34'>»The people of Jerusalem say: King Nebuchadnezzar made us panic. That monster big snake filled up with our treasures, leaving us empty. He gobbled down what he wanted and spit out the rest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.35'>»The people of Babylon harmed some of us and killed others. Now Jehovah will make them pay.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.36'>Therefore Jehovah says: »I am going to plead your case and exact full vengeance for you. I will dry up her sea and make her fountain dry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.37'>»Babylon will become a heap of ruins, a haunt of jackals, an object of horror and hissing, without inhabitants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.38'>»They will roar together like young lions. They will growl like lions' cubs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.39'>»When they become heated up, I will serve them their banquet and make them drunk, that they may become jubilant. Then they may sleep a perpetual sleep and not wake up, declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.40'>»I will bring them down like lambs to the slaughter, like rams together with male goats.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.41'>»How Sheshak has been captured, and the praise of the whole earth been seized! How Babylon has become an object of horror among the nations!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.42'>»The sea has come up over Babylon. She has been engulfed with its tumultuous waves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.43'>»Her cities have become an object of horror, a parched land and a desert, a land in which no man lives and through which no son of man passes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.44'>»I will punish Bel in Babylon. I will make Bel spit out everything that it has swallowed. Nations will no longer stream to Babylon. Its walls will fall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.45'>»Get out of her, my people! Run for your lives! Run from the burning anger of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.46'>»Do not lose courage or be afraid when rumors are heard in the land. One rumor comes one year; another rumor comes the next year. Rumors of violence are in the land. Rumors that one ruler will fight against another are in the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.47'>That is why the days are coming when I will punish Babylon's idols. The whole country will be put to shame, and all its soldiers will lie dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.48'>»Then heaven and earth and everything in them will rejoice over Babylon. Destroyers from the north will attack it,« declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.49'>Because the people of Babylon have killed many Israelites and because they have killed many people throughout the earth, Babylon must fall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.50'>You people escaped from the sword. Now leave! Do not just stand there. Remember Jehovah in a distant land and think about Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.51'>We have been put to shame. We have been disgraced. Shame covers our faces, because foreigners have gone into the holy places of Jehovahs temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.52'>»That is why the days are coming,« declares Jehovah, »when I will punish their idols, and those who are wounded will moan everywhere in the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.53'>»The people of Babylon might go up to heaven. They might fortify their strongholds. But destroyers will still come from me against them,« declares Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.54'>Cries of agony are heard from Babylon. Sounds of terrible destruction are heard from the land of the Babylonians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.55'>Jehovah will destroy Babylon. He will silence the loud noise coming from it. Waves of enemies will come roaring in like raging water. The noise will be heard everywhere.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.56'>A destroyer will attack Babylon, its soldiers will be captured, and their bows and arrows will be broken. I Jehovah am a God who punishes evil. I will certainly punish them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.57'>»I will make their officials and wise men drunk, along with their governors, officers, and soldiers. They will fall into a deep sleep and never wake up,« proclaims the king, whose name is Jehovah of Hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.58'>This is what Jehovah of Hosts says: The thick walls of Babylon will be leveled, and its high gates will be set on fire. People exhaust themselves for nothing. The nations wear themselves out only to have a fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.59'>This is the message that the prophet Jeremiah gave to Seraiah, son of Neriah and grandson of Mahseiah, when Seraiah went to Babylon with King Zedekiah of Judah in the fourth year of Zedekiah's rule. Seraiah was the quartermaster.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.60'>Jeremiah wrote on a scroll all the disasters that would happen to Babylon. He wrote all these things that have been written about Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.61'>Jeremiah said to Seraiah: »When you come to Babylon, see that you read all this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.62'>Then says: Jehovah, you have threatened to destroy this place so that no person or animal will live here. It will become a permanent ruin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.63'>»When you finish reading this scroll, tie a stone to it and throw it into the middle of the Euphrates River.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.51.64'>»Say: Babylon will sink like this scroll. It will never rise again because of the disasters that I will bring on it.« The words of Jeremiah end here.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jer.52'>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.1'>Zedekiah was twenty-one years old when he began to rule. He ruled for eleven years in Jerusalem. His mother's name was Hamutal, daughter of Jeremiah from Libnah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.2'>Zedekiah did what Jehovah considered evil, as Jehoiakim had done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.3'>Jehovah became angry at Jerusalem and Judah and threw the people out of his sight. Zedekiah rebelled against the king of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.4'>On the tenth day of the tenth month of the ninth year of Zedekiah's reign, King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon attacked Jerusalem with his entire army. They set up camp and built dirt ramps around the city walls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.5'>The blockade of the city lasted until Zedekiah's eleventh year as king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.6'>On the ninth day of the fourth month, the famine in the city became so severe that the common people had no food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.7'>The enemy broke through the city walls, and all Judah's soldiers fled. They left the city at night through the gate between the two walls beside the king's garden. While the Babylonians were attacking the city from all sides, they took the road to the plain of Jericho.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.8'>The Babylonian army pursued King Zedekiah and caught up with him in the plain of Jericho. His entire army had deserted him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.9'>The Babylonians captured the king and brought him to the king of Babylon at Riblah in Hamath. The king of Babylon passed sentence on him there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.10'>The king of Babylon slaughtered Zedekiah's sons as Zedekiah watched. He also slaughtered all the officials of Judah at Riblah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.11'>Then he blinded Zedekiah and put him in bronze shackles. The king of Babylon took him to Babylon and put him in a prison, where he stayed until he died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.12'>On the tenth day of the fifth month of Nebuchadnezzar's nineteenth year as king of Babylon, Nebuzaradan, who was the captain of the guard and an officer of the king of Babylon, came to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.13'>He burned down Jehovahs Temple, the royal palace, and all the houses in Jerusalem. Every important building was burned down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.14'>The entire Babylonian army that was with the captain of the guard tore down the walls around Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.15'>Nebuzaradan, the captain of the guard, captured the few people left in the city, those who surrendered to the king of Babylon, and the rest of the population.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.16'>Nebuzaradan, the captain of the guard, left some of the poorest people in the land to work in the vineyards and on the farms.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.17'>The Babylonians broke apart the copper pillars of Jehovahs Temple, the stands, and the copper pool in Jehovahs Temple. They shipped all the copper to Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.18'>they took the pots, shovels, snuffers, bowls, dishes, and all the copper utensils used in the Temple service.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.19'>The captain of the guard also took pans, incense burners, bowls, pots, lamp stands, dishes, and the bowls used for wine offerings. The captain of the guard took all of the trays and bowls that were made of gold or silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.20'>The copper from the two pillars, the pool, and the twelve copper bulls under the stands that King Solomon had made for Jehovahs Temple could not be weighed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.21'>One pillar was twenty-seven feet high and eighteen feet in circumference. It was three inches thick and hollow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.22'>The crown that was on it was seven and one half feet high with filigree and pomegranates around it. They were all made of copper. The second pillar was the same. It also had pomegranates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.23'>There were ninety-six pomegranates on the sides. The total number of pomegranates on the surrounding filigree was one hundred.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.24'>The captain of the guard took the chief priest Seraiah, the second priest Zephaniah, and the three doorkeepers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.25'>From the city he also took an army commander, seven men who had access to the king whom he found in the city, the scribe who was in charge of the militia, and sixty common people whom he found in the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.26'>Nebuzaradan, the captain of the guard, brought them to the king of Babylon at Riblah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.27'>The king of Babylon executed them at Riblah in the territory of Hamath. So the people of Judah were captives as they left their land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.28'>These are the people whom Nebuchadnezzar took captive: In his seventh year as king, he took three thousand and twenty-three Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.29'>In his eighteenth year, Nebuchadnezzar took eight hundred and thirty-two people from Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.30'>In Nebuchadnezzar's twenty-third year as king, Nebuzaradan, the captain of the guard, took away seven hundred and forty-five Jews. In all, four thousand six hundred people were taken away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.31'>On the twenty-fifth day of the twelfth month of the thirty-seventh year of the imprisonment of King Jehoiakin of Judah, King Evil Merodach of Babylon, in the first year of his reign, freed King Jehoiakin of Judah and released him from prison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.32'>He treated him well and gave him a special position higher than the other kings who were with him in Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.33'>Jehoiakin no longer wore prison clothes, and he ate his meals in the king's presence as long as he lived.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jer.52.34'>The king of Babylon gave him a daily food allowance as long as he lived.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>