<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisIDWork='NSB' osisRefWork='Bible' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='NSB'>
        <title>New Simplified Bible</title>
        <contributor>xxx</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>The New Simplified Bible is not affiliated with any Bible publishing society or religious organization. It is not related to the publishing and preaching work of Jehovah's Witnesses and it is not endorsed by the Watch Tower Society.</description>
        <publisher>Jim Madsen, NSB</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>NSB</identifier>
        <source>http://www.geocities.com/simplifiedbible/index.html - the Word-Files</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>
used by Permission from Jim Madsen, NSB, 
when distribute them as long as they
are offered free of charge

New Simplified Bible
All Rights Reserved Worldwide
Copyright (c) 2003-2006

     </rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='John'>
      <chapter osisID='John.1'>
        <title>(Writer: Apostle John, means Jehovah Has Shown Favor) (98 C.E.) (Near Ephesus) (92% of this Gospel is new information not contained in the other three Gospels)</title>
        <verse osisID='John.1.1'>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was like God God-like.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.2'>The same was in the beginning with God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.3'>All things were made through him and without him not one thing was made.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.4'>He lived and his life gives light to all people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.5'>His light shines through darkness and it cannot be extinguished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.6'>God sent a man named John. (Malachi 3:1)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.7'>He came to tell witnesstestify about the light and help people have faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.8'>Not being the light he came to give a witness of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.9'>The true light, which gives light to every man, came into the world. (Isaiah 49:6)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.10'>The world was made through him. He was in the world and the world did not recognize him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.11'>He came to his own. They did not receive him!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.12'>He gave the right to become children of God to all who received him. Even to those who believe in his name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.13'>They were born from God. It was not from blood, or the will of the flesh, or the will of man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.14'>The Word Jesus became flesh a human being and lived with us. We saw the glory of the only begotten son from the Father. He was full of loving-kindness and truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.15'>John spoke about him and declared: He is the one I said would come after me. He is greater than I am because he lived before me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.16'>Out of the fullness of his undeserved kindness he gives us one blessing after another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.17'>The law came through Moses. Loving-kindness and truth came through Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.18'>No man has ever seen God. The only begotten God-like one who is closest to the Father in the bosom of the Father tells us about him. (Psalm 8:5)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.19'>John gave his witness even as Jewish authorities sent priests and Levites from Jerusalem. They asked him: »Who are you?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.20'>He said: »I am not the Christ.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.21'>They asked him: »Are you Elijah?« He said: »I am not.« »Are you the prophet?« He answered: »No.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.22'>They said to him: »Who are you? We need to know so we can tell the ones who sent us.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.23'>He said: »I am the voice of one crying in the wilderness. Isaiah the prophet said: Make straight the way of Jehovah.« (Isaiah 40:3)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.24'>They were sent from the Pharisees.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.25'>They said to him: »Why do you baptize if you are not the Christ, not Elijah, and not the prophet?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.26'>John answered: »I baptize in water. There is one in your midst whom you do not know.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.27'>»I am not worthy to fasten his shoes.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.28'>These things were done in Bethany beyond the Jordan, where John was baptizing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.29'>The next day he saw Jesus coming to him. He boldly declared: »Behold! The Lamb of God that takes away the sin of the world!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.30'>»This is he whom I said would come after me. He is greater than I am because he came before me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.31'>»I did not know him. I came baptizing in water so that everyone in Israel will come to know him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.32'>John said: »I saw the spirit descending as a dove out of heaven upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.33'>»I did not know he was the one. God sent me to baptize in water and said: You will see one upon whom the spirit descends. The same is he who baptizes in Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.34'>»I have seen, and have borne witness that this is the Son of God.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.35'>The next day John was standing with two of his disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.36'>He looked at Jesus as he walked, and said: »Behold, the Lamb of God!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.37'>The two disciples heard him speak and they followed Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.38'>Jesus turned and saw them following. He asked them, »What are you after? They asked him: »Teacher, where are you staying?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.39'>He said« »Come and see.« So they came to where he was staying. They stayed with him that day. It was about the tenth hour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.40'>One of the two, who heard John speak and followed him, was Andrew, Simon Peters brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.41'>He found his brother Simon first. He said to him: »We have found the Messiah Christ.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.42'>He took him to Jesus. Jesus looked at him, and said: »You are Simon the son of John: you will be called Cephas meaning: Peter.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.43'>The next day he was reminded to go into Galilee. There he found Philip. Jesus said to him, »Follow me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.44'>Philip was from Bethsaida, of the city of Andrew and Peter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.45'>Philip found Nathanael, and said to him: »We have found the person Moses and the prophets wrote about in the Law and Gods word. It is Jesus of Nazareth, the son of Joseph.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.46'>And Nathanael said to him: »Could any good thing come out of Nazareth?« Philip said: »Come and see.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.47'>Jesus saw Nathanael coming to him. He said: »Look an Israelite indeed. There is no deceit in him!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.48'>Nathanael asked: »How do you know me?« Jesus answered: »I saw you under the fig tree before Philip called you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.49'>Nathanael answered: »Rabbi you are the Son of God. You are King of Israel.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.50'>Jesus responded: »I told you I saw you under the fig tree. Is this why you believe? You will see greater things than these.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.51'>Jesus continued: »You will see the heavens opened and you will see the angels of God ascending and descending upon the Son of man.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.2'>
        <verse osisID='John.2.1'>There was a marriage in Cana of Galilee on the third day. The mother of Jesus was there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.2'>Jesus and his disciples were also invited to the marriage feast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.3'>They ran out of wine. So the mother of Jesus said to him: »They have no wine.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.4'>Jesus said to her: »Woman what have I to do with you? My hour has not arrived.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.5'>His mother told the servants to do whatever he says.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.6'>Six stone water jars were placed there to honor purification rules of the Jews. Each contained more than twenty gallons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.7'>Jesus said to them: »Fill the jars with water.« They filled them to the brim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.8'>»Draw some out,« he said, »and take it to the master of the feast.« So they drew some out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.9'>The master of the feast did not know about the water turned into wine. He tasted it and called the bridegroom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.10'>He said to him: »Every man sets out the good wine first. When the men have drunk freely the lower quality wine is served. You have kept the good wine until now.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.11'>This was the first miracle Jesus performed in Cana of Galilee. It gave evidence of his glory and his disciples believed in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.12'>He, his mother, brothers and disciples traveled to Capernaum. They stayed there many days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.13'>The Passover of the Jews was at hand and Jesus went to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.14'>He found the merchants who sold oxen, sheep and doves. The moneychangers were sitting nearby.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.15'>He made a whip of cords, and chased them all out of the temple, including the sheep and the oxen. He poured out the coins of the moneychangers and overturned the tables.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.16'>He told those who sold doves: »Take these things away. Do not make my Fathers house a house of merchandise.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.17'>His disciples remembered what was written. Zeal for your house shall eat me up. (Psalm 69:9)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.18'>The Jews asked him: »What sign would you show us seeing that you do these things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.19'>Jesus replied: »Destroy this temple and in three days I will raise it up.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.20'>The Jews responded: »It took forty-six years to build this temple and you will raise it up in three days?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.21'>But he spoke of the temple of his body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.22'>When he was raised from the dead his disciples remembered that he said this. Then they believed the Scripture and the word that Jesus said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.23'>When he was in Jerusalem at the Passover feast, many saw the signs he did and expressed active faith in his name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.24'>Jesus did not trust his security to them for he understood all men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.25'>He did not need evidence about men for he knew what was in man.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.3'>
        <verse osisID='John.3.1'>Now there was a man of the Pharisees named Nicodemus, a ruler of the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.2'>He came to Jesus by night, and said to him: »Rabbi! We know you are a teacher from God. No one can do these signs that you do unless God is with him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.3'>Jesus answered: »Truly I tell you unless a person is born again brought forth from above he cannot see the kingdom of God.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.4'>Nicodemus asked: »How could a man be born when he is old? Can he enter his mothers womb again and be born?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.5'>Jesus responded: »I tell you truth, except a man be born of water and the spirit he cannot enter into the kingdom of God!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.6'>»That which is born from the flesh is flesh and that which is born from the Spirit is spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.7'>»Do not marvel that I say you must be born again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.8'>»The wind blows where it will. You hear the sound of it. Yet you do not know where it comes from or where it goes. It is like this with every one who is born from the Spirit.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.9'>Nicodemus asked: »How can these things be?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.10'>Jesus answered: »Are you a teacher of Israel and you do not understand these things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.11'>»This is the truth. We speak what we know and witness about what we have seen. But you do not receive our testimony.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.12'>»If I told you earthly things and you did not have faith, how will you have faith if I tell you heavenly things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.13'>»No one has ever ascended into heaven but the Son of man who descended from heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.14'>»As Moses lifted up the serpent in the wilderness, so the Son of man must also be lifted up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.15'>»Everyone who has an active faith in him may have everlasting life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.16'>»For God loved the world so much, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoever has an active faith in him should not perish, but have everlasting life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.17'>»God did not send the Son into the world to judge the world. Instead the world should be saved through him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.18'>»He who has an active faith in him is not judged. He who does not have an active faith has been judged already for he has not had faith in the name of the only begotten Son of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.19'>»This is the judgment, that the light has come into the world. People loved the darkness rather than the light for their works were evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.20'>»Every one who does evil hates the light. He does not come to the light because his works would be reproved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.21'>»He who practices the truth comes to the light. His works are made known that they are from God.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.22'>After these things Jesus and his disciples traveled to the land of Judea where he stayed with them and baptized.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.23'>John was also baptizing in Aenon near to Salim, because there was much water there. People came and were baptized.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.24'>John had not yet been thrown into prison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.25'>There was a controversy between some of Johns disciples and the Jews about purification.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.26'>They went to John and said: »Rabbi, he who was with you beyond the Jordan, the one about whom you witnessed, he and the men with him baptize.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.27'>John answered: »A man can receive nothing unless it is given to him from heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.28'>»You bear witness that I said I am not the Christ. I have been sent before him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.29'>»He that has the bride is the bridegroom. The friend of the bridegroom stands and listens to him. He rejoices greatly because he hears the bridegrooms voice. This fills me with joy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.30'>»He must increase and I must decrease.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.31'>»He who comes from above is above all. He who is of the earth belongs to the earth and speaks from an earthly viewpoint. He who comes from heaven is superior.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.32'>»He testifies about what he has seen and heard, but no man accepts his testimony.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.33'>»He who receives his testimony confirms by his seal that God is true.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.34'>»For he whom God has sent speaks the words of God. God does not give the spirit by measure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.35'>»The Father loves the Son and has given all things into his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.36'>»He who puts active faith in the Son has everlasting life. He who disobeys* the Son will not see life for the wrath of God remains upon him.« *Greek: apeitheo: willfully disobey, not having faith</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.4'>
        <verse osisID='John.4.1'>The Lord was aware that the Pharisees had heard that Jesus made and baptized more disciples than John.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.2'>Actually Jesus did not baptize. His disciples baptized.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.3'>He left Judea, and departed again into Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.4'>He needed to travel through Samaria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.5'>He arrived at a city of Samaria called Sychar. It is near the parcel of ground that Jacob gave to his son Joseph.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.6'>Jacobs well was there. It was about the sixth hour when Jesus arrived. Being weary from the journey he sat down by the well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.7'>A woman of Samaria came to draw water. Jesus said to her: »Please give me a drink.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.8'>His disciples went away to the city to buy meat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.9'>The woman of Samaria asked: »How is it that you being a Jew ask for a drink from me? I am a woman of Samaria.« The Jews did not associate with Samaritans.Not in early manuscripts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.10'>Jesus answered: »If you know the gift of God and who asked you for a drink, you would have asked him to give you living water.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.11'>The woman said to him: »Sir, you do not have anything with which to draw water and the well is deep. Where do you get that living water?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.12'>»Are you greater than our father Jacob? He gave us the well. He and his children and cattle drank from it.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.13'>Jesus answered: »Whoever drinks from this water will thirst again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.14'>»But whoever drinks from the water that I give him will never thirst. The water that I will give him will be in him a well of water springing up into everlasting life.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.15'>The woman said to him: »Sir, give me this water! That way I will not thirst and not come here to draw.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.16'>Jesus said to her: »Go call your husband and come here.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.17'>The woman answered: »I have no husband.« Jesus replied to her: »You said well, »I have no husband.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.18'>»For you have had five husbands. The one you have now is not your husband, this is true.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.19'>The woman said to him: »Sir, I perceive that you are a prophet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.20'>»Our fathers worshipped in this mountain. But you say Jerusalem is the place where men ought to worship.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.21'>Jesus replied: »Woman believe me. The hour comes when you will worship the Father neither in the mountain nor in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.22'>»You worship what you do not know. We worship what we know. Salvation is from the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.23'>»But the hour comes and now is when the true worshippers shall worship the Father with spirit and truth. The Father seeks such people to worship him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.24'>»God is a Spirit. They who worship him must worship him with spirit and truth.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.25'>The woman responded: »I know that Christ the Messiah is coming. When he comes he will tell us all things.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.26'>Jesus said: »I that speak to you am he.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.27'>His disciples came and wondered why he talked with the woman. Yet no one asked: »What are you looking for? Why did you talk to her?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.28'>The woman left her water pot and went to the city. She spoke to the men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.29'>»Come see a man who told me everything I have ever done. Could this be the Christ?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.30'>They left the city to see him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.31'>In the meantime his disciples urged him to eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.32'>He said: »I have food to eat that you do not know about.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.33'>So the disciples said to each other: »Has any man brought him something to eat?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.34'>Jesus said: »My food is to do the will of him that sent me. To finish his work!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.35'>»Do you say there are four months until the harvest comes? I say to you lift up your eyes and look on the fields. They are already white for harvest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.36'>»He who reaps receives wages, and gathers fruit for life eternal. Both he who sows and he who reaps may rejoice together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.37'>»That saying is true. One sows and another reaps.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.38'>»I sent you to reap that for which you did not labor. Other men labored and you entered into their labors.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.39'>Many Samaritans of that city put faith believed in him because of what the woman said: »He told me everything I have ever done.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.40'>When the Samaritans came to him they urged him to stay with them. So he stayed there two days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.41'>Many more believed because of the words he spoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.42'>They told the woman: »We believe because of what you said and we heard him ourselves. We know that this is indeed the Christ, the Savior of the world!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.43'>After two days he departed from there and went to Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.44'>Jesus testified that a prophet has no honor in his own country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.45'>The Galileans welcomed him. They saw all the things he did at the feast in Jerusalem for they were at the feast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.46'>Jesus returned to Cana of Galilee where he turned the water into wine. There was a nobleman whose son was sick at Capernaum.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.47'>He heard that Jesus came from Judea into Galilee. He went to him and urged him to come see his son. His son was near death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.48'>»Until you see signs and wonders you will not believe,« Jesus said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.49'>The nobleman said: »Sir, come or my child would die.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.50'>Jesus replied: »Go your way. Your son lives!« The man believed the word that Jesus spoke to him, and he went his way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.51'>His servants met him as he returned and said: »Your son is alive!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.52'>He asked them about the hour he was healed. They said: »Yesterday at the seventh hour the fever left him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.53'>The father knew that it was the same hour in which Jesus said: »Your son lives.« He and his entire household believed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.54'>This is the second miracle that Jesus did when he came out of Judea into Galilee.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.5'>
        <verse osisID='John.5.1'>After this the Jews had a Festival holy day, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.2'>There is a pool by the sheep-market gate at Jerusalem. It is called in the Hebrew tongue Bethzatha. It has five porches colonnades.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.3'>In these lay a great crowd of sick people, of blind and lame waiting for the water to bubble up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.4'>Not in older manuscripts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.5'>A man who had an infirmity for thirty-eight years was present.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.6'>Jesus saw him lying there. He knew that he had been sick for a long time. So he asked him: »Do you want to get well?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.7'>The sick man replied: »I have no man to put me in the pool when the water is stirred. Others step down before I can go.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.8'>Jesus said: »Arise pick up your bed and walk.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.9'>Immediately the man was made whole. He picked up his bed and walked. It happened on the Sabbath day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.10'>So the Jews told the man who was cured: »It is not lawful for you to pickup your bed for it is the Sabbath.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.11'>He answered: »He who made me whole told me to pick up my bed and walk.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.12'>»Who is the man,« they asked, »that said to you pick up your bed and walk?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.13'>He did not know who healed him for Jesus quietly left the crowd.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.14'>Later Jesus found him in the temple and told him: »Now that you are healed do not sin anymore and avoid worse things happening to you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.15'>The man went away and told the Jews Jesus made him whole.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.16'>The Jews persecuted Jesus because he did these things on the Sabbath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.17'>Jesus responded to them: »My Father works until now and I work.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.18'>The Jews intensified their efforts to kill him for these reasons: he broke the Sabbath and he also called God his own Father, making himself equal with God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.19'>Jesus answered them: »Truly I tell you the Son can do nothing by himself. He sees the Father do something and then he does it. Whatever the Father does the Son does in like manner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.20'>»The Father loves the Son. He shows him all of the things he does. He will show him greater works than these. And you will marvel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.21'>»The Father raises the dead and gives them life. The Son also gives life to those he wills.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.22'>»The Father does not judge any man for he has given all judgment to the Son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.23'>»All may honor the Son, even as they honor the Father. He who does not honor the Son does not honor the Father that sent him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.24'>»Truly, Truly I say to you, he who hears my word, and believes him that sent me, has everlasting life. He will not receive judgment for he has passed out of death into life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.25'>»Truly I tell you, the hour is coming when the dead will hear the voice of the Son of God and those who hear listenunderstand will live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.26'>»The Son has life in himself just as the Father has life in himself. For the Father gave him life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.27'>»And he gave him authority to execute judgment, because he is the Son of man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.28'>»Do not wonder about this for the hour is coming when everyone in the grave will hear his voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.29'>»They will return. Those who did good will have the resurrection of life. Those who did evil will receive the resurrection of judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.30'>»I can do nothing by myself. So I hear and judge and my judgment is righteous. I do not seek my own will, but the will of him that sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.31'>»If I alone testify about myself, my testimony is not enough truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.32'>»There is another who testifies about me. I know that his evidence about me is true.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.33'>»You sent people to John the Baptist and he has witnessed about the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.34'>»The testimony I receive is not from man. However I say these things that you may be saved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.35'>»He was the lamp that burns and shines. You were willing to rejoice for a season in his light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.36'>»The testimony I have is greater than that of John. The works I do are the works the Father gave me to accomplish. They testify that the Father has sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.37'>»The Father who sent me testifies about me. You have not heard his voice nor seen him at any time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.38'>»You do not have his word dwelling in you. This is because you do not believe in the person he has sent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.39'>»You search investigatestudy the Scriptures because you think that in them you have everlasting life. These Scriptures testify about me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.40'>»And yet you will not come to me that you may have life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.41'>»I do not accept glory from men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.42'>»I know that the love of God is not in you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.43'>»I came in my Fathers name and you did not receive me. If another came in his own name you would receive him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.44'>»How can you believe? You seek praise and glory from one another? Why do you not seek the glory that comes from the only God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.45'>»Do not think that I will accuse you before the Father. Moses on whom you have set your hope is a plaintiff against you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.46'>»It is a fact! If you believed Moses you would believe me. He wrote about me!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.47'>»If you do not believe his writings how will you believe my words?«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.6'>
        <verse osisID='John.6.1'>After this Jesus went to the other side of the Sea of Galilee, which is the sea of Tiberias.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.2'>A great crowd followed him because they saw the signs miracles he performed on the sick.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.3'>Jesus and his disciples went to the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.4'>It was time for the Passover feast of the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.5'>Jesus looked up and saw a great crowd coming to him. He asked Philip: »Where will we buy enough bread to feed them?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.6'>He said this to test him for he knew what he would do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.7'>Philip answered: »Two hundred shillings worth of bread is not sufficient for everyone to take a little.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.8'>Andrew, Simon Peters brother, one of his disciples said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.9'>»There is a lad here who has five barley loaves and two fish. What are these among so many?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.10'>Jesus said: »Make the people sit down.« There were about five thousand men who sat down on the grass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.11'>Jesus gave thanks and then he distributed the loaves along with the fish to those sitting on the grass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.12'>When they were filled he told the disciples to gather up the broken pieces left over so nothing would be wasted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.13'>They gathered twelve baskets of leftovers after everyone had eaten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.14'>When the people saw the miracle performed they said: »Truly this is the prophet who came into the world.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.15'>Jesus knew that they were about to take him by force and make him king. So he withdrew again to the mountain by himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.16'>That evening his disciples went to the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.17'>They boarded a boat to travel over the sea to Capernaum. It was dark and Jesus had not yet come to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.18'>A great wind made the sea rise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.19'>They rowed about four miles and saw Jesus walking on the sea. He came close to the boat. They were afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.20'>He said to them: »It is I. Do not be afraid!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.21'>They eagerly brought him into the boat. The boat soon arrived at the land where they were going.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.22'>The next day the crowd stood by the side of the sea. Jesus entered the only boat while his disciples went away alone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.23'>Small boats from Tiberias came there to the place where they ate the bread after the Lord gave thanks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.24'>When the crowd saw that Jesus and his disciples were not there they got into the boats and traveled to Capernaum seeking Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.25'>They found him on the other side of the sea and said: »Rabbi Teacher when did you come here?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.26'>Jesus said: »Truly I tell you, you seek me not because you saw miracles but because you ate of the loaves and were full.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.27'>»Do not work for food that perishes but for food that offers everlasting life. The Son of man will give you this food. The Father, even God, has set his seal upon him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.28'>They asked: »What must we do, that we may work the works of God?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.29'>Jesus answered: »This is the work of God, that you have an active faith in the one whom he has sent.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.30'>They asked: »What do you offer for a sign miracle that we may see and believe you? What work will you do?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.31'>»Our fathers ate manna in the wilderness. It is written, He gave them bread out of heaven to eat.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.32'>Jesus responded: »I speak the truth! It was not Moses who gave you the bread out of heaven. My Father gives you the true bread out of heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.33'>»For the bread of God is that which comes down out of heaven. It gives life to the world.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.34'>They responded: »Lord, always give us this bread.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.35'>Jesus replied: »I am the bread of life. He who comes to me will not hunger. The one who puts active faith in me will never thirst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.36'>»I told you. You have seen me and yet do not believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.37'>»That which the Father gives me will come to me. I will not reject him who comes to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.38'>»I do not do my own will. I came down from heaven to do the will of him that sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.39'>»This is the will of him that sent me that I should not lose any of those he has given me, but I should raise them up at the last day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.40'>»For this is the will of my Father. Every one who sees the Son and puts active faith in him will have everlasting life, and I will raise him up at the last day.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.41'>The Jews complained about him. This is because he said I am the bread that came down out of heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.42'>They said: »Is Jesus the son of Joseph? We know his father and mother. How does he now say, I came down out of heaven?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.43'>Jesus answered: »Stop complaining and saying things against me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.44'>»No man can come to me unless the Father, who sent me, draws him. I will resurrect him raise him up in the last day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.45'>»It is written in the prophets: Jehovah shall teach them all. Every one who hears the Father and has learned comes to me. (Jeremiah 31:34)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.46'>»No one has seen the Father. Only he who is from God, He has seen the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.47'>»Truly, truly I tell you, he who believes has everlasting life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.48'>»I am the bread of life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.49'>»Your fathers ate the manna in the wilderness and they died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.50'>»This is the bread that comes down out of heaven that a man may eat of it and not die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.51'>»I am the living bread that came down out of heaven. If any man eats of this bread he will live forever. Yes and the bread that I will give is my flesh for the life of the world.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.52'>The Jews argued with one another saying: »How can this man give us his flesh to eat?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.53'>Jesus responded to them: »Truly I tell you if you do not eat the flesh of the Son of man and drink his blood you will not have life in yourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.54'>»He who eats my flesh and drinks my blood has everlasting life! I will raise him up at the last day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.55'>»For my flesh is meat indeed, and my blood is drink indeed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.56'>»He who eats my flesh and drinks my blood abides with me, and I with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.57'>»The living Father sent me and I live because of the Father. He who takes me for his food will live because of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.58'>»This is the bread that came down out of heaven. It is not like the bread manna the fathers ate and then died. He who eats this bread will live forever.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.59'>He said these things in the synagogue when he taught in Capernaum.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.60'>When they heard this many of his disciples said: »This is a hard saying; who can listen to it?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.61'>He knew his disciples complained about this. Jesus said: »Does this cause you to stumble?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.62'>»What if you see the Son of man ascending where he was before?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.63'>»It is the spirit that gives life. The flesh profits nothing. The words that I spoke to you are spirit and life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.64'>»There are some of you who do not believe.« Jesus knew from the beginning whom they were who did not believe and who would betray him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.65'>He stated: »For this reason listen to what I say. No man can come to me, except it be given to him from the Father.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.66'>After this many of his disciples returned to their old ways. They did not walk with him anymore.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.67'>Jesus asked the twelve: »Will you also go away?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.68'>Simon Peter answered him: »Lord, to whom shall we go? You have the words of everlasting life!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.69'>»We believe and know that you are the Holy One of God.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.70'>Jesus replied: »Did I not choose you, the twelve? And yet one of you is a devil false accuserslandererdemon«.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.71'>He spoke of Judas the son of Simon Iscariot one of the twelve, for he would betray him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.7'>
        <verse osisID='John.7.1'>After that Jesus walked in Galilee. He would not walk in Judea because the Jews looked for ways to kill him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.2'>It was time for the Jewish Feast of Tabernacles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.3'>His brothers said to him: »Leave here and go to Judea. That way your disciples also may see the works that you do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.4'>»No one does anything in secret when he seeks to be known publicly. If you do these things, show yourself to the world.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.5'>For his brothers did not express active faith in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.6'>Then Jesus replied: »My time is not yet here but your time is always ready.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.7'>»The world has no reason to hate you. But it hates me because I testify that its works are evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.8'>»You go to this feast. I will not go to this feast for my time has not yet come.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.9'>When he said these words to them he stayed in Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.10'>When his brothers left he secretly went to the feast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.11'>The Jews looked for him at the feast and they said: »Where is he?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.12'>There was much whispering among the people concerning him. Some said: »He is a good man.« Others said: »No, he deceives the people.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.13'>However no man spoke openly about him out of fear of the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.14'>Midway through the feast Jesus went to the temple and taught.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.15'>The Jews wondered saying: »How does this man know letters? He has had no formal education.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.16'>Jesus replied: »My teaching is not my own. It is his who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.17'>»If any man does his will he shall know the teachings. He will know if it is from God, or whether I speak from myself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.18'>»He who speaks from his own authority seeks his own glory. He who seeks glory for the one who sent him is true. Unrighteousness is not found in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.19'>»Did Moses give you the law? / Yet none of you obey the law! Why do you seek to kill me?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.20'>The crowd answered: »You have a demon! Who seeks to kill you?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.21'>Jesus responded: »I did one work and you all marveled because of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.22'>»Moses gave you circumcision. Not that it is of Moses, but of the fathers. And you circumcise a man on the Sabbath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.23'>»A man receives circumcision on the Sabbath. That way the Law of Moses may not be broken. Are you angry with me, because I made an entire man whole on the Sabbath?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.24'>»Do not judge according to appearance! Judge a righteous judgment.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.25'>Some in Jerusalem asked: »Is this he whom they seek to kill?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.26'>»He spoke openly and they said nothing to him. Can it be that the rulers indeed know that this is the Christ?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.27'>»How is it we know where this man is from but when the Christ comes no one will know where he is from?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.28'>Jesus shouted in the temple: »You know me and from where I came. I did not come on my own. He who sent me is true and you do not know him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.29'>»I know him because I am from him and he sent me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.30'>They looked for a way to capture him. But no man laid his hand on him. This is because his hour had not yet arrived.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.31'>Many in the crowd believed in him. They asked: »When the Christ comes will he do more signs than those this man has done?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.32'>The Pharisees heard the crowd whispering these things concerning him. The chief priests and the Pharisees sent officers to capture him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.33'>Jesus therefore said: »I am with you a little while. Then I go to him who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.34'>»You will seek me and will not find me. You cannot come where I am going.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.35'>The Jews said among themselves: »Where will this man go that we shall not find him? Will he go to the Dispersion among the Greeks, and teach the Greeks?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.36'>»What is this word that he said: You will seek me, and will not find me; and you cannot come where I am going?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.37'>On the last day, the great day of the feast, Jesus stood and shouted in a loud voice: »If any man thirst let him come to me and drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.38'>»Rivers of living water will flow from the innermost being of the man who believes in me. This is according to the scriptures.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.39'>He spoke this by the Spirit. Those who believed in him were to receive the Spirit. The Spirit was not yet given because Jesus was not yet glorified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.40'>When they heard these words some of the crowd proclaimed: »This truly is the prophet!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.41'>Others said: »This is the Christ.« But some asked: »Does the Christ come out of Galilee?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.42'>»Do the Scriptures say that the Christ comes from the seed of David and from Bethlehem, the village where David was?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.43'>So there arose a division in the crowd because of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.44'>Some of them wanted to apprehend him. Yet no man laid hands on him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.45'>The chief priests and Pharisees asked the officers: »Why did you not bring him?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.46'>»No man has ever spoken the way he speaks,« they replied.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.47'>The Pharisees therefore answered them: »Are you also deceived?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.48'>»Have any of the rulers or the Pharisees believed in him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.49'>»This crowd does not know the law. It is contemptible«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.50'>Nicodemus spoke to them. He is the Pharisee who earlier went to Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.51'>»Does our law convict a man without first hearing from him to find out what he has done?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.52'>They replied: »Are you also from Galilee? Search, and see that no prophet comes out of Galilee.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.53'>Then each man went to his own house.questionable text</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.8'>
        <verse osisID='John.8.1'>John 8:111 is not found in early manuscripts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.2'/>
        <verse osisID='John.8.3'/>
        <verse osisID='John.8.4'/>
        <verse osisID='John.8.5'/>
        <verse osisID='John.8.6'/>
        <verse osisID='John.8.7'/>
        <verse osisID='John.8.8'/>
        <verse osisID='John.8.9'/>
        <verse osisID='John.8.10'/>
        <verse osisID='John.8.11'/>
        <verse osisID='John.8.12'>Again Jesus spoke to them, saying: »I am the light of the world. He that follows me will not walk in the darkness, but will have the light of life.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.13'>The Pharisees therefore replied to him: »You testify about yourself. Your evidence is not true!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.14'>Jesus answered them: »Even if I bear witness about myself, my testimony is true! I know where I came from and I know where I am going. You do not know where I came from or where I am going.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.15'>»You judge according to the flesh. I judge no one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.16'>»Yes and if I judge my judgment is true. I am not alone for I am with the Father who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.17'>»It is written in your law that the witness of two men is true.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.18'>»I testify about myself and the Father who sent me testifies about me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.19'>They said: »Where is your Father?« Jesus answered: »You do not know me, nor do you know my Father! If you knew me you would also know my Father.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.20'>He spoke these words at the treasury as he taught in the temple. No one tried to arrest him because his hour had not yet arrived.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.21'>He said: »I go away. You will seek me and will die in your sin. You cannot come where I go.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.22'>The Jews asked: »Would he kill himself? For he said you could not come where I go.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.23'>He responded to them: »You are from below. I am from above. You are from this world. I am not from this world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.24'>»I said to you that you would die in your sins. Unless you believe that I am he, you will die in your sins!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.25'>»Who are you,« they asked. Jesus replied: »What have I been telling you from the beginning?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.26'>»I have many things to speak and to judge concerning you. He that sent me is true. I tell the world the things he told me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.27'>They were not aware that he spoke to them about the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.28'>Jesus said: »When you have lifted up impaled the Son of man you will know that I am that person. I do nothing by myself! I speak what the Father taught me!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.29'>»He sent me and is with me. He has not left me alone. I always do the things that are pleasing to him!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.30'>Many believed when he said these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.31'>Jesus told the Jews who believed him: »If you dwell in my word you truly are my disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.32'>»You will know the truth and the truth will make you free!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.33'>They answered him: »We are Abrahams seed, and have never been in bondage to any man. How can you say we will be made free?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.34'>Jesus answered: »Truly I tell you every one who commits sin is a slave of sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.35'>»The slave does not abide in the house forever. The son abides forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.36'>»If therefore the Son will make you free, you will be free indeed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.37'>»I know that you are Abrahams seed. Yet you seek to kill me. That is because my word has no place among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.38'>»I speak the things that I have seen and heard when I was with my Father. You also do the things that you heard from your father.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.39'>They answered: »Our father is Abraham.« Jesus replied: »If you were Abrahams children, you would do the works of Abraham.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.40'>»You seek to kill me. I told you the truth! I heard it from God. Abraham did not do this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.41'>»You do the works of your father.« They said: »We were not born of fornication. We have one Father, God!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.42'>Jesus said: »If God were your Father you would love me. I came from God! I have not come from myself. He sent me!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.43'>»Why do you not understand what I say? Can you not hear me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.44'>»You are from your father Satan the Devil slandererfalse accuser! You want to do the desires of your father. He was a murderer from the beginning. He does not stand for the truth. There is no truth in him. When he speaks a lie, he speaks his own lies. He is a liar and the father of the lie!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.45'>»I tell you the truth and you do not believe me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.46'>»Which of you convicted me of sin? If I speak truth, why do you not believe me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.47'>»He that is of God hears the words of God. That is why you do not listen. You are not from God!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.48'>The Jews answered: »Do we not speak correctly that you are a Samaritan and have a demon?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.49'>Jesus answered: »I have no demon. I honor my Father and you dishonor me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.50'>»I do not seek my own glory. There is one that seeks and judges.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.51'>»Truly I tell you if a man obeys my word he will never see death.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.52'>The Jews said to him: »Now we know that you have a demon. Abraham and the prophets died. And you say if a man obeys my word he will never taste of death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.53'>»Are you greater than our father Abraham? He died! The prophets also died. Who do you make yourself out to be?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.54'>Jesus answered: »If I glorify myself, my glory is nothing. My Father glorifies me. He is the one whom you say is your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.55'>»You do not know him. I know him. If I say I do not know him I would be like you, a liar! But I know him and obey his word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.56'>»Your father Abraham rejoiced to see my day. He saw it and was glad.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.57'>The Jews replied: »You are not yet fifty years old. Have you seen Abraham?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.58'>Jesus said: »I tell you the truth, I existed before Abraham was born!« (Ex 3:14-15)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.59'>They took up stones to throw at him. But Jesus hid himself and left the temple.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.9'>
        <verse osisID='John.9.1'>He saw a man who was blind from birth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.2'>His disciples asked him: »Rabbi he was born blind. Who sinned, this man or his parents?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.3'>Jesus answered: »This man did not sin. Neither did his parents sin. The works of God should be made known in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.4'>»We must work the works of him that sent me while it is day. When the night comes no man can work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.5'>»When I am in the world, I am the light of the world.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.6'>He spat on the ground and made clay of the spittle. Then he anointed the eyes of the blind with the clay.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.7'>He told him: »Go wash in the pool of Siloam.« He went there and washed. And he could see!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.8'>The neighbors saw him afterwards. They knew he was a blind beggar. So they asked: Is this he who sat and begged?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.9'>Others said: »It is he.« Yet others said: »No, but he is like him.« He said: »I am he!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.10'>How were your eyes opened? They asked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.11'>He answered: »The man that is called Jesus made clay, and anointed my eyes. Then he told me to go to Siloam and wash. I went there and washed, and I received sight.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.12'>They inquired asked: »Where is he?« He responded: »I do not know.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.13'>They brought the former blind man to the Pharisees.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.14'>Jesus healed the blind man on the Sabbath day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.15'>The Pharisees asked him how he received his sight. He said to them: « He put clay on my eyes, I washed and now I see.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.16'>Some of the Pharisees said: »This man is not from God, because he does not keep the Sabbath.« Others said: »How could a man that is a sinner perform such signs?« There was division among them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.17'>They spoke again to the former blind man. »What do you say about him?« He said: »He is a prophet.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.18'>The Jews did not believe that he had been blind and then received his sight. So they called his parents.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.19'>They asked the parents: »Is this your son? Was he born blind? How does he see now?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.20'>His parents answered: »This is our son and he was born blind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.21'>»We do not know how he now sees or who opened his eyes. Ask him. He is of age and he will speak for himself.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.22'>The parents said these things because they feared the Jews. The Jews had agreed that if any man should confess him to be Christ, he should be put out of the synagogue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.23'>So the parents said: »Ask him, he is of age.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.24'>So they called the man that was blind a second time, and said to him: »Give glory to God. We know that this man is a sinner.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.25'>He answered: »I do not know if he is a sinner. One thing I know, I was blind and now I see.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.26'>They asked: »What did he do to you? How did he open your eyes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.27'>He answered them: »I told you before and you did not listen. Why do you want to hear it again? Would you also become his disciples?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.28'>Then they spoke abusively to him: »You are his disciple! We are disciples of Moses.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.29'>We know that God spoke to Moses. As for this man we do not know where he is from.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.30'>The man answered: »This certainly is a marvel that you do not know where he is from and yet he opened my eyes.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.31'>»We know that God does not listen to sinners. If any man respects God and does his will, God listens to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.32'>»Since the world began no one ever heard of a man opening the eyes of someone born blind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.33'>»If this man were not from God, he could do nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.34'>They answered: »You were born in sin and you teach us?« Then they threw him out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.35'>Jesus heard that they threw him out. He found him and said: »Do you believe in the Son of God?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.36'>He answered: »Who is he Lord that I may believe in him?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.37'>Jesus replied: »You both see and hear him for he speaks with you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.38'>»Lord I believe,« he said. And he bowed down to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.39'>Jesus said: »I came into the world for this judgment that those not seeing may see and those seeing may become blind.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.40'>Those of the Pharisees who were with him heard these things, and said to him: »Are we also blind?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.41'>Jesus replied: »If you were blind you would have no sin. But you say we see so your sin remains.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.10'>
        <verse osisID='John.10.1'>»Truly I tell you, he who does not enter the sheepfold by the door but climbs up some other way is a thief and a robber.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.2'>»He who enters in by the door is the shepherd of the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.3'>»The doorkeeper opens to him and the sheep hear his voice. He calls his sheep by name and leads them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.4'>»When all of his own are out he leads them. The sheep follow him for they know his voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.5'>»They will not follow a stranger but will flee from him. They do not know the voice of a stranger.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.6'>They did not understand this illustration Jesus spoke to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.7'>Jesus explained: »I am the door of the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.8'>»Thieves and robbers came in place of me but the sheep did not listen to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.9'>»I am the door. If any man enters through me he will be saved. He will go in and out and find pasture.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.10'>»The thief comes to steal, and kill, and destroy. I came that they may have life, and may have it abundantly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.11'>»I am the good shepherd. The good shepherd lays down his life for the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.12'>»The hired man owns no sheep. He is not the shepherd. He sees the wolf coming and abandons the sheep. The wolf snatches them, and scatters them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.13'>»He leaves because he is a hired man and does not care for the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.14'>»I am the good shepherd. I know my own, and my own know me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.15'>Just as the Father knows me I know the Father! I lay down my life for the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.16'>»I have other sheep that are not of this fold. I will also bring them. They will hear my voice and they will become one flock, one shepherd.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.17'>»The Father loves me. Therefore I lay down my life and I take it back again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.18'>»No one takes it away from me, but I lay it down voluntarily. I have authority jurisdictionright to lay it down, and I have authority to take it again. I have received this commandment from my Father.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.19'>The Jews were again divided because of what Jesus said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.20'>Many of them said: »He has a demon and is mad. Why listen to him?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.21'>Others said: »These are not the sayings of one possessed with a demon. Can a demon open the eyes of the blind?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.22'>It was the feast of the dedication at Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.23'>It was wintertime. Jesus was walking in the temple on Solomons porch the Colonnade of Solomon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.24'>The Jews came to him and asked: »How long will you keep us in suspense? If you are the Christ, tell us plainly.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.25'>Jesus replied: »I told you and you do not believe. The works that I do in my Fathers name bear witness of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.26'>»You do not believe because you are not my sheep!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.27'>»My sheep hear my voice. I know them and they follow me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.28'>»I give them eternal life. They will never perish. No one will snatch them out of my hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.29'>»My Father has given them to me. He is greater than all and no one is able to snatch them out of the Fathers hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.30'>»The Father and I are one united in purpose.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.31'>The Jews picked up stones again to stone him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.32'>Jesus replied to them: »I have shown you many good works from the Father. For which of those works do you stone me?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.33'>The Jews answered him: »We do not stone you for good work but for blasphemy. You are a man and you make yourself like God.« (John 1:1)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.34'>Jesus said: »Is it not written in your law, I said, you are god-like ones?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.35'>»So if he called them god-like ones, those to whom the word of God came, and the Scriptures may not be annulled,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.36'>»do you say to the one whom the Father sanctified and sent into the world, you blaspheme? And this because I said, I am the Son of God. (Psalm 82:1, 6) (John 1:34; John 5:18) (Luke 1:35)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.37'>»If I am not doing the works of my Father, do not believe me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.38'>»But if I do them and you do not believe me, believe the works! That way you may know and understand that the Father is with me, and I am with the Father.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.39'>They tried again to capture him but he escaped from them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.40'>He traveled beyond the Jordan into the place where John first baptized and stayed there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.41'>Many came to him and they said: »John indeed did not perform a single miracle. Yet everything John said about this man was true.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.42'>Many believed in him there.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.11'>
        <verse osisID='John.11.1'>A man named Lazarus was sick. He lived at Bethany where his sisters Mary and Martha lived.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.2'>This is the same Mary who anointed the Lord with ointment, and wiped his feet with her hair. It was her brother Lazarus who was sick.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.3'>The sisters therefore sent for the Lord, They said: »The one for whom you have great affection is sick.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.4'>When Jesus heard it he said: »This sickness will not end in death. It is for the glory of God, that the Son of God may be glorified by it.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.5'>Jesus loved Martha, and her sister, and Lazarus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.6'>When he heard the news he stayed where he was for two days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.7'>After this he said to the disciples: »Let us go to Judea again.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.8'>The disciples said: »Rabbi, the Jews were seeking to stone you and you go there?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.9'>Jesus answered: »Are there not twelve hours in the day? If a man walks in the day he does not stumble because he sees the light of this world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.10'>»But if a man walk in the night, he stumbles, because the light is not in him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.11'>Then he told them: »Our friend Lazarus has fallen asleep. I go to wake him out of sleep.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.12'>The disciples said, »Lord, if he has fallen asleep, he would recover.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.13'>Jesus spoke of his death. They thought he spoke of taking rest in sleep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.14'>Then Jesus said plainly: »Lazarus is dead!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.15'>»I am glad for your sakes that I was not there, for it will help you believe. Let us go to him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.16'>Thomas, who is called Didymus, said to his fellow disciples: »Let us also go that we may die with him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.17'>When Jesus arrived he found Lazarus had been in the grave four days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.18'>Now Bethany was near Jerusalem, about two miles away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.19'>Many of the Jews came to Martha and Mary, to console them about their brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.20'>Martha went out to meet Jesus and Mary sat in the house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.21'>Martha said to Jesus: »Lord if you had been here my brother would not have died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.22'>»Even now I know that what ever you ask of God he will give it to you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.23'>Jesus replied: »Your brother will rise again.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.24'>Martha exclaimed: »I know he will rise again in the resurrection at the last day.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.25'>Jesus said: »I am the resurrection and the life. He who puts active faith in me will live, even if he dies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.26'>»Whoever lives and puts active faith in me will never die. Do you believe this?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.27'>She said: »Yes Lord, I believe that you are the Christ, the Son of God who is to come into the world.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.28'>After she said this she went away and secretly called her sister Mary. She said: »The teacher is here and calls you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.29'>Mary got up quickly and went to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.30'>Now Jesus had not yet arrived at the village and was still at the place where Martha met him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.31'>The Jews were with her in the house, consoling her. They saw Mary get up quickly and leave. So they followed her, supposing that she was going to the tomb to weep there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.32'>When Mary saw Jesus she fell down at his feet. She said: »Lord; if you had been here my brother would not have died.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.33'>Jesus groaned in his spirit and was troubled when he saw her weeping and the Jews who came with her weeping.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.34'>He asked: »Where have you laid him?« They answered: »Come and see Lord.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.35'>Jesus wept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.36'>The Jews therefore said: »Look how deeply he loved him!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.37'>Some of them said: »This man opened the eyes of the blind. Could he have prevented this man from dying?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.38'>Again Jesus groaned in himself. He went to the tomb. It was a cave with a stone laid against it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.39'>Jesus said: »Take away the stone.« Martha, the sister of the dead man said: »Lord by now the body has decayed for he has been dead four days.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.40'>Jesus said to her: »Did I not say that if you believe you shall see the glory of God?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.41'>So they took away the stone. Jesus lifted up his eyes, and said: »Father, I thank you that you hear me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.42'>»I knew that you always hear me. But because of the crowd that stands here I said it, that they may believe that you did send me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.43'>After he finished he cried out loud: »Lazarus, come out!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.44'>He that was dead came out. He was bound hand and foot with grave-clothes and his face was bound about with a napkin. Jesus commanded them: »Unwrap him and let him go.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.45'>Many of the Jews, who came to Mary and saw what he did, believed in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.46'>Some of them went to the Pharisees and told them the things that Jesus had done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.47'>The chief priests and the Pharisees gathered a council. They asked what they should do. »This man does many signs and miracles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.48'>»If we let him alone all men will believe in him. Then the Romans will come and take away both our place and our nation.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.49'>Caiaphas the high priest that year said to them: »You know nothing at all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.50'>»You do not understand that it is expedient for you that one man should die for the people. That way the whole nation will not perish.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.51'>He did not say this from his own understanding. As high priest that year he prophesied that Jesus should die for the nation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.52'>He would die for the nation. He would also gather together the children of God that are scattered abroad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.53'>So from that day forth they took counsel that they might put him to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.54'>Jesus did not walk openly among the Jews anymore. He departed into the wilderness of the nearby country. He and his disciples stayed at a city called Ephraim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.55'>It was the Jewish Passover. Many went out of the country to Jerusalem to purify themselves before the Passover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.56'>They searched for Jesus. They stood in the temple speaking to one another: »What do you think? Will he come to the feast?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.57'>Now the chief priests and the Pharisees had given orders that, if any man knew where he was, he should report it that they might seize him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.12'>
        <verse osisID='John.12.1'>Six days before the Passover Jesus traveled to Bethany. This was where Lazarus lived. He was the man Jesus raised from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.2'>Jesus ate supper there. He and Lazarus sat at the meal while Martha served.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.3'>Mary took a pound of very precious ointment of pure nard and anointed the feet of Jesus. She wiped his feet with her hair. The house was filled with the odor of the ointment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.4'>Judas Iscariot, the disciple who would betray him said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.5'>»Why was this ointment not sold for three hundred danarii, and given to the poor?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.6'>He did not say this because he cared for the poor. He was a thief. He had the moneybox and took away what was put in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.7'>Jesus therefore replied: »Let her alone that she may preserve it for the day of my burial.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.8'>»You always have the poor with you, but you do not always have me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.9'>The common people of the Jews learned that he was there. So they came to see Jesus and Lazarus, whom he raised from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.10'>The chief priests took counsel that they might put Lazarus also to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.11'>This is because by reason of Lazarus many of the Jews believed in Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.12'>The next day a great crowd came to the feast. They heard that Jesus was coming to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.13'>They took palm branches and met him. They cried out, »Hosanna: Blessed is he who comes in the name of Jehovah, even the King of Israel!« (Psalm 118:26)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.14'>Jesus found a young donkey and sat on it just as it is written:</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.15'>»Do not fear daughter of Zion. Behold, your King comes sitting on a donkeys colt.« (Zechariah 9:9)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.16'>His disciples did not understand these things at first. However when Jesus was glorified they remembered the things that were written about him. They also remembered the things that had been done to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.17'>The crowd that was with him when he called Lazarus out of the tomb, and raised him from the dead, gave witness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.18'>For this reason also the crowd met him, for they heard that he had performed this miracle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.19'>The Pharisees spoke among themselves: »You see that you are not accomplishing anything. Look the world has gone after him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.20'>Now there were Greeks among those who went up to worship at the feast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.21'>They approached Philip, who was of Bethsaida of Galilee, and told him: »We wish to see Jesus.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.22'>Philip and Andrew told Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.23'>Jesus answered: »The time has come for the Son of man to be glorified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.24'>»Truly I tell you unless a grain of wheat falls to the earth and dies, it remains alone; but if it dies it bears much fruit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.25'>»He that loves his life in this world loses it; and he that detests does not love his life in this world shall save it for everlasting life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.26'>»If you want to serve me follow me! My servant will be where I am and the Father will honor my servant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.27'>»I am troubled! What should I say? Father, save me out of this hour? It is for this purpose that I came to this hour! (Hebrews 5:7)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.28'>»Father, glorify your name.« A voice came from heaven: »I have both glorified it, and will glorify it again.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.29'>The crowd near him only heard thunder. Some said an angel spoke to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.30'>Jesus said: »This voice came for your sake and not for mine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.31'>»Now judgment is on this world. Now the ruler of this world will be cast out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.32'>»When I am lifted up from the earth I will draw all men to myself.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.33'>He said this indicating the type of death he would experience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.34'>The crowd answered him: »We have heard from the law that the Christ lives forever. Why do you say the Son of man must be lifted up? Who is this Son of man?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.35'>Jesus said to them: »The light will be with you for a little while. Walk while you have the light, that darkness does not overtake you. He who walks in the darkness does not know where he goes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.36'>»While you have the light, exert active faith in the light, that you may become sons of light.« Jesus said this and then he departed and hid himself from them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.37'>Even though he performed many miracles in front of them they did not believe in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.38'>The word of Isaiah the prophet was fulfilled: »Jehovah who has believed our report? And to whom has the arm of Jehovah been revealed?« (Isaiah 53:1)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.39'>Isaiah revealed the reason they could not believe:</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.40'>»He has blinded their eyes. He hardened their heart. Otherwise they would see with their eyes and perceive with their heart. Then they would turn and I would heal them.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.41'>Isaiah said these things because he saw and spoke about his glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.42'>Many of the rulers believed in him, although they did not confess their faith because of the Pharisees, for they would be expelled from the synagogue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.43'>They loved the glory from men more than the glory from God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.44'>Jesus cried out: »He, who believes in me, believes not in me, but in him who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.45'>»He that sees me sees perceivesdiscernsexperiences the one who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.46'>»I have come as a light to the world. Everyone who believes in me will not remain in darkness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.47'>»If any man hears my sayings and does not obey them I will not judge him. I came not to judge the world, but to save the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.48'>»He that rejects me and does not accept my message has one that judges him. The word divine expressionGods Word that I spoke shall judge him now and in the last day. (Deuteronomy 18:19)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.49'>»I spoke not from myself but from the Father who sent me. He has given me a commandment concerning what I should say when I speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.50'>»I know that his commandment means everlasting life. Therefore I say the things the Father tells me to say.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.13'>
        <verse osisID='John.13.1'>Jesus knew before the feast of the Passover that the time had come for him to leave this world and return to his Father. He loved his own who were in the world to the very end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.2'>The devil influenced the heart of Judas Iscariot, Simons son. So he betrayed him during the meal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.3'>Jesus knew that the Father had given him power over all things. He also knew it came from God and he returns it to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.4'>He got up from the meal and laid aside his garments. He wrapped a towel around his waist.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.5'>Then he poured water into the basin and washed the disciples feet. He wiped them with the towel he was wearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.6'>When he approached, Simon Peter said: »Lord do you wash my feet?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.7'>»You do not know what I do now,« Jesus said: »but you will understand later.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.8'>Peter said: »You will never wash my feet.« Jesus answered him: »If I do not wash you; you have no part with me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.9'>Simon Peter replied: »Lord, not my feet only, but also my hands and my head.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.10'>Jesus responded: »He that is bathed must wash his feet. He is clean everywhere and you are clean, but not all.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.11'>He knew who would betray him. That is why he said you are not all clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.12'>After he washed their feet he put his outer garments on and sat down. He asked: »Do you know what I have done to you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.13'>»You call me Teacher and Lord and you are right for I am.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.14'>»If the Teacher and Lord washed your feet you should wash one anothers feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.15'>»I have given you an example. You should also do as I have done to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.16'>»Truly I tell you, a servant is not greater than his master. Neither is one that is sent greater than he that sent him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.17'>»If you know these things, you are blessed if you do them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.18'>»I do not speak about all of you. I know whom I have chosen! This way the scripture may be fulfilled: He that eats my bread lifted up his heel against me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.19'>»I tell you before it happens. So that when it takes place you may believe that I am he.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.20'>»Truly I say to you, he who receives whom ever I send receives me. And he who receives me receives him who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.21'>After Jesus said this he was troubled in spirit and said: One of you will betray me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.22'>The disciples looked at each other. They were perplexed and wondered who it would be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.23'>The disciple whom Jesus loved was leaning on his chest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.24'>Simon Peter motioned to him: »Ask him who it is,« he urged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.25'>He leaned back on Jesus breast and said to him: »Lord, who is it?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.26'>Jesus answered: »It is he to whom I give a piece of bread after I dip it.« So when he dipped the bread he gave it to Judas, the son of Simon Iscariot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.27'>After he was given the piece of bread Satan entered him. Jesus said to him: »Do what you do quickly.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.28'>No man at the table knew for what purpose he spoke this to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.29'>Some thought Judas was going to shop for food for the feast or give something to the poor. Judas was in charge of the moneybox.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.30'>He received the morsel of bread and left immediately. It was night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.31'>When he was gone Jesus said: »Now the Son of man is glorified praisedexultedproclaimedhonored and God is glorified through him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.32'>»If God is glorified through him, God will also immediately glorify him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.33'>»Little children I am with you for a little while. You will seek me and as I told the Jews now I say to you, where I go, you cannot come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.34'>»I give you a new commandment, that you love one another. Just as I have loved you, you also love one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.35'>»All men will know that you are my disciples if you have love for one another.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.36'>Simon Peter said: »Lord where are you going?« Jesus answered: »Where I am going you cannot follow me now. You will follow me later.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.37'>Peter said: »Lord, why can I not follow you now? I will lay down my life for you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.38'>Jesus answered: »Will you lay down your life for me? Truly I tell you the cock will not crow till you have denied me three times.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.14'>
        <verse osisID='John.14.1'>»Do not let your hearts be troubled. You believe in God, believe also in me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.2'>»In my Fathers house are many dwelling places. If it were not so, I would have told you. I go to prepare a place for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.3'>»If I go and prepare a place for you I will come again and I will receive you to myself, for where I am you may also be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.4'>»You know where I go and you know the way.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.5'>Thomas said to him: »Lord, we do not know where you go. How do we know the way?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.6'>Jesus proclaimed: »I am the way, the truth, and the life! No one comes to the Father except through me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.7'>»If you had known me, you would have perceived my Father also. From now on you understand him and have experienced him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.8'>Philip said: »Lord, show us the Father, and it is sufficient for us.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.9'>Jesus responded: »Have I been with you so long a time and you do not know me Philip? He who has seen me has discerned experiencedperceived the Father. And you say, show us the Father?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.10'>»Do you not believe that I am with the Father and that the Father is with me? The words I say to you are not from me, but the Father dwells with me and does his works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.11'>»Believe me that I am with the Father and the Father is with me, or else believe me because of the works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.12'>»Truly I tell you, he who exerts active faith in me will do the works that I do. In fact he will do greater works than these. I go to the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.13'>»Whatever you ask in my name, I will do. That way the Father may be glorified because of the Son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.14'>»If you ask anything in my name, I will do it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.15'>»If you love me, you will keep obey my commandments!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.16'>»I will pray to the Father, and he will give you another helper, that he the Father may be with you forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.17'>»It is the Spirit of the truth. The world cannot receive it. The world does not see or know it. You know it because it lives with you and will be with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.18'>»I will not leave you desolate. I will come to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.19'>»A little while and the world will not see me anymore, but you will. I live and you will also live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.20'>»In that day you will know that I am with my Father, and you with me, and I with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.21'>»He that has my commandments, and obeys them loves me. My Father will love the person who loves me. I will love him and disclose myself to him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.22'>Judas not Iscariot asked him: »Lord, what will happen that you will disclose yourself to us, and not to the world?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.23'>Jesus answered: »If a man loves me, he will obey my word. My Father will love him, and we will come to him and dwell with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.24'>»He who does not love me does not obey my words. The word you hear is not mine, but comes from the Father who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.25'>»I speak these things while being present with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.26'>»The Father will send a helper in my name, the Holy Spirit, which Greek: hos he howhichthat one will teach you all things and bring to your memory all that I said to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.27'>»Peace I leave with you! My peace I give to you. I do not give as the world gives to you. Do not let your heart be troubled or full of fear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.28'>»You heard me say I will go away and I will come again to you. If you loved me, you would have rejoiced, because I go to the Father. The Father is greater than I!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.29'>»Now I told you before it takes place. That way when it happens you may believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.30'>»I will speak no more with you. The prince of the world comes. He has no hold on me!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.31'>»The world must know that I love the Father. And I obey the Fathers commandments. Get up and let us leave here.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.15'>
        <verse osisID='John.15.1'>»I am the true vine, and my Father is the cultivator.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.2'>»He takes away the branches in me that do not bear fruit. He cleans every branch that bears fruit. That way it may bear more fruit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.3'>»You are clean because of the word that I have spoken to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.4'>»Remain with me, and I with you. The branch cannot bear fruit by itself. It must remain on the vine. Neither can you bear fruit unless you remain with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.5'>»I am the vine and you are the branches. He that remains with me, and I with him, the same bears much fruit. You can do nothing apart from me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.6'>»If a man does not remain with me, he is removed as a branch, and withers. They gather them and throw them into the fire where they are burned destroyedconsumed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.7'>»If you remain with me, and my words remain with you, ask whatever you will, and it will be done for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.8'>»My Father is glorified when you bear much fruit. You will be my disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.9'>»I love you just as the Father has loved me. Remain in my love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.10'>»If you obey my commandments you will remain in my love. I have obeyed my Fathers commandments and remain in his love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.11'>»I spoke these things in order that my joy may continue with you and your joy may be made full.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.12'>»This is my commandment, that you love one another, even as I have loved you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.13'>»No man has greater love then this that a man lay down his life for his friends.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.14'>»You are my friends if you do the things that I command you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.15'>»I no longer call you servants for the servant does not know what the lord does. I have called you friends; for all things that I heard from my Father, I have made known to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.16'>»You did not choose me. I chose you and appointed you. You should go and bear fruit and your fruit should remain. Whatever you ask the Father in my name, he may give it to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.17'>»These things I command you, that you may love one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.18'>»If the world hates you, you know that it has hated me before it hated you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.19'>»If you were of the world, the world would love its own. I chose you out of the world. The world hates you because you are not of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.20'>»Remember the word I said to you. A servant is not greater than his master. If they persecuted me, they will also persecute you. If they obeyed my word, they will obey yours also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.21'>»They will do all these things to you for my names sake. It is because they do not know the one that sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.22'>»If I had not come and spoken to them, they would not have sin. Now they have no excuse for their sin!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.23'>»He who hates me hates my Father also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.24'>»If I had not done among them the works that no one else did, they would have no sin. They have seen and hated both my Father and me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.25'>»This took place that the word written in the Law may be fulfilled: They hated me without a cause.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.26'>»I will send the helper from the Father, the Spirit of truth, which proceeds from the Father to bear witness of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.27'>»You also bear witness because you have been with me from the beginning.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.16'>
        <verse osisID='John.16.1'>»I have spoken these things to you that you should not be made to stumble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.2'>»They will throw you out of the synagogues. Yes, the hour comes that whoever kills you will think that he offered service to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.3'>»But they do these things because they do not know the Father or me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.4'>»I tell you these things so you will remember that I told you when the time comes. I did not tell this from the beginning because I was with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.5'>»I go to him that sent me. None of you asks me: Where are you going?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.6'>»Now that I have spoken these things to you, sorrow fills your heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.7'>»Nevertheless I tell you the truth. It is for your benefit that I go away. For if I do not go away the helper will not come to you. But if I go, I will send it to you. Greek: autos: it</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.8'>»Upon arrival this one will convict the world of sin, and of righteousness, and of judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.9'>»First of sin because they do not practice active faith in me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.10'>»Second, of righteousness, because I go to the Father and you will not see me anymore.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.11'>»And third, of judgment because the prince of this world has been judged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.12'>»I have yet many things to say to you, but you cannot endure them now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.13'>»When the Spirit of truth comes it will guide you to all truth for it will not speak from itself. It will speak the things it hears and declare to you the things that are to come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.14'>»It will glorify me and will take of what I have and declare it to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.15'>»All the things the Father has are mine. That is why I said the Spirit takes what I have and declares it to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.16'>»A little while and you will see me no more and again a little while, and you will see me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.17'>Some of his disciples said to one another: »What is this he says, a little while, and you see me no more and again a little while and you will see me because I go to the Father?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.18'>»What is this that he says: A little while? We do not know what he says.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.19'>Jesus perceived what they wanted to ask him. He said to them: »You inquire among yourselves concerning what I said. A little while, and you will not see me, and again a little while, and you will see me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.20'>»Truly I tell you, you will weep and lament, but the world will rejoice. You will be sorrowful, but your sorrow will be turned into joy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.21'>»A woman in tribulation has sorrow, because her hour to give birth has come. When she delivers the child, she remembers no more anguish, because of the joy that a man is born into the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.22'>»You have sorrow now. But I will see you again. Your heart will rejoice and no one can take your joy from you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.23'>»You will ask me for nothing then. Truly I say to you, if you ask anything of the Father, he will give it to you in my name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.24'>»Until now you have not asked a single thing in my name. Ask, and you will receive, that your joy may be made full.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.25'>»I have spoken to you in figurative language illustrations and proverbs. The hour comes when I will no longer speak to you in figurative language. I will tell you plainly from the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.26'>»In that day you will ask in my name. I do not say to you, that I will pray to the Father for you. It will not be necessary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.27'>The Father loves you, because you loved me, and believed that I came from the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.28'>»I came out from the Father and came into the world. I leave the world and go to the Father.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.29'>His disciples said: »See now you speak plainly and use no figurative language.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.30'>»We are sure you know all things and have no need that any man ask you questions. Because of this we believe you came from God.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.31'>Jesus asked them: »Do you now believe?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.32'>»Behold! The hour comes, and indeed, it is here, that you will be scattered and each one will leave me alone. Yet I am not alone because the Father is with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.33'>»I spoke to you that in me you might have peace. In the world you have tribulation. Be of good cheer for I have conquered the world!«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.17'>
        <verse osisID='John.17.1'>Jesus spoke these things and lifted up his eyes to heaven. He said: »Father, the hour has come. Glorify your Son, that the son may glorify you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.2'>»You have given him authority over all flesh that he may give everlasting life to the ones whom you have given him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.3'>»This is everlasting life that they should have *deep, intimate knowledge of you, the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom you have commissioned. *Greek: ginosko: know, perceive, be sure, understand</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.4'>»I glorified you on the earth. I accomplished the work you gave me to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.5'>»And now, Father, glorify me with you, the glory that I had with you before the world existed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.6'>»I taught your name to the men whom you gave me out of the world. They were yours and you gave them to me. They have lived by your word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.7'>»Now they know that all things you gave me are from you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.8'>»I gave them the words that you gave me. They understood them and knew I came from you. They believed you sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.9'>»I pray for them. I do not pray for the world. I pray only for those you gave me, for they are yours.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.10'>»All things that are mine are yours, and yours are mine and I am glorified in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.11'>»I am no more in the world but they are in the world. I come to you Holy Father. Keep them in your name, which you have given to me, that they may be one*, even as we are. *Greek: heis; united in purpose and love</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.12'>»While I was with them I kept them in your name, which you have given to me. I guarded them, and not one of them perished, except the son of perdition; that the Scripture might be fulfilled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.13'>»Now I come to you. I spoke these things in the world, that they may have my joy made full in themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.14'>»I gave them your word. The world hated them because they are not of the world, even as I am not of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.15'>»I do not pray that you take them out of the world, but that you keep them from the evil one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.16'>»They are not of the world even as I am not of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.17'>»Sanctify them by your truth. Your word is truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.18'>»As you commissioned sent me into the world, I commissioned sent them into the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.19'>»I sanctify myself for them, that they may be sanctified by truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.20'>»I pray, not for these alone but for those who will believe in me through their word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.21'>»May they all be united in agreement as one. Just as you, Father, are with me, and I am with you. Help them be united with us! That way the world may believe that you sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.22'>»I have given them the glory that you gave me in order that they may be one even as we are one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.23'>»I with them, and you with me, that they may accomplish complete unity. That way the world may know that you sent me and that you love them just as you love me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.24'>»Father, I desire that these whom you gave me may be with me where I am. I want them to see the glory you have given me. For you loved me before the creation of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.25'>»Righteous Father, the world has not known you. I know you and those you sent me know you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.26'>»I have made your name known, and will make it known. That way your love for me may be with them and I may be with them.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.18'>
        <verse osisID='John.18.1'>When Jesus finished his prayer he and his disciples crossed the Kedron winter stream to a garden.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.2'>Judas, who betrayed him, knew the place because Jesus went there frequently with his disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.3'>Judas brought a band of armed men and police from the chief priests and Pharisees there with lights and with weapons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.4'>Jesus knew what was about to happen to him. He asked: »Whom do you seek?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.5'>They answered him: »Jesus of Nazareth.« Jesus replied: »I am he.« Judas the betrayer was with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.6'>When he said to them I am he they drew back and fell to the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.7'>Again he asked: »Whom do you seek?« And they said: »Jesus of Nazareth.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.8'>Jesus answered: »I told you that I am he. If you seek me let these go their way.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.9'>That way the word he spoke might be fulfilled; I lost none of those you gave me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.10'>Simon Peter drew the sword he had, struck the high priests servant, and cut off his right ear. The servants name was Malchus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.11'>Jesus said to Peter: »Put the sword in the sheath. Shall I drink the cup the Father has given me?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.12'>The soldiers, the military commanders, and the officers of the Jews, seized Jesus and bound him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.13'>They led him to Annas first for he was father in law to Caiaphas who was high priest that year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.14'>Caiaphas was the man who gave counsel to the Jews that it was for their benefit that one man should die for the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.15'>Simon Peter followed Jesus and so did another disciple. The high priest knew that disciple. He entered the court of the high priest with Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.16'>Peter stood outside the door. The disciple known by the high priest went out and spoke to the woman who kept the door and he brought in Peter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.17'>The maid that kept the door asked Peter: »Are you also one of this mans disciples?« He said: »I am not.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.18'>It was cold. So the servants and officers warmed themselves by the fire. Peter also stood by the fire to get warm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.19'>The high priest asked Jesus about his disciples and about the things he taught.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.20'>Jesus answered him: »I have spoken openly to the world. I always taught in synagogues, and in the temple where all the Jews gathered. I spoke nothing in secret.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.21'>»Why do you ask me? Ask them that heard me what I spoke to them. They know the things I said.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.22'>When he said this one of the officers standing nearby struck Jesus with his hand, saying: »You answer the high priest!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.23'>Jesus answered him: »If I spoke evil, bear witness of the evil. But if I spoke honestly, why do you strike me?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.24'>Annas sent him bound to Caiaphas the high priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.25'>Simon Peter stood nearby warming himself. They asked him: »Are you also one of his disciples?« He denied it saying: »I am not.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.26'>One of the servants of the high priest, being a relative of him whose ear Peter cut off, said: »Did I see you in the garden with him?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.27'>Peter denied it again. Then the cock crowed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.28'>They lead Jesus from Caiaphas into the Praetorium. It was early and they did not enter directly into the Praetorium, that they might not be defiled, but might eat the Passover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.29'>Pilate went to them and asked: »What accusation do you make against this man?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.30'>They answered: »If this man were not an evildoer we would not deliver him to you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.31'>Pilate replied: »Take him yourselves and judge him according to your law.« The Jews said: »It is not lawful for us to put any man to death.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.32'>Thus the word of Jesus would be fulfilled when he spoke about the kind of death he would experience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.33'>Pilate entered again into the Praetorium. He called Jesus and asked him: »Are you the King of the Jews?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.34'>Jesus answered: »You say this about me. Or did others tell you it concerning me?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.35'>Pilate answered: »Am I a Jew? Your own nation and the chief priests delivered you to me! What have you done?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.36'>Jesus answered: »My kingdom is not of this world! If my kingdom were of this world my servants would fight that I should not be delivered to the Jews. My kingdom is not from this domain.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.37'>Pilate said: »Are you a king then?« Jesus answered: »As you say I am a king. I was born and came into the world for this purpose, that I should bear witness to the truth! Every one who is of the truth hears my voice.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.38'>Pilate then asked: »What is truth?« After saying this, he went out again to the Jews and said to them: »I find no fault in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.39'>»You have a custom that I release someone to you at the Passover. Do you want me to release to you the King of the Jews?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.40'>They cried out: »Not this man, but Barabbas. Barabbas was a robber.«</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.19'>
        <verse osisID='John.19.1'>Then Pilate took Jesus and whipped him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.2'>The soldiers braided a crown of thorns and put it on his head. They dressed him in a purple garment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.3'>They came to him, and said: »Hail, King of the Jews!« They struck him with their hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.4'>Pilate went out again, and said to them: »Look, I bring him out to you, that you may know that I find no fault in him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.5'>Jesus came out, wearing the crown of thorns and the purple garment. Pilate said: »Look, the man!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.6'>When the chief priests and officers saw him, they cried out: »Impale him! Impale him!« Pilate replied: »Take him yourselves, and impale him for he has committed no crime!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.7'>The Jews answered him: »We have a law, and by that law he ought to die, because he made himself the Son of God.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.8'>When Pilate heard this he was more afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.9'>He entered into the Praetorium again, and said to Jesus: »Where are you from?« But Jesus gave him no answer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.10'>Pilate said: »Will you not speak to me? Do you know I have the power to release you and the power to impale you?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.11'>Jesus answered him: »You would have no power against me except it was given you from above. Therefore he that delivered me to you has greater sin.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.12'>As a result of this Pilate sought to release him. The Jews cried out: »If you release this man you are not Caesars friend. Every one that makes himself a king speaks against Caesar.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.13'>When Pilate heard these words he brought Jesus out and sat down on the judgment-seat. They were at a place called The Stone Pavement, but in Hebrew, Gabbatha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.14'>Now it was the Preparation of the Passover, about the sixth hour. And he said to the Jews: »Behold, your King!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.15'>They cried out: »Away with him, away with him, impale him!« Pilate asked: »Should I impale your King?« The chief priests answered: »We have no king but Caesar.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.16'>Then he delivered him to them to be impaled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.17'>They took Jesus bearing his own stake to the place called the place of a skull, which is called in Hebrew, Golgotha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.18'>They impaled him there. Two others were impaled and Jesus stake was placed in the middle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.19'>Pilate wrote a title and put it on the stake. There it was written, JESUS OF NAZARETH, THE KING OF THE JEWS.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.20'>This title was read by many of the Jews, for the place where Jesus was impaled was near the city. It was written in Hebrew, Latin and Greek.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.21'>The chief priests of the Jews said to Pilate: »Do not write, The King of the Jews; but that he said, I am King of the Jews.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.22'>Pilate answered: »What I have written, I have written.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.23'>After they impaled Jesus the soldiers took his garments and made four parts, one for each soldier. The coat was without seam, woven from the top throughout.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.24'>They said to one another, Let us not tear the coat. So they cast lots for it. That fulfilled the scripture that said: »They parted my garments among them, and they cast lots for my covering.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.25'>His mother stood by the stake of Jesus, and his mothers sister, Mary the wife of Clopas, and Mary Magdalene.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.26'>Jesus saw his mother, and the disciple whom he loved. He said to his mother, »Woman, look, your son!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.27'>Then he said to the disciple, »Look, your mother!« That hour forward the disciple took her to his home.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.28'>He knew that it was over. In order that the scripture might be accomplished, he said: »I thirst.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.29'>A vessel full of vinegar was setting there. They put a sponge full of vinegar upon a hyssop branch and brought it to his mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.30'>When Jesus received the vinegar, he said, »it is finished.« He bowed his head, and he stopped breathing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.31'>It was Preparation and the Jews insisted that bodies not remain on the stake on the Sabbath. The day of that Sabbath was a high day. They asked Pilate that the legs be broken and that they might be taken away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.32'>The soldiers broke the legs of the two who were impaled with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.33'>When they came to Jesus, and saw that he was dead already so they did not break his legs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.34'>The soldier with the spear pierced his side and suddenly blood and water came out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.35'>He who saw testified and his testimony is true. He knows and he speaks truth that you also may believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.36'>These things came to pass in order that the scripture might be fulfilled: A bone of him shall not be broken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.37'>And again another scripture said: They should look on him whom they pierced.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.38'>Joseph of Arimathaea was a disciple of Jesus. He approached Pilate secretly for fear of the Jews. He asked Pilate for permission to take away the body of Jesus. Pilate gave him permission. So he took the body away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.39'>Nicodemus also came with a mixture of myrrh and about a hundred pounds of aloes. Nicodemus is the one who came to Jesus at night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.40'>They prepared the body of Jesus for burial. They bound it in linen cloths with spices. This was the custom of the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.41'>There was a garden at the place where he was impaled. It contained a new tomb where no one had been buried.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.42'>They laid Jesus there because the Jews Preparation was close at hand.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.20'>
        <verse osisID='John.20.1'>Mary Magdalene arrived at the tomb early on the first day of the week while it was still dark. She saw the stone was taken away from the tomb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.2'>She ran to Simon Peter and the other disciple whom Jesus loved and said to them: »They have taken the Lord away out of the tomb. We do not know where they laid him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.3'>Peter and the other disciple went to the tomb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.4'>They both ran together. The other disciple out ran Peter and got to the tomb first.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.5'>He stooped and looked inside where he saw the linen clothes. He did not enter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.6'>Simon Peter followed him to the tomb and entered to see the linen clothes laying there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.7'>The napkin that was on his head was not with the linen clothes. It was rolled up by itself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.8'>The other disciple entered the tomb. He saw and believed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.9'>They still did not know the Scripture that he must rise from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.10'>The disciples went away again to their own home.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.11'>Mary stood outside the tomb weeping. She stooped and looked into the tomb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.12'>She saw two angels in white sitting, one at the head, and one at the feet, where the body of Jesus had lain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.13'>»Woman why do you weep,« they asked? She told them: »They have taken my Lord and I do not know where they laid him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.14'>She turned and look there was Jesus standing nearby. She did not know it was Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.15'>Jesus said to her: »Woman, why do you weep? Who are you looking for?« She thought he was the gardener. She said: »Sir, if you have carried him somewhere else tell me where you laid him and I will take him away.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.16'>Jesus said: »Mary.« She turned and said to him in Hebrew: »Rabboni,« which is to say, Teacher.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.17'>Jesus said: »Do not touch me for I am not yet ascended to the Father. Go to my brothers, and say to them, I ascend to my Father and youre Father, and my God and your God.« (Revelation 3:12)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.18'>Mary Magdalene went to tell the disciples: »I have seen the Lord! He said these things to me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.19'>It was evening of the first day of the week. The disciples shut the doors where they stayed for fear of the Jews. Jesus came and stood in the midst, and said to them: »May you have Peace.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.20'>When he said this, he showed them his hands and his side. The disciples were glad, when they saw the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.21'>Jesus therefore said to them again: »May you have peace. As the Father sent me, even so I send you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.22'>After he said this he breathed on them and said: »Receive Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.23'>»Forgive sins and they are forgiven. Do not forgive sins and they are not forgiven.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.24'>Thomas, one of the twelve, called Didymus, was not with them when Jesus came.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.25'>The other disciples therefore said to him: »We have seen the Lord.« He said: »Unless I feel the print of the nails in his hands and put my hand into his side, I will not believe.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.26'>Eight days later the disciples were inside with the doors shut and Thomas was with them. Jesus came in and stood in the midst, and said: »Peace be with you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.27'>Jesus said to Thomas: »Put your finger here and look at my hands. Put your hand into my side. Stop doubting and believe!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.28'>Thomas answered: »My Lord and my God!« (John 1:18; John 10:36; John 20:17)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.29'>Jesus said to him: »Because you saw me, you believe. Blessed are they that have not seen, and yet believe!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.30'>Jesus did many miracles signs in the presence of the disciples. They are not written in this book.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.31'>These are written that you may believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God. By believing you may have life in his name.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.21'>
        <verse osisID='John.21.1'>Jesus showed himself again to the disciples at the sea of Tiberias. He presented himself this way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.2'>There were together Simon Peter; Thomas called Didymus, and Nathanael of Cana in Galilee, the sons of Zebedee, and two other of his disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.3'>Simon Peter said to them: »I am going fishing.« They told him: »We would also come with you.« They boarded the boat and caught nothing that night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.4'>Jesus stood on the beach at daybreak. The disciples did not know it was Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.5'>Jesus said to them: »Children, have you anything to eat?« They answered him: »No.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.6'>He said: »Cast the net on the right side of the boat and you will find fish.« They cast it and they were not able to draw it for the multitude of fishes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.7'>That disciple whom Jesus loved said to Peter: »It is the Lord.« So when Simon Peter heard that it was the Lord, he wrapped his coat about him for he was dressed only in undergarments, and jumped into the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.8'>The other disciples came in the little boat for they were not far from the land, but about one hundred yards away, dragging the net full of fishes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.9'>When they got to land, they saw a fire of coals and fish laid on it, and bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.10'>Jesus said: »Bring the fish you caught.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.11'>Simon Peter went to draw the net to land. It was full of great fishes, a hundred and fifty three in all. There were so many and yet the net was not torn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.12'>Jesus said to them: »Come and eat.« And none of the disciples dared to inquire, who are you? They just knew it was the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.13'>Jesus came, took the bread and fish and gave it to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.14'>This is the third time Jesus was seen by the disciples since he was raised from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.15'>When they had eaten Jesus said to Simon Peter: »Simon, son of John, do you love me more than these?« He said: »Yes Lord; you know I have affection for you.« Jesus said to him: »Feed my lambs.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.16'>He spoke to him a second time: »Simon, son of John, do you love me?« He replied: »Yes Lord, you know I have affection for you.« Then Jesus said: »Shepherd my sheep.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.17'>The third time Jesus said to him: »Simon, son of John, do you have affection for me?« Peter was grieved. Because he said to him the third time, do you have affection for me? Peter replied: »Lord, you know all things; you know I have affection for you!« Jesus said to him: »Feed my sheep.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.18'>»Truly, truly, I tell you, when you were young you dressed yourself and walked wherever you wanted. But when you become old, you stretch out your hands and another dresses you, and carries you where you do not want to go.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.19'>Now this he spoke, signifying by what manner of death he should glorify God. After he spoke he said: »Follow me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.20'>Peter, turning about, saw the disciple whom Jesus loved following. He is the one who also leaned back on his breast at the supper, and said,« Lord, who is he that betrays you?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.21'>Seeing this Peter said to Jesus: Lord, what shall this man do?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.22'>Jesus said: »If it is my will that he stay until I come, what is that to you? You follow me.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.23'>This expression went among the brethren, that that disciple should not die. Yet Jesus did not say that he should not die. He only said: »If I will that he stay until I come, what is that to you?«</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.24'>This is the disciple that bears witness of these things, and wrote these things. That way we know that his witness is true.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.25'>There are many other things that Jesus did. Should all of them be written I suppose the world would not contain the books written.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>