<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='mkjv1962' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='mkjv1962'>
        <title>Modern KJV 1963</title>
        <contributor>xxx</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy</subject>
        <date>2009-01-23</date>
        <description>Modern King James Version of the Holy Bible 1962</description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>mkjv1962</identifier>
        <source/>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='2Tim'>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.1'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.1'>Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, according to the promise of life which [is] in Christ Jesus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.2'>to Timothy, [my] dearly beloved child. Grace, mercy, peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.3'>I thank God, whom I serve from [my] forefathers with pure conscience, that without ceasing I remember you in my prayers night and day,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.4'>greatly desiring to see you, being mindful of your tears, so that I may be filled with joy,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.5'>taking recollection of the unfeigned faith that is in you, which first dwelt in your grandmother Lois, and in your mother Eunice. And I am persuaded that it is in you also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.6'>Therefore I remind you to inflame anew the gift of God, which is in you by the putting on of my hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.7'>For God has not given us the spirit of fear, but of power and of love and of a sound mind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.8'>Therefore you should not be ashamed of the testimony of our Lord, nor [of] me His prisoner. But be partaker of the afflictions of the gospel according to [the] power of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.9'>who has saved us and called [us] with a holy calling, not according to our works, but according to His own purpose and grace which was given us in Christ Jesus before the eternal times.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.10'>But it is now having been manifested by the appearing of our Savior Jesus Christ, who has made death of no effect, bringing life and immortality to light through the gospel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.11'>to which I am appointed a preacher and an apostle and a teacher of the nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.12'>For this cause I also suffer these things; but I am not ashamed, for I know whom I have believed, and I am persuaded that He is able to guard My deposit unto that Day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.13'>Hold fast the pattern of sound words which you have heard from me, in faith and love [which is] in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.14'>Guard the good Deposit [given] through [the] Holy Spirit indwelling in us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.15'>This you know, that all those in Asia have turned away from me, of whom are Phygellus and Hermogenes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.16'>May the Lord give mercy to the house of Onesiphorus, for he often refreshed me and was not ashamed [of] my chain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.17'>But when he was in Rome, he sought me out very diligently and found [me].</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.18'>May the Lord grant to him that he may find mercy from [the] Lord in that Day. And in what things he ministered [to me] at Ephesus, you know very well.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.2'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.1'>Therefore, my son, be strong in the grace [that is] in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.2'>And the things that you have heard from me among many witnesses, commit the same to faithful men who will be able to teach others also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.3'>Therefore endure hardness, as a good soldier of Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.4'>No one who wars tangles with the affairs of [this] life, that he may please him who chose [him] to be a soldier.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.5'>And also if anyone competes, he is not crowned unless he competes lawfully.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.6'>It is right for the laboring farmer to partake first of the fruits.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.7'>Consider what I say, and the Lord will give you understanding in all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.8'>Remember that Jesus Christ of the seed of David was raised from [the] dead according to my gospel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.9'>in which I suffer ill as an evildoer, [even] to bonds. But the Word of God is not chained.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.10'>Therefore I endure all things for the sake of the elect, that they may also obtain the salvation which is in Christ Jesus with eternal glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.11'>For faithful is the Word, for if we died with [Him], we shall also live with [Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.12'>If we suffer, we shall also reign with [Him]. If we deny [Him], He also will deny us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.13'>If we do not believe [Him], [yet] He remains faithful; He cannot deny Himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.14'>Put [them] in memory of these things, charging them before the Lord not to dispute about words to no profit, to the subverting of the hearers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.15'>[Study] earnestly to present yourself approved to God, a workman that does not need to be ashamed, rightly dividing the Word of Truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.16'>But shun profane, vain babblings, for they will increase to more ungodliness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.17'>And their word will eat like a gangrene; among whom [are] Hymeneus and Philetus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.18'>who have erred concerning the truth, saying that the resurrection is already past, and who overthrow the faith of some.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.19'>Nevertheless the foundation of God stands sure, having this seal:  The] Lord knew those who are His. And, Let everyone who names the name of Christ depart from iniquity!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.20'>But in a great house there are not only vessels of gold and of silver, but also of wood and of earth; and some to honor, and some to dishonor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.21'>Therefore if anyone purges himself from these, he shall be a vessel to honor, sanctified and useful to the Master, prepared for every good work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.22'>But flee youthful lusts, and follow righteousness, faith, love, peace, with those who call on the Lord out of a pure heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.23'>But avoid foolish and unlearned questions, knowing that they give birth to strifes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.24'>But the servant of [the] Lord must not strive, but to be gentle to all, apt to teach, patient,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.25'>in meekness instructing those who oppose, if perhaps God will give them repentance to the acknowledging of [the] truth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.26'>and [that] they awake out of the snare of the Devil, having been taken captive by him, so as to do the will of that one.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.3'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.1'>Know this also, that in [the] last days grievous times will be at hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.2'>For men will be self-lovers, money-lovers, boasters, proud, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.3'>without natural affection, unyielding, false accusers, without self-control, savage, despisers of good,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.4'>traitors, reckless, puffed up, lovers of pleasure rather than lovers of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.5'>having a form of godliness, but denying the power of it; even turn away from these.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.6'>For of these are those who creep into houses and lead captive silly women loaded with sins, led away with different kinds of lusts,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.7'>ever learning and never able to come to the full knowledge of [the] truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.8'>But as Jannes and Jambres withstood Moses, so these also resist the truth, men of corrupt mind, reprobate concerning the faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.9'>But they shall proceed no further. For their foolishness shall be plain to all, as theirs also became.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.10'>But you have fully known my doctrine, manner of life, purpose, faith, long-suffering, love, patience,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.11'>persecutions, afflictions, such as happened to me at Antioch, at Iconium, at Lystra. What persecutions I endured! But the Lord delivered me out of all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.12'>Yea, and all who desire to live godly in Christ Jesus will be persecuted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.13'>But evil men and seducers will go forward to worse, deceiving and being deceived.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.14'>But continue in the things that you have learned and have been assured of, knowing from whom you have learned [them] ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.15'>and that from a babe you have known the Holy Scriptures, which are able to make you wise to salvation through faith in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.16'>All Scripture [is] God-breathed, and is profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for instruction in righteousness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.17'>that the man of God may be perfected, thoroughly furnished to every good work.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.4'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.1'>Therefore I solemnly witness before God and the Lord Jesus Christ, who is going to judge [the] living and [the] dead according to His appearance and His kingdom,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.2'>preach the Word, be instant in season and out of season, reprove, rebuke, exhort with all long-suffering and doctrine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.3'>For a time will be when they will not endure sound doctrine, but they will heap up teachers to themselves according to their own lusts, tickling the ear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.4'>And they will turn away [their] ears from the truth and will be turned to myths.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.5'>But you watch in all things, endure afflictions, do [the] work of an evangelist, fully carry out your ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.6'>For I am already being poured out, and the time of my release is here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.7'>I have fought the good fight, I have finished the course, I have kept the faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.8'>Now there is laid up for me the crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous Judge, shall give me at that Day; and not to me only, but also to all those who love His appearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.9'>Make haste to come to me quickly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.10'>For Demas has forsaken me, having loved this present world, and [he] has departed to Thessalonica. Crescens [went] to Galatia, Titus to Dalmatia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.11'>Only Luke is with me. Take Mark [and] bring [him] with you, for he is profitable to me for [the] ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.12'>And I sent Tychicus to Ephesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.13'>When you come, bring the cloak that I left at Troas with Carpus, and the books, especially the parchments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.14'>Alexander the coppersmith showed many evil things to me. The Lord will give back to him according to his works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.15'>You also should beware of [him], for he has greatly withstood our words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.16'>At my first answer no one was beside me, but all deserted me. May it not be laid to their charge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.17'>But the Lord stood with me and strengthened me, that through me the preaching might be fulfilled, and [that] all the nations might hear. And I was delivered out of [the] mouth of the] lion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.18'>And the Lord shall deliver me from every evil work and will preserve [me] to His heavenly kingdom, to whom [be] glory forever and ever. Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.19'>Greet Priscilla and Aquila and the household of Onesiphorus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.20'>Erastus stayed at Corinth, but Trophimus I left sick at Miletus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.21'>Try to come before winter. Eubulus greets you, and Pudens, and Linus, and Claudia, and all the brothers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.22'>May the Lord Jesus Christ [be] with your spirit. Grace [be] with you. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>