<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='mkjv1962' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='mkjv1962'>
        <title>Modern KJV 1963</title>
        <contributor>xxx</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy</subject>
        <date>2009-01-23</date>
        <description>Modern King James Version of the Holy Bible 1962</description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>mkjv1962</identifier>
        <source/>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Col'>
      <chapter osisID='Col.1'>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.1'>Paul, [an] apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, and Timothy [our] brother,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.2'>to the saints and faithful brothers in Christ at Colosse. Grace to you, and peace from God our Father and from [the] Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.3'>We give thanks to God and the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, praying always for you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.4'>since we heard of your faith in Christ Jesus, and of the love [you have] to all the saints,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.5'>for the hope which is laid up for you in Heaven, of which you heard before in the Word of the truth of the gospel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.6'>which has come to you as [it has] also in all the world, and it is bearing fruit, even also among you, since the day you heard and fully knew the grace of God in truth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.7'>even as you learned from Epaphras our beloved fellow-servant, who is a faithful minister of Christ for you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.8'>he also having shown your love in [the] Spirit to us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.9'>For this cause we also, since the day we heard, do not cease to pray for you, and to desire that you might be filled [with] the knowledge of His will in all wisdom and spiritual understanding,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.10'>that you might walk worthy of the Lord to all pleasing, being fruitful in every work and increasing in the knowledge of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.11'>being empowered with all power, according to the might of His glory, to all patience and long-suffering with joyfulness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.12'>giving thanks to the Father, who has made us meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the saints in light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.13'>[For He] has delivered us from the power of darkness and has translated [us] into the kingdom of His dear Son;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.14'>in whom we have redemption through His blood, the remission of sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.15'>who is [the] image of the invisible God, [the] First-born of all creation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.16'>For all things were created in Him, the things in the heavens, and the things on the earth, the visible and the invisible, whether thrones or dominions or principalities or powers, all things were created through Him and for Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.17'>And He is before all things, and by Him all things consist.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.18'>And He is [the] Head of the body, the church, who is [the] Beginning, the First-born from the dead, that He may be pre-eminent in all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.19'>For it pleased [the Father] that in Him all fullness should dwell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.20'>And through Him having made peace through the blood of His cross, it pleased the Father to reconcile all things to Himself through Him, whether the things on earth or the things in Heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.21'>And you, who were once alienated and enemies in [your] mind by wicked works, yet now He has reconciled</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.22'>in the body of His flesh through death, to present you holy and without blemish, and without charge in His sight,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.23'>if indeed you continue in the faith grounded and settled, and [are] not moved away from the hope of the gospel, which you have heard [and] which was proclaimed in all the creation under Heaven, of which I, Paul, became a minister,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.24'>who now rejoice in my sufferings on your behalf, and I fill up the things lacking of the afflictions of Christ in my flesh, on behalf of His body, which [is] the church;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.25'>of which I became a minister, according to the administration of God given to me for you, to fulfill the word of God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.26'>the mystery which has been hidden from ages and from generations, but now has been revealed to His saints.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.27'>[For to them] God would make known what [are] the riches of the glory of this mystery among the nations, which is Christ in you, the hope of glory,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.28'>whom we preach, warning every man and teaching every man in all wisdom, so that we may present every man perfect in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.29'>For which I also labor, striving according to the working of Him who works in me in power.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Col.2'>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.1'>For I want you to know what a great conflict I have for you and those at Laodicea, and [for] as many as have not seen my face in [the] flesh,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.2'>that their hearts might be comforted, being knit together in love, and to all riches of the full assurance of the understanding, to [the] full knowledge of the mystery of God, and of the Father, and of Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.3'>in whom are hidden all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.4'>And I say this that not anyone should beguile you with enticing words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.5'>For though I am absent in the flesh, yet I am with you in the spirit, rejoicing and beholding your order and the steadfastness of your faith in Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.6'>Therefore as you have received Christ Jesus the Lord, [so] walk in Him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.7'>rooted and built up in Him, and established in the faith, as you have been taught, abounding in it with thanksgiving.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.8'>Beware lest anyone rob you through philosophy and vain deceit, according to the tradition of men, according to the elements of the world, and not according to Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.9'>For in Him dwells all the fullness of the Godhead bodily.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.10'>And you are complete in Him, who is the Head of all principality and power,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.11'>in whom also you are circumcised with the circumcision made without hands, in putting off the body of the sins of the flesh by the circumcision of Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.12'>buried with Him in baptism, in whom also you were raised through the faith of the working of God, raising Him from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.13'>And you, being dead in your sins and the uncircumcision of your flesh, He has made alive together with Him, having forgiven you all trespasses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.14'>blotting out the handwriting of ordinances that was against us, which was contrary to us, and has taken it out of the way, nailing it to the cross.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.15'>Having stripped rulers and authorities, He made a show of them publicly, triumphing [over] them in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.16'>Therefore let no one judge you in food or in drink, or in respect of a feast, or of the new moon, or of the sabbaths.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.17'>For these are a shadow of things to come, but the body [is] of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.18'>Let no one defraud you, delighting in humility and worship of the angels, intruding into things which he has not seen, without a cause [being] vainly puffed up by his fleshly mind,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.19'>and not holding the Head, from whom all the body, having been supplied through the joints and bands, and having been joined together, will grow with the growth of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.20'>If then you died with Christ from the elements of the world, why, as [though] living in [the] world, are you subject to [its] ordinances:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.21'>touch not, taste not, handle not;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.22'>which things are all for corruption in the using, according to the commands and doctrines of men?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.23'>[These] things indeed have a reputation of wisdom in self-imposed worship and humility, and unsparing severity of the] body, not in any honor for the satisfying of the flesh.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Col.3'>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.1'>If then you were raised with Christ, seek those things which are above, where Christ is sitting at [the] right hand of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.2'>Be mindful of things above, not on things on the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.3'>For you died, and your life has been hidden with Christ in God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.4'>When Christ our Life [is] revealed, then you also will be revealed with Him in glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.5'>Therefore put to death your members which are on the earth: fornication, uncleanness, passion, evil desire, and covetousness (which is idolatry),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.6'>on account of which things' sake the wrath of God is coming on the sons of disobedience,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.7'>among whom you also once walked, when you lived in these.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.8'>But now also put off all [these] things: anger, wrath, malice, blasphemy, shameful speech out of your mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.9'>Do not lie to one another, having put off the old man with his deeds</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.10'>and having put on the new, having been renewed in knowledge according to [the] image of Him who created him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.11'>where there is neither Greek nor Jew, circumcision and uncircumcision, foreigner, Scythian, slave [or] freeman, but Christ [is] all things in all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.12'>Therefore, as the elect of God, holy and beloved, put on tender feelings of mercy, kindness, humbleness of mind, meekness, long-suffering,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.13'>forbearing one another and forgiving yourselves, if anyone has a complaint against any. As Christ forgave you, so also you [do].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.14'>And above all these things [put on] love, which is [the] bond of perfectness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.15'>And let the peace of God rule in your hearts, to which you also are called in one body, and be thankful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.16'>Let the word of Christ dwell in you richly in all wisdom, teaching and admonishing one another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing with grace in your hearts to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.17'>And everything, whatever you do in word or deed, [do] all in the name of [the] Lord Jesus, giving thanks to God and [the] Father by Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.18'>Wives, be subject to [your] own husbands, as is becoming in [the] Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.19'>Husbands, love [your] wives, and do not be bitter against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.20'>Children, obey [your] parents in all things, for this is well-pleasing to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.21'>Fathers, do not provoke your children, lest they be discouraged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.22'>Slaves, obey [your] masters according to the flesh in all things; not with eye-service, as men-pleasers, but in singleness of heart, fearing God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.23'>And whatever you do, do [it] heartily, as to the Lord and not to men;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.24'>knowing that from the Lord you shall receive the reward of the inheritance. For you serve [the] Lord Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.25'>But he who does wrong shall receive [justice] for the wrong which he did, and there is no respect of persons.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Col.4'>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.1'>Masters, give to [your] slaves what [is] just and equal, knowing that you also have a Master in Heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.2'>Continue in prayer and watch in it with thanksgiving,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.3'>praying together about us also, that God may open to us a door of the Word, to speak the mystery of Christ, for which I also have been bound,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.4'>that I may make it clear, as I ought to speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.5'>Walk in wisdom toward those on the outside, redeeming the time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.6'>Let your speech [be] always with grace, having been seasoned with salt, that you may know how you ought to answer each one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.7'>Tychicus, the beloved brother and faithful minister and fellow-servant in [the] Lord, will make known to you all things about me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.8'>I sent [him] to you for this very purpose, that he might know the things about you, and that he might comfort your hearts,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.9'>along with Onesimus, a faithful and beloved brother, who is [one] of you. They shall make known to you all things here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.10'>Aristarchus my fellow prisoner greets you, and Mark, the cousin of Barnabas (regarding whom you received commandments; if he comes to you, receive him),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.11'>and [greetings from] Jesus, who is called Justus, those being of the circumcision. These alone [are my] fellow-workers for the kingdom of God, who became a comfort to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.12'>Epaphras greets you, he being of you, a servant of Christ, always laboring fervently for you in prayers, that you may stand perfect and complete in all the will of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.13'>For I bear him record that he has a great zeal for you and for those [who are] in Laodicea and those in Hierapolis.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.14'>Luke, the beloved physician, and Demas, greet you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.15'>Greet the brothers who are in Laodicea, and Nymphas, and the church in his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.16'>And when this letter is read before you, cause that it be read also in the church of the Laodiceans, and that you also read the [letter] of Laodicea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.17'>And say to Archippus, Take heed to the ministry which you have received in [the] Lord, that you fulfill it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.18'>The salutation of Paul, by my own hand. Remember my bonds. Grace [be] with you. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>