<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='mkjv1962' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='mkjv1962'>
        <title>Modern KJV 1963</title>
        <contributor>xxx</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy</subject>
        <date>2009-01-23</date>
        <description>Modern King James Version of the Holy Bible 1962</description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>mkjv1962</identifier>
        <source/>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Dan'>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.1'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.1'>In the third year of the reign of Jehoiakim king of Judah, Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came to Jerusalem and besieged it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.2'>And the Lord gave Jehoiakim king of Judah into his hand, with part of the vessels of the house of God, which he carried into the land of Shinar to the house of his god. And he brought the vessels into the treasure house of his god.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.3'>And the king spoke to Ashpenaz the master of his eunuchs that he should bring [some] of the sons of Israel, and of the king's seed, and of the rulers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.4'>sons [in] whom was no blemish, but who were handsome and skillful in all wisdom; and who had knowledge and understanding, even those who were able to stand in the king's palace, and to whom they might teach the writing and the language of the Chaldeans.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.5'>And the king gave them the portion of a day in its day from the king's food, and the wine which he drank, even to rear them three years, so that at their end they might stand before the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.6'>And among them were [four] of the sons of Judah: Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.7'>to whom the ruler of the eunuchs gave names. For he called Daniel, Belteshazzar; and Hananiah, Shadrach; and Mishael, Meshach; and Azariah, Abednego.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.8'>But Daniel laid on his heart that he would not defile himself with the king's food, nor with the wine which he drank. So he asked permission of the chief of the eunuchs that he might not defile himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.9'>And God had given Daniel kindness and compassion before the chief of the eunuchs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.10'>And the chief of the eunuchs said to Daniel, I fear my lord the king, who has chosen your food and your drink. For why should he see your faces worse looking than the boys who [are] of your kind? Then you would forfeit my head to the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.11'>And Daniel said to Melzar, whom the chief of the eunuchs had set over Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.12'>I beg you, try your servants ten days. And let them give us vegetables to eat and water to drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.13'>Then let our look be seen before you, and the look of the boys who eat of the king's food. And as you see, deal with your servants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.14'>So he listened to them in this matter, and tried them for ten days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.15'>And at the end of ten days their faces looked fairer and fatter in flesh than all the boys who had eaten the king's food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.16'>So Melzar took away their part of the food, and the wine that they were to drink, and gave them vegetables.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.17'>As for these four boys, God gave them knowledge and skill in all writing and wisdom. And Daniel had understanding in all visions and dreams.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.18'>And at the end of the days that the king had said he would bring them in, the chief of the eunuchs brought them in before Nebuchadnezzar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.19'>And the king talked with them. And among them all were found none like Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah. So they stood before the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.20'>And [in] any matters of wisdom [and] understanding that the king asked them, he found them ten times better than all the horoscopists [and] conjurers who were in all his kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.1.21'>And Daniel continued to the first year of King Cyrus.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.2'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.1'>And in the second year of the reign of king Nebuchadnezzar, Nebuchadnezzar dreamed dreams, with which his spirit was troubled and his sleep left him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.2'>And the king commanded to call to the horoscopists, and to the conjurers, and to the sorcerers, and to the Chaldeans, to tell to the king his dreams. So they came and stood before the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.3'>And the king said to them, I have dreamed a dream, and my spirit was troubled to know the dream.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.4'>And the Chaldeans spoke to the king [in] Aramaic, O king, live forever. Tell your servants the dream, and we will reveal the meaning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.5'>The king answered and said to the Chaldeans, The thing has gone from me. If you will not make known to me the dream, with its meaning, you will be made into [mere] members, and your houses shall be made an outhouse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.6'>But if you make known the dream and its meaning, you shall receive gifts and a present and great honor from me. Therefore reveal to me the dream and its meaning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.7'>They answered again and said, Let the king tell his servants the dream, and we will reveal its meaning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.8'>The king answered and said, For I know that you surely want to gain time, because you see the thing is gone from me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.9'>But if you will not make the dream known to me, [there is] only one judgment for you. For you have prepared lying and deceiving words to speak before me, until the time has changed. Therefore tell me the dream, and I shall know that you can reveal to me its meaning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.10'>The Chaldeans answered before the king and said, There is not a man on the earth who can reveal the king's matter, because not any king, lord, nor ruler has asked such a thing from any horoscopist or conjurer or Chaldean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.11'>And [it is] a rare thing that the king asks, and there is no other who can reveal it before the king, except the gods, whose dwelling is not with flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.12'>For this cause the king was enraged and angered, and commanded all the wise men of Babylon to be destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.13'>And the law went out that the wise men should be killed. And they sought Daniel and his fellows to be killed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.14'>Then Daniel answered [with] counsel and insight to Arioch the chief of the king's executioners, who had gone forth to kill the wise men of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.15'>He answered and said to Arioch the king's captain, Why is the decree so hasty from the king? Then Arioch made the thing known to Daniel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.16'>Then Daniel went in and asked of the king that he would give him time, and that he would make known the meaning to the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.17'>Then Daniel went to his house and made the thing known to Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah, his companions,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.18'>that they might pray for the mercies of God in Heaven concerning this secret, that Daniel and his companions should not perish with the rest of the wise men of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.19'>Then the secret was revealed to Daniel in a night vision. And Daniel blessed the God of Heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.20'>Daniel answered and said, Blessed be the name of God forever and ever, for wisdom and might are His.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.21'>And He changes the times and the seasons; He removes kings and sets up kings. He gives wisdom to the wise and knowledge to those who have understanding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.22'>He reveals the deep and secret things; He knows what [is] in the darkness, and the light dwells with Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.23'>I thank You, and praise You, O God of my fathers, who has given me wisdom and might, and have made known to me now what we asked of You. For You have now made known to us the king's matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.24'>Then Daniel went in to Arioch, whom the king had chosen to destroy the wise men of Babylon. He went and said this to him; Do not destroy the wise men of Babylon. Bring me in before the king, and I will declare the meaning to the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.25'>Then Arioch quickly brought Daniel in before the king, and said this to him, I have found a man of the captives of Judah who will make the meaning known to the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.26'>The king answered and said to Daniel, whose name [was] Belteshazzar, Are you able to make known to me the dream which I have seen, and its meaning?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.27'>Daniel answered before the king and said, The secret which the king has demanded cannot be shown to the king by the wise men, the conjurers, the horoscopists, or the fortune-tellers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.28'>But there is a God in Heaven who reveals secrets and makes known to King Nebuchadnezzar what shall be in the latter days. Your dream, and the visions of your head upon your bed [are] these.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.29'>As for you, O king, your thoughts came on your bed, what should happen after this. And He who reveals secrets makes known to you what shall happen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.30'>But as for me, this secret is not revealed to me for [any] wisdom that I have more than any living man, but so that the meaning might be known to the king, and that you might know the thoughts of your heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.31'>You, O king, were seeing. And, behold! A great image! That great image, whose brightness was excellent, stood before you. And its form [was] dreadful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.32'>This image's head [was] of fine gold; his breast and his arms [were] of silver; his belly and his thighs [were] of bronze;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.33'>his legs [were] of iron; his feet [were] part of iron and part of clay.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.34'>You watched until a stone was cut out without hands, which struck the image upon its feet [which were] of iron and clay, and broke them to pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.35'>Then the iron, the clay, the bronze, the silver, and the gold were broken to pieces together. And they became like the chaff of the summer threshing floors. And the wind carried them away, so that no place was found for them. And the stone that struck the image became a great mountain and filled the whole earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.36'>This [is] the dream. And we will tell its meaning before the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.37'>You, O king, [are] a king of kings. For the God of Heaven has given you a kingdom, power, and strength, and glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.38'>And wherever the sons of men, the beasts of the field, and the birds of the heavens live, He has given [them] into your hand, and has made you ruler over them all. You are this head of gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.39'>And after you shall arise another kingdom lower than you, and another third kingdom of bronze, which shall rule over all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.40'>And the fourth kingdom shall be [as] strong as iron. Since iron crushes and smashes all things; and as the iron that shatters all these, it will crush and shatter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.41'>And as to that which you saw: the feet and toes, part of potters' clay and part of iron; [the] kingdom shall be divided. But there shall be in it the strength of the iron, because you saw the iron mixed with miry clay.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.42'>And [as] the toes of the feet [were] part of iron and part of clay, [so] the kingdom shall be partly strong and partly brittle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.43'>And as you saw iron mixed with miry clay, they shall mix themselves with the seed of men. But they shall not cling to one another, even as iron is not mixed with clay.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.44'>And in the days of these kings, the God of Heaven shall set up a kingdom which shall never be destroyed. And the kingdom shall not be left to other peoples, but it shall crush and destroy all these kingdoms, and it shall stand forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.45'>Because you saw that the stone was cut out of the mountain without hands, and that it crushes the iron, the bronze, the clay, the silver, and the gold, the great God has made known to the king what shall occur after this. And the dream  is] certain, and its meaning is sure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.46'>Then King Nebuchadnezzar fell on his face and worshiped Daniel, and he commanded to offer an offering and incense to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.47'>The king answered Daniel and said, It is true that your God [is] a God of gods, and a Lord of kings, and a revealer of secrets, since you could reveal this secret.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.48'>Then the king made Daniel great, and gave him many great gifts, and made him ruler over all the province of Babylon, and chief of the prefects over all the wise men of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.2.49'>And Daniel asked the king, and he set Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego over the affairs of the province of Babylon. But Daniel [sat] in the gate of the king.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.3'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.1'>Nebuchadnezzar the king made an image of gold, whose height [was] sixty cubits, and its breadth six cubits. He set it up in the plain of Dura, in the province of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.2'>Then Nebuchadnezzar the king sent to gather together the satraps, the prefects, the governors, the counselors, the treasurers, the judges, the justices, and all the officials of the provinces, to come to the dedication of the image which Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.3'>Then were gathered the satraps, the prefects, the governors, the counselors, the treasurers, the judges, the justices, and all the officials of the provinces, to the dedication of the image that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up. And they stood before the image that Nebuchadnezzar had set up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.4'>Then a herald cried aloud, To you it is commanded, O people, nations, and languages,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.5'>at the time you hear the sound of the horn, the pipe, zither, the lyre, harp, bagpipe, and all kinds of music, you shall fall down and worship the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king has set up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.6'>And whoever does not fall down and worship, at that moment they will be thrown into the middle of a burning fiery furnace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.7'>Therefore at that time, when all the people heard the sound of the horn, the pipe, zither, the lyre, harp, and all kinds of music, all the people, the nations, and the languages, fell down and worshiped the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.8'>Then at that time certain Chaldeans came near and accused the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.9'>They spoke and said to king Nebuchadnezzar, O king, live forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.10'>You, O king, have made a decree that every man who shall hear the sound of the horn, the pipe, zither, the lyre, harp, and the bagpipe, and all kinds of music, shall fall down and worship the golden image.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.11'>And whoever does not fall down and worship, he should be thrown into the midst of a burning fiery furnace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.12'>There are men, Jews, whom you have set over the business of the province of Babylon, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. These men, O king, do not heed you. They do not serve your gods nor worship the golden image which you have set up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.13'>Then Nebuchadnezzar in anger and wrath commanded them to bring Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. Then they brought these men before the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.14'>Nebuchadnezzar spoke and said to them, [Is it] true, O Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego? Do you not serve my gods, nor worship the golden image which I have set up?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.15'>Now if you are ready, at the time you hear the sound of the horn, the pipe, zither, the lyre, harp, and bagpipe, and all kinds of music, fall down and worship the image which I have made. But if you do not worship, in that moment you shall be thrown into the middle of a burning fiery furnace. And who is that god who shall deliver you out of my hand?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.16'>Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego answered and said to the king, O Nebuchadnezzar, we [have] no need to return a word to you on this matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.17'>If it is [so that] our God whom we serve is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace, then He will deliver us out of your hand, O king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.18'>But if not, let it be known to you, O king, that we will not serve your gods nor worship the golden image which you have set up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.19'>Then Nebuchadnezzar was filled with wrath, and the form of his face was changed against Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. He spoke and commanded that they should heat the furnace seven times more than it was usually heated.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.20'>And he commanded mighty men in his army to tie up Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, and to throw [them] into the burning fiery furnace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.21'>Then these men were tied up in their slippers, their tunics, and their mantles, and their [other] clothes, and were thrown into the middle of the burning fiery furnace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.22'>Then because the king's commandment was urgent, and the furnace exceedingly hot, the flame of the fire killed those men who took up Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.23'>And these three men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, fell down bound into the midst of the burning fiery furnace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.24'>Then Nebuchadnezzar the king was amazed. And he rose up in haste and spoke and said to his advisers, Did we not throw three men bound into the middle of the fire? They answered and said to the king, True, O king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.25'>He answered and said, Behold! I see four men loose, walking in the middle of the fire, and there is no harm among them. And the form of the fourth is like a son of [the] gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.26'>Then Nebuchadnezzar came near the door of the burning fiery furnace. He answered and said, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, servants of the most high God, come forth and come [here]. Then Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, came forth from the middle of the fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.27'>And the satraps, the prefects, the governors, and the king's advisers gathered and saw these men [on whose] bodies the fire had no power (and the hair of their head was not scorched, nor were their slippers changed, nor had the smell of fire clung on them).</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.28'>Nebuchadnezzar spoke and said, Blessed [be] the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, who has sent His Angel and has delivered His servants who trusted in Him, and have changed the king's words and has given their bodies that they might not serve nor worship any god except their own God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.29'>And a decree is given by me, that every people, nation, and language, who speak anything amiss against the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, shall be made into mere members, and his house shall be made an outhouse. Because there is no other God who can deliver in this way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.3.30'>Then the king made Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego prosper in the province of Babylon.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.4'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.1'>Nebuchadnezzar the king, to all people, nations, and languages, that dwell in all the earth: Peace be multiplied to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.2'>It seemed good before me to declare the signs and wonders that the Most High God has done with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.3'>How great [are] His signs! And how mighty [are] His wonders! His kingdom [is] an everlasting kingdom, and His rule [is] from generation to generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.4'>I, Nebuchadnezzar, was at rest in my house and flourishing in my palace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.5'>I saw a dream and it terrified me, and [the] thoughts on my bed and the visions of my head troubled me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.6'>So I made a decree to bring in all the wise men of Babylon before me, that they might make known to me the meaning of the dream.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.7'>Then the horoscopists, the conjurers, the Chaldeans, and the fortune-tellers came in. And I told the dream before them, but they did not make its meaning known to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.8'>But at last Daniel came in before me, whose name [was] Belteshazzar, according to the name of my god, and in whom [is] the spirit of the holy gods. And I told the dream before him, [saying] ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.9'>O Belteshazzar, master of the horoscopists, because I know that the spirit of the holy gods [is] in you, and no secret troubles you, tell me the visions of my dream that I have seen, and its meaning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.10'>As to the visions of my head on my bed: I saw, and behold a tree in the midst of the earth, and its height [was] great.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.11'>The tree grew and was strong, and its height reached to the heavens; and the sight of it reached to the end of all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.12'>Its leaves [were] beautiful, and its fruit plentiful, and in it [was] food for all. The animals of the field sought shade under it, and the birds of the heavens lived in its boughs, and all flesh was fed by it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.13'>I saw in the visions of my head on my bed, and behold, a watcher and a holy one came down from Heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.14'>He cried aloud and said this, Cut down the tree, and cut off its branches; shake off its leaves and scatter its fruit. Let the animals get away from under it, and the birds from its branches.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.15'>But leave the stump of its roots in the earth, even with a band of iron and bronze, in the tender grass of the field. And let it be wet with the dew of heaven, and let its portion [be] with the animals in the grass of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.16'>Let his heart be changed from man's, and let the heart of an animal be given to him. And let seven times pass over him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.17'>This matter is by the decree of the watchers, and the demand by the word of the holy ones, so that the living may know that the Most High rules in the kingdom of men, and gives it to whomever He will, and sets up over it the lowest of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.18'>I, King Nebuchadnezzar, have seen this dream. Now you, O Belteshazzar, declare its meaning, because all the wise men of my kingdom are not able to make the meaning known to me. But you are able, for the spirit of the holy gods [is] in you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.19'>Then Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, was stunned for one hour, and his thoughts troubled him. The king spoke and said, Belteshazzar, do not let the dream or its meaning trouble you. Belteshazzar answered and said, My lord, the dream  is] to those who hate you, and its meaning to your foes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.20'>The tree that you saw, which became great and strong, whose height reached to the heaven, and the sight of it to all the earth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.21'>whose leaves were fair, and its fruit plentiful, and in it [was] food for all, under which the animals of the field dwelt, and on whose branches the birds of the heavens had their home;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.22'>it [is] you, O king, for you have become great and strong, for your greatness has grown and reached to the heaven, and your rule to the end of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.23'>And as the king saw a watcher and a holy one coming down from Heaven, and saying, Cut the tree down and destroy it; yet leave the stump of the roots of it in the earth, even with a band of iron and bronze, in the tender grass of the field; and let it be wet with the dew of heaven, and [let] his portion [be] with the animals of the field, until seven times pass over him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.24'>this [is] the meaning, O king, and this the decree of the Most High, which has come on my lord the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.25'>They shall drive you from men, and your dwelling shall be with the animals of the field, and they shall make you eat grass like oxen. And they shall wet you [with] the dew of heaven, and seven times shall pass over you, until you know that the Most High rules in the kingdom of men, and gives it to whomever He will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.26'>And in that they commanded to leave the stump of the tree roots; your kingdom [shall be] sure to you after you have known that Heaven rules.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.27'>Therefore, O king, let my advice be pleasing to you, and break off your sins by righteousness, and your iniquities by showing mercy to the poor, whether there will be duration to your prosperity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.28'>All this came on the king Nebuchadnezzar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.29'>At the end of twelve months he walked in the palace of the kingdom of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.30'>The king spoke and said, [Is] this not great Babylon that I have built for the house of the kingdom by the might of my power and for the honor of my majesty?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.31'>While the word [was] in the king's mouth, a voice fell from Heaven, saying, O King Nebuchadnezzar, to you it is spoken. The kingdom has departed from you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.32'>And they shall drive you from men, and your dwelling shall be with the animals of the field. They shall make you eat grass like oxen, and seven times shall pass over you, until you know that the Most High rules in the kingdom of men, and gives it to whomever He will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.33'>The same hour the thing was fulfilled on Nebuchadnezzar. And he was driven from men, and ate grass like oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of the heavens, until his hair had grown like eagles'  feathers], and his nails like birds' [claws].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.34'>And at the end of days, I Nebuchadnezzar lifted up my eyes to Heaven, and my understanding returned to me, and I blessed the Most High, and I praised and honored Him who lives forever, whose kingdom  is] an everlasting kingdom, and His rule is from generation to generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.35'>And all the people of the earth are counted as nothing; and He does according to His will in the army of heaven, and [among] the people of the earth. And none can strike His hand, or say to Him, What are You doing?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.36'>At that time my reason returned to me. And the glory of my kingdom, my honor and brightness returned to me. And my advisers and my lords came for me, and I was established in my kingdom, and excellent majesty was added to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.4.37'>Now I Nebuchadnezzar praise and exalt and honor the King of heaven, all whose works are truth and His ways judgment. And those who walk in pride He is able to humble.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.5'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.1'>Belshazzar the king made a great feast to a thousand of his lords, and drank wine before the thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.2'>When tasting the wine, Belshazzar commanded to bring the golden and silver vessels which his father Nebuchadnezzar had taken out of the temple in Jerusalem, that the king and his rulers, his wives and his concubines, might drink from them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.3'>Then they brought the golden vessels that were taken out of the temple of the house of God in Jerusalem. And the king, and his rulers, his wives, and his concubines, drank in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.4'>They drank wine, and praised the gods of gold, and of silver, and of bronze, of iron, of wood, and of stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.5'>At that moment fingers of a man's hand came out and wrote on the plaster of the wall of the king's palace across from the lampstand. And the king saw the part of the hand that wrote.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.6'>Then the king's face was changed, and his thoughts troubled him, so that the joints of his loins were loosened, and his knees knocked against one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.7'>The king cried aloud to bring in the conjurers, the Chaldeans, and the fortune-tellers. The king spoke and said to the wise men of Babylon, Whoever shall read this writing, and show me its meaning, shall be clothed with scarlet, and [have a chain of gold around his neck, and shall be the third ruler in the kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.8'>Then all the king's wise men came in. But they could not read the writing, nor make the meaning known to the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.9'>Then King Belshazzar was greatly troubled, and his face was changing in him, and his lords were perplexed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.10'>The queen came into the banquet house because of the king's words, and his nobles. And the queen spoke and said, O king, live forever. Do not let your thoughts trouble you, nor let your face be changed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.11'>There [is] a man in your kingdom, in whom [is] the spirit of the holy gods. And in the days of your father there was found in him light and understanding and wisdom, like the wisdom of the gods. Your father, King Nebuchadnezzar, your father the king, appointed him master of the horoscopists, conjurers, Chaldeans, [and] fortune-tellers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.12'>because an excellent spirit, and knowledge, and understanding, explaining of dreams, and revealing of hard sentences, and the unraveling of knots, were found in this Daniel, whom the king named Belteshazzar. Now let Daniel be called, and he will reveal the meaning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.13'>Then Daniel was brought in before the king. The king spoke and said to Daniel, Are you that Daniel who [is] of the exiled sons of Judah, whom the king my father brought out of Judah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.14'>I have even heard of you, that the spirit of the gods [is] in you, and that light and understanding and excellent wisdom are found in you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.15'>And now the wise men and the conjurers have been brought in before me, that they might read this writing and make the meaning known to me. But they could not declare the meaning of the thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.16'>And I have heard of you that you can interpret meanings and unravel knots. Now if you can read the writing, and reveal its meaning to me, you shall be clothed with scarlet and [have] a chain of gold around your neck, and shall be the third ruler in the kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.17'>Then Daniel answered and said before the king, Let your gifts be to yourself, and give your rewards to another. Yet I will read the writing to the king, and make the meaning known to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.18'>O king, the Most High God gave Nebuchadnezzar your father a kingdom, and majesty, and glory, and honor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.19'>And for the majesty that He gave him, all people, nations, and languages trembled and feared before him. He killed whom he would, and whom he would he kept alive. And whom he would, he set up; and whom he would, he put down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.20'>But when his heart was lifted up, and his mind hardened in pride, he was put down from the throne of his kingdom, and they took his glory from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.21'>And he was driven from the sons of men. And his heart was made like the animals, and his dwelling [was] with the wild asses. They fed him with grass like oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of the heavens, until he knew that the Most High God rules in the kingdom of men, and that He appoints over it whomever He will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.22'>And you his son, O Belshazzar, have not humbled your heart, though you knew all this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.23'>But you have lifted up yourself against the Lord of heaven. And they have brought the vessels of His house before you; and you, and your lords, your wives, and your concubines, have drunk wine from them. And you have praised the gods of silver, and gold, or bronze, iron, wood, and stone, which do not see, nor hear, nor know. And you have not glorified the God in whose hand [is] your breath and all your ways.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.24'>Then the part of the hand was sent from Him. And this writing was written.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.25'>And this [is] the writing that was written, A MINA, A MINA, A SHEKEL, AND HALF-MINAS.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.26'>This [is] the meaning of the thing: A MINA, God has numbered your kingdom and finished it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.27'>A SHEKEL, You are weighed in the balances and found wanting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.28'>HALF-MINAS, Your kingdom is divided and given to [the] Medes and Persians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.29'>Then Belshazzar commanded, and they clothed Daniel with scarlet and a golden chain around his neck, and made a proclamation concerning him that he should be the third ruler in the kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.30'>In that night Belshazzar the king of the Chaldeans was killed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.5.31'>And Darius the Mede took the kingdom, being a son of sixty-two years.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.6'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.1'>It pleased Darius to set over the kingdom a hundred and twenty satraps, that they might be over the whole kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.2'>And over them [were] three presidents (Daniel was one of them), so that these satraps might give account to them, and the king should have no loss.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.3'>Then this Daniel was made overseer of the presidents and satraps, because an excellent spirit [was] in him. And the king was planning to set him over all the kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.4'>Then the presidents and rulers sought to find occasion against Daniel concerning the kingdom. But they could find no occasion or fault, because he [was] faithful. Neither [was] there any error or fault found in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.5'>Then these men said, We shall not find any occasion against this Daniel unless we find it against him concerning the law of his God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.6'>Then these presidents and rulers assembled to the king, and said this to him: King Darius, live forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.7'>All the presidents of the kingdom, the prefects, and the satraps, and the officials and governors, have planned together to establish a royal law, and to make a strong ban that whoever shall ask a petition of any god or man for thirty days, except from you, O king, he shall be thrown into the den of lions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.8'>Now, O king, establish the ban and sign the writing, so that it may not be changed, according to the law of the Medes and Persians which cannot be changed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.9'>Therefore king Darius signed the writing and the ban.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.10'>And when he had learned that the document was signed, Daniel went to his house. And his windows were open in his roof room toward Jerusalem; and he kneeled on his knees three times a day and prayed, and gave thanks before his God, as he did before.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.11'>Then these men assembled and found Daniel praying and confessing before his God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.12'>Then they came near and spoke before the king concerning the king's ban. Have you not signed a ban that every man who shall ask a petition of any god or man within thirty days, except of you, O king, shall be thrown into the lion's den? The king answered and said, The thing is true, according to the law of the Medes and Persians, which cannot be changed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.13'>Then they answered and said before the king, Daniel, who [is] of the exiled sons of Judah, has not respected you, O king, nor the ban that you have signed, but makes his prayer three times a day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.14'>Then the king, when he heard the word, was very much displeased with himself. And he set [his] heart on Daniel to deliver him. And he labored until sundown to deliver him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.15'>Then these men met before the king and said to the king, Know, O king, that the law of the Medes and Persians [is] that no ban nor law which the king establishes may be changed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.16'>Then the king commanded, and they brought Daniel and threw him into the lions' den. The king answered and said to Daniel, Your God, whom you always serve, will deliver you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.17'>And a stone was brought and laid on the mouth of the den. And the king sealed it with his own signet, and with the signet of his lords, that the purpose might not be changed concerning Daniel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.18'>Then the king went to his palace and spent the night fasting. And diversions were not brought before him; and his sleep fled from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.19'>Then the king arose very early in the morning and hurried to the lions' den.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.20'>And when he came to the den, he cried with a grieved voice to Daniel. The king spoke and said to Daniel, O Daniel, servant of the living God, is your God whom you always serve able to deliver you from the lions?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.21'>Then Daniel said to the king, O king, live forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.22'>My God has sent His Angel, and has shut the lions' mouths, and they have not hurt me, because before Him purity was found in me. And also before you, O king, I have done no harm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.23'>Then the king was exceedingly glad for him, and commanded that they should take Daniel up out of the den. So Daniel was taken up out of the den, and no kind of hurt was found on him, because he trusted in his God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.24'>And the king commanded, and they brought those men who had accused Daniel, and they threw [them] into the lions' den; them, their sons, and their wives. And the lions overpowered them and broke all their bones in pieces before they came to the bottom of the den.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.25'>Then king Darius wrote to all people, nations, and languages who dwell in all the earth. Peace be multiplied to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.26'>I make a decree that in all the domain of my kingdom, [there] shall be trembling and fear before the God of Daniel. For He [is] the living God, and endures forever, and His kingdom is that which shall not be destroyed, and His rule [shall be] to the end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.27'>He delivers and rescues, and He works signs and wonders in the heavens and in earth, He who has delivered Daniel from the power of the lions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.6.28'>And this Daniel was blessed in the reign of Darius, and in the reign of Cyrus the Persian.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.7'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.1'>In the first year of Belshazzar king of Babylon, Daniel had a dream and visions of his head on his bed. Then he wrote the dream and gave the sum of the matters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.2'>Daniel spoke and said, In my vision by night I was looking: and behold, the four winds of the heavens were stirring up the Great Sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.3'>And four great beasts came up from the sea, different from one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.4'>The first was like a lion and had eagle's wings. I watched until its wings were plucked, and it was lifted up from the earth and made to stand on its feet like a man. And a man's heart was given to it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.5'>And behold another beast, a second, like a bear. And it raised itself up on one side, and it had three ribs in its mouth between its teeth. And they said this to it: Arise, eat up much flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.6'>After this I saw, and lo, another, like a leopard, which [had] four wings of a bird on its back. The beast also [had] four heads; and rulership was given to it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.7'>After this I looked in the night visions, and behold, a fourth beast, frightening and terrifying, and very strong. And it [had] great iron teeth; it devoured and broke in pieces, and stamped the rest with its feet. And it [was] different from all the beasts before it; and it had ten horns.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.8'>I was thinking about the horns, and behold, there came up among them another little horn, before whom three of the first horns were uprooted. And behold, in this horn [were] eyes like the eyes of man, and a mouth speaking great things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.9'>I watched until the thrones were thrown up, and the Ancient of Days sat, whose robe [was] white as snow, and the hair of His head like the pure wool. His throne [was] like flames of fire, and His wheels [like] burning fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.10'>A stream of fire went out and came out from before Him. A thousand thousands served Him, and ten thousand times ten thousand stood before Him. The judgment was set, and the books were opened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.11'>Then I was looking because of the voice of the great words which the horn spoke. I watched until the beast was slain, and his body was destroyed and given to the burning flame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.12'>And the rest of the beasts, their dominion was taken away. Yet their lives were made longer for a season and time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.13'>I saw in the night visions, and behold, [One] like the Son of man came with the clouds of heaven, and came to the Ancient of Days, and they brought Him near before Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.14'>And dominion and glory was given Him, and a kingdom, that all peoples, nations and languages, should serve Him. His dominion [is] an everlasting dominion which shall not pass away, and His kingdom that which shall not be destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.15'>I Daniel was distressed in My spirit in its body, and the visions of my head troubled me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.16'>And I came near one of those who stood by, and asked him the truth of all this. So he told me, and made me know the meaning of the things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.17'>These four great beasts [are] four kings; they shall arise out of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.18'>But the saints of the Most High shall take the kingdom and possess the kingdom forever, even forever and ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.19'>Then I wanted to know the truth of the fourth beast, which [was] different from all the others, very frightening, whose teeth [were of] iron, and his nails of bronze; [who] devoured, broke in pieces, and stamped the rest with his feet;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.20'>and of the ten horns that were in his head, and [of] the other which came up, and before whom three fell; even [of] that horn that had eyes, and a mouth speaking very great things, whose look [was] greater than his fellows.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.21'>I watched, and that horn made war with the saints and overcame them</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.22'>until the Ancient of Days came, and judgment was given to the saints of the Most High. And the time came that the saints possessed the kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.23'>And he said, The fourth beast shall be the fourth kingdom on earth, which shall be different from all kingdoms and shall devour the whole earth, and shall trample it and crush it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.24'>And the ten horns out of this kingdom [are] ten kings that shall arise. And another shall arise after them. And he shall be different from the first, and he shall humble three kings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.25'>And he shall speak words against the Most High, and shall wear out the saints of the Most High, and plot to change times and laws. And they shall be given into his hand until a time and times and one-half time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.26'>But the judgment shall sit, and they shall take away his rulership, to cut off and to destroy until the end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.27'>And the kingdom and rulership, and the greatness of the kingdom under all the heavens, shall be given to the people of the saints of the Most High, whose kingdom [is] an everlasting kingdom. And all kingdoms shall serve and obey Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.7.28'>Here [is] the end of the matter. As for me Daniel, my thoughts troubled me much, and my face changed on me. But I kept the matter in my heart.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.8'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.1'>In the third year of the reign of king Belshazzar a vision appeared to me, [to] me, Daniel, after that which appeared to me at the first.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.2'>And in a vision I looked. And it happened when I looked, I [was] at Shushan the palace, which [is] in the province of Elam. And in a vision I looked, and I was by the Ulai Canal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.3'>Then I lifted up my eyes, and looked. And behold, a ram with [two] horns stood before the Canal [having] two horns, and the [two] horns were high, but one [was] higher than the other, and the higher came up last.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.4'>I saw the ram pushing westward and northward and southward; so that no beasts could stand before him, nor any that could deliver out of his hand. But he did according to his will, and became great.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.5'>And as I was watching, behold, a he-goat came from the west, over the face of the all earth, and did not touch the ground. And the he goat [had] an outstanding horn between his eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.6'>And he came to the ram that [had two] horns, which I had seen standing before the river, and ran to him in the fury of his power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.7'>And I saw him come close beside the ram, and he was moved with anger against him, and struck the ram and shattered his two horns. And there was no power in the ram to stand before him. But he threw him down to the ground and stamped on him. And none could deliver the ram out of his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.8'>Then the he-goat became very great. And when he was strong, the great horn was broken. And in its place came up four outstanding [ones] towards the four winds of the heavens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.9'>And out of one of them came forth a little horn, which became very great, toward the south and toward the east and toward the bountiful [land].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.10'>And it became great, [even] to the host of heaven. And it made fall some of the host and of the stars to the ground, and trampled them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.11'>Yea, he magnified himself, even to the ruler of the host, and the daily [sacrifice] was taken away by him, and the place of his sanctuary was cast down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.12'>And an army was given [to him] against the daily [sacrifice] because of transgression, and it cast the truth to the ground. And it worked and succeeded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.13'>Then I heard a certain holy one speaking, and another holy one said to that one who spoke, Until when shall the vision last, concerning the daily [sacrifice] and the transgression that astounds, to give both the sanctuary and the host to be trampled?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.14'>And he said to me, For two thousand, three hundred evenings and mornings. Then the sanctuary shall be vindicated.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.15'>And it happened when I, even I Daniel, had seen the vision, and sought for the meaning, then, behold, there stood before me the form of a man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.16'>And I heard a man's voice between [the banks of] Ulai, which called and said, Gabriel, make this one understand the vision.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.17'>So he came near beside my place. And when he came, I was afraid and fell on my face. But he said to me, Understand, O son of man, for the vision [is] for the time of the end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.18'>And as he was speaking with me, I was stunned, on my face toward the ground. But he touched me and set me upright.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.19'>And he said, Behold, I will make you know what shall happen in the last end of the indignation. For [it is] for the time appointed for the end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.20'>The ram which you saw having two horns [are] the kings of Media and Persia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.21'>And the shaggy goat [is] the king of Greece. And the great horn between his eyes is the first king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.22'>And as for that being broken, and four stood up in its place; four kingdoms shall stand up out of the nation, but not in its power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.23'>And in the latter time of their kingdom, when the transgressors have come to the full, a king, fierce of face, and skilled at intrigues, shall stand up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.24'>And his power shall be mighty, but not by his own power. And he shall destroy marvelously, and shall prosper and work, and destroy the mighty and the holy people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.25'>And also through his understanding, he shall cause deceit to succeed in his hand. And he shall magnify himself in his heart, and by peace shall destroy many. He also shall stand up against the Ruler of rulers. But he shall be broken without a hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.26'>And the vision of the evening and the morning which was told [is] true. But you shall shut up the vision; for it [shall be] for many days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.8.27'>And I Daniel fainted, and was sick [for] days. Afterward I rose up, and did the king's business. And I was amazed at the vision, but there was no understanding.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.9'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.1'>In the first year of Darius the son of Ahasuerus, of the seed of the Medes, who was made king over the realm of the Chaldeans,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.2'>in the first year of his reign, I, Daniel, understood the number of the years by books, which came of the Word of the LORD to Jeremiah the prophet, that he would accomplish seventy years in the desolations of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.3'>And I set my face toward the Lord God, to seek by prayer and holy desires, with fasting, and sackcloth, and ashes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.4'>And I prayed to the LORD my God, and made my confession, and said, O Lord, the great and awesome God, keeping the covenant and mercy to those who love Him, and to those who keep His commandments,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.5'>we have sinned and have committed iniquity, and have done wickedly, and have rebelled, even by departing from Your commandments and from Your judgments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.6'>Neither have we listened to Your servants the prophets, who spoke in Your name to our kings, our rulers, and our fathers, and to all the people of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.7'>O Lord, righteousness [belongs] to You, but to us the shame of [our] faces, as [it is] today to the men of Judah and to the people of Jerusalem, and to all Israel who are near and who are afar off, through all the countries where You have driven them because of their sin which they have sinned against You.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.8'>O Lord, shame of face [belongs] to us, to our kings, to our rulers, and to our fathers, because we have sinned against You.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.9'>To the Lord our God [belong] mercies and forgivenesses, though we have rebelled against Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.10'>We have not obeyed the voice of the LORD our God, to walk in His laws which He set before us by His servants the prophets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.11'>Yea, all Israel has transgressed Your law, and turned aside, that they might not obey Your voice. Therefore the curse has been poured out on us, and the oath that is written in the law of Moses the servant of God, because we have sinned against Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.12'>And He has confirmed His words which He spoke against us and against our judges who judged us, by bringing on us a great evil. For under all the heavens [it] has not been done as [it] has been done to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.13'>As [it is] written in the law of Moses, all this evil has come on us. Yet we did not make our prayer before the LORD our God, that we might turn from our iniquities, and understand Your truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.14'>Therefore the LORD has watched over the evil, and has brought it on us. For the LORD our God [is] righteous in all His works which He does; for we did not obey His voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.15'>And now, O Lord our God, who have brought Your people out from the land of Egypt with a mighty hand, and have brought fame to Yourself, as it is today, we have sinned, we have done wrong.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.16'>O Lord, I pray You, according to all Your righteousness let Your anger and Your fury be turned away from Your city Jerusalem, Your holy mountain. Because for our sins, and for the iniquities of our fathers, Jerusalem and Your people [have become] a curse to all those who are around us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.17'>And now, O our God, hear the prayer of Your servant, and his holy desires, and cause Your face to shine on Your sanctuary that [is] desolate, for the Lord's sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.18'>O my God, bow down Your ear and hear. Open Your eyes and behold our ruins, and the city which is called by Your name. For we do not present our prayers before You on account of our righteousnesses, but because of Your great mercies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.19'>O LORD, hear; O LORD, forgive; O LORD, listen and do. Do not delay, for Your own sake, O my God; for Your city and Your people are called by Your name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.20'>And while I was speaking, and praying, and confessing my sin, and the sin of my people Israel, and presenting my cry before the LORD my God for the holy mountain of my God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.21'>yes, while I was speaking in prayer, even the man Gabriel, whom I had seen in the vision at the beginning, touched me in [my] severe exhaustion, about the time of the evening sacrifice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.22'>And he enlightened me, and talked with me, and said, O Daniel, I have now come out to give you skill and understanding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.23'>At the beginning of your prayers the commandment came out, and I have come to explain. For you are greatly beloved; therefore understand the matter, and attend to the vision:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.24'>Seventy weeks are decreed as to your people and as to your holy city, to finish the transgression and to make an end of sins, and to make atonement for iniquity, and to bring in everlasting righteousness, and to seal up the vision and prophecy, and to anoint the Most Holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.25'>Know therefore and understand, [that] from the going out of the command to restore and to build Jerusalem, to Messiah [the] Prince, shall be seven weeks, and sixty-two weeks. The street shall be built again, and the wall, even in times of affliction.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.26'>And after sixty-two weeks Messiah shall be cut off, but not [for] Himself. And the people of the ruler who shall come shall destroy the city and the sanctuary. And the end of it [shall be with the flood, and ruins are determined, until [the] end [shall be] war.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.9.27'>And he shall confirm a covenant with many [for] one week. And in the midst of the week he shall cause the sacrifice and the offering to cease, and on a corner [of the altar] desolating abominations, even until [the] end. And that which was decreed shall be poured on the desolator.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.10'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.1'>In the third year of Cyrus king of Persia a thing was revealed to Daniel, whose name was called Belteshazzar. And the thing was true, and a great conflict. And he understood the thing, and had understanding of the vision.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.2'>In those days I, Daniel, was mourning three full weeks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.3'>I ate no food for delight, neither came flesh nor wine in my mouth, nor did I anoint myself at all, until three whole weeks were fulfilled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.4'>And in the twenty-fourth day of the first month, as I was by the side of the great river, which [is] Tigris,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.5'>then I lifted up my eyes and looked, and behold, a certain man was clothed in linen, whose loins were girded with fine gold of Uphaz.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.6'>His body also [was] like the beryl, and his face looked like lightning. And his eyes [were] like lamps of fire, and his arms and his feet in color were like polished bronze, and the voice of his words like the sound of a multitude.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.7'>And I, Daniel, alone saw the vision. For the men who were with me did not see the vision; but a great quaking fell on them, so that they fled to hide themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.8'>Therefore I was left alone, and saw this great vision, and there remained no strength in me. For my beauty was turned within me to corruption, and I kept no strength.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.9'>Yet I heard the voice of his words. And when I heard the voice of his words, then I was in a deep sleep on my face, and my face [was] toward the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.10'>And behold, a hand touched me, which set me shaking on my knees and the palms of my hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.11'>And he said to me, O Daniel, a man greatly beloved, understand the words that I speak to you, and stand upright. For to you I am now sent. And when he had spoken this word to me, I stood trembling.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.12'>Then he said to me, Do not fear, Daniel; for from the first day that you set your heart to understand and to chasten yourself before your God, your words were heard. And I have come for your words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.13'>But the ruler of the kingdom of Persia withstood me twenty-one days. But lo, Michael, one of the chief rulers, came to help me; and I remained there with the kings of Persia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.14'>Now I have come to make you understand what shall happen to your people in the latter days. For the vision is yet for [many] days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.15'>And when he had spoken such words to me, I bowed my face toward the ground, and I became dumb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.16'>And behold, one looking like the sons of men touched my lips. Then I opened my mouth and spoke and said to him who stood before me, O lord, my sorrows are turned on me by the vision, and I have kept no strength.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.17'>For how can the servant of my lord talk with my lord? For as for me, immediately there remained no strength in me, nor is there breath left in me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.18'>Then again [one] like a man in form came and touched me, and he made me stronger</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.19'>and said, O man greatly beloved, do not fear. Peace to you; be strong; yes, be strong. And when he had spoken to me, I was made stronger, and [I] said, Speak my lord, for you have made me stronger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.20'>Then he said, Do you know why I come to you? And now I will return to fight with the ruler of Persia. And when I have gone out, lo, the ruler of Greece shall come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.10.21'>But I will show you that which is written in the Scripture of Truth. And there is none who holds strongly with me in these things, but Michael your ruler.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.11'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.1'>And I, in the first year of Darius the Mede, I was standing for a supporter and for a fortress for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.2'>And now I will declare to you the truth. Behold, there shall stand up yet three kings in Persia. And the fourth shall be far richer than all of them. And by his strength, through his riches, he shall stir up all against the kingdom of Greece.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.3'>And a mighty king shall stand up, one who shall rule with great power and do according to his will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.4'>And when he shall stand up, his kingdom shall be broken and shall be divided toward the four winds of the heavens. And it shall not be given to his sons, nor according to his power with which he ruled; for his kingdom shall be pulled up, even for others besides these.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.5'>And the king of the south shall be strong. And [one] of his rulers, even he shall overcome him and have power. His kingdom [shall be] a great kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.6'>And in the end of years they shall join together; for the king's daughter of the south shall come to the king of the north to make a treaty. But she shall not keep the power of the arm. Nor shall he stand, nor his arm. But she [shall be given up, and those who brought her in, and her begetter, and he who made her strong in [these] times.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.7'>But out of a branch of her roots, one shall stand up [in] his place, who shall come with an army and shall enter into the fortress of the king of the north. And he shall act against them, and show himself strong.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.8'>And he shall also carry their gods captives with their molten images into Egypt, and with their precious vessels of silver and of gold. And he shall stand [for] years away from the king of the north.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.9'>So the king of the south shall come into [his] kingdom, and shall return into his own land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.10'>But his sons shall be stirred up and shall gather a multitude of great forces. And [one] shall certainly come and overflow, and pass through. Then he shall return and be stirred up, even to his fortress.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.11'>And the king of the south shall be bitter, and shall come out and fight with him, even with the king of the north. And he shall send out a great multitude; but the multitude shall be given into his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.12'>And when he has taken away the multitude, his heart shall be lifted up. And he shall cast down many ten thousands, but he shall not be made stronger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.13'>For the king of the north shall return, and shall send out a multitude greater than the former, and at the end of times, years, shall come with a great army and with much equipment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.14'>And in those times there shall stand up many against the king of the south. Also the robbers of your people shall rise up to establish [the] vision, but they shall fall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.15'>So the king of the north shall come, and cast up a siege mound, and take a fortified city. And the arms of the south shall not hold out, nor his chosen people, nor [will be] any strength to hold out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.16'>But he who comes against him shall do according to his own will, and none shall stand before him. And he shall stand in the glorious land, which [shall be] destroyed by his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.17'>He also shall set his face to enter with the strength of all his kingdom, and upright ones with him. So he shall do. And [he] shall give the daughter of women to him, to destroy it; but she shall not stand, nor be for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.18'>And he shall turn his face to the coastlands, and shall capture many. But a ruler shall make cease his reproach for him, but his reproach will return to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.19'>And he shall turn his face to the fortresses of his land. But he shall stumble and fall, and shall not be found.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.20'>And one who sends an exacter shall stand in his place, [for] the glory of [the] kingdom. But within few days he shall be broken, not in anger nor in battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.21'>And a despised one shall stand up in his place, and they shall not give to him the honor of the king; but he will enter while at ease and seize [the] kingdom by intrigues.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.22'>And the forces of the overflow will be swept from before him, and they will be broken, and also the ruler of a covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.23'>And after they join him, he will practice deceit. For he will come and be strong with a few people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.24'>He shall enter safely, even into the rich places of [the] province. And he shall do what his fathers have not done, nor his fathers' fathers. He shall plunder, and spoil, and scatter goods among them. And he shall devise his plots against the strongholds, even for a time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.25'>And he shall stir up his power and his heart against the king of the south with a great army. And the king of the south shall be stirred up to battle with a very great and mighty army, but he shall not stand. For they shall devise plots against him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.26'>Yea, those who eat his food shall break him, and his army shall overflow. And many shall fall down slain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.27'>And both these kings' hearts shall be to do evil, and they shall speak lies at one table. But it shall not succeed. For still [the] end [comes] at the time appointed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.28'>And he shall return to his land with great riches. And his heart [shall be] against [the] holy covenant. And he will act, and he shall return to his land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.29'>At the time appointed he shall return and come against the south. But it shall not be as the former or as the latter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.30'>For the ships of Kittim shall come against him. And he shall be grieved and return, and have fury against the holy covenant. So he shall do; he shall even return and give heed to those who forsake the holy covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.31'>And forces will stand from him, and they will profane the sanctuary, the fortress, and shall remove the daily [sacrifice], and they shall place the desolating abomination.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.32'>And he will ruin by flattery those who do evil against [the] covenant. But the people who know their God will be strong and will work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.33'>And those who understand among [the] people shall teach many; yet they shall fall by the sword, and by flame, by exile, and spoil, for days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.34'>And when they stumble, they shall be helped with a little help, but many will join them, with hypocrisy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.35'>And [many] of those who understand shall stumble, to refine and purge them, and [to] make white, to the time of [the] end. Because [it is] still for the appointed time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.36'>And the king shall do according to his will. And he shall exalt and magnify himself above every god, and shall speak marvelous things against the God of gods, and shall prosper until the fury is fulfilled. For that which is decreed shall be done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.37'>He will not regard the God of his fathers, nor the desire of women, nor regard any god. For he shall magnify himself above all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.38'>But in his place he shall honor the god of forces; and a god whom his fathers did not know, he shall honor with gold and silver, and with precious stones and desirable things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.39'>So he shall act in the fortresses of [the] strongholds with a strange god, whom he shall acknowledge. He shall multiply in glory, and he shall cause them to rule over many, and shall divide the land for a price.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.40'>And at the end-time, the king of the south shall butt at him. And the king of the north shall come against him like a tempest, with chariots and with horsemen and with many ships.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.41'>And he shall enter into the countries and shall overflow and pass over. He shall also enter into the glorious land, and many shall be stumbled. But these shall escape out of his hand: Edom and Moab, and the chief of the sons of Ammon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.42'>And he shall stretch out his hand on the lands. And the land of Egypt shall not escape.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.43'>But he shall have power over the treasures of gold and silver, and over all the precious things of Egypt. And the Libyans and the Ethiopians [shall be] at his steps.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.44'>But news out of the east and out of the north shall trouble him. Then he will go out with great fury to destroy, and to devote many to destruction.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.11.45'>And he shall plant his palace tents between [the] seas in the glorious holy mountain. Yet he shall come to his end, and none shall help him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Dan.12'>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.1'>And at that time Michael shall stand up, the great ruler who stands for the sons of your people. And there shall be a time of trouble, such as never was since there was a nation; until that time. And at that time your people shall be delivered, every one that shall be found written in the book.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.2'>And many of those who sleep in the dust of the earth shall awake, some to everlasting life, and some to shame [and] everlasting contempt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.3'>And those who are wise shall shine as the brightness of the sky; and those who turn many to righteousness shall shine as the stars forever and ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.4'>But you, O Daniel, shut up the words and seal the book, even to the time of the end. Many shall run to and fro, and knowledge shall be increased.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.5'>Then I Daniel looked, and behold, there stood another two, the one on this [side], and the one on that [side] of the bank of the river.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.6'>And [one] said to the man clothed in linen on the waters of the river: Until when [shall be] the end of these wonders?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.7'>And I heard the man clothed in linen, who [was] on the waters of the river, when he held up his right and his left [hand] to Heaven, and swore by Him who lives forever that it [shall be] for a time, times, and a half. And when they have made an end of scattering the power of the holy people, all these things shall be finished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.8'>And I heard, but I did not understand. Then I said, O my lord, what [shall be] the end of these things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.9'>And He said, Go, Daniel! For the words [are] closed up and sealed until the end-time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.10'>Many shall be purified, and made white, and tried. But the wicked shall do wickedly. And none of the wicked shall understand, but the wise shall understand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.11'>And from the time that the daily [sacrifice] shall be taken away, and the desolating abomination set up, a thousand two hundred and ninety days [shall occur].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.12'>Blessed [is] he who waits and comes to the thousand three hundred and thirty-five days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Dan.12.13'>But you go on to the end, for you shall rest and stand in your lot at the end of the days.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>