<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='mkjv1962' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='mkjv1962'>
        <title>Modern KJV 1963</title>
        <contributor>xxx</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy</subject>
        <date>2009-01-23</date>
        <description>Modern King James Version of the Holy Bible 1962</description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>mkjv1962</identifier>
        <source/>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Deut'>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.1'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.1'>These [are] the words which Moses spoke to all Israel beyond Jordan in the wilderness, in the plain opposite the Red Sea, between Paran and Tophel and Laban and Hazeroth and Dizahab,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.2'>eleven days from Horeb by way of Mount Seir to Kadesh-barnea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.3'>And it happened, in the fortieth year, in the eleventh month, on the first of the month, Moses spoke to the sons of Israel according to all that Jehovah had commanded him concerning them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.4'>after he had smitten Sihon the king of the Amorites, who lived in Heshbon, and Og the king of Bashan, who lived in Ashtaroth in Edrei,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.5'>beyond the Jordan, in the land of Moab, Moses began to explain this law, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.6'>Jehovah our God spoke to us in Horeb, saying, You have had enough of dwelling in this mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.7'>Turn and pull up [stakes], and enter the hill-country of the Amorites, and to all [its] neighboring places, in the Arabah in the hill-country, and in the low country, and in the south, and in the shore of the sea, the land of the Canaanites and of Lebanon, to the great river, the river Euphrates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.8'>Behold, I have set before you the land; go in and possess the land which the LORD has sworn to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give to them and to their seed after them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.9'>And I spoke to you at that time, saying, I am not able to bear you by myself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.10'>Jehovah your God has multiplied you, and, behold, today you [are] as the stars of heaven for multitude.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.11'>May the LORD, the God of your fathers, make you a thousand times more than you [are], and bless you as He has said to you!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.12'>How can I by myself bear your pressure and your burden and your strife?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.13'>Give wise and understanding men, and [those] known to your tribes, and I will appoint them rulers over you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.14'>And you answered me and said, The thing which you have spoken [is] good to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.15'>And I took the chiefs of your tribes, wise and noted men, and made them heads over you, captains over thousands, and captains over hundreds, and captains over fifties, and captains over tens, and officers among your tribes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.16'>And I commanded your judges at that time saying, Hear [the causes] between your brothers, and judge righteously between a man and his brother, and the stranger with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.17'>You shall not respect persons in judgment. You shall hear the small as well as the great. You shall not be afraid of the face of man, for the judgment [is] God's. And the cause that is too hard for you, bring to me, and I will hear it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.18'>And I commanded you at that time all the things which you should do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.19'>And when we pulled up from Horeb, we went [through] all that great and terrible wilderness which you saw by the way of the mountain of the Amorites, as the LORD our God commanded us. And we came to Kadesh-barnea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.20'>And I said to you, You have come to the mountain of the Amorites, which the LORD our God has given unto us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.21'>Behold, the LORD your God has set the land before you. Go up. Possess [it], even as the LORD God of your fathers has said to you. Do not fear, neither be troubled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.22'>And you came near to me, every one of you, and said, We will send men before us, and they shall search out the land and bring us word again by what way we must go up, and into what cities we shall come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.23'>And the saying pleased me very much. And I took twelve men of you, one of a tribe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.24'>And they turned and went up into the mountain and came to the valley of Eshcol, and searched it out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.25'>And they took of the fruit of the land in their hands, and brought [it] down to us, and brought us word again and said, It is a good land which the LORD our God gives us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.26'>But you would not go up, but rebelled against the command of the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.27'>And you murmured in your tents and said, Because the LORD hates us, He has brought us forth out of the land of Egypt to deliver us into the hand of the Amorites, to destroy us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.28'>Where [shall] we go up? Our brothers have broken our heart, saying, We have seen there a people greater and taller than we [are]. The cities are great and walled up to the heavens, also the sons of the giants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.29'>Then I said to you, Do not dread them nor be afraid of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.30'>The LORD your God who goes before you shall fight for you, according to all that He did for you in Egypt before your eyes,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.31'>and in the wilderness where you have seen how the LORD your God carried you, as a man carries his son, in all the way that you went until you came into this place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.32'>Yet in this thing you did not believe the LORD your God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.33'>who went in the way before you to search you out a place to pitch your tents, in fire by night, to show you by what way you should go, and in a cloud by day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.34'>And the LORD heard the voice of your words, and was angry and swore, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.35'>Surely there shall not one of these men of this evil generation see that good land, which I swore to give to your fathers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.36'>except Caleb the son of Jephunneh; he shall see it, and to him I will give the land that he has trodden upon, and to his sons, because he has fully followed the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.37'>Also the LORD was angry with me for your sakes, saying, You also shall not go in there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.38'>Joshua the son of Nun, who stands before you, he shall go in there. Make him strong, for he shall cause Israel to inherit it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.39'>And your little ones, who you said would be a prey, and your sons who in that day had no knowledge between good and evil, they shall go in there. And I will give it to them, and they shall possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.40'>But you turn and pull up into the wilderness by the way of the Red Sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.41'>And you answered and said to me, We have sinned against the LORD; we will go up and fight according to all that the LORD our God commanded us. And when each one of you had buckled on his weapons of war, you were ready to go up into the hill.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.42'>But the LORD said to me, Say to them, Do not go up, nor fight, for I [am] not among you, you will be beaten by your enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.43'>So I spoke to you. And you would not hear, but rebelled against the command of the LORD, and went presumptuously into the hill.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.44'>And the Amorites who lived in that mountain came out against you and chased you, even as bees do, and destroyed you in Seir, to Hormah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.45'>And you returned and wept before the LORD. But the LORD would not listen to your voice, nor give ear to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.46'>So you stayed in Kadesh many days, according to the days that you remained.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.2'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.1'>Then we turned and took our journey into the wilderness by the way of the Red Sea, as the LORD spoke to me. And we went around Mount Seir many days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.2'>And the LORD spoke to me, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.3'>You have gone around this mountain long enough. Turn northward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.4'>And command the people saying, You [are] to pass through the border of your brothers, the sons of Esau, who dwell in Seir. And they shall be afraid of you. Therefore be careful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.5'>Do not meddle with them, for I will not give you of their land, no, not so much as a foot breadth, because I have given Mount Seir to Esau [for] a possession.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.6'>You shall buy food from them for silver, so that you may eat. And you shall also buy water from them for silver, so that you may drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.7'>For the LORD your God has blessed you in all the works of your hand. He knows your walking [through] this great wilderness. The LORD your God [has been] with you these forty years. You have lacked nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.8'>And when we left our brothers the sons of Esau who lived in Seir, through the way of the Arabah from Elath, and from Ezion-geber, we turned and passed by the way of the wilderness of Moab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.9'>And the LORD said to me, Do not besiege Moab, nor fight with them in battle. For I will not give you any of their land [for] a possession. Because I have given Ar to the sons of Lot [for] a possession.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.10'>The Emim lived there in times past, a great people, who were many and tall like the Anakim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.11'>And they were known as giants, like the sons of Anak, but the Moabites called them Emim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.12'>The Horim also lived in Seir in times past. But the sons of Esau took their place when they had destroyed them from before them, and lived in their place; as Israel did to the land of his possession, which the LORD gave to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.13'>Now rise up and cross over the brook Zered. And we went over the brook Zered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.14'>And the days in which we came from Kadesh-barnea, until we had come over the brook Zered [were] thirty-eight years; until the end of all the generation. The men of war [were] destroyed from the midst of the camp, as the LORD swore to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.15'>And the hand of the LORD was against them, to destroy them from among the camp, until they were consumed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.16'>And it happened, when all the men of war had finished dying from among the people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.17'>the LORD spoke to me, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.18'>today you are] passing over the border of Moab, even] Ar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.19'>And when you come near, across from the sons of Ammon, do not trouble them nor be stirred up against them. For I will not give you [any] possessions from the land of the sons of Ammon, because I have given it to the sons of Lot [for a possession.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.20'>It also was known to be a land of giants. Giants lived there in past times. And the Ammonites call them Zamzumim,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.21'>a great and plentiful people, and tall, like the sons of Anak, but the LORD destroyed them before them. And they expelled them and lived in their place,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.22'>as He did to the sons of Esau who lived in Seir, when he destroyed the Horim from before them. And they expelled them and lived in their place even to this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.23'>And the Avvim who lived in villages as far as Azzah, the Caphtorites, who came forth out of Caphtor destroyed them, and lived in their place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.24'>Rise up, set out and cross over the river Arnon. Behold! I have given into your hand Sihon the Amorite, king of Heshbon, and his land. Begin to possess, and fight with him in battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.25'>Today, I will begin to put your dread and your fear upon the nations under the whole heavens; who shall hear report of you, and shall tremble and be in anguish because of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.26'>And I sent messengers out of the wilderness of Kedemoth to Sihon king of Heshbon [with] words of peace, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.27'>Let me pass through your land. I will go along by the highway. I will neither turn [to] the right hand nor to the left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.28'>You shall sell me food for silver, so that I may eat, and give me water for silver so that I may drink. Only I will pass through on my feet,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.29'>as the sons of Esau who live in Seir, and the Moabites who live in Ar, did to me, until I shall cross over Jordan into the land which the LORD our God gives us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.30'>But Sihon king of Heshbon would not let us pass by him. For the LORD your God hardened his spirit and made his heart stubborn so that He might deliver him into your hand, as [it is] this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.31'>And the LORD said to me, Behold, I have begun to give Sihon and his land before you. Begin to possess it so that you may inherit his land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.32'>Then Sihon came out against us, he and all his people, to fight at Jahaz.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.33'>And the LORD our God delivered him before us. And we struck him and his sons and all his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.34'>And we took all his cities at that time and completely destroyed the men and the women and the little ones of every city. We left none to remain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.35'>Only we plundered the cattle for ourselves, and we took the spoil of the cities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.36'>From Aroer, by the brink of the river of Arnon, and the city by the river, even unto Gilead, there was not one city too strong for us. The LORD our God delivered all to us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.37'>Only to the land of the sons of Ammon you did not come, to any place of the river Jabbok, nor to the cities in the mountains, nor to whatever the LORD our God denied us.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.3'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.1'>And we turned and went up the way to Bashan. And Og the king of Bashan came out against us, he and all his people, to battle [at] Edrei.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.2'>And the LORD said to me, Do not fear him, for I will deliver him and all his people, and his land, into your hand. And you shall do to him as you did to Sihon king of the Amorites, who lived at Heshbon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.3'>So the LORD our God delivered Og into our hands also, the king of Bashan, and all his people. And we struck him until none [was] left remaining to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.4'>And we took all his cities at that time. There was not a city which we did not take from them, sixty cities, all the region of Argob, the kingdom of Og in Bashan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.5'>All these cities [were] fortified with high walls, gates, and bars; besides a good many unwalled towns.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.6'>And we completely destroyed them, as we did to Sihon king of Heshbon, completely destroying the men, women, and children of every city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.7'>But we took the cattle and the spoil of the cities as a prize for ourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.8'>And we took at that time out of the hand of the two kings of the Amorites the land on this side Jordan, from the river of Arnon to Mount Hermon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.9'>(the Hermon [which] the Sidonians call Sirion, and the Amorites call it Senir).</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.10'>All the cities of the plain, and all Gilead, and all Bashan, and Salecah and Edrei, cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan [were taken].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.11'>For only Og king of Bashan remained of the rest of the giants. Behold! His bedstead [was] a bedstead of iron. Is it not in Rabbath of the sons of Ammon? Nine cubits [was] its length, and four cubits its width, according to the cubit of a man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.12'>And this is the land [which] we possessed at that time, from Aroer by the river Arnon, and half of Mount Gilead, and its cities, I gave to the men of Reuben and of Gad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.13'>And the rest of Gilead, and all Bashan, the kingdom of Og, I gave to the half tribe of Manasseh, all the region of Argob, with all Bashan, which was called the land of giants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.14'>Jair the son of Manasseh took all the country of Argob, as far as the border of the Geshurites and the Maachathites. And he called them after his own name, Bashan (Towns of Jair) to this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.15'>And I gave Gilead to Machir.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.16'>And to the Reubenites and to the Gadites I gave from Gilead even to the river Arnon, half the valley, and the border even to the river Jabbok, the border of the sons of Ammon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.17'>the plain also, and Jordan, and its border, from Chinnereth even to the sea of the plain, the Salt Sea, under The Slopes of Pisgah eastward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.18'>And I commanded you at that time saying, The LORD your God has given you this land to possess it. You shall pass over armed before your brothers the sons of Israel, all the sons of might.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.19'>But your wives and your little ones, and your cattle, (I know that you have much cattle), shall stay in your cities which I have given you</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.20'>until the LORD has given rest to your brothers, as well as to you, and they also possess the land which the LORD your God [has] given them beyond Jordan. And then you shall each one return to his possessions which I have given you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.21'>And I commanded Joshua at that time saying, Your eyes have seen all that the LORD your God has done to these two kings. So the LORD shall do to all the kingdoms where you pass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.22'>You shall not fear them. For the LORD your God shall fight for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.23'>And I begged the LORD at that time saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.24'>O, LORD God, You have begun to show Your servant Your greatness, and Your mighty hand. For what God [is there] in heaven or in earth who can do according to Your works, and according to Your might?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.25'>I pray you, let me go over and see the good land beyond Jordan, this good hill-country and Lebanon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.26'>But the LORD was angry with me because of you and would not hear me. And the LORD said to me, [Let it be] enough for you. Speak no more to Me of this matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.27'>Go up into the top of Pisgah and lift up your eyes westward and northward and southward and eastward, and behold [it] with your eyes. For you shall not go over this Jordan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.28'>But charge Joshua, and encourage him, and strengthen him. For he shall go over before this people, and he shall cause them to inherit the land which you shall see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.29'>So we stayed in the valley over against Beth-peor.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.4'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.1'>And now, Israel, listen to the statutes and to the judgments which I teach you, in order to do them, so that you may live and go in and possess the land which the LORD God of your fathers gives you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.2'>You shall not add to the word which I command you, neither shall you take away from it, so that you may keep the commands of the LORD your God which I command you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.3'>Your eyes have seen what the LORD did because of Baal-peor. For the LORD your God has destroyed from among you all the men that followed Baal-peor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.4'>And you who held fast to the LORD your God [are] alive, every one of you, this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.5'>Behold, I have taught you statutes and judgments, even as the LORD my God commanded me, so that you should do so in the land where you go to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.6'>And you shall keep and do [them], for this is your wisdom and your understanding in the sight of the nations, which shall hear all these statutes and say, Surely this great nation [is] a wise and understanding people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.7'>For who is a great nation whose God [is] coming near to them, as Jehovah our God [is], in all our calling on him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.8'>And who is a great nation whose statutes and judgments [are so] righteous as all this law which I set before you today?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.9'>Only take heed to yourself and keep your soul carefully, lest you forget the things which your eyes have seen, and lest they depart from your heart all the days of your life. But teach them to your sons, and your sons' sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.10'>Remember the day that you stood before the LORD your God in Horeb, when the LORD said to me, Gather the people to Me, and I will make them hear My words so that they may learn to fear Me all the days that they shall live upon the earth, and they may teach their sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.11'>And you came near and stood under the mountain. And the mountain burned with fire to the midst of heaven, with darkness, clouds, and thick darkness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.12'>And the LORD spoke to you out of the midst of the fire. You heard the voice of the words, but saw no likeness, only a voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.13'>And He declared to you His covenant which He commanded you to perform, ten commandments. And He wrote them on two tablets of stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.14'>And the LORD commanded me at that time to teach you statutes and judgments so that you might do them in the land where you go over to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.15'>Therefore take good heed to yourselves, for you saw no kind of likeness on the day the LORD spoke to you in Horeb out of the midst of the fire,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.16'>lest you act corruptly and make yourselves a graven image, the likeness of any figure, the likeness of male or female,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.17'>the likeness of any beast on the earth, the likeness of any winged fowl that flies in the air,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.18'>the likeness of anything that creeps on the ground, the likeness of any fish in the waters beneath the earth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.19'>and lest you lift up your eyes to the heavens, and when you see the sun, and the moon, and the stars, all the host of heaven, lest you should be driven to worship them and serve them, which the LORD your God has allotted to all nations under all the heavens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.20'>But the LORD has taken you and brought you out from the iron furnace, out of Egypt, to be to Him a people of inheritance, as [you are] today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.21'>And the LORD was angry with me for your sakes, and swore that I should not go over Jordan, and that I should not go in to that good land which the LORD your God gives you [for] an inheritance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.22'>But I must die in this land; I must not go over Jordan. But you [shall] go over and possess that good land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.23'>Take heed to yourselves, lest you forget the covenant of the LORD your God, which He made with you, and make you a graven image, a likeness of anything which the LORD your God has forbidden you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.24'>For the LORD your God [is] a consuming fire, a jealous God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.25'>When you father sons and sons of sons, and when you shall have remained long in the land and have dealt corruptly by making a graven image, the likeness of anything, and shall do evil in the sight of the LORD your God, to provoke Him to anger,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.26'>I call Heaven and earth to witness against you this day, that you shall soon utterly perish from off the land which you are crossing over Jordan to possess. You shall not prolong [your] days upon it, but shall utterly be destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.27'>And the LORD shall scatter you among the nations, and you shall be left few in number among the nations where the LORD shall drive you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.28'>And there you shall serve gods, the work of men's hands, wood and stone, which neither see nor hear nor eat nor smell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.29'>But if you shall seek the LORD your God from there, you shall find [Him], if you seek Him with all your heart and with all your soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.30'>When you are in trouble and when all these things have found you in the latter days, then you shall return to the LORD your God and shall be obedient to His voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.31'>For the LORD your God [is] a merciful God; He will not forsake you, nor destroy you, nor forget the covenant of your fathers which He swore to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.32'>For ask now of the days past which were before you, since the day that God created man upon the earth, and from the one end of the heavens to the other end of the heavens, where there has been a thing as great as this, or has been heard any like it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.33'>Did people ever hear the voice of God speaking out of the midst of the fire as you have heard and live?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.34'>Or has God gone forth to take a nation for himself from the midst of a nation, by trials, by signs, and by wonders, and by war, and by a mighty hand, and by a stretched out arm, and by great terrors, according to all that the LORD your God did for you in Egypt before your eyes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.35'>It was shown to you so that you might know that Jehovah [is] God, [and] no one else beside Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.36'>He made you hear His voice out of Heaven so that He might teach you. And He showed you His great fire upon earth. And you heard His words out of the midst of the fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.37'>And because He loved your fathers, therefore He chose their seed after them, and brought you out in His sight with His mighty power out of Egypt,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.38'>in order to drive out from before you nations greater and mightier than you, to bring you in, to give you their land for an inheritance, as [it is] this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.39'>Therefore, know this day and consider within your heart, that the LORD [is] God in Heaven above and on the earth beneath. There is no other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.40'>Therefore, you shall keep His statutes and His commandments which I command you this day, so that it may go well with you and with your sons after you, and so that you may make your days longer upon the earth which the LORD your God gives you forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.41'>Then Moses separated three cities on this side Jordan towards the sunrise,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.42'>so that the slayer might flee there, he who should kill his neighbor through error and who did not hate him [in] times past, and he fleeing to one of these cities might live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.43'>They were Bezer in the wilderness, in the plain country, of the Reubenites; and Ramoth in Gilead of the Gadites; and Golan in Bashan, for the Manassites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.44'>And this [is] the law which Moses set before the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.45'>These [are] the testimonies and the statutes and the judgments which Moses spoke to the sons of Israel after they came forth out of Egypt,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.46'>beyond Jordan, in the valley over against Beth-peor, in the land of Sihon king of the Amorites, who lived at Heshbon, whom Moses and the sons of Israel killed, after they had come forth out of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.47'>And they possessed his land, and the land of Og king of Bashan, two kings of the Amorites, who [were] on this side Jordan toward the sunrise,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.48'>from Aroer, on the edge of the river Arnon, even to Mount Zion, which [is] Hermon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.49'>and all the plain on this side Jordan eastward, even to the sea of the plain, under the Slopes of Pisgah.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.5'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.1'>And Moses called all Israel and said to them, Hear, O Israel, the statutes and judgments which I speak in your ears this day, so that you may learn them and keep and do them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.2'>The LORD our God made a covenant with us in Horeb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.3'>The LORD did not make this covenant with our fathers, but with us, even us, all of us here, alive today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.4'>The LORD talked with you face to face in the mountain out of the midst of the fire;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.5'>(I stood between the LORD and you at that time, to show you the Word of the LORD, for you were afraid because of the fire, and did not go up into the mountain,) saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.6'>I [am] the LORD your God who brought you out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.7'>You shall have no other gods besides Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.8'>You shall not make a graven image for you, any likeness [of anything] that is in the heavens above, or in the earth beneath, or in the waters beneath the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.9'>You shall not bow yourself down to them, nor serve them. For I the LORD your God [am] a jealous God, visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the sons to the third and fourth [generation] of those who hate Me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.10'>and doing mercy to thousands of those who love Me and keep My commandments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.11'>You shall not take the name of the LORD your God in vain, for the LORD will not acquit [the one] who takes His name in vain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.12'>Keep the sabbath day to sanctify it, as the LORD your God has commanded you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.13'>Six days you shall labor and do all your work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.14'>But the seventh day [shall be] the sabbath of the LORD your God. [In it] you shall not do any work, you, nor your son, nor your daughter, nor your manservant, nor your maidservant, nor your ox, nor your ass, nor any of your cattle, nor your stranger inside your gates, so that your manservant and your maidservant may rest like yourself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.15'>And remember that you were a slave in the land of Egypt, and the LORD your God brought you out from there with a mighty hand and with a stretched-out arm. Therefore the LORD your God commanded you to keep the sabbath day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.16'>Honor your father and your mother, as the LORD your God has commanded you, so that your days may be made longer, and that it may go well with you in the land which the LORD your God gives you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.17'>You shall not kill.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.18'>And you shall not commit adultery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.19'>And you shall not steal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.20'>And you shall not bear false witness against your neighbor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.21'>And you shall not lust after your neighbor's wife, nor shall you covet your neighbor's house, his field, or his manservant, or his maidservant, his ox, or his ass, or any [thing] that is your neighbor's.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.22'>The LORD spoke these words to all your assembly in the mountain out of the midst of the fire of the cloud and of the thick darkness with a great voice. And He added no more. And He wrote them in two tablets of stone and delivered them to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.23'>And it happened when you heard the voice out of the midst of the darkness, for the mountain burned with fire, you came near me, all the heads of your tribes and your elders,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.24'>and you said, Behold! The LORD our God has revealed His glory and His greatness, and we have heard His voice out of the midst of the fire. We have seen today that God talks with man yet he [still] lives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.25'>Now therefore why should we die? For this great fire will consume us. If we hear the voice of the LORD our God any more, then we shall die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.26'>For who of all flesh has heard the voice of the living God speaking out of the midst of the fire, as we [have], and lived?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.27'>You go near and hear all that the LORD our God shall say. And you speak to us all that the LORD our God shall speak to you, and we will hear and act.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.28'>And the LORD heard the voice of your words when you spoke to me. And the LORD said to me, I have heard the voice of the words of this people, which they have spoken to you. They have well [said] all that they have spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.29'>Oh that there were such a heart in them that they would fear Me and keep all My commandments always, so that it might be well with them and with their sons forever!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.30'>Go say to them, Go into your tents again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.31'>But as for you, you stand here by Me, and I will speak to you all the commandments and the statutes and the judgments which you shall teach them, that they may do [them] in the land which I am giving them, to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.32'>And you shall be careful to do as the LORD your God has commanded you. You shall not turn aside to the right hand or to the left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.33'>You shall walk in all the ways which the LORD your God has commanded you so that you may live and that good [may be] to you, and you may make [your] days longer in the land which you shall possess.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.6'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.1'>And these [are] the commandments, the statutes, and the judgments, which the LORD our God commanded to teach you so that you might do [them] in the land where you go, to possess it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.2'>that you might fear the LORD your God, to keep all His statutes and His commandments which I command you, you, and your son, and your son's son, all the days of your life, and so that your days may be prolonged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.3'>Then hear, O, Israel, and be careful to [do] it, so that it may be well with you, and that you may greatly multiply, as the LORD God of our fathers has promised you, in the land that flows with milk and honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.4'>Hear, O, Israel. The LORD our God [is] one LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.5'>And you shall love the LORD your God with all your heart and with all your soul and with all your might.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.6'>And these words which I command you this day shall be in your heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.7'>And you shall carefully teach them to your sons, and shall talk of them when you sit in your house and when you walk by the way, and when you lie down, and when you rise up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.8'>And you shall bind them for a sign upon your hand, and they shall be as frontlets between your eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.9'>And you shall write them upon the posts of your house, and on your gates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.10'>And it shall be when the LORD your God has brought you into the land which He swore to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give you great and good cities which you did not build,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.11'>and houses full of every good [thing] which you did not fill, and wells which are dug, but which you did not dig, vineyards and olive trees which you did not plant, and you shall eat and be full,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.12'>you shall be on guard lest you forget the LORD who brought you forth out of the land of Egypt, from the house of slaves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.13'>You shall fear the LORD your God and serve Him, and shall swear by His name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.14'>You shall not go after other gods, of the gods of the people all around you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.15'>for the LORD your God [is] a jealous God among you, lest the anger of the LORD your God be kindled against you and destroy you from off the face of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.16'>You shall not tempt the LORD your God as you tempted in Massah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.17'>You shall carefully keep the commandments of the LORD your God, and His testimonies, and His statutes which He has commanded you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.18'>And you shall do the right and good in the sight of the LORD, so that it may be well with you, and so that you may go in and possess the good land which the LORD swore to your fathers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.19'>to cast out all your enemies from before you, as the LORD has spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.20'>When your son asks you in time to come, saying, What are the testimonies, and the statutes and the judgments which the LORD our God has commanded you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.21'>Then you shall say to your son, We were Pharaoh's slaves in Egypt, and the LORD brought us out of Egypt with a mighty hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.22'>And the LORD gave signs and wonders, great and evil signs, upon Egypt, upon Pharaoh and upon all his household, before our eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.23'>And He brought us out from there so that He might bring us in to give us the land which He swore to our fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.24'>And the LORD commanded us to do all these statutes, to fear the LORD our God, for our good always, so that He might preserve us alive, as [it is] today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.25'>And if we are careful to do all this commandment before the LORD our God, as He has commanded us, it shall be our righteousness.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.7'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.1'>When the LORD your God shall bring you into the land where you go to possess it, and has cast out many nations before you, the Hittites, and the Girgashites, and the Amorites, and the Canaanites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites, seven nations greater and mightier than you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.2'>and the LORD your God shall deliver them before you, you shall crush them, completely destroy them. You shall make no covenant with them nor show mercy to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.3'>Nor shall you make marriages with them. You shall not give your daughter to his son, nor shall you take his daughter to your son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.4'>For they will turn away your son from following Me, so that they may serve other gods. So the anger of the LORD will be kindled against you and will destroy you suddenly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.5'>But you shall deal with them in this way: you shall destroy their altars and break down their images, and cut down their groves and burn their graven images with fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.6'>For you [are] a holy people to the LORD your God. The LORD your God has chosen you to be a special people to Himself above all people that are upon the face of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.7'>The LORD did not set His love upon you, nor choose you, because you were more in number than any people, for you [were] the fewest of all people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.8'>But because the LORD loved you, and because He would keep the oath which He had sworn to your fathers, the LORD has brought you out with a mighty hand and redeemed you out of the house of slaves, from the hand of Pharaoh king of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.9'>Therefore, know that the LORD your God, He [is] God, the faithful God who keeps covenant and mercy with them that love Him and keep His commandments, to a thousand generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.10'>And he repays those who hate Him to their face, to destroy them. He will not be slow to repay him who hates Him. He will repay him to his face.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.11'>And you shall keep the commandments and the statutes and the judgments which I command you today, to do them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.12'>And it shall be, because you listen to these judgments and keep and do them, the LORD your God shall keep to you the covenant and the mercy which He swore to your fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.13'>And He will love you and bless you and multiply you. He will also bless the fruit of your womb, and the fruit of your land, your grain, and your wine, and your oil, the increase of your cattle, and the flocks of your sheep, in the land which He swore to your fathers to give you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.14'>You shall be blessed above all people. There shall not be male or female barren among you or among your cattle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.15'>And the LORD will take away from you all sickness, and will put none of the evil diseases of Egypt which you know upon you. But He will lay them upon all who hate you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.16'>And you shall destroy all the people which the LORD your God shall deliver you. Your eye shall have no pity upon them, neither shall you serve their gods, for [they will be] a snare to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.17'>If you shall say in your heart, These nations [are] more than I; how can I throw them out?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.18'>You shall not be afraid of them, [but] shall well remember what the LORD your God did to Pharaoh and to all Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.19'>[Remember] the great temptations which your eyes saw, and the signs, and the wonders, and the mighty hand, and the stretched-out arm by which the Lord your God brought you out. So shall the LORD your God do to all the people of whom you are afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.20'>And the LORD your God will send the hornet among them, until the ones who are left, and who hide themselves from you, are destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.21'>You shall not be afraid of them, for the LORD your God [is] among you, a mighty and terrible God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.22'>And the LORD your God will put out those nations before you by little and little. You may not destroy them at once, lest the beasts of the field increase upon you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.23'>And the LORD your God shall deliver them to you, and shall destroy them with a mighty ruin until they are destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.24'>And He shall deliver their kings into your hand, and you shall destroy their name from under the heavens. No man shall be able to stand before you until you have destroyed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.25'>You shall burn the graven images of their gods with fire. You shall not desire the silver or gold on them, nor take [it] for yourself, so that you may not be snared in it. For it is an abomination to the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.26'>And you shall not bring an abomination into your house, lest you be a cursed thing like it. You shall utterly hate it, and you shall utterly despise it. For it [is] a cursed thing.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.8'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.1'>All the commandments which I command you this day shall you be careful to do, that you may live and multiply and go in and possess the land which the LORD swore to your fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.2'>And you shall remember all the way which the LORD your God led you these forty years in the wilderness in order to humble you, to prove you, to know what is in your heart, whether you would keep His commandments or not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.3'>And He humbled you and allowed you to hunger, and then He fed you with manna, which you did not know, neither did your fathers know [it], so that He might make you know that man shall not live by bread alone, but by every [word] that comes out of the mouth of the LORD man shall live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.4'>Your clothing did not wear out on you, nor did your foot swell, these forty years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.5'>And you have known with your heart that as a man chastens his son, [so] the LORD your God chastens you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.6'>And you shall keep the commandments of the LORD your God, to walk in His ways and to fear him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.7'>For the LORD your God brings you into a good land, a land of brooks of water, of fountains and depths that spring out of valleys and hills,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.8'>a land of wheat and barley and vines and fig trees and pomegranates, a land of olive oil and honey,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.9'>a land in which you shall eat bread without want. You shall not lack any [thing] in it. [It is] a land whose stones are iron, and out of whose hills you may dig copper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.10'>And you shall eat and be satisfied, then you shall bless the LORD your God for the good land which He has given you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.11'>Beware that you do not forget the LORD your God, in not keeping His commandments, and His judgments, and His statutes, which I command you today,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.12'>lest [when] you have eaten and are full and have built good houses and lived in [them,]</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.13'>and [when] your herds and your flocks multiply, and your silver and your gold is multiplied, and all that you have is multiplied,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.14'>then your heart might be lifted up, and you might forget the LORD your God who brought you forth out of the land of Egypt, from the house of slaves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.15'>He led you through the great and terrible wilderness, [with] fiery serpents and scorpions and thirsty ground, where [there was] no water, who brought you forth water out of the rock of flint,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.16'>who fed you in the wilderness with manna which your fathers did not know, so that He might humble you and so that He might prove you, to do you good in your latter end,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.17'>and so that you might not say in your heart, My power and the might of [my] hand has gotten me this wealth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.18'>But you shall remember the LORD your God, for [it is] He who gives you power to get wealth, so that He may confirm His covenant which He has sworn to your fathers, as it is today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.19'>And it shall be if you do at all forget the LORD your God and walk after other gods and serve them and worship them, I testify against you today that you shall surely perish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.20'>As the nations whom the LORD destroys before your face, so you shall perish because you would not listen to the voice of the LORD your God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.9'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.1'>Hear, O, Israel! You [are] to pass over Jordan today, to go in to expel nations greater and mightier than you, cities great and fenced up to heaven,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.2'>a people great and tall, the sons of the giants, whom you know and have heard it said, Who can stand before the sons of Anak!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.3'>Therefore, understand today that the LORD your God [is] He who goes over before you. [Like] a consuming fire, He shall destroy them, and He shall bring them down before your face. So you shall drive them out and destroy them quickly, as the LORD has said to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.4'>Do not speak in your heart, after the LORD your God has cast them out from before you, saying: For my righteousness, the LORD has brought me in to possess this land. But for the wickedness of these nations, the LORD your God drives them out from before you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.5'>Not for your righteousness, or for the uprightness of your heart, do you go to possess their land. But for the wickedness of these nations the LORD your God drives them out from before you, so that He may perform the word which the LORD swore to your fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.6'>Therefore, understand that the LORD your God does not give you this good land, to possess it, for your righteousness. For you [are] a stiff-necked people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.7'>Remember, [and] do not forget, how you provoked the LORD your God to wrath in the wilderness. From the day you departed out of the land of Egypt, until you came to this place, you have been rebellious against the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.8'>Also in Horeb you provoked the LORD to wrath, so that the LORD was angry with you to have destroyed you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.9'>When I had gone up into the mountain to receive the tablets of stone, the tablets of the covenant which the LORD made with you, then I stayed in the mountain forty days and forty nights. I neither ate bread nor drank water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.10'>And the LORD delivered to me two tablets of stone written with the finger of God, and on them according to all the words which the LORD spoke with you in the mountain out of the midst of the fire in the day of the assembly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.11'>And it happened, at the end of forty days and forty nights the LORD gave me the two tables of stone, the tablets of the covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.12'>And the LORD said to me, Arise! Get down quickly from here, for your people whom you have brought forth out of Egypt have corrupted. They have quickly turned aside out of the way which I commanded them. They have made them a molten image.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.13'>And the LORD spoke to me saying: I have seen this people, and, behold, it [is] a stiff-necked people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.14'>Let Me alone, so that I may destroy them and blot out their name from under the heavens. And I will make of you a nation mightier and greater than they.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.15'>So I turned and came down from the mountain, and the mountain burned with fire. And the two tables of the covenant [were] in my two hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.16'>And I looked, and behold! You had sinned against the LORD your God, and had made you a molten calf. You had turned aside quickly out of the way which the LORD had commanded you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.17'>And I took the two tablets and threw them out of my hands and broke them before your eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.18'>And I fell down before the LORD, as at the first, forty days and forty nights. I neither ate bread nor drank water, because of all your sins which you sinned in doing wickedly in the sight of the LORD to provoke Him to anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.19'>For I was afraid of the anger and fury with which the LORD was angry against you to destroy you. But the LORD listened to me at that time also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.20'>And the LORD was very angry with Aaron to have destroyed him. And I prayed for Aaron also at the same time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.21'>And I took your sin, the calf which you had made, and burned it with fire, and stamped it, grinding [it] very small, until it was as small as dust. And I threw the dust of it into the torrent that descended out of the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.22'>And at Taberah, and at Massah, and at the Graves of Lust, you provoked the LORD to anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.23'>And when the LORD sent you from Kadesh-barnea, saying: Go up and possess the land which I have given you, then you rebelled against the commandment of the LORD your God, and you did not believe Him, nor listened to His voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.24'>You have been rebellious against the LORD from the day that I knew you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.25'>And I fell down before the LORD forty days and forty nights, that I had thrown myself down, for Jehovah had said to destroy you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.26'>I prayed therefore to the LORD and said, O, Lord God, do not destroy Your people and Your inheritance which You have redeemed through Your greatness, which You have brought forth out of Egypt with a mighty hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.27'>Remember Your servants, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. Do not look to the stubbornness of this people, nor to their wickedness, nor to their sin,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.28'>lest the land from where You bring us out say, Because the LORD was not able to bring them into the land which He promised them, and because He hated them, He has brought them out to kill them in the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.29'>Yet they [are] Your people and Your inheritance which You brought out by Your mighty power and by Your stretched-out arm.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.10'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.1'>At that time the LORD said to me: Cut out two tablets of stone like the first, and come up to Me into the mountain, and make an ark of wood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.2'>And I will write on the tablets the words that were in the first tablets which you broke, and you shall put them in the ark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.3'>And I made an ark [of] acacia-wood, and cut out two tablets of stone like the first, and went up into the mountain, having the two tablets in my hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.4'>And He wrote on the tablets, according to the first writing, the Ten Commandments which the LORD spoke to you in the mountain out of the midst of the fire in the day of the assembly. And the LORD gave them to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.5'>And I turned myself and came down from the mountain, and put the tablets in the ark which I had made. And there they are, as the LORD commanded me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.6'>And the sons of Israel pulled up [stakes] from Beeroth of the sons of Jaakan to Mosera. There Aaron died, and there he was buried. And Eleazar his son served in the priest's office in his place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.7'>From there they pulled up to Gudgodah, and from Gudgodah to Jotbath, a land of rivers of water brooks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.8'>At that time the LORD separated the tribe of Levi to carry the ark of the covenant of the LORD, to stand before the LORD to minister to Him, and to bless in His name, until today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.9'>Therefore Levi has no part nor inheritance with his brothers. The LORD [is] his inheritance, according as the LORD your God promised him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.10'>And I stayed in the mountain, according to the first time, forty days and forty nights. And the LORD listened to me at that time also. The LORD would not destroy you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.11'>And the LORD said to me, Arise, Go before the people, causing them to go in and possess the land which I swore to their fathers to give to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.12'>And now, Israel, what does the LORD your God ask of you, but to fear the LORD your God, to walk in all His ways, and to love Him, and to serve the LORD your God with all your heart and with all your soul,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.13'>to keep the commandments of the LORD, and His statutes, which I command you today for your good?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.14'>Behold, the heaven and the heaven of heavens [belong] to the LORD your God, the earth also, with all in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.15'>Only the LORD had a delight in your fathers to love them, and He chose their seed after them, you above all people, as [it is] today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.16'>Therefore, circumcise the foreskin of your heart, and be no longer stiff-necked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.17'>For the LORD your God [is] God of gods, and Lord of lords, a great God, the mighty, and a terrible God, who does not respect persons nor take a bribe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.18'>He executes justice for the fatherless and widow, and loves the stranger in giving him food and clothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.19'>Therefore love the stranger, for you were strangers in the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.20'>You shall fear the LORD your God. You shall serve Him, and you shall hold fast to Him, and swear by His name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.21'>He [is] your praise, and He [is] your God, who has done for you these great and terrible things which your eyes have seen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.22'>Your fathers went down into Egypt with seventy persons. And now the LORD your God has made you as the stars of the heavens for multitude.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.11'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.1'>Therefore you shall love the LORD your God, and keep His charge and His statutes and His judgments and His commandments always.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.2'>And you know today, for [I do] not [speak] with your sons who have not known and who have not seen the chastisement of the LORD your God, His greatness, His mighty hand, and His stretched-out arm,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.3'>and His miracles, and His acts which He did in the midst of Egypt, to Pharaoh the king of Egypt and to all his land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.4'>And [you know] what He did to the army of Egypt, to their horses and to their chariots, how He made the water of the Red Sea to overflow them as they pursued after you, and the LORD has destroyed them to today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.5'>And you [know what] He did to you in the wilderness until you came into this place,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.6'>and what He did to Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab the son of Reuben, how the earth opened its mouth and swallowed them up, and their households, and their tents, and all the substance in their possession, in the midst of all Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.7'>But your eyes have seen all the great acts of the LORD which He did.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.8'>Therefore you shall keep all the commandments which I command you today, so that you may be strong and go in and possess the land where you go to possess it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.9'>and so that you may make [your] days longer in the land which the LORD swore to your fathers to give to them and to their seed, a land that flows with milk and honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.10'>For the land into which you go to possess it, [is] not as the land of Egypt from which you came out, where you sowed your seed and watered [it] with your foot, like a garden of herbs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.11'>But the land which you are entering to possess it [is] a land of hills and valleys, drinking water from the rain of heavens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.12'>It is a land which the LORD your God cares for. The eyes of the LORD your God [are] always upon it, from the beginning of the year even to the end of the year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.13'>And it will be, if you will listen carefully to My commandments which I command you today, to love the LORD your God and to serve Him with all your heart and with all your soul,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.14'>I will give the rain of your land in its due season, the first rain and the latter rain, that you may gather in your grain and your wine and your oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.15'>And I will send grass in your fields for your cattle so that you may eat and be full.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.16'>Take heed to yourselves that your heart may not be deceived, and you turn aside and serve other gods, and worship them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.17'>and the LORD's wrath be kindled against you, and He shut up the heavens so that there will be no rain, and so that the land will not yield her fruit, and you perish quickly from off the good land which the LORD gives you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.18'>Therefore you shall lay up these my words in your hearts and in your souls, and bind them for a sign upon your hand, so that they may be as frontlets between your eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.19'>And you shall teach them to your sons, speaking of them when you sit in your house, and when you walk by the way, when you lie down, and when you rise up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.20'>And [you] shall write them upon the door posts of your house, and upon your gates,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.21'>so that your days and the days of your sons may be multiplied in the land which the LORD swore to give to your fathers, like the days of the heavens upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.22'>For if you will carefully keep all these commandments which I command you, to do them, to love the LORD your God, to walk in all His ways, and to hold fast to Him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.23'>then the LORD will drive out all these nations from before you, and you shall possess greater and mightier nations than you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.24'>Every place on which the soles of your feet shall tread shall be yours, from the wilderness and Lebanon, from the river, the river Euphrates, even to the furthest sea shall your border be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.25'>There shall no man stand before you, [for] the LORD your God shall lay the fear of you and the dread of you upon the face of all the land that you shall tread upon, as He has said to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.26'>Behold, I set before you today a blessing and a curse:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.27'>A blessing if you obey the commandments of the LORD your God which I command you today,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.28'>and a curse if you will not obey the commandments of the LORD your God, but will turn aside out of the way which I command you today, to go after other gods which you have not known.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.29'>And it will be, when the LORD your God has brought you into the land where you go to possess it, you shall set the blessing upon Mount Gerizim, and the curse upon Mount Ebal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.30'>[Are] they not on the other side Jordan, by the way of the sunset, in the land of the Canaanites, who dwell in the plain across from Gilgal beside the plains of Moreh?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.31'>For you shall pass over Jordan to go in to possess the land which the LORD your God gives you, and you shall possess it and dwell in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.32'>And you shall be careful to do all the statutes and judgments which I set before you today.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.12'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.1'>These [are] the statutes and judgments which you shall be careful to do in the land which the LORD God of your fathers gives you to possess it, all the days that you live upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.2'>You shall completely destroy all the places in which the nations which you shall possess served their gods, on the high mountains and on the hills and under every green tree.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.3'>And you shall overthrow their altars and break their pillars, and burn their pillars with fire. And you shall cut down the carved images of their gods, and destroy their names out of that place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.4'>You shall not do so to the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.5'>But you shall seek to the place which the LORD your God shall choose out of all your tribes to put His name there, even to His dwelling place you shall seek, and there you shall come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.6'>And there you shall bring your burnt offerings, and your sacrifices, and your tithes, and heave offering of your hand, and your vows, and your free-will offerings, and the first-born of your herds and of your flocks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.7'>And there you shall eat before the LORD your God, and you shall rejoice in all that you put your hand to, you and your households in which the LORD your God has blessed you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.8'>You shall not do according to all that we do here today, each doing whatever [is] right in his own eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.9'>For you have not as yet come to the rest and to the inheritance which the LORD your God gives you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.10'>But [when] you go over Jordan and live in the land which the LORD your God gives you to inherit, and He gives you rest from all your enemies all around, so that you live in safety,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.11'>then there shall be a place which the LORD your God shall choose to cause His name to dwell there. There you shall bring all that I command you, your burnt offerings, and your sacrifices, your tithes, and the heave offering of your hand, and all your choice vows which you vow to the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.12'>And you shall rejoice before the LORD your God, you, your sons, your daughters, your men-servants, your female-servants, and the Levite that [is] within your gates (because he has no part nor inheritance with you).</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.13'>Take heed to yourself that you do not offer your burnt offerings in every place that you see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.14'>But in the place which the LORD shall choose in one of your tribes, there you shall offer your burnt offerings, and there you shall do all that I command you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.15'>However, with all your soul's desire you shall sacrifice and eat flesh in all your gates, according to the blessing of the LORD your God which He has given you, the clean and the unclean, one may eat, as of the gazelle, and as of the hart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.16'>Only you shall not eat the blood. You shall pour it on the earth like water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.17'>You may not eat inside your gates the tithe of your grain or of your wine or of your oil, or the first-born of your herds or of your flock, or any of your vows which you vow, or your free-will offerings or the heave offering of your hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.18'>But you must eat them before the LORD your God in the place which the LORD your God shall choose, you, and your son, and your daughter, and your manservant, and your maidservant, and the Levite within your gates. And you shall rejoice before the LORD your God in all that you put your hand [to].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.19'>Take heed to yourself that you do not forsake the Levite as long as you live on the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.20'>When the LORD your God shall make your border larger, as He has promised you, and you shall say, I will eat flesh, because your soul longs to eat flesh; you may eat flesh, whatever your soul desires.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.21'>If the place which the LORD your God has chosen to put his name there is too far from you, then you shall kill of your herd and of your flock which the LORD has given you, as I have commanded you, and you shall eat in your gates whatever your soul desires.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.22'>Even as the gazelle and the hart is eaten, so you shall eat them. The unclean and the clean shall eat [of] them alike.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.23'>Only be sure that you do not eat the blood. For the blood [is] the life. And you may not eat the life with the flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.24'>You shall not eat it. You shall pour it on the earth like water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.25'>You shall not eat it, so that it may go well with you and with your sons after you, when you shall do what [is] right in the sight of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.26'>Only your holy things which you have, and your vows, you shall take and go to the place which the LORD shall choose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.27'>And you shall offer your burnt offerings, the flesh and the blood, on the altar of the LORD your God. And the blood of your sacrifices shall be poured out on the altar of the LORD your God, and you shall eat the flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.28'>Be careful to hear all these words which I command you, so that it may go well with you and with your sons after you forever, when you do the good and right in the sight of the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.29'>When the LORD your God shall cut off the nations before you, where you go to possess them, and you take their place and dwell in their land,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.30'>take heed to yourself that you do not become snared by following them, after they are destroyed from before you, and that you do not ask about their gods, saying, How did these nations serve their gods that I too may do likewise?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.31'>You shall not do so to the LORD your God. For every abomination to the LORD, which He hates, they have done to their gods; even their sons and their daughters they have burned in the fire to their gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.32'>All the things I command you, be careful to do it. You shall not add to it, nor take away from it.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.13'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.1'>If a prophet rises among you, or a dreamer of dreams, and gives you a sign or a wonder,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.2'>and the sign or the wonder which he foretold to you occurs, saying, Let us go after other gods which you have not known, and let us serve them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.3'>you shall not listen to the words of that prophet or that dreamer of dreams. For the LORD your God [is] testing you to know whether you love the LORD your God with all your heart and with all your soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.4'>You shall walk after the LORD your God and fear Him, and keep His commandments, and obey His voice, and you shall serve Him and hold fast to Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.5'>And that prophet or that dreamer of dreams shall be put to death, because he has spoken to turn [you] away from the LORD your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt and redeemed you out of the house of slaves, to thrust you out of the way in which the LORD your God commanded you to walk. So you shall put the evil away from the midst of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.6'>If your brother, the son of your mother, or your son, or your daughter, or the wife of your bosom, or your friend who [is] like your own soul, lures you secretly, saying, Let us go and serve other gods which you have not known, you nor your fathers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.7'>that is, of the gods of the people who [are] around you, near you or far off from you, from the one end of the earth even to the other end of the earth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.8'>you shall not consent to him nor listen to him. Nor shall your eye pity him, nor shall you spare, nor shall you hide him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.9'>But you shall surely kill him. Your hand shall be first on him to put him to death, and afterwards the hand of all the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.10'>And you shall stone him with stones so that he dies, because he has sought to drive you away from the LORD your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, from the house of slaves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.11'>And all Israel shall hear, and fear, and shall do no more any such wickedness as this among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.12'>If, in one of your cities which the LORD your God has given you to dwell in, you shall hear [one] saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.13'>Men, the sons of Belial, have gone out from among you and have drawn away those who live in their city, saying, Let us go and serve other gods, which you have not known,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.14'>then you shall inquire and make search, and ask carefully. And behold, [if it is true], and the thing is certain, [that] such an abomination is done among you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.15'>you shall surely strike those who live in that city with the edge of the sword, destroying it completely, and all that [is] in it, and all the cattle of it, with the edge of the sword.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.16'>And you shall gather all its spoil into the middle of its street, and shall burn the city with fire, and all its spoil, every bit of it, for the LORD your God. And it shall be a heap forever. It shall not be built again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.17'>And let nothing of the cursed thing cling to your hand, so that the LORD may turn from the heat of his anger and show you mercy, and give mercies to you, and multiply you as He has sworn to your fathers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.18'>when you listen to the voice of the LORD your God, to keep all His commandments which I command you today, to do the right in the eyes of the LORD your God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.14'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.1'>You [are] the sons of the LORD your God. You shall not cut yourselves nor make [any] baldness between your eyes for the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.2'>For you [are] a holy people to the LORD your God, and the LORD has chosen you to be a peculiar people to Himself, above all the nations that are on the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.3'>You shall not eat any hateful thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.4'>These [are] the animals which you shall eat: the ox, the sheep, and the goat,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.5'>the hart, and the gazelle, and the roe deer, and the wild goat, and the mountain goat, and the wild ox, and the mountain-sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.6'>And every animal that divides the hoof, and divides it into two hooves, [and] chews the cud among the animals, that you shall eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.7'>But these you shall not eat, of those which chew the cud, or of those that divide the cloven hoof: the camel, and the hare, and the rock badger, for they chew the cud, but do not divide the hoof. They [are] unclean to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.8'>And the swine, because it divides the hoof but does not chew the cud; it [is] unclean to you. You shall not eat of their flesh nor touch their dead body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.9'>These you shall eat of all that [are] in the waters: all that have fins and scales you shall eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.10'>And whatever does not have fins and scales you shall not eat. It [is] unclean to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.11'>You shall eat all clean birds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.12'>But you shall not eat of these: the eagle, and the ossifrage, and the osprey,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.13'>and the hawk, and the falcon, and the vulture after its kind,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.14'>and every raven after its kind,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.15'>and the owl, and the night hawk, and the cuckoo, and the hawk after its kind,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.16'>the little owl, and the great owl, and the swan,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.17'>and the pelican, and the owl, and the cormorant,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.18'>and the stork, and the heron after its kind, and the hoopoe, and the bat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.19'>And every creeping thing that flies [is] unclean to you. They shall not be eaten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.20'>You may eat all clean fowls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.21'>You shall not eat anything that dies of itself. You shall give it to the stranger that [is] in your gates, so that he may eat it. Or you may sell [it] to a stranger. For you [are a holy people to the LORD your God. You shall not boil a kid in its mother's milk.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.22'>You shall truly tithe all the increase of your seed that the field brings forth year by year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.23'>And you shall eat before the LORD your God in the place which He shall choose to place His name there, the tithe of your grain, of your wine, and of your oil, and the first-born of your herds and of your flocks, so that you may learn to fear the LORD your God always.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.24'>And if the way is too long for you, so that you are not able to carry it, [or] if the place is too far from you, which the LORD your God shall choose to set His name there, when the LORD your God has blessed you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.25'>then you shall turn [it] into silver and bind up the silver in your hand, and shall go to the place which the LORD your God shall choose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.26'>And you shall pay that silver for whatever your soul desires, for oxen, or for sheep, or for wine, or for strong drink, or for whatever your soul desires. And you shall eat there before the LORD your God, and you shall rejoice, you and your household</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.27'>and the Levite within your gates, you shall not forsake him, for he has no part nor inheritance with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.28'>At the end of three years you shall bring forth all the tithe of your increase the same year, and shall lay [it] up inside your gates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.29'>And the Levite, because he has no part nor inheritance with you, and the stranger, and the fatherless, and the widow, who [are] inside your gates, shall come, and shall eat and be satisfied, so that the LORD your God may bless you in all the work of your hand which you do.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.15'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.1'>At the end of [every] seven years you shall make a release.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.2'>And this [is] the manner of the release. Every man who has a loan to his neighbor shall release it. He shall not exact [it] from his neighbor, or from his brother, because it is called the LORD's release.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.3'>You may exact [it] from a foreigner, but your hand shall release that which is yours with your brother,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.4'>except when there shall be no poor among you. For the LORD shall greatly bless you in the land which the LORD your God gives you [for] an inheritance to possess it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.5'>only if you carefully listen to the voice of the LORD your God to be careful to do all these commandments which I command you today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.6'>For the LORD your God blesses you as He promised you. And you shall lend to many nations, but you shall not borrow. And you shall reign over many nations, but they shall not reign over you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.7'>If there is among you a poor man of one of your brothers inside any of your gates in your land which the LORD your God gives you, you shall not harden your heart nor shut your hand from your poor brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.8'>But you shall open your hand wide to him, and shall surely lend him enough for his need, that which he lacks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.9'>Beware that there is not a thought in your wicked heart, saying, The seventh year, the year of release, is at hand, and your eye may be evil against your poor brother, and you give him nothing. And he may cry to the LORD against you, and it is sin to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.10'>You shall surely give to him, and your heart shall not be grieved when you give to him, because for this thing the LORD your God shall bless you in all your works, and in all that you put your hand to.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.11'>For the poor shall never cease out of the land. Therefore, I command you saying, You shall open your hand wide to your brother, to your poor, and to your needy, in your land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.12'>If your brother, a Hebrew man or a Hebrew woman, is sold to you and serves you six years, then in the seventh year you shall let him go free from you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.13'>And when you send him out free from you, you shall not let him go away empty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.14'>You shall richly bestow on him from your flock, and from your grain floor, and from your winepress; with what the LORD your God has blessed you, you shall give to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.15'>And you shall remember that you were a slave in the land of Egypt, and the LORD your God redeemed you. Therefore I command you this thing today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.16'>And if he says to you, I will not go away from you, because he loves you and your house, because it [has been] good for him with you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.17'>then you shall take an awl and put [it] through his ear to the door, and he shall be your servant forever. And also to your slave-girl you shall do so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.18'>It shall not seem hard to you when you send him away from you free, for he has been worth a double hired servant in serving you six years. And the LORD your God shall bless you in all that you do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.19'>All the first-born males that come from your herd and from your flock, you shall set apart to the LORD your God. You shall do no work with the first-born of your bull, nor shear the first-born of your sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.20'>You shall eat before the LORD your God year by year in the place which the LORD shall choose, you and your household.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.21'>And if there is a blemish in it, lame, or blindness, or any ill blemish, you shall not sacrifice it to the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.22'>You shall eat it inside your gates. The unclean and the clean shall [eat it] alike, as the gazelle, and as the hart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.23'>Only you shall not eat the blood of it. You shall pour it on the ground like water.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.16'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.1'>Observe the month Abib, and keep the Passover to the LORD your God. For in the month of Abib, the LORD your God brought you forth out of Egypt by night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.2'>And you shall therefore sacrifice the Passover to the LORD your God, of the flock and the herd, in the place which the LORD shall choose to place His name there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.3'>You shall eat no leavened [bread] with it. Seven days you shall eat unleavened bread with it, the bread of affliction, for you came forth out of the land of Egypt in haste, so that you may remember the day that you came forth out of the land of Egypt all the days of your life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.4'>And there shall be no leavened [bread] seen with you in all your borders for seven days. Nor shall [any] of the flesh which you sacrificed in the first day at evening remain all night until the morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.5'>You may not sacrifice the Passover within any of your gates, which the LORD your God gives you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.6'>but at the place which the LORD your God shall choose to place His name in, there you shall sacrifice the Passover at evening, at the going of the sun, at the time that you came out of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.7'>And you shall roast and eat in the place which the LORD your God shall choose. And in the morning you shall turn and go to your tents.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.8'>Six days you shall eat unleavened [bread]. And on the seventh day [shall be] a solemn assembly to the LORD your God. You shall do no work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.9'>You shall count seven weeks to yourselves. Begin to count the seven weeks from the time you began [to put] the sickle to the grain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.10'>And you shall keep the Feast of Weeks to the LORD your God with a measure of a free-will offering of your hand, which you shall give according as the LORD your God has blessed you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.11'>And you shall rejoice before the LORD your God, you, and your son, and your daughter, and your male servant, and your slave-girl, and the Levite inside your gates, and the stranger, and the fatherless, and the widow, those among you, in the place which the LORD your God has chosen to place His name there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.12'>And you shall remember that you were a slave in Egypt. And you shall be careful to do these statutes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.13'>You shall keep the Feast of Tabernacles seven days after you have gathered in your grain floor and your wine press.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.14'>And you shall rejoice in your feast, you, and your son, and your daughter, and your male slave, and your slave-girl, and the Levite, the stranger, and the fatherless, and the widow inside your gates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.15'>Seven days you shall keep a solemn feast to the LORD your God in the place which the LORD shall choose. Because the LORD your God shall bless you in all your increase, and in all the works of your hands, therefore you shall surely rejoice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.16'>Three times in a year shall all your males appear before the LORD your God in the place which He shall choose: in the Feast of Unleavened [Bread], and in the Feast of Weeks, and in the Feast of Tabernacles. And they shall not appear before the LORD empty,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.17'>[but] each with his gift in his hand, according to the blessing of the LORD your God, which He has given you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.18'>You shall appoint judges and officers for yourself in all your gates which the LORD your God gives you, tribe by tribe. And they shall judge the people with righteous judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.19'>You shall not pervert judgment; you shall not respect persons, nor take a gift. For a bribe blinds the eyes of the wise and perverts the words of the righteous.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.20'>You shall follow that which is altogether just, that you may live and inherit the land which the LORD your God gives you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.21'>You shall not set up for yourself pillars of any trees near the altar of the LORD your God which you shall make for yourself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.22'>Nor shall you set up an image, which the LORD your God hates.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.17'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.1'>You shall not sacrifice to the LORD your God [any] bull or sheep in which there is a blemish, any evil thing, for that is an abomination to the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.2'>If there is found among you, inside any of your gates which the LORD your God gives you, a man or woman who does what is evil in the sight of the LORD your God, in breaking His covenant,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.3'>and has gone and served other gods and worshiped them, either the sun, or moon, or any [of] the host of heaven, which I have not commanded,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.4'>and if it is told you, and you have heard and inquired carefully, and, behold, it is true and the thing is certain, such abomination is done in Israel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.5'>then you shall bring forth that man or that woman who has committed that evil thing, to your gates, even that man or that woman, and shall stone them with stones until they die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.6'>At the mouth of two witnesses or three witnesses shall he that is worthy of death be put to death. At the mouth of one witness he shall not be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.7'>The hands of the witnesses shall be first on him to put him to death, and afterwards the hands of all the people. So you shall put the evil away from among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.8'>If a matter [is] too hard for you in judgment, between blood and blood, between plea and plea, and between stroke and stroke, matters of strife within your gates, then you shall arise and go up to the place which the LORD your God shall choose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.9'>And [you] shall come to the priests of the Levites, and to the judge that shall be in those days, and ask. And they shall declare to you the sentence of judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.10'>And you shall do according to the sentence which they declare to you from that place which the LORD shall choose. And you shall be careful to do according to all that they tell you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.11'>According to the sentence of the law which they shall teach you and according to the judgment which they shall tell you, you shall do. You shall not turn aside from the sentence which they shall show you, to the right hand or the left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.12'>And the man that acts proudly and will not listen to the priest who stands to minister there before the LORD your God, or to the judge, even that man shall die. And you shall put away the evil from Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.13'>And all the people shall hear and fear, and not be presumptuous any more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.14'>When you come to the land which the LORD your God gives you, and shall possess it and shall live in it and shall say, I will set a king over me, like all the nations around me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.15'>you shall surely set a king over you, whom the LORD your God shall choose. You shall set a king over you from among your brothers. You may not set a stranger over you, who is not your brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.16'>But he shall not multiply horses to himself, nor cause the people to return to Egypt, so as to multiply horses, because the LORD has said to you, You shall return no more that way from now on.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.17'>Nor shall he multiply wives to himself, so that his heart does not turn away. Nor shall he greatly multiply silver and gold to himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.18'>And it shall be, when he sits on the throne of his kingdom, he shall write a copy of this law in a book from before the priests the Levites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.19'>And it shall be with him, and he shall read it all the days of his life, so that he may learn to fear the LORD his God, to keep all the words of this law, and these statutes, to do them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.20'>so that his heart may not be lifted up above his brothers, and that he does not turn aside from the commandment, to the right or the left, so that he may make his days longer in his kingdom, he and his sons, in the midst of Israel.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.18'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.1'>The priests, the Levites, all the tribe of Levi, [shall have] no part nor inheritance with Israel. They shall eat the offerings of the LORD made by fire, and His inheritance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.2'>Therefore they shall have no inheritance among their brothers. The LORD [is ] their inheritance, as He has said to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.3'>And this shall be the priest's due from the people, from those that offer a sacrifice, whether ox or sheep. And they shall give to the priest the shoulder and the two cheeks, and the stomach.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.4'>You shall give him the first-fruit of your grain, of your wine, and of your oil, and the first of the fleece of your sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.5'>For the LORD your God has chosen him out of all your tribes, to stand to minister in the name of the LORD, him and his sons forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.6'>And if a Levite comes from any of your gates out of all Israel, where he lived, and come with all the desire of his mind to the place which the LORD shall choose,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.7'>then he shall minister in the name of the LORD his God, as all his brothers and Levites who stand there before the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.8'>They shall have the same portions to eat, besides that of the sales of [the inheritance from] his father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.9'>When you come to the land which the LORD your God gives you, you shall not learn to do according to the abominations of those nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.10'>There shall not be found among you anyone who makes his son or his daughter to pass through the fire, [or] that uses divination, an observer of clouds, or a fortune-teller, or a witch,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.11'>or a charmer, or a consulter with familiar spirits, or a wizard, or one who calls to the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.12'>For all that do these things [are] an abomination to the LORD. And because of these abominations the LORD your God drives them out from before you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.13'>You shall be perfect with the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.14'>For these nations whom you shall possess listened to observers of clouds and to diviners. But as for you, the LORD your God has not allowed you [to do] so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.15'>The LORD your God will raise up to you a Prophet from the midst of you, of your brothers, One like me. To Him you shall listen,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.16'>according to all that you desired of the LORD your God in Horeb in the day of the assembly, saying: Let me not hear again the voice of the LORD my God, neither let me see this great fire any more, so that I do not die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.17'>And the LORD said to me, They have spoken well what they have spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.18'>I will raise them up a Prophet from among their brothers, [one] like you, and will put My words in His mouth. And He shall speak to them all that I shall command Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.19'>And it shall happen, whatever man will not listen to My words which He shall speak in My name, I will require [it] of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.20'>But the prophet who shall presume to speak a word in My name which I have not commanded him to speak or who shall speak in the name of other gods, even that prophet shall die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.21'>And if you say in your heart, How shall we know the word which the LORD has not spoken?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.22'>When a prophet speaks in the name of the LORD, if the thing does not follow nor come to pass, that [is] the thing which the LORD has not spoken. The prophet has spoken it presumptuously. You shall not be afraid of him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.19'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.1'>When the LORD your God has cut off the nations whose land the LORD your God gives you, and when you take their place and live in their cities and in their houses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.2'>you shall separate three cities for you in the middle of your land, which the LORD your God gives you to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.3'>You shall prepare you a way, and divide the borders of your land which the LORD your God gives you to inherit, into three parts, so that every slayer may flee there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.4'>And this [is] the case of the slayer who shall flee there that he may live: whoever in error kills his neighbor whom he did not hate him before,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.5'>even he who goes into the wood with his neighbor to cut wood, and his hand brings a stroke with the axe to cut down the tree, and the head slips from the wood and lights on his neighbor so that he dies; he shall flee to one of those cities and live,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.6'>so that the avenger of the blood may not pursue the slayer while his heart is hot, and overtake him because the way is long, and kill him, and he had no sentence worthy of death, for he did not hate him in time past.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.7'>Therefore I command you saying, You shall separate three cities for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.8'>And if the LORD your God makes your border larger, as He has sworn to your fathers, and gives you all the land which He promised to give to your fathers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.9'>if you will keep all these commandments which I command you today, to do them, to love the LORD your God, and to walk always in His ways, then you shall add to yourself three more cities to these three,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.10'>so that innocent blood may not be shed in your land which the LORD your God gives you [for] an inheritance and blood may not be on you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.11'>But if a man hates his neighbor and lies in wait for him and rises up against him and strikes his life from him, so that he dies, and flees to one of these cities,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.12'>then the elders of his city shall send and bring him away from there and deliver him into the hand of the avenger of blood so that he may die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.13'>Your eye shall not pity him, but you shall put away innocent blood from Israel, so that it may go well with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.14'>You may not remove your neighbor's landmark, which those in the past have set in your inheritance, which you shall inherit in the land which the LORD your God gives you to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.15'>One witness shall not rise up against a man for any iniquity, or for any sin, in any sin that he sins. At the mouth of two witnesses, or at the mouth of three witnesses, shall the matter be made sure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.16'>If a false witness rises up against any man to testify a falling away against him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.17'>then both the men who are disagreeing shall stand before the LORD, before the priests and the judges which shall be in those days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.18'>And the judges shall make careful inquiry. And behold, [if] the witness [is] a false witness [and] has testified falsely against his brother,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.19'>then you shall do to him as he had thought to have done to his brother. So you shall put the evil away from among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.20'>And those who remain shall hear and fear, and shall commit from then on no such evil among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.21'>And your eye shall not pity. Life [shall go] for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.20'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.1'>When you go out to battle against your enemies and see horses and chariots, a people more than you, do not be afraid of them. For the LORD your God [is] with you, who brought you up out of the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.2'>And it shall be, when you come near to the battle, the priest shall go up and speak to the people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.3'>and shall say to them, Hear, O, Israel, today you go up to battle against your enemies. Do not let your hearts faint, do not fear, and do not tremble, neither be terrified before their faces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.4'>For the LORD your God [is] He who goes with you to fight for you against your enemies, to save you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.5'>And the officers shall speak to the people saying, Who [is] the man that has built a new house and has not dedicated it? Let him go and return to his house, lest he die in the battle and another man dedicate it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.6'>And who [is] the man that has planted a vineyard and has not used its fruits? Let him go and return to his house, lest he die in the battle and another man use its fruits.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.7'>And who [is] the man that has become engaged to a wife and has not taken her? Let him go and return to his house, lest he die in the battle and another man take her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.8'>And the officers shall speak further to the people, and they shall say, Who [is] the man that is fearful and faint-hearted? Let him go and return to his house, lest his brothers' heart faint as well as his heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.9'>And it shall be, when the officers have made an end of speaking to the people, they shall make captains of the armies to lead the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.10'>When you come near a city to fight against it, then shout peace to it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.11'>And it shall be, if it makes the answer of peace and opens to you, then all the people found in it shall be forced laborers to you, and they shall serve you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.12'>But if it will make no peace with you, but will make war against you, then you shall besiege it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.13'>And when the LORD your God has delivered it into your hands, you shall strike every male of it with the edge of the sword.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.14'>But the women, and the little ones, and the cattle, and all that is in the city, all the spoil of it, you shall take to yourself. And you shall eat the spoil of your enemies, which the LORD your God has given you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.15'>So you shall do to all the cities [which are] very far off from you, which are not of the cities of these nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.16'>But of the cities of these people, which the LORD your God gives you [for] an inheritance, you shall save alive nothing that breathes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.17'>But you shall utterly destroy them: the Hittites, and the Amorites, the Canaanites, and the Perizzites, the Hivites and the Jebusites; as the LORD your God has commanded you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.18'>so that they may not teach you to do according to all their abominations which they have done to their gods. So you would sin against the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.19'>When you shall besiege a city a long time in making war against it to take it, you shall not destroy its trees by forcing an axe against them. For you may eat of them, and you shall not cut them down. For [is] the tree of the field a man that it should go before you to lay siege?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.20'>Only the trees which you know that they [are] not trees for food, you shall destroy and cut them down. And you shall build bulwarks against the city that makes war with you, until it is subdued.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.21'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.1'>If [one] is found dead in the land which the LORD your God gives you to possess it, lying in the field, and it is not known who has killed him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.2'>then your elders and your judges shall come forth. And they shall measure to the cities which [are] around him who is dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.3'>And it shall be, the city nearest to the slain one, even the elders of that city shall take a heifer which has not been worked with, which has not drawn in the yoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.4'>And the elders of that city shall bring down the heifer to an ever-flowing stream, which is neither plowed nor sown, and shall strike off the heifer's neck there in the stream.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.5'>And the priests, the sons of Levi, shall come near. For the LORD your God has chosen them to minister to him, and to bless in the name of the LORD, and by their word shall every controversy and every stroke be [tried].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.6'>And all the elders of that city nearest to the slain one, shall wash their hands over the heifer that has been beheaded in the stream.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.7'>And they shall answer and say, Our hands have not shed this blood, neither have our eyes seen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.8'>Be merciful, O LORD, to Your people Israel, whom You have redeemed, and do not lay innocent blood to the charge of Your people Israel. And the blood shall be forgiven them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.9'>So you shall put away innocent blood from among you, when you do the right in the sight of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.10'>When you go forth to war against your enemies, and the LORD your God has delivered them into your hands and you have taken them captive,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.11'>and see among the captives a beautiful woman, and have a desire to her, that you would take [her] for your wife,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.12'>then you shall bring her home to your house. And she shall shave her head and dress her nails.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.13'>And she shall put off the clothing of her captivity, and shall remain in your house, and shall sorrow for her father and her mother a full month. And after that you shall go in to her and be her husband, and she shall be your wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.14'>And it shall be, if you have no delight in her, then you shall let her go where she will. But you shall not sell her at all for silver, you shall not make a slave of her, because you have humbled her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.15'>If a man has two wives, one beloved and another hated, and they have borne him sons, the beloved and the hated; and [if] the first-born son was of her that was hated,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.16'>then it shall be in the day when he makes his sons to inherit what he has, he may not cause to [inherit] the son of the beloved first-born before the son of the hated one, he who [is truly] the first-born.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.17'>But he shall acknowledge the son of the hated as the first-born by giving him a double portion of all that he has. For he [is] the beginning of his strength. The right of the first-born is his.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.18'>If a man has a son who is stubborn and rebels, who will not obey his father's voice or his mother's voice, even when they have chastened him [he] will not listen to them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.19'>then his father and his mother shall lay hold on him and bring him out to the elders of his city, and to the gate of his place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.20'>And they shall say to the elders of his city, this son of ours [is] stubborn and rebellious. He will not obey our voice. [He is] a glutton and a drunkard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.21'>And all the men of his city shall stone him with stones so that he dies. So shall you put evil away from you, and all Israel shall hear and fear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.22'>And if a man has committed a sin worthy of death, and if he is put to death and you hang him on a tree,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.23'>his body shall not remain all night on the tree. But you shall surely bury him that day (for he that [is] hanged is accursed of God), so that your land may not be defiled, which the LORD your God gives you [for] an inheritance.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.22'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.1'>You shall not see your brother's ox or his sheep go astray and hide yourself from them. You shall surely bring them again to your brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.2'>And if your brother [is] not near you, or if you do not know him, then you shall bring [it] into your own house, and it shall be with you until your brother seeks after it, and you shall give it back to him again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.3'>In the same way you shall do with his ass. And so shall you do with his clothing. And with any lost thing of your brother's, which he has lost and you have found, you shall do the same. You may not hide yourself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.4'>You shall not see your brother's ass or his ox fall down by the way, and hide yourself from them. You shall surely [help] him to lift [it] up again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.5'>There shall not be the thing of a man on a woman, neither shall a man put a woman's garment on. For all that do so [are] abominable to the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.6'>If a bird's nest happens to be before you in the way in any tree, or on the ground, [with] young ones or eggs, and the mother sitting on the young or on the eggs, you shall not take the mother with the young.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.7'>You shall in every case let the mother go and take the young for yourself, so that it may be well with you, and you may make [your] days longer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.8'>When you build a new house, then you shall make a guard rail for your roof, so that you do not bring blood on your house, if one falls from it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.9'>You shall not sow your vineyard with different kinds of seeds, lest the fruit of your seed which you have sown and the fruit of your vineyard be defiled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.10'>You shall not plow with an ox and an ass together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.11'>You shall not wear a garment of different kinds, of wool and linen together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.12'>You shall make for yourself tassels on the four corners of your cloak with which you cover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.13'>If any man takes a wife and goes in to her, and hates her,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.14'>and makes shameful charges against her, and brings up an evil name on her, and says, I took this woman, and when I came to her, I did not find in her the tokens of virginity,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.15'>then shall the father of the girl, and her mother, take and bring tokens of the girl's virginity to the elders of the city in the gate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.16'>And the girl's father shall say to the elders, I gave my daughter to this man to wife, and he hates her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.17'>And, lo, he has made shameful charges [against her], saying, I have not found in your daughter the tokens of virginity. And yet these are the tokens of my daughter's virginity. And they shall spread the cloth before the elders of the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.18'>And the elders of that city shall take that man and punish him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.19'>And they shall fine him a hundred [shekels] of silver, and give them to the father of the girl, because he has brought an evil name on a virgin of Israel. And she shall be his wife. He may not put her away all his days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.20'>But if this thing is true and tokens of virginity are not found for the girl,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.21'>then they shall bring the girl out to the door of her father's house, and the men of her city shall stone her with stones so that she dies because she has done foolishness in Israel to play the harlot in her father's house. So you shall put evil away from among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.22'>If a man is found lying with a woman married to a husband, then they shall both of them die, the man that lay with the woman, and the woman. So you shall put away evil from Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.23'>If a girl [who is] a virgin is engaged to a husband, and a man finds her in the city and lies with her,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.24'>then you shall bring them both out to the gate of that city, and you shall stone them with stones that they die; the girl because she did not cry out in the city, and the man because he has humbled his neighbor's wife. So you shall put away evil from among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.25'>But if a man finds an engaged girl in the field, and the man forces her and lies with her, then only the man that lay with her shall die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.26'>But you shall do nothing to the girl. No sin [worthy] of death [is] in the girl; for as when a man rises against his neighbor and slays him, even so is this matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.27'>For he found her in the field, the engaged girl cried out, but [there was] none to save her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.28'>If a man finds a girl, a virgin not engaged, and lays hold on her, and lies with her, and they are found,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.29'>then the man who lay with her shall give to the girl's father fifty [shekels] of silver, and she shall be his wife. Because he has humbled her, he may not put her away all his days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.30'>A man shall not take his father's wife, nor uncover his father's skirt.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.23'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.1'>He who is wounded, crushed, or who has his male member cut off, shall not enter into the congregation of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.2'>A bastard shall not enter into the congregation of the LORD. Even to his tenth generation he shall not enter into the congregation of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.3'>An Ammonite or Moabite shall not enter into the congregation of the LORD. Even to their tenth generation they shall not enter into the congregation of the LORD forever,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.4'>because they did not meet you with bread and with water in the way when you came forth out of Egypt, and because they hired against you Balaam the son of Beor, of Pethor of Mesopotamia, to curse you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.5'>But the LORD your God would not listen to Balaam, but the LORD your God turned the curse to a blessing to you, because the LORD your God loved you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.6'>You shall not seek their peace nor their prosperity all your days forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.7'>You shall not despise an Edomite, for he [is] your brother. You shall not despise an Egyptian, because you were a stranger in his land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.8'>The sons that are born to them shall enter into the congregation of the LORD in their third generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.9'>When the army goes forth against your enemies, then keep yourself from every wicked thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.10'>If there is among you any man who is not clean because of an accident at night, then he shall go outside the camp. He shall not come inside the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.11'>And it shall be as evening turns, he shall wash with water. And when the sun is down, he shall come into the the middle of the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.12'>You shall also have a place outside the camp where you shall go forth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.13'>And you shall have a paddle on your weapon. And it shall be, when you sit down outside, you shall dig with it, and shall turn back and cover that which comes from you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.14'>For the LORD your God walks in the middle of your camp, to deliver you and to give up your enemies before you. Therefore your camp shall be holy, so that He may see no unclean thing in you and turn away from you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.15'>You shall not deliver to his master the servant who has escaped from his master to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.16'>He shall live with you, among you, in that place which he shall choose in one of your gates, where it seems good to him. You shall not oppress him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.17'>There shall be no harlot of the daughters of Israel, nor a sodomite of the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.18'>You shall not bring the hire of a harlot, or the price of a dog, into the house of the LORD your God for any vow. For even both these [are] hateful to the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.19'>You shall not lend for interest to your brother, interest of silver, interest of food, interest of anything that is loaned on interest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.20'>You may lend on interest to a stranger, but you shall not lend on interest to your brother, so that the LORD your God may bless you in all that you set your hand to in the land where you go to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.21'>When you shall vow a vow to the LORD your God, you shall not wait to pay it, for the LORD your God will surely require it of you, and it would be sin in you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.22'>But if you shall cease to vow, it shall be no sin in you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.23'>That which has gone out of your lips you shall keep and perform, even a free-will offering, according as you have vowed to the LORD your God, which you have promised with your mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.24'>When you come into your neighbor's vineyard, then you may eat grapes to your fill at your own pleasure, but you shall not put [any] in your vessel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.25'>When you come into the standing grain of your neighbor, then you may pluck the heads with your hand, but you shall not move a sickle into your neighbor's standing grain.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.24'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.1'>When a man has taken a wife and married her, and it happens that she finds no favor in his eyes, because he has found some uncleanness in her, then let him write her a bill of divorce and put  it] in her hand, and send her out of his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.2'>And when she has departed from his house, she goes and becomes another man's;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.3'>and the latter husband hates her and writes her a bill of divorce and puts [it] in her hand and sends her out of his house; or if the latter husband dies, he who took her to be his wife</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.4'>her former husband, who sent her away, may not take her again to be his wife after she is defiled. For that [is] hateful before the LORD. And you shall not cause the land to sin, which the LORD your God gives you for an inheritance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.5'>When a man has taken a new wife, he shall not go out to war, neither shall he be charged with any duty. He shall be free at home one year, and shall cheer up his wife whom he has taken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.6'>No man shall take the lower or the upper millstone to pledge, for he takes [a man's] life to pledge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.7'>If a man is found stealing a person of his brothers, the sons of Israel, and makes a slave of him, or sells him, then that thief shall die. And you shall put evil away from among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.8'>Be careful in the plague of leprosy, that you watch carefully and do according to all that the priests the Levites shall teach you. As I commanded them, you shall be careful to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.9'>Remember what the LORD your God did to Miriam by the wayside, after you had come forth out of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.10'>When you loan a loan of any kind to your brother, you shall not go into his house to bring forth his pledge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.11'>You shall stand outside, and the man to whom you loan shall bring the pledge outside to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.12'>And if the man [is] poor, you shall not sleep with his pledge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.13'>You shall certainly give back to him the pledge at sundown, that he may sleep in his own clothing, and bless you. And it shall be righteousness to you before the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.14'>You shall not oppress a hired servant who [is] poor and needy, of your brothers, or of your strangers that [are] in your land within your gates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.15'>At his day you shall give [him] his hire, neither shall the sun go down on it. For he [is] poor and sets his heart on it; lest he cry against you to the LORD, and it shall be sin to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.16'>The fathers shall not be put to death for the sons, neither shall the sons be put to death for the fathers. Every man shall be put to death for his own sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.17'>You shall not pervert the rightful judgment of the stranger [nor] of the fatherless; nor take a widow's clothing to pledge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.18'>But you shall remember that you were a slave in Egypt, and the LORD your God redeemed you from there. Therefore I command you to do this thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.19'>When you cut down your harvest in your field, and have forgotten a sheaf in the field, you shall not go again to bring it. It shall be for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the widow; so that the LORD your God may bless you in all the work of your hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.20'>When you beat your olive tree, you shall not go over the boughs again. It shall be for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the widow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.21'>When you gather the grapes from your vineyard, you shall not glean afterward. It shall be for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the widow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.22'>And you shall remember that you were a slave in the land of Egypt. Therefore I command you to do this thing.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.25'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.1'>If there is a controversy between men, and they come to judgment, and they have been judged, and the righteous one is declared righteous, and the wrongdoer declared guilty,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.2'>then it shall be, if the wrongdoer [is] worthy to be beaten, the judge shall cause him to fall down. And one shall strike him in his presence, enough for his wrong, by a certain number.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.3'>He may give him forty stripes, no more, lest he should exceed and beat him above these [with] many stripes, then your brother would be dishonored before your eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.4'>You shall not muzzle an ox when he treads out [the grain].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.5'>If brothers live together, and one of them dies and has no child, the wife of the dead shall not marry outside to a stranger. Her husband's brother shall go in to her and take her as a wife for himself, and perform the duty of a husband's brother to her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.6'>And it shall be, the first-born whom she bears shall succeed in the name of his dead brother, so that his name may not be put out of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.7'>And if the man does not want to take his brother's wife, then let his brother's wife go up to the gate to the elders and say, My husband's brother refuses to raise up a name in Israel to his brother. He will not perform my levirate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.8'>Then the elders of his city shall call him and speak to him. And [if] he stands and says, I do not desire to take her,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.9'>then his brother's wife shall come to him in the presence of his elders, and take off his shoe from his foot, and spit in his face, and shall answer and say, So shall it be done to that man who will not build up his brother's house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.10'>And his name shall be called in Israel, The house of him who has his shoe taken off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.11'>When men strive together with one another, and the wife of the one draws near to deliver her husband out of the hand of him who strikes him, and puts forth her hand and takes him by the secret parts,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.12'>then you shall cut off her hand. Your eye shall not pity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.13'>You shall not have in your bag two kinds of weights, a great stone and a small.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.14'>You shall not have in your house two kinds of measures, a great ephah and a small.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.15'>You shall have a perfect and just weight, a perfect and just measure you shall have, so that your days may be lengthened in the land which the LORD your God gives you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.16'>For all that do such things, all that do unrighteousness, [are] hateful to the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.17'>Remember what Amalek did to you by the way, when you came forth out of Egypt,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.18'>how he met you by the way and struck those of you who were behind, all the feeble behind you, when you [were] faint and weary. And he did not fear God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.19'>And it shall be when the LORD your God has given you rest from all your enemies all around in the land which the LORD your God gives you [for] an inheritance to possess it, you shall blot out the remembrance of Amalek from under heavens. You shall not forget.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.26'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.1'>And it shall be, when you come into the land which the LORD your God gives you for an inheritance, and possess it, and live in it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.2'>you shall take of the first of all the fruit of the earth which you shall bring of your land that the LORD your God gives you, and you shall put [it] in a basket, and shall go to the place which the LORD your God shall choose to place His name there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.3'>And you shall go to the priest in those days, and say to him, I profess today to the LORD your God that I have come into the land which the LORD swore to our fathers to give us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.4'>And the priest shall take the basket out of your hand and set it down before the altar of the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.5'>And you shall speak and say before the LORD your God, My father [was] a Syrian ready to perish. And he went down to Egypt, and stayed there with a few, and became there a nation, great, mighty, and many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.6'>And the Egyptians ill-treated us, and afflicted us, and laid hard bondage on us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.7'>And when we cried to the LORD God of our fathers, the LORD heard our voice and looked on our afflictions and our labor and our oppression.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.8'>And the LORD brought us forth out of Egypt with a mighty hand, and with an outstretched arm, and with fearful might, and with miracles and with wonders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.9'>And He has brought us into this place, and has given us this land, a land that flows with milk and honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.10'>And now, behold, I have brought the firstfruits of the land which You, O LORD, have given me. And you shall set it before the LORD your God, and worship before the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.11'>And [you shall] rejoice in all the good which the LORD your God has given to you, and to your house; you, and the Levite, and the stranger in your midst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.12'>When you have made an end of tithing all the tithes of your increase the third year, the year of tithing, and have given [it] to the Levite, the stranger, the fatherless, and the widow (that they may eat inside your gates and be filled),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.13'>then you shall say before the LORD your God, I have brought away the holy things out of my house, and also have given them to the Levite, and to the stranger, to the fatherless, and to the widow, according to all Your commandments which You have commanded me. I have not broken Your commandments, neither have I forgotten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.14'>I have not eaten of it in my mourning, neither have I put [any] of it away for unclean [use], nor have I given of it for the dead. I have listened to the voice of the LORD my God, and have done according to all that You have commanded me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.15'>Look down from Your holy dwelling, from Heaven, and bless Your people Israel and the land which You have given us, as You swore to our fathers, a land that flows with milk and honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.16'>Today the LORD your God has commanded you to do these statutes and judgments. You therefore shall keep and do them with all your heart and with all your soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.17'>You have today said that the LORD is your God, and that you would walk in His ways, and keep His statutes and His commandments and His judgments, and listen to His voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.18'>And the LORD has taken you today to be His peculiar people, as He has promised you, and to keep all His commandments,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.19'>and to make you high above all nations which he has made, in praise and in name and in honor, and that you may be a holy people to the LORD your God, even as He has spoken.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.27'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.1'>And Moses with the elders of Israel commanded the people saying, Keep all the commandments which I command you today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.2'>And it will be, on the day when you shall pass over Jordan to the land which the LORD your God gives you, you shall set up great stones and plaster them with plaster.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.3'>And you shall write on them all the words of the law when you have passed over, so that you may go in to the land which the LORD your God gives you, a land that flows [with] milk and honey, as the LORD God of your fathers has promised you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.4'>Therefore it shall be when you have gone over Jordan, you shall set up these stones which I command you today, in Mount Ebal. And you shall plaster them with plaster.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.5'>And you shall build an altar there to the LORD your God, an altar of stones. You shall not lift up [any] iron [tool] on them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.6'>You shall build the altar of the LORD your God [of] uncut stones, and you shall offer burnt offerings on it to the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.7'>And you shall offer peace offerings, and shall eat there, and rejoice before the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.8'>And you shall write all the words of this law very plainly on the stones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.9'>And Moses and the priests the Levites spoke to all Israel, saying: Take heed and listen, O Israel. Today you have become the people of the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.10'>You shall therefore obey the voice of the LORD your God, and do His commandments and His statutes which I command you today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.11'>And Moses charged the people the same day, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.12'>These shall stand on Mount Gerizim to bless the people when you have come over Jordan: Simeon, and Levi, and Judah, and Issachar, and Joseph, and Benjamin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.13'>And these shall stand on Mount Ebal to curse: Reuben, Gad, and Asher, and Zebulun, Dan, and Naphtali.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.14'>And the Levites shall speak and say to all the men of Israel with a loud voice,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.15'>Cursed [is] the man that makes any graven or molten image, an abomination to the LORD, the work of the hands of the craftsman, and puts [it] in a secret place. And all the people shall answer and say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.16'>Cursed [is] he who thinks lightly of his father or his mother. And all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.17'>Cursed [is] he who removes his neighbor's landmark. And all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.18'>Cursed [is] he who makes the blind to wander out of the way. And all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.19'>Cursed [is] he who perverts the judgment of the stranger, fatherless, and widow. And all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.20'>Cursed [is] he who lies with his father's wife, because he uncovers his father's skirt. And all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.21'>Cursed [is] he who lies with any kind of animal. And all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.22'>Cursed [is] he who lies with his sister, the daughter of his father or the daughter of his mother. And all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.23'>Cursed [is] he who lies with his mother-in-law. And all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.24'>Cursed [is] he who strikes his neighbor secretly. And all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.25'>Cursed [is] he who takes reward to kill an innocent person. And all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.26'>Cursed [is] he who does not confirm [all] the words of this law, to do them. And all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.28'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.1'>And it will be, if you shall listen carefully to the voice of the LORD your God, to observe [and] to do all His commandments which I command you today, the LORD your God will set you on high above all nations of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.2'>And all these blessings shall come on you and overtake you, if you will listen to the voice of the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.3'>You [shall be] blessed in the city, and be blessed in the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.4'>The fruit of your body [shall be] blessed, and the fruit of your ground, and the fruit of your cattle, the increase of your cows, and the flocks of your sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.5'>Your basket and your store [shall be] blessed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.6'>You [shall be] blessed when you come in, and blessed when you go out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.7'>The LORD shall cause your enemies that rise up against you to be stricken before your face. They shall come out against you one way, and flee before you seven ways.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.8'>The LORD shall command the blessing on you in your storehouses, and all that you set your hand to. And He shall bless you in the land which the LORD your God gives you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.9'>The LORD shall establish you a holy people to Himself, as He has sworn to you, if you shall keep the commandments of the LORD your God and walk in His ways.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.10'>And all the peoples of the earth shall see that you are called by the name of the LORD, and they shall be afraid of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.11'>And the LORD shall prosper you in goods, in the fruit of your body, and in the fruit of your cattle, and in the fruit of your ground, in the land which the LORD swore to your fathers to give you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.12'>The LORD shall open to you His good treasure, the heaven to give the rain to your land in its season, and to bless all the work of your hand. And you shall loan to many nations, and you shall not borrow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.13'>And the LORD shall make you the head, and not the tail. And you shall be always above, and you shall not be beneath, if you listen to the commandments of the LORD your God, which I command you today, to observe and to do them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.14'>And you shall not go aside from any of the words which I command you today, to the right hand or the left, to go after other gods to serve them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.15'>And it shall be, if you will not listen to the voice of the LORD your God, to observe and to do all His commandments and His statutes which I command you today, all these curses shall come on you and overtake you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.16'>You [shall be] cursed in the city, and cursed in the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.17'>Your basket and your store [shall be] cursed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.18'>The fruit of your body [shall be] cursed, and the fruit of your land, the increase of your cows, and the flocks of your sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.19'>You [shall be] cursed when you come in, and cursed when you go out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.20'>The LORD shall send on you cursing, vexation, and rebuke, in all that you set your hand to do, until you are destroyed, and until you perish quickly, because of the wickedness of your doings [by] which you have forsaken Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.21'>The LORD shall make the plague cling to you until He has consumed you from off the land where you go to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.22'>The LORD shall strike you with lung disease and with a fever, and with an inflammation, and with an extreme burning, and with the sword, and with blasting, and with mildew. And they shall pursue you until you perish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.23'>And your heavens over your head shall be bronze, and the earth that is under you iron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.24'>The LORD shall make the rain of your land powder and dust. It shall come down from the heavens on you until you are destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.25'>The LORD shall cause you to be stricken before your enemies. You shall go out one way against them, and flee seven ways before them. And you shall be a trembling to all the kingdoms of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.26'>And your body shall be food to all birds of the air, and to the beasts of the earth. And no man shall frighten [them] away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.27'>The LORD will strike you with the boils of Egypt, and with the hemorrhoids, and with the scab, and with the itch, of which you cannot be healed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.28'>The LORD shall strike you with madness and blindness, and astonishment of heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.29'>And you shall grope at noonday, as the blind gropes in darkness, and you shall not prosper in your ways. And you shall always be pressed down and spoiled forever, and no man shall save you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.30'>You shall become engaged to a wife, and another man shall lie with her. You shall build a house, and you shall not live in it. You shall plant a vineyard, and you shall not gather the grapes of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.31'>Your ox [shall be] slain before your eyes, and you shall not eat of it. Your ass [shall be] violently taken away from before your face, and shall not be restored to you, your sheep given to your enemies, and you [shall have none to rescue them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.32'>Your sons and your daughters [shall be] given to another people, and your eyes shall look and fail for them all the day long. And [there shall be] no power in your hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.33'>The fruit of your land, and all your labors, shall be eaten up by a nation which you do not know. And you shall always be oppressed and crushed,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.34'>and you shall be mad because of that which you shall see with the sight of your eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.35'>The LORD shall strike you in the knees and in the legs with an evil ulcer that cannot be healed, from the sole of your foot to the top of your head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.36'>The LORD shall bring you, and your king which you shall set over you, to a nation which neither you nor your fathers have known. And there you shall serve other gods, wood and stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.37'>And you shall become an astonishment, a proverb, and a by-word among all nations where the LORD shall lead you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.38'>You shall carry much seed out into the field, and shall gather little in, for the locust shall eat it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.39'>You shall plant vineyards and dress [them], but shall neither drink the wine nor gather, for the worm shall eat them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.40'>You shall have olive trees throughout all your coasts, but you shall not anoint [with] the oil, for your olive shall drop off [its fruit].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.41'>You shall father sons and daughters, but you shall not enjoy them, for they shall go into captivity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.42'>All your trees and the fruit of your land the locust shall possess.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.43'>The stranger within you shall get up above you very high, and you shall come down very low.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.44'>He shall loan to you, and you shall not loan to him. He shall be the head, and you shall be the tail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.45'>And all these curses shall come on you, and shall pursue you and overtake you, until you are destroyed, because you did not listen to the voice of the LORD your God, to keep His commandments and His statutes which He commanded you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.46'>And they shall be on you for a sign and for a wonder, and on your seed forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.47'>Because you did not serve the LORD your God with joyfulness and with gladness of heart for the abundance of all [things] ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.48'>therefore you shall serve your enemies which the LORD shall send against you, in hunger, and in thirst, and in nakedness, and in the lack of all [things]. And he shall put a yoke of iron on your neck until he has destroyed you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.49'>The LORD shall bring a nation against you from far, from the end of the earth, as the eagle flies; a nation whose tongue you shall not understand,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.50'>a nation fierce of face who shall not regard the person of the old, nor show favor to the young.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.51'>And he shall eat the fruit of your cattle and the fruit of your land, until you are destroyed. He shall not leave you grain, wine, or oil, the increase of your livestock, or flocks of your sheep, until he has destroyed you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.52'>And he shall besiege you in all your gates until your high and fortified walls in which you trusted come down, throughout all the land. And he shall besiege you in all your gates throughout all your land which the LORD your God has given you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.53'>And you shall eat the fruit of your own body, the flesh of your sons and of your daughters, which the LORD your God has given you, in the siege and in the anguish with which your enemies shall distress you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.54'>The man [that is] tender among you, and very delicate, his eye shall be evil toward his brother and toward the wife of his bosom, and toward the rest of his sons which he has left;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.55'>so that he will not give to any of them of the flesh of his sons whom he shall eat, because he has nothing left to him in the siege and in the anguish with which your enemies shall distress you in all your gates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.56'>The tender and delicate woman among you, who would not have ventured to set the sole of her foot on the ground for delicateness and tenderness, her eye shall be evil toward the husband of her bosom, and toward her son, and toward her daughter,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.57'>and toward her young one who comes out from between her feet, and toward her sons whom she shall bear. For she shall eat them secretly for lack of all [things], in the siege and anguish with which your enemies shall distress you in your gates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.58'>If you will not observe to do all the words of this law that are written in this book, that you may fear this glorious and fearful name, JEHOVAH YOUR GOD,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.59'>then Jehovah will make your plagues remarkable, and the plagues of your seed great and persistent plagues; with evil and long-lasting sicknesses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.60'>Also, He will bring on you all the diseases of Egypt of which you were afraid. And they shall cling to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.61'>Also, every sickness and every plague which [is] not written in the book of this law, the LORD will bring them on you until you are destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.62'>And you shall be left few in number, whereas you were as the stars of the heavens for multitude, because you would not obey the voice of the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.63'>And it shall be, as the LORD rejoiced over you to do you good and to multiply you, so the LORD will rejoice over you to destroy you and to bring you to nothing. And you shall be plucked from off the land where you go to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.64'>And the LORD shall scatter you among all people, from the [one] end of the earth even to the [other], and you shall serve other gods there, which neither you nor your fathers have known, wood and stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.65'>And among these nations you shall find no ease, neither shall the sole of your foot have rest. But the LORD shall give you there a trembling heart and failing of eyes and sorrow of mind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.66'>And your life shall hang in doubt before you, and you shall fear day and night, and shall have no assurance of your life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.67'>In the morning you shall say, Oh that it were evening! And at evening you shall say, Oh that it were morning, for the fear of your heart with which you shall fear, and for the sight of your eyes which you shall see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.68'>And the LORD shall bring you into Egypt again with ships, by the way of which I said to you, You shall see it no more again. And there you shall be sold to your enemies for men-slaves and women-slaves, and no man shall buy [you].</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.29'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.1'>These [are] the words of the covenant which the LORD commanded Moses to make with the sons of Israel in the land of Moab, besides the covenant which He made with them in Horeb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.2'>And Moses called to all Israel and said to them, You have seen all that the LORD did before your eyes in the land of Egypt to Pharaoh and to all his servants, and to all his land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.3'>Your eyes have seen the great trials, the signs, and those great miracles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.4'>Yet the LORD has not given you a heart to perceive, and eyes to see, and ears to hear, until today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.5'>And I have led you forty years in the wilderness. Your clothes have not become old on you, and your shoe has not become old on your foot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.6'>You have not eaten bread, neither have you drunk wine or strong drink, so that you might know that I [am] the LORD your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.7'>And when you came to this place, Sihon the king of Heshbon, and Og the king of Bashan, came out against us to battle, and we struck them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.8'>And we took their land and gave it for an inheritance to the Reubenites and to the Gadites and to the half tribe of Manasseh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.9'>Therefore, keep the words of this covenant and do them, so that you may act wisely in all that you do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.10'>You stand today, all of you, before the LORD your God; your captains of your tribes, your elders, and your officers, all the men of Israel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.11'>your little ones, your wives, and your stranger that [is] in your camp, from the cutter of your wood to the drawer of your water;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.12'>so that you should enter into covenant with the LORD your God, and into His oath, which the LORD your God makes you today;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.13'>that He may establish you today for a people to Himself, and [that] He may be a God to you, as He has said to you, and as He has sworn to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.14'>Nor do I make this covenant and this oath with you only,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.15'>but with [him] who stands here with us today before the LORD our God, and also with him that is not here with us today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.16'>(For you know how we have lived in the land of Egypt, and how we came through the nations which you passed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.17'>And you have seen their abominations and their idols, wood and stone, silver and gold, which [were] among them)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.18'>lest there should be among you man, or woman, or family, or tribe, whose heart turns away today from the LORD our God, to go serve the gods of these nations; lest there should be among you a root that bears gall and wormwood,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.19'>and it happens when he hears the words of this curse, that he shall bless himself in his heart, saying, I shall have peace, though I walk in the stubbornness of my heart, to snatch away the drunken with the thirsty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.20'>The LORD will not be willing to forgive him, but then the anger of the LORD and His jealousy shall smoke against that man, and all the curses that are written in this book shall lie on him, and the LORD shall blot out his name from under heavens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.21'>And the LORD shall set him apart to evil out of all the tribes of Israel, according to all the curses of the covenant that are written in this book of the law;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.22'>so that the generation to come of your sons that shall rise up after you, and the stranger that shall come from a far land, shall say (when they see the plagues of that land, and the sicknesses which the LORD has laid on it)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.23'>the whole land shall be burned [with] brimstone, and salt; it shall not be sown; nor shall it sprout; nor shall there be any grass in it. It [shall be] like the overthrow of Sodom and Gomorrah, Admah, and Zeboim, which the LORD overthrew in His anger, and in His wrath,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.24'>even all nations shall say, Why has the LORD done this to this land? [For] what [is] the heat of this great anger?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.25'>Then [men] shall say, Because they have forsaken the covenant of the LORD God of their fathers, which He made with them when He brought them forth out of the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.26'>For they went and served other gods, and worshiped them, gods whom they did not know, and who had not given to them any portion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.27'>And the anger of the LORD was kindled against this land, to bring on it all the curses that are written in this book.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.28'>And the LORD rooted them out of their land in anger and wrath, and in great indignation, and cast them into another land, as [it is] today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.29'>The secret things [belong] to the LORD our God, but the revealed things [belong] to us and to our sons forever, so that we may do all the words of this law.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.30'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.1'>And it shall be when all these things have come on you, the blessing and the curse which I have set before you, and when you shall call [them] to mind among all the nations where the LORD your God has driven you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.2'>and shall return to the LORD your God and shall obey His voice according to all that I command you today, you and your sons, with all your heart, and with all your soul,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.3'>then the LORD your God will turn your captivity. And He will have compassion on you, and will return and gather you from all the nations where the LORD your God has scattered you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.4'>If you are driven out into the outermost [parts] of the heavens, the LORD your God will gather you from there, and He will bring you from there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.5'>And the LORD your God will bring you into the land which your fathers possessed, and you shall possess it. And He will do you good, and multiply you above your fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.6'>And the LORD your God will circumcise your heart and the heart of your seed, to love the LORD your God with all your heart and with all your soul, so that you may live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.7'>And the LORD your God will put all these curses on your enemies, and on those that hate you, who persecuted you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.8'>And you shall return and obey the voice of the LORD, and do all His commandments which I command you today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.9'>And the LORD your God will make you have plenty in every work of your hand, in the fruit of your body, and in the fruit of your cattle, and in the fruit of your land, for good. For the LORD will again rejoice over you for good, as He rejoiced over your fathers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.10'>for you shall listen to the voice of the LORD your God, to keep His commandments and His statutes which are written in this book of the law, [and] if you turn to the LORD your God with all your heart and with all your soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.11'>For this commandment which I command you today [is] not hidden from you, neither is it far off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.12'>It [is] not in Heaven, [that you should] say, Who shall go up for us to Heaven, and bring it to us, so that we may hear it and do it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.13'>Nor [is] it beyond the sea, [that you should] say, Who shall go over the sea for us to the region beyond the sea, and bring it to us, so that we may hear it and do it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.14'>But the word [is] very near you, in your mouth and in your heart, so that you may do it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.15'>Behold! I have set before you today life and good, and death and evil,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.16'>in that I command you today to love the LORD your God, to walk in His ways, and to keep His commandments and His statutes and His judgments, so that you may live and multiply. And the LORD your God shall bless you in the land where you go to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.17'>But if you turn away your heart, so that you will not hear, but shall be drawn away and worship other gods and serve them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.18'>I declare to you today that you shall surely perish; you shall not prolong [your] days on the land where you pass over Jordan to go to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.19'>I call Heaven and earth to record today against you. I have set before you life and death, blessing and cursing. Therefore, choose life, so that both you and your seed may live,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.20'>so that you may love the LORD your God, [and] that you may obey His voice, and that you may cling to Him. For He is your life and the length of your days, so that you may dwell in the land which the LORD swore to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give it to them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.31'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.1'>And Moses went and spoke these words to all Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.2'>And he said to them, I [am] a hundred twenty years old today. I can no more go out and come in. Also the LORD has said to me, You shall not go over this Jordan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.3'>The LORD your God will go over before you. He will destroy these nations from before you, and you shall possess them. Joshua [is] the one crossing over before you, as the LORD has said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.4'>And the LORD shall do to them as He did to Sihon and to Og, kings of the Amorites, and to the land of those whom He destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.5'>And the LORD shall give them up before your face, so that you may do to them according to all the commandments which I have commanded you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.6'>Be strong and of a good courage. Do not fear nor be afraid of them. For the LORD your God [is] He who goes with you. He will not fail you nor forsake you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.7'>And Moses called to Joshua and said to him in the sight of all Israel, Be strong and of a good courage. For you must go with this people to the land which the LORD has sworn to their fathers to give  it to] them, and you shall cause them to inherit it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.8'>And Jehovah [is] He who goes before you. He will be with you; He will not fail you nor forsake you. Do not fear; nor be dismayed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.9'>And Moses wrote this law and delivered it to the priests, the sons of Levi, who carried the ark of the covenant of the LORD, and to all the elders of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.10'>And Moses commanded them, saying: At the end of seven years, at the set time of the year of release, in the Feast of Tabernacles,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.11'>when all Israel has come to appear before the LORD your God in the place which He shall choose, you shall read this law before all Israel in their hearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.12'>Gather the people, men and women and the little ones, and your stranger who [is] within your gates, so that they may hear and that they may learn and fear the LORD your God, and be careful to do all the words of this law,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.13'>and [that] their sons who have not known may hear and learn to fear the LORD your God, as long as you live in the land where you go over Jordan to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.14'>And the LORD said to Moses, Behold, your days are coming near to die. Call Joshua and present yourselves in the tabernacle of the congregation, and that I shall charge him. And Moses and Joshua went. And they presented themselves in the tabernacle of the congregation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.15'>And the LORD appeared in the tabernacle in a pillar of a cloud. And the pillar of the cloud stood over the door of the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.16'>And the LORD said to Moses, Behold, you shall sleep with your fathers. And this people shall rise up and go lusting after the gods of the strangers of the land into which they are going, into their midst. And they will forsake Me and break My covenant which I made with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.17'>Then My anger shall be kindled against them in that day, and I will forsake them. And I will hide My face from them, and they shall be devoured, and many evils and troubles shall befall them, so that they will say in that day, Have not these evils come on us because our God [is] not among us?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.18'>And I will surely hide My face in that day for all the evils which they have done, for they shall turn to other gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.19'>Now, therefore, write this song for you, and teach it to the sons of Israel. Put it in their mouths, so that this song may be a witness for Me against the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.20'>For when I shall have brought them into the land which I swore to their fathers, the land that flows [with] milk and honey, and they shall have eaten and have become satisfied, and become fat, then turn to other gods and serve them, and provoke Me and break My covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.21'>And it shall be when many evils and troubles have found them, this song shall testify against them as a witness. For it shall not be forgotten out of the mouths of their seed. For I know their imagination which they do, even now, before I have brought them into the land which I swore.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.22'>And Moses wrote this song the same day, and taught it to the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.23'>And he commanded Joshua the son of Nun, and said: Be strong and of a good courage. For you shall bring the sons of Israel into the land which I swore to them, and I will be with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.24'>And it happened when Moses had made an end of writing the words of this law in a book, until they were finished,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.25'>Moses commanded the Levites who carried the ark of the covenant of the LORD, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.26'>Take this book of the law, and put it in the side of the ark of the covenant of the LORD your God, so that it may be there for a witness against you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.27'>For I know your rebellion and your stiff neck. Behold, while I am still alive with you today, you have been rebellious against the LORD. And how much more after my death?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.28'>Gather to me all the elders of your tribes, and your officers, so that I may speak these words in their ears, and call Heaven and earth to record against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.29'>For I know that after my death you will become utterly corrupt, and turn aside from the way which I have commanded you. And evil will happen to you in the latter end of the days, because you will do evil in the sight of the LORD, to provoke Him to anger through the work of your hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.30'>And Moses spoke in the ears of all the congregation of Israel the words of this song, until their conclusion.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.32'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.1'>Give ear, O heavens, and I will speak; and hear, O earth, the words of my mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.2'>My doctrine shall drop as the rain; my speech shall drop down as the dew, as the small rain on the tender plant, and as the showers on the grass;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.3'>because I will proclaim the name of the LORD, ascribe greatness to our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.4'>[He is] the Rock; His work [is] perfect. For all His ways [are] just, a God of faithfulness, and without evil; just and upright is He.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.5'>They have corrupted themselves: [they are] not His sons; [it is] their blemish; [they are] a crooked and perverse generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.6'>Do you thus give back to the LORD, Oh foolish and unwise people? [Is] He not your Father who bought you? [Has] He [not] made you and established you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.7'>Remember the days of old; consider the years of many generations. Ask your father, and he will show you; your elders, and they will tell you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.8'>When the Most High divided to the nations their inheritance, when He separated the sons of Adam, He set the bounds of the people according to the number of the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.9'>For the LORD's portion [is] His people. Jacob [is] the lot of His inheritance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.10'>He found him in a desert land, and in the deserted, howling wilderness. He led him about, He cared for him, He kept him as the pupil of His eye.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.11'>As an eagle stirs up her nest, flutters over her young, spreads abroad her wings, takes them and bears them on her wing,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.12'>the LORD alone led him, and [there was] no strange god with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.13'>He made him ride on the high places of the earth, so that he might eat the increase of the fields. And He made him suck honey out of the rock, and oil out of the flinty rock,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.14'>butter from cows, and milk from sheep, with fat of lambs, and rams of the sons of Bashan, and goats, with the fat of kidneys of wheat. And you drank the blood of the grape.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.15'>But Jeshurun grew fat and kicked. You grew fat, thick, [and] satisfied. Then he forsook God who made him, and lightly esteemed the Rock of his salvation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.16'>They provoked Him to jealousy with strange [gods]; with abominations they provoked Him to anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.17'>They sacrificed to devils, not to God; to gods whom they knew not, to new ones newly come up, whom your fathers did not fear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.18'>You forgot the Rock [who] brought you forth, and ceased to care for God who formed you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.19'>And the LORD saw, and despised [them] because of the provoking of His sons and of His daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.20'>And He said, I will hide My face from them; I will see what their end [shall be]. For they [are] a very perverse generation, sons in whom [is] no faithfulness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.21'>They have moved Me to jealousy with a no-god. They have provoked Me to anger with their vanities. And I will move them to jealousy with a no-people. I will provoke them to anger with a foolish nation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.22'>For a fire is kindled in My anger, and shall burn to the lowest hell, and shall consume the earth with its increase, and set on fire the foundations of the mountains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.23'>I will heap evils on them. I will spend My arrows on them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.24'>Exhaustion by famine, and consumption by burning heat, and bitter destruction, and the teeth of beasts I will send on them, with the poison of crawling things of the dust.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.25'>The sword outside, and the terror inside, shall destroy both the young man and the virgin, the suckling [also] with the man of grey hairs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.26'>I said I would dash them to pieces; I would make the memory of them to cease from among men,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.27'>were it not the provocation of an enemy I feared, lest their enemies should misconstrue; lest they should say, Our hand [is] high and the LORD has not done all this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.28'>For they [are] a nation without wisdom, neither is there any understanding in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.29'>If they were wise, they would understand this; they would consider their latter end!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.30'>How shall one chase a thousand, and two put ten thousand to flight, unless their Rock had sold them and the LORD had shut them up?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.31'>For their rock [is] not as our Rock, even our enemies themselves being judges.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.32'>For their vine [is] of the vine of Sodom, and of the fields of Gomorrah. Their grapes are grapes of gall. Their clusters [are] bitter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.33'>Their wine [is] the poison of serpents, and the cruel venom of asps.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.34'>[Is] not this laid up in store with Me and sealed up among My treasures?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.35'>Vengeance and retribution [belong] to Me. Their foot shall slide in time, for the day of their calamity [is] at hand, and the things that shall come on them make haste.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.36'>For the LORD will bring His people justice; and He shall have compassion on His servants, for He sees that [their] power is gone, and only the imprisoned and abandoned [remain].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.37'>And He shall say, Where [are] their gods, [their] rock in whom they trusted?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.38'>Who ate the fat of their sacrifices [and] drank the wine of their drink offerings? Let them rise up and help you; let it be your hiding place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.39'>See now that I, I am He, and there is no god with me. I kill, and I make alive; I wound and I heal; and there is no deliverer out of My hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.40'>For I lift up My hand to Heaven and say, I live forever!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.41'>If I sharpen My glittering sword, and if My hand takes hold in judgment, I will give vengeance to My enemies and will reward those that hate Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.42'>I will make My arrows drunk with blood, and My sword shall devour flesh, with the blood of the slain and of the captives, from the hairy scalp of the enemy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.43'>Rejoice, O, nations, [with] His people; for He will avenge the blood of His servants, and will render vengeance to His foes and will be merciful to His land, to His people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.44'>And Moses came and spoke all the words of this song in the ears of the people, he and Joshua the son of Nun.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.45'>And Moses made an end of speaking all these words to all Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.46'>And he said to them, Set your hearts to all the words which I testify among you today, which you shall command your sons to observe and to do, all the words of this law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.47'>For it [is] not a vain thing for you, because it is your life. And by this word you shall prolong [your] days in the land where you go over Jordan, there to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.48'>And the LORD spoke to Moses that same day, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.49'>Go up into Mount Abarim, [to] Mount Nebo in the land of Moab, which is opposite Jericho; and behold the land of Canaan which I am giving to the sons of Israel for a possession.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.50'>And die in the mountain where you go up, and be gathered to your people, as Aaron your brother died in Mount Hor and was gathered to his people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.51'>because you sinned against Me among the sons of Israel at the Waters of Strife in Kadesh, in the wilderness of Zin, because you did not sanctify Me in the midst of the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.52'>Yet you shall see the land before [you], but you shall not go there to the land which I [am] giving to the sons of Israel.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.33'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.1'>And this [is] the blessing [with] which Moses the man of God blessed the sons of Israel before his death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.2'>And he said: The LORD came from Sinai and rose up from Seir to them. He shone forth from Mount Paran, and He came with ten thousands of saints. From His right went a fiery law for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.3'>Yea, He loved the people. All His saints [are] in Your hand, and they sat down at Your feet. Everyone shall receive of Your words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.4'>Moses commanded us a law, the inheritance of the congregation of Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.5'>And he was king in Jeshurun, when the heads of the people [and] the tribes of Israel were gathered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.6'>Let Reuben live and not die, and let [not] his men be few.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.7'>And this for Judah: And he said, Hear, LORD, the voice of Judah, and bring him to his people. Let his hands be sufficient for him, and You shall be a help [to him] from his enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.8'>And of Levi he said, [Let] Your Thummim and Your Urim [be] with Your holy one whom You proved at Massah; You strove with him at the Waters of Strife,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.9'>who said to his father and to his mother, I have not seen him; and he has not acknowledged his brothers, nor knew his own son, for they have observed Your word and kept Your covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.10'>Let them teach Jacob Your judgments, and Israel Your law. Let them put incense before You and whole burnt sacrifice on Your altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.11'>O, LORD, bless his strength, and accept the work of his hands. Strike through the loins of those who rise against him, and [of those] who hate him, that they should not rise again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.12'>Of Benjamin he said, The beloved of the LORD shall live in safety beside Him, [and] shall cover him all the day long, yea he shall dwell between His shoulders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.13'>And of Joseph he said, Blessed of the LORD [be] his land, with the precious things of the heavens, for the dew, and for the deep that crouches beneath,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.14'>and for the precious fruits of the sun, and with the best yield of [the] months.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.15'>And with the first of the ancient mountains, and for the precious things of the everlasting hills,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.16'>and for the precious things of the earth and fullness of it, and [for] the good will of Him who lived in the Bush. Let the blessing come on the head of Joseph, and on the top of the head of him who was separated from his brothers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.17'>His glory [is like] the first-born of his bull, and his horns are like the horns of the wild ox. With them he shall push the people together to the ends of the earth. And they are the ten thousands of Ephraim, and they are the thousands of Manasseh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.18'>And of Zebulun he said, Rejoice, Zebulun, in your going out, and Issachar in your tents.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.19'>They shall call the peoples to the mountain. There they shall offer sacrifices of righteousness, for they shall suck the bounty of the seas and treasures hidden in the sand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.20'>And of Gad he said, Blessed [is] he who makes Gad greater. He lives as a lion and tears the arm and the crown of the head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.21'>And he provided the first part for himself, because there was the portion of the lawgiver hidden. And he came [with] the heads of the people. He executed the justice of the LORD, and His judgments with Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.22'>And of Dan he said, Dan [is] a lion's whelp. He shall leap from Bashan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.23'>And of Naphtali he said, O Naphtali, satisfied with favor, and full with the blessing of the LORD, possess the west and the south.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.24'>And of Asher he said, Asher [shall be] blessed with sons, let him be pleasing to his brothers, and let him dip his foot in oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.25'>Your shoes [shall be] iron and bronze. And as your days, so shall your strength be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.26'>[There is] none like the God of Jeshurun, who rides on the heaven to your help, and in His majesty on the clouds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.27'>The eternal God [is your] refuge, and underneath [are] the everlasting arms. And He shall throw the enemy out from before you, and shall say, Destroy!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.28'>And Israel shall dwell in safety alone; the fountain of Jacob in a land of grain and wine; and his heavens shall drop down dew.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.29'>Blessed [are] you, O Israel! Who [is] like you, O people saved by the LORD, the shield of your help, and who [is] the sword of your excellency! And your enemies shall be found liars to you, and you shall tread on their high places.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.34'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.1'>And Moses went up from the plains of Moab to the mountain of Nebo, to the top of Pisgah that [is] opposite Jericho. And the LORD showed him all the land of Gilead, to Dan,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.2'>and all Naphtali, and the land of Ephraim and Manasseh, and all the land of Judah, to the furthest sea,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.3'>and the south, and the plain of the valley of Jericho, the city of palm trees, to Zoar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.4'>And the LORD said to him, This [is] the land which I swore to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, saying, I will give it to your seed. I have caused you to see it with your eyes, but you shall not go over there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.5'>And Moses the servant of the LORD died there in the land of Moab, according to the word of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.6'>And He buried him in a valley in the land of Moab, opposite Beth-peor. But no man knows of his grave to this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.7'>And Moses [was] a hundred and twenty years old when he died. His eye was not dim, nor had he lost any of his natural strength.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.8'>And the sons of Israel wept for Moses in the plains of Moab thirty days. And the days of weeping [and] mourning for Moses were ended.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.9'>And Joshua the son of Nun was full of the spirit of wisdom, for Moses had laid his hands on him. And the sons of Israel listened to him, and did as the LORD commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.10'>And never since has a prophet like Moses arisen in Israel, whom the LORD knew face to face,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.11'>in all the signs and the wonders which the LORD sent him to do in the land of Egypt, to Pharaoh, and to all his servants, and to all his land,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.12'>and in all that mighty hand, and in all the great terror which Moses showed in the eyes of all Israel.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>