<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='mkjv1962' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='mkjv1962'>
        <title>Modern KJV 1963</title>
        <contributor>xxx</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy</subject>
        <date>2009-01-23</date>
        <description>Modern King James Version of the Holy Bible 1962</description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>mkjv1962</identifier>
        <source/>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Jonah'>
      <chapter osisID='Jonah.1'>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.1'>And the Word of Jehovah came to Jonah the son of Amittai, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.2'>Arise, go to Nineveh, that great city, and cry against it; for their evil has come up before Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.3'>But Jonah rose up to flee to Tarshish from the presence of Jehovah. And he went down to Joppa. And he found a ship going to Tarshish. And he gave its fare, and went down into it, in order to go with them to Tarshish, away from the sight of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.4'>But Jehovah hurled a great wind into the sea, and there was a great storm in the sea, so that the ship [was] thought to be broken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.5'>Then the seamen were afraid, and each man cried to his god. And they threw out the [ship's] articles in the ship, into the sea in order to lighten [it]. But Jonah had gone down into the hold of the ship; and he lay there, and was fast asleep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.6'>And the chief of the seaman came to him and said to him, What [is it] to you, O sound sleeper? Arise, call upon your God! It may be that our god will notice us, and we will not perish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.7'>And they said, each one to his fellow, Come and let us cast lots, so that we may know who has caused this evil [to occur] to us. And they cast lots, and the lot fell on Jonah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.8'>Then they said to him, Please tell us, for what reason this evil [has come] on us. What is your business? And where do you come from? Where [is] your country? And of what people [are] you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.9'>And he said to them, I [am] a Hebrew; and I fear Jehovah, the God of heaven, who has made the sea and the dry land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.10'>Then the men were afraid [with] a great fear. And they said to him, What is this you have done? For the men knew that he was fleeing from before the face of Jehovah, because he had told them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.11'>Then they said to him, What shall we do to you, that the sea may be calm to us? For the sea was going on and being stormy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.12'>And he said to them, Take me up and throw me out into the sea. And the sea shall be calm to you; for I know that this great storm [has come] on you for my sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.13'>But the men rowed hard to bring it to the land; but they could not, for the sea was going on and being stormy against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.14'>And they cried to Jehovah and said, We beg You, O Jehovah, we beg You, let us not perish for this man's life, and do not lay on us innocent blood. For You, O Jehovah, have done as it pleased You.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.15'>And they lifted Jonah up and threw him out into the sea; and the sea ceased from its raging.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.16'>Then the men feared Jehovah exceedingly, and offered a sacrifice to Jehovah, and vowed vows.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.1.17'>And Jehovah had prepared a great fish to swallow up Jonah. And Jonah was in the belly of the fish three days and three nights.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jonah.2'>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.2.1'>And Jonah prayed to Jehovah his God out of the fish's belly,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.2.2'>and he said, I cried to Jehovah from my distress. And He answered me. Out of the belly of Sheol I cried for help, [and] You heard my voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.2.3'>For You cast me [into the] depths of the seas, and the current surrounded me. All Your breakers and Your waves passed over me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.2.4'>Then I said, I am cast off from Your eyes, yet I will look again toward Your holy temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.2.5'>Waters encompassed me, [even] to the soul; the depth closed around me; the seaweed was bound to my head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.2.6'>I went down to the bottoms of the mountains; the earth with her bars was around me forever; yet You have brought up my life from the pit, O Jehovah my God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.2.7'>When my soul fainted within me, I remembered Jehovah; and my prayer came in to You, into Your holy temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.2.8'>They who take heed to lying vanities forsake their kindness;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.2.9'>but I will sacrifice to You with the voice of thanksgiving; I will fulfill that which I have vowed. Salvation [belongs] to Jehovah!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.2.10'>And Jehovah spoke to the fish, and it vomited Jonah out on the dry land.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jonah.3'>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.3.1'>And the Word of Jehovah came to Jonah the second time, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.3.2'>Arise, go to Nineveh, that great city, and cry out to it the proclamation that I am declaring to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.3.3'>And Jonah arose and went to Nineveh, according to the Word of Jehovah. And Nineveh was a very great city of three days' journey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.3.4'>And Jonah began to enter into the city a day's journey, and he cried and said, Yet forty days and Nineveh shall be overthrown!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.3.5'>And the people of Nineveh believed God. And they called a fast, and put on sackcloth, from the greatest of them even to the least of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.3.6'>For word came to the king of Nineveh, and he arose from his throne. And he laid his robe from him, and covered himself [with] sackcloth, and sat in ashes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.3.7'>And he cried out and said in Nineveh by the decree of the king and his great ones, saying, Do not let man or beast, herd or flock taste anything; do not let them feed, nor drink water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.3.8'>But let man and animal be covered [with] sackcloth, and cry mightily to God. And let them each one turn from his evil way, and from the violence that [is] in their hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.3.9'>Who knows? He may repent, and God may have pity and turn away from the glow of His anger, so that we do not perish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.3.10'>And God saw their works, that they turned from their evil way. And God was compassionate over the evil that He had said to do to them, and He did not do [it].</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jonah.4'>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.4.1'>But it [was] a great calamity in Jonah's sight, and it kindled [anger] in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.4.2'>And he prayed to Jehovah and said, Please, O Jehovah, [was] this not my saying when I was still in my land? On account of this I fled before to Tarshish. For I knew that You [are] a gracious God, and merciful, slow to anger, and of great kindness, and One who repents over calamity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.4.3'>And now, O Jehovah, I beseech You, take my life from me. For better [is] my death than my life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.4.4'>And Jehovah said, Is anger rightly kindled in you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.4.5'>And Jonah went out of the city and sat on the east of the city. And he made himself a booth there and sat under it in the shade, until he might see what would happen in the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.4.6'>And Jehovah God prepared a plant, and it came up over Jonah, to be shade over his head, in order to deliver him from his misery. And Jonah rejoiced [with] great joy over the plant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.4.7'>But God prepared a worm as the morning dawned the next day. And it struck the plant, and it withered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.4.8'>And it happened when the sun shone, God ordained a scorching east wind. And the sun beat on the head of Jonah, so that he fainted. And he asked for his life to die. And he said, Better [is] my death than my life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.4.9'>And God said to Jonah, Is your anger rightly kindled over the plant? And he said, My anger is rightly kindled, [even] to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.4.10'>And Jehovah said, You have had pity on the plant, for which you had not labored, nor made it grow, which was a son of a night, and perished the son of a night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jonah.4.11'>And should I not spare Nineveh, that great city, in which are more than a hundred and twenty thousand men who do not know between [their] right [and their] left hand, besides much cattle?</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>