<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='mkjv1962' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='mkjv1962'>
        <title>Modern KJV 1963</title>
        <contributor>xxx</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy</subject>
        <date>2009-01-23</date>
        <description>Modern King James Version of the Holy Bible 1962</description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>mkjv1962</identifier>
        <source/>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Lam'>
      <chapter osisID='Lam.1'>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.1'>How alone sits the city [that was] full of people! She has become like a widow, [once] great among the nations, a noblewoman among the nations, [but now] has become a tribute-payer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.2'>She bitterly weeps in the night, and her tears [are] on her cheeks; among all her lovers, she has none to comfort her. All her friends have dealt deceitfully with her; they became her enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.3'>Judah went into captivity because of affliction, and from great slavery. She dwells among the nations; she finds no rest; all her pursuers have overtaken her between the narrows.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.4'>The roads of Zion mourn without [any] going to the appointed feasts. All her gates are deserted; her priests sigh; her virgins are afflicted, and she [is] in bitterness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.5'>Her enemies have become as chief; her haters are at ease; for the LORD has afflicted her for the multitude of her sins. Her children have gone, captive before the enemy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.6'>And from the daughter of Zion all her beauty has departed. Her rulers have become like bucks: they find no pasture, and they have gone without strength before the pursuer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.7'>[In the] days of her affliction and her wandering Jerusalem remembered all her desirable things from previous days; when her people fell into the hand of the foe; and there is no ally for her. The foes saw her; they laughed at her annihilation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.8'>Jerusalem has grievously sinned, therefore she has been removed. All knowing her despise her because they saw her nakedness; yea, she sighs and turns backward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.9'>Her uncleanness [is] in her skirts; she did not remember her end, and has gone down astoundingly. There is no comforter for her. O LORD, behold my affliction, for the enemy has magnified [himself].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.10'>The enemy has spread out his hand upon all her desirable things; for she has seen the nations enter her holy place, whom You commanded that they should not enter into Your congregation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.11'>All her people sigh; they seek bread. They have given their desirable things for food to relieve the soul. See, O LORD, and look on [me], for I have become vile.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.12'>[Is it] nothing to you, all you who pass by? Behold and see if there is any sorrow like my sorrow which is done to me, with which the LORD has afflicted [me] in the day of His fierce anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.13'>From above He has sent fire into my bones and it has laid them low. He has spread a net for my feet; He has turned me back; He has made me amazed [and] faint all the day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.14'>The yoke of my transgressions is bound by His hand; they intertwine; they rise on my neck. He has made my strength to falter; the LORD has delivered me into [their] hands. I am not able to rise up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.15'>The LORD has trampled all my mighty ones in my midst; He has called a gathering against me to crush my young men. The LORD has trod the virgin daughter of Judah, [as] in a winepress.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.16'>For these I weep; my eye, my eye runs down [with] water, because the comforter who could refresh my soul is far from me. My sons are desolated because the enemy prevails.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.17'>Zion spreads forth her hands; none [is] comforting to me; the LORD has commanded concerning Jacob that his enemies [should be] all around him; Jerusalem has become as an impure thing among them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.18'>The LORD [is] righteous, for I have rebelled against His command. I beseech you, all peoples, hear and behold my sorrow. My virgins and my young men went into exile.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.19'>I called for my lovers, [but] they deceived me; my priests and my elders expired in the city while they sought food for them to bring back their life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.20'>Behold, O LORD, for I [am] in trouble; my inward parts ferment; my heart is turned within me, for I have grievously rebelled. On the outside the sword bereaves; in the house [it is] as death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.21'>They hear that I sigh; [there is] none to comfort me. All my enemies have heard my evil; they are glad that You have done [it]. You will bring the day [that] You have called, and they shall be like me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.1.22'>Let all their wickedness come before You; and do to them as You have done to me for all my transgressions. For my sighs [are] many, and my heart [is] faint.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lam.2'>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.1'>How the Lord has covered the daughter of Zion with a cloud in His anger! He cast down the beauty of Israel from the heavens to the earth and remembered not His footstool in the day of His anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.2'>The Lord swallowed up all the dwelling-places of Jacob [and] has not pitied. In His wrath He has thrown down the strongholds of the daughter of Judah; He has brought [them] down to the ground. He has defiled the kingdom and its rulers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.3'>He has cut off all the horn of Israel in [His] fierce anger; He has drawn back His right hand from before the enemy, and He burned against Jacob like flaming fire [which] devours all around.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.4'>He has bent His bow like an enemy; [He stood with] His right hand like an adversary, and killed all [who were] desirable to the eye in the tabernacle of the daughter of Zion. He poured out His fury like fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.5'>The LORD was like an enemy; He swallowed up Israel; He has swallowed up all her palaces, [and] destroyed His strongholds. And [He] has increased mourning and weeping in the daughter of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.6'>And He violated His booth like a garden, [and] destroyed His meeting places. The LORD caused the meeting places and sabbaths to be forgotten in Zion, and He despised the king and the priest in the fury of His anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.7'>The LORD has cast off His altar; He rejected His sanctuary; He has given up the walls of her palaces into the hater's hand. They gave a noise in the house of the LORD, as a day of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.8'>The LORD purposed to destroy the wall of the daughter of Zion; He has stretched out a line; He has not withdrawn His hand from swallowing, and He made rampart and wall lament; they languish together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.9'>Her gates have sunk in the ground; He has destroyed and broken her bars. Her kings and her rulers [are] among the nations. The law is no more; also her prophets also find no vision from the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.10'>The elders of the daughter of Zion sit upon the ground and [are] silent; they send up dust on their heads; they gird on sackclothes. The virgins of Jerusalem hang down their heads to the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.11'>My eyes fail with tears; my inward parts ferment; my liver is poured on the ground for the ruin of the daughter of my people, in that the children and the babies faint in the streets of the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.12'>They say to their mothers, Where [are] grain and wine? In their fainting [they are] like the wounded in the streets of the city, in their pouring out their lives to their mothers' bosom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.13'>What can I testify for you? What thing shall I compare to you, O daughter of Jerusalem? What shall I equal to you, so that I may comfort you, O virgin daughter of Zion? For your break [is] great like the sea! Who can heal you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.14'>Your prophets have seen false and foolish things for you, and they have not uncovered your iniquity, to turn away your captivity; but they have seen false oracles and seductions for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.15'>All who pass by clap [their] hands at you; they hiss and wag their head at the daughter of Jerusalem, [saying], Is this the city which they called the perfection of beauty, the joy of the whole earth?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.16'>All your enemies have opened their mouth against you; they hiss and gnash the teeth; they say, We have swallowed [her] up. Certainly this [is] the day that we looked for; we have found, we have seen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.17'>The LORD has done [what] He has purposed; He has fulfilled His word which He commanded from the days of old. He has thrown down and not pitied. And He caused your hater to rejoice over you; He has set up the horn of your foes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.18'>Their heart cried to the LORD. O wall of the daughter of Zion, let tears run down like a torrent day and night; give yourself no rest. Let not the daughter of your eye cease.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.19'>Arise, cry out in the night. At the beginning of the watches, pour out your heart like water before the face of the LORD. Lift up your hands toward Him for the life of your children who are faint for hunger in the head of every street.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.20'>Behold, O LORD, and consider to whom You have done this. Shall the women eat their fruit, children of tender care? Shall the priest and the prophet be killed in the holy place of the Lord?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.21'>Young and old lie on the ground in the streets; my virgins and my young men have fallen by the sword. You have killed [them] in the day of Your anger; You have killed and not pitied.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.2.22'>You have called as in a solemn day my terrors all around, and there was not an escaped one or a survivor in the day of the LORD's anger. Those whom I have nursed and multiplied, my enemy has consumed.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lam.3'>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.1'>I the man have seen affliction by the rod of His wrath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.2'>He has led me and made [me] go in darkness and not into light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.3'>Surely He turned [against me]; He turns His hand all the day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.4'>He has wasted my flesh and my skin; He has broken my bones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.5'>He built against me and has circled [me] with bitterness and hardship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.6'>He has made me live in dark places, like the dead of old.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.7'>He has set a fence around me and I cannot go out; He has made my bronze [chain] heavy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.8'>Also when I cry and shout, He shuts out my prayer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.9'>He walled up my ways with cut stone; my paths are crooked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.10'>He [was] a bear lying in wait for me, a lion in secret places.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.11'>He has turned my ways aside and torn me in pieces. He made me desolate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.12'>He has bent His bow and set me as a mark for the arrow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.13'>He has caused the arrows of His quiver to enter into my inward parts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.14'>I was a mockery to all my people, their song all the day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.15'>He has filled me with bitterness [and] made me drunk [with] wormwood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.16'>He also broke my teeth with gravel; He has covered me in the ashes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.17'>And You cast off my soul from peace; I have forgotten blessedness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.18'>And I said, My strength and my hope from the LORD [are] gone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.19'>Remember my affliction and my wandering, [as] wormwood and bitterness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.20'>My soul vividly remembers and bows down on me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.21'>I recall this to my mind; therefore I hope.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.22'>[It is] by the LORD's kindnesses that we are not destroyed, because His mercies never fail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.23'>[They are] new every morning; great [is] Your faithfulness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.24'>The LORD [is] my portion, says my soul; therefore I will hope in Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.25'>The LORD [is] good to those who wait for Him, to the soul who seeks Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.26'>[It is] good that one should hope for the salvation of the LORD, even in silence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.27'>[It is] good for a man that he bear the yoke in his youth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.28'>He sits alone and keeps silence because He laid [it] on him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.29'>He puts his mouth in the dust, if perhaps there may be hope.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.30'>He gives [his] cheek to Him who strikes him; he is filled with reproach.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.31'>For the Lord will not cast off forever;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.32'>for though He causes grief, yet He will have pity according to the multitude of His kindnesses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.33'>For He does not afflict from His heart, nor does He grieve the sons of men;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.34'>to crush all the prisoners of the earth under his feet;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.35'>to turn aside the right of a man before the face of the Most High;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.36'>to pervert a man in his cause-- [this] the LORD does not see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.37'>Who [is] this [who] speaks, and it occurs, [when] the Lord does not command it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.38'>From the mouth of the Most High does not go out the evil and the good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.39'>What? Should mankind complain, a living man, because of his sins?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.40'>Let us search and try our ways, and turn again to the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.41'>Let us lift up our heart [and] hands to God in Heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.42'>We have sinned and have rebelled; You have not forgiven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.43'>You have wrapped Yourself with anger and pursued us; You have slain; You have not pitied.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.44'>You have wrapped Yourself with a cloud from [any] prayer passing through.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.45'>You have made us [as] the sweepings and garbage in the midst of the peoples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.46'>All our enemies have opened their mouths against us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.47'>Fear and a pit have come to us, shame and ruin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.48'>Streams of water run down my eye for the ruin of the daughter of my people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.49'>My eye flows out and does not cease, from there being no intermission,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.50'>until the LORD shall look down and behold from Heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.51'>My eye pains my soul because of all the daughters of my city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.52'>My haters have hunted me, like a bird, without cause.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.53'>They have cut off my life in the pit, and cast a stone at me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.54'>Waters flowed over my head; [then] I said, I am cut off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.55'>I called on Your name, O LORD, out of the lowest pit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.56'>You have heard my voice; do not hide Your ear at my relief, at my cry for help.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.57'>You drew near in the day [that] I called on You; You said, Fear not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.58'>O Lord, You strove for the causes of my soul; You redeemed my life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.59'>O Jehovah, You have seen my wrong; judge my cause.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.60'>You have seen all their vengeance, all their plots against me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.61'>You have heard their reproach, O LORD, all their plots against me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.62'>the lips of those who rose up against me, and their scheming against me all the day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.63'>Behold their sitting down and their rising up; I [am] their song.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.64'>You will return to them a recompense, O LORD, according to the work of their hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.65'>You will give them dullness of heart, Your curse on them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.3.66'>Pursue and destroy them in anger from under the heavens of the LORD.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lam.4'>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.1'>How the gold has become dim; the fine gold has changed! The stones of the sanctuary are poured out at the head of every street.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.2'>The precious sons of Zion are weighed against pure gold; how they are counted as earthen vessels, the work of a potter's hand!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.3'>Even the jackals draw out the breast; they suckle their young ones. The daughter of my people [is] cruel, like the ostriches in the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.4'>The suckling's tongue cleaves to his palate in thirst; the young children ask bread; there is no breaking to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.5'>Those who ate delicacies are desolate in the streets; those reared in scarlet embrace dunghills.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.6'>And the iniquity of the daughter of my people is heaped more than the sin of Sodom, overthrown as [in] a moment, and no hands spun on her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.7'>Her Nazarites [were] purer than snow, whiter than milk; they [were] redder [of] bone than corals; their cuttings [as] lapis lazuli, [azure blue].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.8'>Their appearance is blacker than soot; they are not recognized in the streets; their skin has shriveled on their bones; it is dried up; it has become like wood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.9'>Better [are] the ones slain by the sword than the ones slain by hunger; those who pine away, pierced because the fruits of my fields [failed].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.10'>The hands of the pitying women have boiled their own children; they became their food in the ruin of the daughter of my people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.11'>The LORD has fulfilled His fury; He has poured out His fierce anger, and has kindled a fire in Zion, and it has devoured its foundations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.12'>The kings of the earth, and all the people of the world, would not have believed that the foe and the hater would go into Jerusalem's gates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.13'>For the sins of her prophets [and] the iniquities of her priests, shedding the blood of the just in her midst,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.14'>they reeled blind in the streets; they are defiled with blood, so that not [any] can touch their clothes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.15'>They cried to them, Depart! Unclean! Depart, depart! Touch not! Indeed they fled and reeled; they said among the nations, They will not continue to live [there].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.16'>The face of the LORD has shared them out; He will no longer look on them; they did not respect the persons of the priests; they did not favor the elders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.17'>While we are, our eyes fail, for our help is vain; in our watching we have watched for a nation; it does not save.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.18'>They hunted our steps from going in our streets; our end was near, our days were fulfilled, for our end has come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.19'>Our pursuers were swifter than the eagles of the heavens; they pursued us on the mountains, they lay in wait for us in the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.20'>The breath of our nostrils, the anointed [of] the LORD, was taken in their pits; of whom we said, In his shadow we shall live among the nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.21'>Rejoice and be glad, O daughter of Edom, who lives in the land of Uz. The cup also shall pass through unto you; you shall be drunken and stripped naked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.4.22'>The punishment of your iniquity [is] fulfilled, O daughter of Zion; He will exile you no more. He will visit your iniquity, O daughter of Edom; He will expose your sins.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lam.5'>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.1'>Remember, O LORD, what has been to us; look down and see our shame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.2'>Our inheritance has turned to aliens, our houses to foreigners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.3'>We are orphans and fatherless; our mothers [are] as widows.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.4'>We have drunk our water for silver; our wood comes for a price.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.5'>We [are] pursued on our necks; we grow weary; rest is not given to us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.6'>We have given the hand [to] Egypt, to Assyria, to be satisfied with bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.7'>Our fathers have sinned [and are] not; we have borne their iniquities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.8'>Servants rule over us; [there is] no rescuer out of their hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.9'>We bring in our bread with our souls, because of the sword of the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.10'>Our skin [is] hot like an oven because of the fever heat of famine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.11'>They raped the women in Zion, virgins in the cities of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.12'>Rulers were hanged by the hand; the faces of elders were not honored.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.13'>They took the young men [to] grind, and the youths stumbled at the wood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.14'>The elders have ceased from the gate, the young men from their music.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.15'>The joy of our heart has ceased; our dance has turned into mourning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.16'>The crown has fallen [from] our head. Woe now to us! For we have sinned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.17'>Our heart is faint for this; our eyes are dim for these [things].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.18'>On the mountain of Zion [is] laid waste, the foxes walk on it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.19'>You, O LORD, remain forever; Your throne to generation and generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.20'>Why do You forget us forever [and] forsake us the length of days?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.21'>Return us to You, O LORD, and we will turn; renew our days as of old,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lam.5.22'>unless You have utterly rejected us; You are very angry against us.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>