<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='mkjv1962' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='mkjv1962'>
        <title>Modern KJV 1963</title>
        <contributor>xxx</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy</subject>
        <date>2009-01-23</date>
        <description>Modern King James Version of the Holy Bible 1962</description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>mkjv1962</identifier>
        <source/>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Neh'>
      <chapter osisID='Neh.1'>
        <verse osisID='Neh.1.1'>The words of Nehemiah the son of Hachaliah. And it happened in the month Chisleu, in the twentieth year, as I was in Shushan the palace,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.1.2'>Hanani, one of my brothers, came, he and men of Judah. And I asked them concerning the Jews who had escaped, who were left of the captivity, and concerning Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.1.3'>And they said to me, The remnant left of the captivity there in the province [is] in great affliction and shame. And the wall of Jerusalem [is] broken down, and its gates are burned with fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.1.4'>And it happened when I heard these words, I sat down and wept. And I mourned [for] days, and fasted, and prayed before the God of Heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.1.5'>And I said, I pray You, O LORD God of Heaven, the great and awesome God who keeps covenant and mercy for those who love Him and keep His commandments;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.1.6'>let Your ear now be open, and Your eyes open, so that You may hear the prayer of Your servant, which I pray before You now, day and night, for the sons of Israel Your servants, and confessing the sins of the sons of Israel which we have sinned against You. Both I and my father's house have sinned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.1.7'>We have acted very wickedly against You, and have not kept the commandments nor the statutes nor the judgments which You commanded Your servant Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.1.8'>I pray You, remember the word that You commanded Your servant Moses, saying, [If] you sin, I will scatter you among the nations,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.1.9'>but [if] you turn to Me, and keep My commandments and do them, though you were cast out to the outermost part of the heavens, [yet] I will gather you from there and will bring you to the place that I have chosen to set My name there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.1.10'>And these [are] Your servants and Your people whom You have redeemed by Your great power and by Your strong hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.1.11'>O LORD, I pray You, let now Your ear be open to the prayer of Your servant, and to the prayer of Your servants who desire to fear Your name. And I pray You, bless Your servant today, and grant him mercy in the sight of this man. (For I was the king's cupbearer.)</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Neh.2'>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.1'>And it happened in the month Nisan, in the twentieth year of Artaxerxes the king, wine [was] before him. And I took up the wine and gave [it] to the king. Now I had not been sad in his presence before.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.2'>And the king said to me, Why [is] your face sad, since you [are] not sick? This [is] nothing but sorrow of heart. Then I was very much afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.3'>And [I] said to the king, Let the king live forever. Why should not my face be sad, when the city, the place of my fathers' tombs, [lies] waste, and its gates are burned with fire?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.4'>And the king said to me, For what do you ask? So I prayed to the God of Heaven,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.5'>and I said to the king, If it please the king, and if your servant has found favor in your sight, I pray that you would send me to Judah, to the city of my fathers' tombs, so that I may build it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.6'>And the king said to me (the queen also sitting by him), For how long shall your journey be? And when will you return? So it pleased the king to send me, and I set him a time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.7'>And I said to the king, If it please the king, let letters be given me to the governors Beyond the River, so that they may let me pass through until I come to Judah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.8'>and a letter to Asaph the keeper of the kings forest, so that he may give me timber to make beams for the gates of the palace which [belong] to the house, and for the wall of the city, and for the house into which I shall enter. And the king granted me what I asked, according to the good hand of my God upon me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.9'>And I came to the governors of [the province] Beyond the River and gave them the king's letters. And the king had sent captains of the army and horsemen with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.10'>And Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobiah the servant, the Ammonite, heard. And it grieved them very much that there had come a man to seek the good of the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.11'>And I came to Jerusalem and was there three days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.12'>And I arose in the night, I and some few men with me. And I did not tell to a man what my God had put in my heart to do at Jerusalem. And [there was] no animal with me, except the animal that I rode upon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.13'>And I went out by night by the Valley Gate, even before the Jackal Fountain, and to the Dung Gate, and looked at the walls of Jerusalem which were broken down, and its gates which were burned with fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.14'>And I went on to the Fountain Gate, and to the King's Pool. But [there was] no place for the animal that was under me to pass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.15'>And I went up in the night by the brook and looked at the wall, and turned back, and entered by the Valley Gate, and returned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.16'>And the rulers did not know where I had gone, nor what I was doing. Nor had I told the Jews as yet, nor to the priests, nor to the nobles, nor to the rulers, nor to the rest that did the work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.17'>And I said to them, You see the distress that we [are] in, how Jerusalem is wasted, and the gates of it are burned with fire. Come and let us build up the wall of Jerusalem, so that we may no more be a reproach.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.18'>And I told them of the hand of my God which was good upon me, and also the king's words that he had spoken to me. And they said, Let us rise up to build. So they made their hands strong for good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.19'>But when Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobiah the servant, the Ammonite, and Geshem the Arabian, heard, they laughed us to scorn, and despised us. And they said, What [is] this that you do? Will you rebel against the king?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.2.20'>And I answered them and said to them, The God of Heaven, He will bless us, and we, His servants, will arise and build. But you have no portion or right or memorial in Jerusalem.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Neh.3'>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.1'>Then Eliashib the high priest rose up with his brothers the priests, and they built the Sheep Gate. They sanctified it and set up its doors, even to the Tower of Meah they sanctified it, to the Tower of Hananeel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.2'>And next to him the men of Jericho built. And next to them Zaccur the son of Imri built.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.3'>But the sons of Hassenaah built the Fish Gate, who laid its beams and set up its doors, its locks, and its bars.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.4'>And next to them Meremoth the son of Urijah, the son of Koz repaired. And next to them Meshullam the son of Berechiah, the son of Meshezabeel repaired. And next to them Zadok the son of Baana repaired.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.5'>And next to them the Tekoites repaired. But their nobles did not put their necks to the work of their Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.6'>And the Old Gate was repaired by Jehoiada the son of Paseah, and Meshullam the son of Besodeiah. They laid its beams and set up its doors and its locks and its bars.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.7'>And next to them Melatiah of Gibeon repaired, and Jadon of Meron, the men of Gibeon and of Mizpah, to the throne of the governor Beyond the River.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.8'>Next to him Uzziel the son of Harhaiah, of the goldsmiths, repaired. And next to him Hananiah, the son of [one of] the perfumers, repaired. And they fortified Jerusalem to the Broad Wall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.9'>And next to them Rephaiah the son of Hur, the ruler of the half part of Jerusalem repaired.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.10'>Next to them Jedaiah the son of Harumaph repaired, even across from his house. And next to him Hattush the son of Hashabniah repaired.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.11'>Malchijah the son of Harim and Hashub the son of Pahath-moab, repaired the other piece, and the Tower of the Furnaces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.12'>And next to him Shallum the son of Halohesh, the ruler of the half part of Jerusalem, he and his daughters repaired.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.13'>Hanun, and the people of Zanoah, repaired the Valley Gate. They built it, and set up its doors, its locks, and its bars, and a thousand cubits on the wall to the Dung Gate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.14'>But the Dung Gate was repaired by Malchiah the son of Rechab, the ruler of part of Beth-haccerem. He built it and set up its doors, its locks, and its bars.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.15'>And the Fountain Gate was repaired by Shallum the son of Colhozeh, the ruler of part of Mizpah. He built it and covered it, and set up its doors, its locks, and its bars, and the wall of the Pool of Shelah by the King's Garden, and to the stairs that go down from the City of David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.16'>After him Nehemiah the son of Azbuk, the ruler of the half part of Beth-zur, repaired across from the tombs of David, and to the pool that was made, and to the house of the mighty men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.17'>After him the Levites, Rehum the son of Bani, repaired. Next to him Hashabiah, the ruler of the half part of Keilah, repaired in his part.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.18'>After him their brothers, Bavai the son of Henadad, the ruler of the half part of Keilah, repaired.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.19'>And next to him, Ezer the son of Jeshua, the ruler of Mizpah, repaired another piece across from the ascent to the armory at the corner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.20'>After him Baruch the son of Zabbai earnestly repaired the other piece, from the corner to the door of the house of Eliashib the high priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.21'>After him Meremoth the son of Urijah the son of Koz repaired another piece, from the door of the house of Eliashib even to the end of the house of Eliashib.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.22'>And after him the priests, the men of the plain, repaired.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.23'>After him Benjamin and Hashub repaired across from their house. After him Azariah the son of Maaseiah the son of Ananiah repaired by his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.24'>After him Binnui the son of Henadad repaired another piece, from the house of Azariah to the corner even to the tower.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.25'>Palal the son of Uzai [repaired] across from the corner, and the tower which lies out from the king's high house, by the court of the prison. After him Pedaiah the son of Parosh [repaired].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.26'>And the temple-slaves who lived in Ophel repaired across from the Water Gate toward the east, and the tower that sticks out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.27'>After them the Tekoites repaired another piece, opposite the great tower that sticks out, even to the wall of Ophel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.28'>The priests repaired from above the Horse Gate, every one across from his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.29'>After them Zadok the son of Immer repaired across from his house. After him Shemaiah the son of Shechaniah, the keeper of the East Gate, repaired.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.30'>After him Hananiah the son of Shelemiah, and Hanun the sixth son of Zalaph repaired another piece. After him Meshullam the son of Berechiah repaired across from his room.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.31'>After him Malchiah the goldsmith's son repaired to the place of the temple-slaves, and of the merchants, across from the Miphkad Gate, and to the going up of the corner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.3.32'>And between the going up of the corner to the Sheep Gate the goldsmiths and the merchants repaired.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Neh.4'>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.1'>But it happened when Sanballat heard that we built the wall, he was angry and greatly displeased, and mocked the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.2'>And he spoke before his brothers and the army of Samaria, and said, What are these feeble Jews doing? Will they fortify themselves? Will they sacrifice? Will they make an end in a day? Will they bring to life the stones out of the heaps of the rubbish which are burned?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.3'>And Tobiah the Ammonite [was] beside him, and he said, Even that which they build, if a fox goes up, he shall even break down their stone wall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.4'>Oh our God, hear, for we are despised. And turn their curse upon their own head, and give them for a prey in the land of captivity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.5'>And do not cover their iniquity, and do not let their sin be blotted out from before You. For they have provoked [You] to anger before the builders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.6'>So we built the wall, and all the wall was joined together to the half of it. For the people had a mind to work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.7'>And it happened, when Sanballat and Tobiah, and the Arabians, and the Ammonites, and the Ashdodites, heard that the walls of Jerusalem had gone up, [and] that the breaks were being filled, they were very angry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.8'>And all of them conspired together to come [and] fight against Jerusalem and do harm to it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.9'>But we made our prayer to our God, and set a watch against them day and night, because of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.10'>And Judah said, The strength of the carriers of burdens is weakening, and [there is] much rubbish, so that we are not able to build the wall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.11'>And our foes have said, They shall not know, or see, until we come in the middle of them, and kill them, and cause the work to cease.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.12'>And it happened when the Jews who lived near them came in, they said to us ten times, From all places where you shall turn to us, [they will be against us].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.13'>And I stationed in the lower places behind the wall, [and] on the higher places, I even set the people according to their families with their sword, their spears, and their bows.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.14'>And I looked and rose up, and said to the nobles and to the rulers and to the rest of the people, Do not be afraid of them. Remember the LORD, [who is] great and terrible, and fight for your brothers, your sons, and your daughters, your wives, and your houses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.15'>And it happened when our enemies heard that it was known to us, and that God had brought their counsel to nothing, all of us returned to the wall, each one to his work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.16'>And it was from that time forth that half of my servants worked in the work, and the other half of them held the spears, the shields, and the bows, and the scale-armor. And the rulers [were] behind all the house of Judah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.17'>the ones who built on the wall, and the ones who carried burdens; with those who were lifting, one a worker in the work, and one held a weapon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.18'>For [of] the builders, [each] one had his sword tied by his side, and built. And he who sounded the trumpet [was] beside me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.19'>And I said to the nobles, and to the rulers, and to the rest of the people, The work [is] great and large, and we are separated upon the wall, far from one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.20'>In whatever place you hear the sound of the trumpet, gather there to us. Our God will fight for us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.21'>And we labored in the work. And half of them held the spears from the rising of the morning until the stars appeared.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.22'>Also at the same time I said to the people, Let everyone with his servant stay inside Jerusalem, so that in the night they may be a guard to us, and labor in the day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.4.23'>And none, I, nor my brothers, nor my servants, nor the men of the guard who followed me, none of us put off our clothes [except that] everyone [had] his vessel of water.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Neh.5'>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.1'>And there was a great cry of the people and of their wives against their brothers the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.2'>For certain ones said, We, our sons, and our daughters, [are] many. Let us get grain for them, so that we may eat and live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.3'>[Some] also said, We have mortgaged our lands, vineyards, and houses. Let us buy grain because of the famine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.4'>And [some] said, We have borrowed money on our lands and vineyards for the king's tax.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.5'>Yet now our flesh [is] like the flesh of our brothers, our sons like their sons. And, lo, we bring our sons and our daughters into bondage, to be slaves, and [some] of our daughters are brought into bondage. And [there is] no power for our hand, for other men have our lands and vineyards.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.6'>And I was very angry when I heard their cry and these words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.7'>And my heart within myself ruled, and I rebuked the nobles and the rulers, and said to them, You exact interest, [each] one from his brother. And I held a great gathering against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.8'>And I said to them, According to our ability we have redeemed our brothers, the Jews who were sold to the nations. And will you even sell your brothers? Or shall they be sold to us? And they were silent and did not find an answer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.9'>And I said, What you do [is] not good. Should you not walk in the fear of our God because of the reproach of the nations our enemies?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.10'>And also I, my brothers and my servants, might take from them silver and grain. Please let us leave this lending at interest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.11'>Please even today give back to them their lands, their vineyards, their olive-yards, and their houses, also the hundredth [part] of the money and of the grain, the wine, and the oil, that you take from them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.12'>And they said, We will restore, and will ask nothing from them. So we will do as you say. Then I called the priests and took an oath from them that they should do according to this promise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.13'>Also I shook my lap and said, So let God shake out every man from his house, and from his labor, who does not keep this promise, even may he be shaken out this way and emptied. And all the congregation said, amen, and praised the LORD. And the people did according to this promise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.14'>And from the time that I was chosen to be their governor in the land of Judah, from the twentieth year even to the thirty-second year of Artaxerxes the king, twelve years, I and my brothers have not eaten the bread of the governor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.15'>But the former governors that [had been] before me were too heavy upon the people, and had taken bread and wine from them, besides forty shekels of silver. Yes, even their servants bore rule over the people. But I did not do this, because of the fear of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.16'>And I also kept on in the work of this wall. Nor did we buy any land. And all my servants gathered there to the work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.17'>And at my table [were] a hundred and fifty of the Jews and rulers, besides those who came to us from among the nations around us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.18'>And that which [was] prepared daily [was] one ox and six choice sheep; and birds were prepared; and once in ten days store of all sorts of wine. Yet for all this I did not seek the bread of the governor, because the bondage was heavy upon this people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.5.19'>Think upon me, my God, for good, [according] to all that I have done for this people.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Neh.6'>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.1'>And it happened, when Sanballat, and Tobiah and Geshem the Arabian, and the rest of our enemies heard that I had built the wall, and that there was no break left in it (though at that time I had not set the doors on the gates),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.2'>Sanballat and Geshem sent to me, saying, Come, let us meet together in the villages in the plain of Ono. But they thought to do me harm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.3'>And I sent messengers to them, saying, I [am] doing a great work, so I cannot come down. Why should the work cease while I leave it and come down to you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.4'>And they sent to me four times in this way. And I answered them in the same way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.5'>Then Sanballat sent his servant to me in the same way the fifth time with an open letter in his hand, in which was written,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.6'>It is reported among the nations, and Gashmu says [it], that you and the Jews are thinking of rebelling, for this reason you build the wall, so that you may be their king, according to these words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.7'>And you have also set up prophets to preach about you at Jerusalem, saying, [There is] a king in Judah. And now it shall be reported to the king according to these words. And now come and let us talk it over together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.8'>And I sent to him saying, These things which you are saying are not happening, but you pretend them out of your own heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.9'>For they all were alarmers of us, saying, Their hands shall be weakened from the work so that it may not be done. And now, [O God], make my hands strong.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.10'>And I came to the house of Shemaiah the son of Delaiah the son of Mehetabeel, who [was] shut up. And he said, Let us meet together in the house of God, inside the temple, and let us shut the doors of the temple. For they will come to kill you. Yea, in the night they will come to kill you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.11'>And I said, Should [such] a man as I flee? And who, [being] as I [am], would go into the temple to save his life? I will not go in.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.12'>And, behold, I understood that God had not sent him, but that he said this prophecy against me because Tobiah and Sanballat had hired him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.13'>Therefore he [was] hired that I should be afraid, and do so, and I should sin, and be for them an evil name, with which they might reproach me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.14'>My God, think upon Tobiah and Sanballat according to these works of theirs, and on the prophetess Noadiah, and the rest of the prophets who would have made me afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.15'>And the wall was finished in the twenty-fifth [day] of Elul, in fifty-two days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.16'>And it happened when all our enemies heard, and all the nations around us saw, they were very much lowered in their own eyes. For they saw that this work was done by our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.17'>And in those days the nobles of Judah were increasing their letters going to Tobiah; and Tobiah's came to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.18'>For many in Judah [were] sworn to him because he [was] the son-in-law of Shechaniah the son of Arah, and his son Jehohanan had taken the daughter of Meshullam the son of Berechiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.6.19'>Also they reported his good deeds before me, and told my words to him. Tobiah sent letters to make me afraid.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Neh.7'>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.1'>And it happened when the wall was built, and I had set up the doors, and the gatekeepers and the singers and the Levites were chosen,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.2'>I gave my brother Hanani, and Hananiah the ruler of the palace, charge over Jerusalem. For he [was] a faithful man, and feared God above many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.3'>And I said to them, Do not let the gates of Jerusalem be opened until the sun is hot. And while they stand by, let them shut and bar the doors. And set guards from the people of Jerusalem, each one in his watch, and each one [to be] across from his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.4'>And the city [was] large and great, but the people in it [were] few, and the houses not built.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.5'>And my God put into my heart to gather together the nobles, and the rulers, and the people, so that they might be counted by genealogy. And I found a register of the genealogy of those who came up at the first. And I found written in it:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.6'>These [are] the sons of the province who went up out of the captivity, of those who had been carried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away. And they came again to Jerusalem and to Judah, every one to his city,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.7'>and came with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, Azariah, Raamiah, Nahamani, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispereth, Bigvai, Nehum, Baanah. The number of the men of the people of Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.8'>The sons of Parosh, two thousand and seventy-two.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.9'>The sons of Shephatiah, three hundred and seventy-two.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.10'>The sons of Arah, six hundred and fifty-two.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.11'>The sons of Pahath-moab, of the sons of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand, eight hundred and eighteen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.12'>The sons of Elam, a thousand two hundred and fifty-four.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.13'>The sons of Zattu, eight hundred and forty-five.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.14'>The sons of Zaccai, seven hundred and sixty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.15'>The sons of Binnui, six hundred and forty-eight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.16'>The sons of Bebai, six hundred and twenty-eight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.17'>The sons of Azgad, two thousand three hundred and twenty-two.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.18'>The sons of Adonikam, six hundred and sixty-seven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.19'>The sons of Bigvai, two thousand and sixty-seven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.20'>The sons of Adin, six hundred and fifty-five.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.21'>The sons of Ater of Hezekiah, ninety-eight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.22'>The sons of Hashum, three hundred and twenty-eight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.23'>The sons of Bezai, three hundred and twenty-four.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.24'>The sons of Hariph, a hundred and twelve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.25'>The sons of Gibeon, ninety-five.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.26'>The men of Bethlehem and Netophah, a hundred and eighty-eight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.27'>The men of Anathoth, a hundred and twenty-eight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.28'>The men of Beth-azmaveth, forty-two.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.29'>The men of Kirjath-jearim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred and forty-three.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.30'>The men of Ramah and Geba, six hundred and twenty-one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.31'>The men of Michmas, a hundred and twenty-two.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.32'>The men of Bethel and Ai, a hundred and twenty-three.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.33'>The men of the other Nebo, fifty-two.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.34'>The sons of the other Elam, a thousand two hundred and fifty-four.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.35'>The sons of Harim, three hundred and twenty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.36'>The sons of Jericho, three hundred and forty-five.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.37'>The sons of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred and twenty-one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.38'>The sons of Senaah, three thousand nine hundred and thirty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.39'>The priests: the sons of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred and seventy-three.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.40'>The sons of Immer, a thousand and fifty-two.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.41'>The sons of Pashur, a thousand two hundred and forty-seven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.42'>The sons of Harim, a thousand and seventeen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.43'>The Levites: the sons of Jeshua, of Kadmiel, [and] of the sons of Hodevah, seventy-four.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.44'>The singers: the sons of Asaph, a hundred and forty-eight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.45'>The gatekeepers: the sons of Shallum, the sons of Ater, the sons of Talmon, the sons of Akkub, the sons of Hatita, and the sons of Shobai, a hundred and thirty-eight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.46'>The temple slaves: the sons of Ziha, the sons of Hashupha, the sons of Tabbaoth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.47'>the sons of Keros, the sons of Sia, the sons of Padon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.48'>the sons of Lebana, the sons of Hagaba, the sons of Shalmai,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.49'>the sons of Hanan, the sons of Giddel, the sons of Gahar,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.50'>the sons of Reaiah, the sons of Rezin, the sons of Nekoda,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.51'>the sons of Gazzam, the sons of Uzza, the sons of Paseah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.52'>the sons of Besai, the sons of Meunim, the sons of Nephishesim,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.53'>the sons of Bakbuk, the sons of Hakupha, the sons of Harhur,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.54'>the sons of Bazlith, the sons of Mehida, the sons of Harsha,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.55'>the sons of Barkos, the sons of Sisera, the sons of Tamah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.56'>the sons of Neziah, the sons of Hatipha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.57'>The sons of Solomon's servants: the sons of Sotai, the sons of Sophereth, the sons of Perida,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.58'>the sons of Jaala, the sons of Darkon, the sons of Giddel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.59'>the sons of Shephatiah, the sons of Hattil, the sons of Pochereth of Zebaim, the sons of Amon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.60'>All the temple-slaves, and the sons of Solomon's servants, three hundred and ninety-two.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.61'>And these [were] they who went up from Tel-melah, Tel-haresha, Cherub, Addon, and Immer. But they could not show their father's house, nor their seed, whether they [were] of Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.62'>The sons of Delaiah, the sons of Tobiah, the sons of Nekoda, six hundred and forty-two.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.63'>And of the priests: the sons of Habaiah, the sons of Koz, the sons of Barzillai, who took [one] of the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite to wife, and was called after their name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.64'>These sought their register [among] those who were reckoned by genealogy, but it was not found. Therefore they were put out, as defiled from the priesthood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.65'>And the governor said to them that they should not eat of the holy things until there stood [up] a priest with Urim and Thummim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.66'>All the congregation together [was] forty-two thousand three hundred and sixty,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.67'>besides their manservants and their maidservants; these [were] seven thousand three hundred and thirty-seven. And they had two hundred and forty-five singing men and singing women.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.68'>Their horses were seven hundred and thirty-six; their mules, two hundred and forty-five;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.69'>camels, four hundred and thirty-five; and six thousand seven hundred and twenty asses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.70'>And some of the chiefs of the fathers gave to the work. The governor gave to the treasury a thousand darics of gold, fifty basins, and five hundred and thirty priest's garments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.71'>And [some] of the chiefs of the fathers gave to the treasury of the work twenty thousand darics of gold, and two thousand two hundred minas of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.72'>And what the rest of the people gave [was] twenty thousand darics of gold and two thousand minas of silver, and sixty-seven priests' garments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.7.73'>And the priests, and the Levites, and the gatekeepers, and the singers, and [some] of the people, and the temple slaves, and all Israel, lived in their cities. And when the seventh month came, the sons of Israel [were] in their cities.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Neh.8'>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.1'>And all the people gathered themselves as one man into the street before the water gate. And they spoke to Ezra the scribe to bring the Book of the Law of Moses, which the LORD had commanded to Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.2'>And Ezra the priest brought the Law before the congregation, both of men and women, and all that could hear with understanding, upon the first day of the seventh month.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.3'>And he read in it before the street in front of the Water Gate from the morning until noon, in front of the men and the women, and those who could understand. And the ears of all the people [listened] to the Book of the Law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.4'>And Ezra the scribe stood upon a pulpit of wood which they had made for the purpose. And beside him stood Mattithiah, and Shema, and Anaiah, and Urijah, and Hilkiah, and Maaseiah, on his right hand; and on his left hand, Pedaiah, and Mishael, and Malchiah, and Hashum, and Hashbadana, Zechariah, and Meshullam.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.5'>And Ezra opened the book in the sight of all the people, for he was above all the people. And when he opened it, all the people stood up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.6'>And Ezra blessed the LORD, the great God. And all the people answered, amen, amen, lifting up their hands. And they bowed their heads and worshiped the LORD with [their] faces to the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.7'>And Jeshua, and Bani, and Sherebiah, Jamin, Akkub, Shabbethai, Hodijah, Maaseiah, Kelita, Azariah, Jozabad, Hanan, Pelaiah, and the Levites, caused the people to understand the law. And the people [were] in their place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.8'>And they read in the Book of the Law of God, clearly. And they gave the sense, and caused [them] to understand the reading.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.9'>And Nehemiah, the governor, and Ezra the priest and scribe, and the Levites who taught the people, said to all the people, This day [is] holy to the LORD your God. Do not mourn or weep. For all the people wept when they heard the words of the law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.10'>Then he said to them, Go eat the fat and drink the sweet, and send portions to him for [whom] nothing is prepared. For [this] day [is] holy to our LORD. And do not be sorry, for the joy of the LORD [is] your strength.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.11'>And the Levites quieted all the people, saying, Be quiet, for the day [is] holy. And do not be grieved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.12'>And all the people went to eat, and to drink, and to send portions, and to make great rejoicing, because they had understood the words which were declared to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.13'>And on the second day the chief of the fathers of all the people, the priests, and the Levites, were gathered to Ezra the scribe, even to understand the words of the law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.14'>And they found written in the law which the LORD had commanded by Moses, that the sons of Israel should dwell in booths in the feast of the seventh month,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.15'>and that they should publish and proclaim in all their cities, and in Jerusalem, saying, Go forth to the mountain and bring olive branches and pine branches and myrtle branches and palm branches, and branches of thick trees, to make booths, as [it is] written.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.16'>And the people went out and brought in, and made themselves booths, each one upon his roof, and in their courts, and in the courts of the house of God, and in the street of the Water Gate, and in the street of the Gate of Ephraim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.17'>And all the congregation of those who had come again out of the captivity made booths, and sat under the booths. For since the days of Joshua the son of Nun until that day, the sons of Israel had not done so. And there was very great gladness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.8.18'>Also day by day, from the first day until the last day, he read in the Book of the Law of God. And they kept the feast seven days, and on the eighth [was] an assembly, according to the law.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Neh.9'>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.1'>And in the twenty-fourth day of this month, the sons of Israel were gathered with fasting and with sackcloth, and with earth upon them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.2'>And the seed of Israel separated themselves from all strangers, and stood and confessed their sins and the sins of their fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.3'>And they stood up in their place, and read in the Book of the Law of the LORD their God a fourth part of the day. And [another] fourth part they confessed and worshiped the LORD their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.4'>And stood upon the stairs, of the Levites, Jeshua, and Bani, Kadmiel, Shebaniah, Bunni, Sherebiah, Bani [and] Chenani, and cried with a loud voice to the LORD their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.5'>And the Levites, Jeshua, and Kadmiel, Bani, Hashabniah, Sherebiah, Hodijah, Shebaniah, [and] Pethahiah, said, Stand up and bless the LORD your God forever and ever. And blessed be Your glorious name, which is exalted above all blessing and praise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.6'>You, even You, [are] LORD alone. You have made the heavens, heaven of the heavens, with all their host, the earth, and all things on it, the seas, and all in them, and You preserve them all. And the host of the heavens worships You.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.7'>You [are] the LORD, the God who chose Abram and brought him out of Ur of the Chaldees, and gave him the name of Abraham,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.8'>and found his heart faithful before You, and made a covenant with him to give the land of the Canaanite, the Hittite, the Amorite, and the Perizzite, and the Jebusite, and the Girgashite, to give [ it] to his seed. And You have performed Your words, for You are righteous.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.9'>And You saw the affliction of our fathers in Egypt, and heard their cry by the Red Sea,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.10'>and gave out signs and wonders upon Pharaoh and upon all his servants and upon all the people of his land. For You knew that they were acting proudly against them. So You got Yourself a name, as today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.11'>And You divided the sea before them, so that they went through the midst of the sea on the dry land. And their pursuers You threw into the deep, like a stone into the mighty waters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.12'>And You led them in the day by a cloudy pillar, and in the night by a pillar of fire, to give them light in the way in which they should go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.13'>And You came down on Mount Sinai, and spoke with them from Heaven, and gave them right judgments and true laws, good statutes and commandments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.14'>And You made known to them Your holy sabbath, and commanded them commandments, statutes, and laws, by the hand of Moses Your servant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.15'>And You gave them bread from the heavens for their hunger, and brought forth water for them out of the rock for their thirst. And You promised them that they should go in to possess the land which You had sworn to give them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.16'>But they and our fathers acted proudly and hardened their necks, and did not listen to Your commandments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.17'>And they refused to obey, neither were they mindful of Your wonders which You did among them. But they hardened their necks, and in their rebellion appointed a captain to return to their bondage. But You [are] a God ready to pardon, gracious and merciful, slow to anger, and of great kindness, and did not forsake them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.18'>Yea, when they had made them a molten calf, and said, This [is] your God who brought you up out of Egypt, and had worked great blasphemies,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.19'>yet You in Your great mercies did not forsake them in the wilderness. The pillar of the cloud did not depart from them by day to lead them in the way, nor the pillar of fire by night, to show them light and the way in which they should go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.20'>You also gave Your good Spirit to teach them, and did not withhold Your manna from their mouth, and gave them water for their thirst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.21'>And forty years You sustained them in the wilderness. They lacked nothing; their clothes did not become old, and their feet did not swell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.22'>And You gave them kingdoms and nations, and divided them into corners. And they possessed the land of Sihon, and the land of the king of Heshbon, and the land of Og king of Bashan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.23'>And You multiplied their sons like the stars of the heavens, and brought them into the land concerning which You had promised to their fathers that they should go in to possess [it].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.24'>And the sons went in and possessed the land, and You humbled the people of the land before them, the Canaanites, and gave them into their hands, with their kings and the people of the land, so that they might do with them as they would.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.25'>And they took strong cities and a rich land, and possessed houses full of all goods, wells already dug, vineyards and olive-yards, and fruit trees in abundance. And they ate and were filled, and became fat, and delighted themselves in Your great goodness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.26'>But they were disobedient and rebelled against You, and cast Your law behind their backs. And they killed Your prophets who testified against them to turn them to You, and they worked great blasphemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.27'>And You delivered them into the hand of their enemies, who troubled them. And in the time of their trouble, they cried to You, and You heard from Heaven. And according to Your manifold mercies, You gave them deliverers, who saved them out of the hand of their enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.28'>But after they had rest, they did evil again before You, and You left them in the hand of their enemies, so that they had the rule over them. But they returned and cried to You, and You heard from Heaven. And many times You delivered them according to Your mercies,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.29'>and testified against them that You might bring them again to Your law. But they acted proudly and did not listen to Your commandments, but sinned against Your judgments (which if a man do, he shall live in them), and withdrew the shoulder, and hardened their neck, and would not hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.30'>And many years You had patience with them, and testified against them by Your Spirit, by Your prophets, but they would not give ear. And You gave them into the hand of the people of the lands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.31'>But for Your great mercies, You did not completely destroy them nor forsake them. For You [are] a gracious and merciful God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.32'>And now, our God, the great, the mighty, and the fearful God, who keeps covenant and mercy, let not all the trouble that has come upon us, on our kings, on our rulers, and on our priests, and on our prophets, and on our fathers, and on all Your people, since the time of the kings of Assyria to this day, seem little before You.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.33'>But You [are] just in all that is brought upon us, for You have done right, but we have done wickedly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.34'>And our kings, our rulers, our priests, and our fathers, have not kept Your law, nor listened to Your commandments and Your words with which You testified against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.35'>For they have not served You in their kingdom, and in Your great goodness which You gave them, and in the large and rich land which You gave before them, and they did not turn from their wicked works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.36'>Behold, we [are] servants today. And the land that You gave to our fathers to eat its fruit, and its good, behold, we are servants in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.37'>And it yields much increase to the kings whom You have set over us because of our sins. And they rule over our bodies, and over our cattle, at their pleasure, and we [are] in great distress.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.9.38'>And because of all this we [are] cutting a sure [covenant], and write [it], and our princes, Levites, [and] priests are sealing it.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Neh.10'>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.1'>And those who sealed [were], Nehemiah, the governor, the son of Hachaliah, and Zidkijah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.2'>Seraiah, Azariah, Jeremiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.3'>Pashur, Amariah, Malchijah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.4'>Hattush, Shebaniah, Malluch,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.5'>Harim, Meremoth, Obadiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.6'>Daniel, Ginnethon, Baruch,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.7'>Meshullam, Abijah, Mijamin,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.8'>Maaziah, Bilgai, Shemaiah. These [were] the priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.9'>And the Levites [were] both Jeshua the son of Azaniah, Binnui of the sons of Henadad, Kadmiel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.10'>and their brothers, Shebaniah, Hodijah, Kelita, Pelaiah, Hanan,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.11'>Micha, Rehob, Hashabiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.12'>Zaccur, Sherebiah, Shebaniah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.13'>Hodijah, Bani, Beninu.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.14'>The chief of the people [were] Parosh, Pahath-moab, Elam, Zatthu, Bani,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.15'>Bunni, Azgad, Bebai,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.16'>Adonijah, Bigvai, Adin,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.17'>Ater, Hizkijah, Azzur,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.18'>Hodijah, Hashum, Bezai,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.19'>Hariph, Anathoth, Nebai,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.20'>Magpiash, Meshullam, Hezir,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.21'>Meshezabeel, Zadok, Jaddua,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.22'>Pelatiah, Hanan, Anaiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.23'>Hoshea, Hananiah, Hashub,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.24'>Hallohesh, Pileha, Shobek,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.25'>Rehum, Hashabnah, Maaseiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.26'>and Ahijah, Hanan, Anan,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.27'>Malluch, Harim, Baanah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.28'>And the rest of the people, the priests, the Levites, the gatekeepers, the singers, the temple-slaves, and all those who had separated from the people of the lands to the Law of God, their wives, their sons, and their daughters (everyone who had knowledge, and who had understanding),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.29'>[were] holding fast to their brothers, their honored ones. And they entered into a curse and into an oath, to walk in God's law which was given by Moses the servant of God, and to be careful to do all the commandments of Jehovah our Lord, and His judgments and His statutes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.30'>And we swore that we would not give our daughters to the people of the land nor take their daughters for our sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.31'>And [if] the people of the land should bring goods or any food on the Sabbath day to sell it, that we would not buy it from them on the Sabbath or on the holy day, and that we would leave the seventh year, and the interest of every debt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.32'>Also we put commands upon ourselves, to charge ourselves yearly with the third part of a shekel for the service of the house of our God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.33'>for the showbread, and for the continual meal offering, and for the continual burnt offering, of the sabbaths, of the new moons, for the set feasts, and for the holy [things], and for the sin offerings to make an atonement for Israel, and for all the work of the house of our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.34'>And we cast the lots among the priests, and the Levites, and the people, for the wood offering, to bring into the house of our God, according to the houses of our fathers, at times appointed year by year, to burn upon the altar of the LORD our God, as [it is] written in the Law</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.35'>and to bring the firstfruits of our ground, and the firstfruits of all fruit of all trees, year by year, to the house of the LORD;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.36'>and to bring the first-born of our sons, and of our cattle, as [it is] written in the Law, and the firstlings of our herds and of our flocks, to bring to the house of our God, to the priests who minister in the house of our God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.37'>and that we should bring the firstfruits of our dough, and our offerings, and the fruit of all kinds of trees, of wine and of oil, to the priests, to the rooms of the house of our God; and the tithes of our ground to the Levites, and they, the Levites, might have the tithes in all the cities we farmed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.38'>And the priest, the son of Aaron, shall be with the Levites, when the Levites take tithes, and the Levites shall bring up the tithe of the tithes to the house of our God, to the rooms, into the treasure house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.10.39'>For the sons of Israel and the sons of Levi shall bring the offering of the grain, of the new wine, and the oil, to the rooms where the vessels of the sanctuary [are], and the priests who minister, and the gatekeepers and the singers. And we will not forsake the house of our God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Neh.11'>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.1'>And the rulers of the people lived at Jerusalem. And the rest of the people cast lots, to bring one of every ten to live in Jerusalem, the holy city, and nine parts in [other] cities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.2'>And the people blessed all the men who willingly offered themselves to live at Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.3'>And these [are] the rulers of the province who lived in Jerusalem. But in the cities of Judah everyone lived in his possession in their cities: Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and the temple-slaves, and the sons of Solomon's servants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.4'>And at Jerusalem lived [certain] of the sons of Judah, and of the sons of Benjamin. From the sons of Judah: Athaiah the son of Uzziah, the son of Zechariah, the son of Amariah, the son of Shephatiah, the son of Mahalaleel, of the sons of Perez,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.5'>and Maaseiah the son of Baruch, the son of Colhozeh, the son of Hazaiah, the son of Adaiah, the son of Joiarib, the son of Zechariah, the son of Shiloni.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.6'>All the sons of Perez who lived in Jerusalem [were] four hundred and sixty-eight mighty men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.7'>And these [are] the sons of Benjamin: Sallu, the son of Meshullam, the son of Joed, the son of Pedaiah, the son of Kolaiah, the son of Maaseiah, the son of Ithiel, the son of Jesaiah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.8'>and after him Gabbai, Sallai, nine hundred and twenty-eight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.9'>And Joel the son of Zichri [was] their overseer. And Judah the son of Senuah [was] second over the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.10'>From the priests [were] Jedaiah the son of Joiarib, Jachin,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.11'>Seraiah, the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, the ruler of the house of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.12'>And their brothers who did the work of the house [were] eight hundred and twenty-two. And Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son of Pelaliah, the son of Amzi, the son of Zechariah, the son of Pashur, the son of Malchiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.13'>and his brothers, chief of the fathers, two hundred and forty-two. And Amashai the son of Azareel, the son of Ahasai, the son of Meshillemoth, the son of Immer,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.14'>and their brothers, mighty men of power, [were] a hundred and twenty-eight. And their overseer [was] Zabdiel, the son of [one of] the great men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.15'>And from the Levites [were] Shemaiah the son of Hashub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Bunni.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.16'>And Shabbethai and Jozabad, of the chief of the Levites, [were over] the outward business of the house of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.17'>And Mattaniah the son of Micha, the son of Zabdi, the son of Asaph, [was] the leader to begin the thanksgiving in prayer. And Bakbukiah was second among his brothers, and then Abda the son of Shammua, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.18'>All the Levites in the holy city [were] two hundred and eighty-four.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.19'>And the gatekeepers, Akkub, Talmon, and their brothers who kept the gates, [were] a hundred and seventy-two.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.20'>And the rest of Israel, of the priests [and] the Levites, [were] in all the cities of Judah, each one in his inheritance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.21'>But the temple-slaves lived in Ophel; and Ziha and Gispa [were] over the temple-slaves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.22'>And the overseer of the Levites at Jerusalem [was] Uzzi the son of Bani, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Micha. Of the sons of Asaph, the singers [were] over the business of the house of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.23'>For [it was] the king's commandment concerning them that a certain portion should be for the singers, due for every day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.24'>And Pethahiah the son of Meshezabeel, of the sons of Zerah the son of Judah, [was] at the king's hand in all matters concerning the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.25'>And for the villages, with their fields, [some] of the sons of Judah lived at Kirjath-arba, and in its villages, and at Dibon, and in its villages, and at Jekabzeel, and its villages,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.26'>and at Jeshua, and at Moladah, and at Beth-phelet,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.27'>and at Hazar-shual, and at Beer-sheba, and [in] its villages,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.28'>and at Ziklag, and at Mekonah, and in its villages,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.29'>and at En-rimmon, and at Zareah, and at Jarmuth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.30'>Zanoah, Adullam, and their villages, at Lachish, and the fields of it, at Azekah, and [in] its villages. And they lived from Beer-sheba to the valley of Hinnom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.31'>And the sons of Benjamin from Geba [lived] at Michmash, and Aija, and Bethel, and their villages,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.32'>at Anathoth, Nob, Ananiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.33'>Hazor, Ramah, Gittaim,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.34'>Hadid, Zeboim, Neballat,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.35'>Lod, and Ono, the Valley of Craftsmen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.11.36'>And divisions of the Levites [were] [in] Judah and for Benjamin.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Neh.12'>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.1'>And these [are] the priests and the Levites who went up with Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua, Seraiah, Jeremiah, Ezra,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.2'>Amariah, Malluch, Hattush,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.3'>Shechaniah, Rehum, Meremoth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.4'>Iddo, Ginnetho, Abijah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.5'>Miamin, Maadiah, Bilgah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.6'>Shemaiah, and Joiarib, Jedaiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.7'>Sallu, Amok, Hilkiah, Jedaiah. These [were] the chief of the priests and of their brothers in the days of Jeshua.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.8'>And the Levites [were] Jeshua, Binnui, Kadmiel, Sherebiah, Judah. Mattaniah [was] over the thanksgiving, he and his brothers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.9'>And Bakbukiah and Unni, their brothers, [were] next to them in the watches.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.10'>And Jeshua fathered Joiakim, and Joiakim fathered Eliashib, and Eliashib fathered Joiada,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.11'>and Joiada fathered Jonathan, and Jonathan fathered Jaddua.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.12'>And in the days of Joiakim were priests, the chief of the fathers: from [the house of] Seraiah was Meraiah; from Jeremiah, Hananiah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.13'>from Ezra, Meshullam; from Amariah, Jehohanan;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.14'>from Melicu, Jonathan; from Shebaniah, Joseph;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.15'>from Harim, Adna; from Meraioth, Helkai;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.16'>from Iddo, Zechariah; from Ginnethon, Meshullam;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.17'>from Abijah, Zichri; from Miniamin of Moadiah, Piltai;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.18'>from Bilgah, Shammua; from Shemaiah, Jehonathan;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.19'>and from Joiarib, Mattenai; from Jedaiah, Uzzi;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.20'>from Sallai, Kallai; from Amok, Eber;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.21'>from Hilkiah, Hashabiah; from Jedaiah, Nethaneel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.22'>The Levites in the days of Eliashib, Joiada, and Johanan, and Jaddua, [were] recorded chief of the fathers and the priests, until the reign of Darius the Persian.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.23'>The sons of Levi, the chief of the fathers, [were] written in the Book of the Chronicles, even until the days of Johanan the son of Eliashib.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.24'>And the chief of the Levites [were] Hashabiah, Sherebiah; and Jeshua the son of Kadmiel, with their brothers next to them, to praise [and] to give thanks, according to the command of David the man of God, watch by watch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.25'>Mattaniah, and Bakbukiah, Obadiah, Meshullam, Talmon, and Akkub, [were] guarding the gates, the guard at the thresholds of the gates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.26'>These [were] in the days of Joiakim the son of Jeshua, the son of Jozadak, and in the days of Nehemiah the governor, and of Ezra the priest, the scribe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.27'>And at the dedication of the wall of Jerusalem, they sought the Levites out of all their places to bring them to Jerusalem, to keep the dedication with gladness, and with thanksgiving, and with singing,  with] cymbals, harps and with lyres.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.28'>And the sons of the singers gathered themselves, both out of the plain country around Jerusalem, and from the villages of the Netophathi;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.29'>and from the house of Gilgal, and out of the fields of Geba and Azmaveth (for the singers had built themselves villages all around Jerusalem.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.30'>And the priests and the Levites purified themselves. And they purified the people, and the gates, and the wall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.31'>Then I brought up the rulers of Judah on the wall, and chose two great choirs of praise. One went to the right upon the wall toward the Dung Gate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.32'>And after them went Hoshaiah, and half the rulers of Judah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.33'>and Azariah, Ezra, and Meshullam,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.34'>Judah, and Benjamin, and Shemaiah, and Jeremiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.35'>and [many] of the priests' sons with trumpets; Zechariah the son of Jonathan, the son of Shemaiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Michaiah, the son of Zaccur, the son of Asaph,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.36'>and his brothers, Shemaiah, and Azareel, Milalai, Gilalai, Maai, Nethaneel, and Judah, Hanani, with the musical instruments of David the man of God, and with Ezra the scribe before them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.37'>And at the Fountain Gate, across from them, they went up by the stairs of the city of David, at the going up of the wall, above the house of David, even to the Water Gate eastward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.38'>And the other choirs of praise went across from [them], and I after them, and half of the people on the wall, from beyond the Tower of the Furnaces even to the Broad Wall,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.39'>and from above the Gate of Ephraim, and above the Old Gate, and above the Fish Gate, and the Tower of Hananeel, and the Tower of Meah, even to the Sheep Gate. And they stood still in the Prison Gate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.40'>And stood the two praise choirs to give thanks in the house of God, and I, and half of the rulers with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.41'>And the priests, Eliakim, Maaseiah, Miniamin, Michaiah, Elioenai, Zechariah, [and] Hananiah, [were] with trumpets,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.42'>and Maaseiah, and Shemaiah, and Eleazar, and Uzzi, and Jehohanan, and Malchijah, and Elam, and Ezer. And the singers sang loud, with Jezrahiah [their] overseer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.43'>And that day they offered great sacrifices, and rejoiced. For God had made them rejoice with great joy. And the wives and the sons rejoiced, so that the joy of Jerusalem was heard even afar off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.44'>And at that time some were chosen over the rooms for the treasuries, for the offerings, for the firstfruits, and for the tithes, to gather to them out of the fields of the cities the portions of the Law for the priests and Levites. For Judah rejoiced for the priests and for the Levites who waited.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.45'>And both the singers and the gatekeepers kept the charge of their God, and the charge of the cleansing, according to the command of David [and] of Solomon his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.46'>For in the days of David and Asaph of old there [were] chief of the singers, and songs of praise and thanksgiving to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.12.47'>And all Israel gave the portions of the singers and the gatekeepers, every day its portion, in the days of Zerubbabel and in the days of Nehemiah. And they set the [holy things] apart for the Levites, and the Levites set them apart for the sons of Aaron.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Neh.13'>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.1'>On that day they read in the book of Moses in the ears of the people. And in it was found written that the Ammonite and the Moabite should not come into the congregation of God forever,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.2'>because they did not meet the sons of Israel with bread and with water, but hired Balaam against them so that he should curse them. But our God turned the curse into a blessing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.3'>And it happened when they had heard the Law, they separated all the mixed multitude from Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.4'>And before this, Eliashib the priest, who was set over the rooms of the house of our God, and who [was] related to Tobiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.5'>and he had prepared for himself a large room where they had in days of old laid the food offering, the frankincense, and the vessels, and the tithes of the grain, the new wine, and the oil, which was commanded [to be given] to the Levites, and the singers, and the gatekeepers, and the offerings of the priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.6'>But in all this [time] I was not at Jerusalem. For in the thirty-second year of Artaxerxes king of Babylon, I came to the king. And after some days I was given permission to leave the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.7'>And I came to Jerusalem, and understood the evil which Eliashib did for Tobiah in preparing him a room in the courts of the house of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.8'>And it grieved me very much. And I threw all the household stuff of Tobiah out of the room.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.9'>Then I commanded, and they purified the rooms. And I brought there again the vessels of the house of God, with the food offering and the frankincense.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.10'>And I saw that the portions of the Levites had not been given [to them]; for the Levites and the singers, who did the work, had fled each one to his field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.11'>And I contended with the rulers and said, Why is the house of God forsaken? And I gathered them together and set them in their place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.12'>And all Judah brought the tithe of the grain and the new wine and the oil into the treasuries.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.13'>And I made treasurers over the treasuries, Shelemiah the priest, and Zadok the scribe, and of the Levites, Pedaiah. And next to them [was] Hanan the son of Zaccur, the son of Mattaniah. For they [were] counted faithful, and their office [was] to distribute to their brothers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.14'>Remember me, O my God, concerning this, and do not wipe out my good deeds which I have done for the house of my God, and for the offices of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.15'>In those days I saw in Judah [some] treading winepresses on the Sabbath, and bringing in sheaves, and loading asses and also wine, grapes, and figs, and all kinds of burdens which they brought into Jerusalem on the Sabbath day. And I testified [against them] in the day in which they sold food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.16'>And men of Tyre lived in it, who brought fish and all kinds of goods, and sold on the Sabbath to the sons of Judah and in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.17'>And I contended with the nobles of Judah and said to them, What evil thing [is] this that you do, and defile the Sabbath day?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.18'>Did not your fathers do this, and did not our God bring all this evil upon us and upon this city? Yet you bring more wrath upon Israel by defiling the Sabbath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.19'>And it happened when the gates of Jerusalem began to be dark before the Sabbath, I commanded that the gates should be shut, and commanded that they should not be opened until after the Sabbath. And I set [some] of my servants at the gates, so that there should be no burden brought in on the Sabbath day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.20'>And the merchants and sellers of all kinds of goods stayed the night outside Jerusalem once or twice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.21'>And I testified against them, and said to them, Why do you stay around the wall? If you do [so] again, I will lay hands on you. From that time on they did not come on the Sabbath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.22'>And I commanded the Levites that they should cleanse themselves, and that they should come [and] keep the gates, to sanctify the Sabbath day. Remember me, O my God, concerning this also, and spare me according to the greatness of Your mercy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.23'>In those days I also saw Jews who lived with women [from] Ashdod, Ammon, [and] from Moab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.24'>And their sons spoke half Ashdod's speech, and there was no caring to speak Jewish, but according to the language of each people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.25'>And I contended with them, and cursed them, and struck [certain] of them, and plucked off their hair. And I made them swear by the name of God, [saying], You shall not give your daughters to their sons, or take their daughters to your sons, or for yourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.26'>Did not Solomon king of Israel sin by these things? Yet among many nations there was no king like him, who was beloved by his God, and God made him king over all Israel. But women from other lands caused even him to sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.27'>Shall we then listen to you, to do all this great evil, to sin against our God in living with foreign women?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.28'>And [one] of the sons of Joiada, the son of Eliashib the high priest, [was] son-in-law to Sanballat the Horonite; and I chased him from me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.29'>Remember them, O my God, because they have defiled the priesthood, and the covenant of the priesthood and of the Levites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.30'>So I cleansed them from all strangers, and appointed charges to the priests and the Levites, every one in his business,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Neh.13.31'>and for the wood offering, at chosen times, and for the firstfruits. Remember me, O my God, for good!</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>