<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='mkjv1962' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='mkjv1962'>
        <title>Modern KJV 1963</title>
        <contributor>xxx</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy</subject>
        <date>2009-01-23</date>
        <description>Modern King James Version of the Holy Bible 1962</description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>mkjv1962</identifier>
        <source/>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Phil'>
      <chapter osisID='Phil.1'>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.1'>Paul and Timothy, the servants of Jesus Christ, to all the saints in Christ Jesus who are at Philippi, with the overseers and deacons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.2'>Grace to you, and peace from God our Father and from [the] Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.3'>I thank my God upon every remembrance of you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.4'>always in every prayer of mine making [my] request for you all with joy</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.5'>for your fellowship in the gospel from [the] first day until now;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.6'>being confident of this very thing, that He who has begun a good work in you will perform [it] until the day of Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.7'>even as it is righteous for me to think this of you all, because you have me in your heart, inasmuch as both in my bonds, and in the defense and confirmation of the gospel, you are all partakers of my grace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.8'>For God is my witness how greatly I long after you all in [the] bowels of Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.9'>And this I pray, that your love may abound yet more and more in full knowledge and [in] all perception;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.10'>that you may distinguish [between] things that differ, that you may be sincere and without offense until the day of Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.11'>being filled [with the] fruits of righteousness through Jesus Christ, to the glory and praise of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.12'>But I desire that you should understand, brothers, that the things [which happened] to me have fallen out rather to [the] furtherance of the gospel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.13'>so that my bonds in Christ are manifest in all the palace, and in all other [places].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.14'>And most of the brothers in [the] Lord, becoming confident by my bonds, are much more bold to speak the word without fear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.15'>Some indeed even preach Christ because of envy and strife, and some also of good will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.16'>Those, indeed, preach Christ out of contention, not sincerely, supposing to add affliction to my bonds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.17'>But these [others] preach in love, knowing that I am set for the defense of the gospel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.18'>What then? Nevertheless, in every way, whether in pretense or in truth, Christ is preached. And I rejoice in this. Yet, also I will rejoice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.19'>For I know that this shall turn to my salvation through your prayer and [the] supply of [the] Spirit of Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.20'>according to my earnest expectation and hope that I shall be ashamed in nothing, but as always now Christ shall be magnified in my body with all boldness, whether it is by life or by death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.21'>For to me to live [is] Christ, and to die [is] gain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.22'>But if [I] live in [the] flesh, this [is] the fruit of [my] labor. Yet I do not know what I shall choose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.23'>For I am pressed together by the two: having a desire to depart and to be with Christ, which is far better.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.24'>But to remain in the flesh [is] more needful for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.25'>And having this confidence, I know that I shall remain and continue with you all, for your advancement and joy of faith,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.26'>so that your rejoicing may be more abundant in Jesus Christ for me by my coming to you again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.27'>Only let your conduct be as becomes the gospel of Christ, so that whether I come and see you, or else am absent, I may hear of your [affairs], that you stand fast in one spirit, striving together with one mind for the faith of the gospel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.28'>and terrified in nothing by your adversaries. [For this is] to them an evident token of perdition, but to you of salvation, and that of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.29'>For to you it is given on behalf of Christ not only to believe on Him, but also to suffer for His sake,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.1.30'>having the same conflict which you saw in me, and now hear [to be] in me.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Phil.2'>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.1'>If [there is] therefore any encouragement in Christ, if any comfort of love, if any fellowship of [the] Spirit, if any tendernesses and mercies,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.2'>then fulfill my joy, that you may be like-minded, having the same love, [being] of one accord and of one mind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.3'>[Let] nothing [be done] through strife or vainglory, but in lowliness of mind let each esteem others better than themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.4'>Do not let each man look upon his own things, but each man also [on] the things of others.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.5'>For let this mind be in you which was also in Christ Jesus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.6'>who, being in the form of God, thought [it] not robbery to be equal with God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.7'>but made Himself of no reputation, and took [upon Himself] the form of a servant, and was made in [the] likeness of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.8'>And being found in fashion as a man, He humbled Himself [and] became obedient unto death, even [the] death of the cross.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.9'>Therefore God has highly exalted Him, and has given Him a name [which is] above every name,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.10'>that at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of heavenly ones, and of earthly ones, and of ones under [the] earth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.11'>and [that] every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ [is] Lord, to [the] glory of God [the] Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.12'>Therefore, my beloved, as you have always obeyed, not as in my presence only, but now much more in my absence, cultivate your own salvation with fear and trembling.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.13'>For it is God who works in you both to will and to do of [His] good pleasure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.14'>Do all things without murmurings and disputings,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.15'>so that you may be blameless and harmless, the sons of God, without rebuke, in the midst of a crooked and perverse nation. Among these you shine as lights in the world,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.16'>holding forth the word of life, so that I may rejoice with you in [the] day of Christ, that I have not run in vain nor labored in vain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.17'>Yea, and if I am offered upon the sacrifice and service of your faith, I joy and rejoice with you all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.18'>And you also rejoice [in] the same, and rejoice with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.19'>But I trust in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy shortly to you, so that I also may be of good comfort when I know [your state].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.20'>For I have no one who is like-minded, who will naturally care for [your state].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.21'>For all seek their own, not the things which are of Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.22'>But you know the proof of him, that, as a son with the father, he has served with me in the gospel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.23'>Therefore I hope to send him presently, as soon as I shall see the things about me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.24'>But I trust in [the] Lord that I myself shall also come shortly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.25'>Yet I thought it necessary to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother and fellow-worker, and fellow-soldier, but your messenger and he who ministered to my wants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.26'>For he longed after you all and was full of heaviness, because you had heard that he had been sick.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.27'>For indeed he was sick, coming near death, but God had mercy on him, and not on him only, but on me also, lest I should have sorrow upon sorrow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.28'>Therefore I sent him the more eagerly, so that you may rejoice when you see him again, and that I may be the less sorrowful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.29'>Therefore receive him in the Lord with all gladness, and hold such in honor,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.2.30'>because for the work of Christ he was near death, not regarding his life, to supply your lack of service toward me.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Phil.3'>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.1'>Finally, my brothers, rejoice in [the] Lord. To write the same things to you is indeed not grievous to me, but for you [it is] safe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.2'>Beware of dogs, beware of evil workers, beware of the concision party.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.3'>For we are the circumcision who worship God in the spirit and rejoice in Christ Jesus and have no confidence in the flesh;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.4'>though I might also have confidence in the flesh. If any other thinks that he has reason to trust in the flesh, I more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.5'>I was circumcised [the] eighth day, of [the] stock of Israel, [of the] tribe of Benjamin, a Hebrew of the Hebrews. As regards the Law, [I was] a Pharisee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.6'>concerning zeal, persecuting the church; regarding the righteousness in the Law, blameless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.7'>But whatever things were gain to me, those I counted loss for Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.8'>But no, rather, I also count all things to be loss for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord, for whose sake I have suffered the loss of all things, and count them [to be] dung, so that I may win Christ</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.9'>and be found in Him; not having my own righteousness, which is of the Law, but through [the] faith of Christ, the righteousness of God by faith,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.10'>that I may know Him and the power of His resurrection and the fellowship of His sufferings, being made conformable to His death;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.11'>if by any means I might attain to the resurrection of the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.12'>Not as though I had already attained, either were already perfect, but I am pressing on, if I may lay hold of that for which I also was taken hold of by Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.13'>My brothers, I do not count myself to have taken possession, but one [thing I do], forgetting the things behind and reaching forward to the things before,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.14'>I press toward the mark for the prize of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.15'>Let us therefore, as many as [are] perfect, be of this mind. And if in anything you are otherwise minded, God shall reveal even this to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.16'>Yet, as to what we have already attained, let us walk in the same rule, let us mind the same thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.17'>Brothers, be imitators together of me, and mark those who walk this way, for you have us [for] a pattern.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.18'>(For many are walking, of whom I have told you often and now tell you even weeping, [as] the enemies of the cross of Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.19'>whose end [is] destruction, whose god [is their] belly, and [whose] glory [is] in their shame, [those] who mind earthly things.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.20'>For our citizenship is in Heaven, from which also we are looking for the Savior, [the] Lord Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.3.21'>who shall change our body of humiliation so that it may be fashioned like His glorious body, according to the working of His power, even to subdue all things to Himself.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Phil.4'>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.1'>Therefore, my brothers, ones loved and longed for, my joy and crown, stand fast in this way in [the] Lord, beloved ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.2'>I beg Euodia and Syntyche that they be of the same mind in [the] Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.3'>And I also beg you, true yoke-fellow, help those women who labored in the gospel with me and with Clement, and others of my fellow-laborers, whose names [are] in the Book of Life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.4'>Rejoice in [the] Lord always. Again I say, Rejoice!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.5'>Let your moderation be known to all men. The Lord [is] at hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.6'>Do not be anxious about anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication, with thanksgiving, let your requests be made known to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.7'>And the peace of God which passes all understanding shall keep your hearts and minds through Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.8'>Finally, my brothers, whatever things are true, whatever things [are] honest, whatever [things are] right, whatever [things are] pure, whatever [things are] lovely, whatever  things are] of good report; if  there is] any virtue and if [there is] any praise, think on these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.9'>Do those things which you have also learned and received and heard and seen in me. And the God of peace shall be with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.10'>But I rejoiced in [the] Lord greatly, that now at the last your care of me has flourished again. Although you indeed did think, but you lacked opportunity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.11'>Not that I speak according to need, for I have learned to be content in whatever state I am.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.12'>I know both how to be abased, and I know how to abound. In everything and in all things I am instructed both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to suffer need.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.13'>I can do all things through Christ who strengthens me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.14'>Yet you did well in sharing my troubles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.15'>Now you Philippians know also that in [the] beginning of the gospel, when I departed from Macedonia, no church communicated with me as regards giving and receiving, except you alone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.16'>For even in Thessalonica you sent once and again to my necessity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.17'>I do not say this because I desire a gift, but I desire fruit that may abound to your account.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.18'>But I have all, and abound. I have been filled, having received from Epaphroditus the things [which you sent], an odor of a sweet smell, a sacrifice acceptable and well-pleasing to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.19'>But my God shall supply all your need according to His riches in glory by Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.20'>Now unto God and our Father [be] glory forever and ever. Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.21'>Greet every saint in Christ Jesus. The brothers who are with me greet you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.22'>All the saints greet you, most of all those who are of Caesar's household.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phil.4.23'>May the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ [be] with you all. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>