<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='mkjv1962' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='mkjv1962'>
        <title>Modern KJV 1963</title>
        <contributor>xxx</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy</subject>
        <date>2009-01-23</date>
        <description>Modern King James Version of the Holy Bible 1962</description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>mkjv1962</identifier>
        <source/>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Titus'>
      <chapter osisID='Titus.1'>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.1'>Paul, a servant of God and an apostle of Jesus Christ (according to [the] faith of God's elect, in the acknowledging of [the] truth which is according to godliness</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.2'>on hope of eternal life, which God, who cannot lie, promised before [the] eternal times,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.3'>but revealed His word in its own times in a proclamation, with which I was entrusted by [the] command of God our Savior,)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.4'>to Titus, a true child according to [our] common faith. Grace mercy and peace from God [the] Father and [the] Lord Jesus Christ our Savior.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.5'>For this cause I left you in Crete, that you should set in order the things that are lacking and ordain elders in every city, as I had appointed you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.6'>if anyone is blameless, husband of one wife, having believing children, not accused of loose behavior, or disobedient.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.7'>For an overseer must be blameless, as a steward of God, not self-willed, not full of passion, not given to wine, not quarrelsome, not greedy for ill gain;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.8'>but hospitable, a lover of good, discreet, just, holy, temperate,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.9'>holding fast the faithful word according to the doctrine, that he may be able, by sound doctrine, both to exhort and to convict the gainsayers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.10'>For there are indeed many unruly men, vain talkers and deceivers, especially those of [the] circumcision,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.11'>whose mouth [you] must stop, who subvert whole houses, teaching things not right for the sake of ill gain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.12'>One of them, a prophet of their own, said, Cretans [are] always liars, evil beasts, lazy gluttons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.13'>This witness is true; for which cause convict them sharply, so that they may be sound in the faith,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.14'>not giving heed to Jewish myths and commandments of men, turning away from the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.15'>To the pure all things [are] pure. But to those who are defiled and unbelieving nothing [is] pure, but even their mind and conscience is defiled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.16'>They profess that they know God, but in [their] works they deny [Him], being abominable and disobedient and reprobate to every good work.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Titus.2'>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.1'>But you speak [the] things which become sound doctrine:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.2'>aged men to be temperate, sensible, discreet, sound in faith, in love, in patience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.3'>Let the aged women likewise [be] in reverent behavior, not slanderers, not enslaved by much wine, teachers of good;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.4'>that they may train the young women to love their husbands, to love their children,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.5'>[to be] discreet, chaste, keepers at home, good, subject to [their] own husbands, that the Word of God may not be blasphemed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.6'>Likewise exhort the young men to be discreet;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.7'>In all things having shown yourself a pattern of good works: in the doctrine, purity, sensibleness, without corruption,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.8'>[in] sound speech that cannot be condemned, that he who is opposed may be ashamed, having no evil thing to say of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.9'>Slaves [are] to be obedient to [their] masters, to please them well in all [things], not talking against,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.10'>not stealing, but showing all good faith, so that they may adorn the doctrine of God our Savior in all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.11'>For the grace of God that brings salvation has appeared to all men,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.12'>teaching us that having denied ungodliness and worldly lusts, we should live discreetly, righteously and godly, in this present world,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.13'>looking for the blessed hope, and the appearance of the glory of our great God and Savior Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.14'>who gave Himself for us that He might redeem us from all iniquity and purify to Himself a special people, zealous of good works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.15'>Speak these things, and exhort, and rebuke with all authority. Let no one despise you.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Titus.3'>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.1'>Put them in mind to be subject to rulers and authorities, to be obedient, to be ready to every good work,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.2'>to speak evil of no one, not being quarrelsome, [but] forbearing, showing all meekness to all men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.3'>For we ourselves also were once foolish, disobedient, deceived, slaving for various lusts and pleasures, living in malice and envy, hateful, hating one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.4'>But when the kindness and love of God our Savior toward man appeared,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.5'>not by works of righteousness which we have done, but according to His mercy He saved us, through the washing of regeneration and renewal of the Holy Spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.6'>whom He poured out on us abundantly through Jesus Christ our Savior,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.7'>that being justified by His grace, we should become heirs according to the hope of eternal life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.8'>Faithful [is] the Word, and as to these things, I desire that you strongly affirm that those believing God might be careful to maintain good works. These things are good and profitable to men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.9'>But avoid foolish questions and genealogies and contentions, and strivings about the Law, for they are unprofitable and vain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.10'>After the first and second warning, reject a man of heresy,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.11'>knowing that he who is such has been perverted, and sins, being self-condemned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.12'>When I send Artemas to you, or Tychicus, hasten to come to me at Nicopolis, for I have determined to winter there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.13'>Diligently set forward Zenas the lawyer, and Apollos, that nothing may be lacking to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.14'>And let ours also learn to maintain good works for necessary uses, so that they may not be unfruitful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.15'>All those with me greet you. Greet those who love us in [the] faith. May grace [be] with you all. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>