<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='BWE' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='BWE'>
        <title>Bible in Worldwide English NT</title>
        <contributor>Sword Project</contributor>
        <creator>darling</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>The Bible in Worldwide English (BWE)\par This New Testament was originally prepared by Annie Cressman, who died in 1993. She was a Canadian Bible teacher in Liberia in West Africa. Whilst teaching students in a Bible School where the language used was English, she found that she was spending more time explaining the meaning of the English than she was teaching the Bible itself. So she decided to write this simple version in easy English so that her students could easily understand.\par\par In 1959 the Full Gospel Publishing House in Toronto, Canada, printed a trial edition of the Gospel of Mark. A further edition was published in 1962 by the American Bible Society. The whole New Testament was first published by SOON Publications in India in 1969 in hardback form. This was assisted by Operation Mobilisation (OM) and was reprinted in 1971.\par\par The vision to reprint a new edition of the whole New Testament has now been carried out by SOON in conjunction with EPH and OM. Where a change to more modern words has been made, this has been kept in line with the the Authorised Version.</description>
        <publisher>freedom for bible ORG</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>BWE</identifier>
        <source>http://www.crosswire.org/sword/servlet/SwordMod.Verify?modName=BWE</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>unknown</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='2Pet'>
      <chapter osisID='2Pet.1'>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.1'>I am Simon Peter. I am a servant and an apostle of Jesus Christ. I send greetings to you who have believed as we have. Believing is worth just as much to you as it is to us. This is because our God and Saviour, Jesus Christ, is right and good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.2'>May the loving kindness of God bless you and give you more and more peace because you know God and Jesus our Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.3'>Christ is God and by his own power he has given us everything that we need to live and to please God. He has given this to us because we know him, and he has called us because he is great and good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.4'>Because of these things, he has promised us things that are worth very much and are very great. He has promised these things to us so that by them you may become like God too.  By them you will be kept free from the selfish desires of the people in the world. These desires lead to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.5'>So now you believe, try to live a good life. When you live a good life, try to learn more about God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.6'>When you have learned more, be strong to do what is right. Then go on doing what is right, even if it is hard. As you go about doing right, keep close to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.7'>As you keep close to God, love your Christian brothers. When you love your Christian brothers, love everyone!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.8'>If you do these things and you do them more and more, you will be good Christians and you will know more and more about our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.9'>But the man who does not do these things is like a blind man. He can see only a little way. He has forgotten that he was made clean from the wrong things he used to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.10'>So my brothers, try to show that God has called you and chosen you. If you do these things, you will never fall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.11'>That will make it easy for you to go into the kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ. His kingdom will be for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.12'>I do want always to bring these things to your minds. I will do this even though you know them, and even though you are strong in the true way that you already have.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.13'>I think it is right, as long as I live, to keep these things in your minds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.14'>I know that I will not live long now. Our Lord Jesus Christ has told me about that.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.15'>But I will try to see that you have something to bring these things to your minds, even after I am gone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.16'>We have told you about the power of our Lord Jesus Christ and that he is coming again.  We did not tell you stories someone told us. We ourselves saw how great he is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.17'>God the Father praised him and showed that he is great. A voice came from the bright cloud and said to him, This is my Son. I love him and he pleases me very much.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.18'>We heard this voice which came from heaven. It happened when we were on the holy hill with Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.19'>And so we are more sure about what the prophets of God said long ago. You will do well to listen to them. It is like a lamp shining in a dark place. Then the daylight will come and the morning star will shine in your hearts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.20'>First you must understand this. The words from the prophets in the holy writings did not come from their own minds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.21'>The prophets did not say what they wanted to say. But the Holy Spirit made them speak.  And they spoke Gods message.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Pet.2'>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.1'>But prophets who were not true were also among the people of Israel. Also there will be teachers who will not be true among you. They will bring in wrong teaching that leads to death. They will even say that they do not belong to the Master who bought them. And so they will quickly bring themselves to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.2'>Many people will do the same wrong things they do. And because of them, men will say wrong things about the true way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.3'>Because they are greedy for money, they will trick you with lies. For a long time God has planned to punish them. They will be punished at the right time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.4'>God punished the angels who did wrong. He put them into the darkest part of hell. They must be kept there until the time when they will be judged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.5'>In the days long ago, God punished the world. But he saved Noah who told people what was right. And God saved seven other people. But he made water cover the world full of bad people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.6'>God burned up the cities of Sodom and Gomorrah. He punished them so that no cities were left. He did this to show what would happen to bad people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.7'>But God saved Lot out of the trouble. Lot was a good man. He did not like the wrong way the bad people lived.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.8'>That good man lived among the bad people and he saw and heard what they did. Day after day, the bad things they did troubled his heart because he was a good man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.9'>The Lord knows how to save good people out of the trouble that tests them. And he knows how to keep bad people until the day when he will judge them. And they are being punished even now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.10'>Most of all, he will punish people who do the wrong things they want to do and who will not obey the men who rule over them. They are very bold and proud. They do not fear to say wrong things about those who are great, even about the angels.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.11'>Angels have more strength and power than they. And yet the angels do not judge them and say wrong things about them to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.12'>These people are like animals that cannot think. They are like animals that are born to be caught and killed. They say wrong things about things they do not understand. They will die like the animals.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.13'>Bad things will happen to them because they have done wrong things. They think it is fun to have a good time during the day. They are like spots and sores. They like to eat and drink at the love feasts with you. They are trying to fool you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.14'>They are always looking for women to have sex with them. They never stop their wrong ways. They fool people whose hearts are not strong to do right. They always want more and more money. Gods curse is on them!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.15'>They have left the right road and have done wrong. They follow the same road that Balaam walked. He was the son of Beor. He loved the pay he would get for doing a wrong thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.16'>But he was told to stop doing wrong. The animal he was riding talked with a mans voice.  It tried to make the prophet stop his foolish way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.17'>These men are like wells with no water in them. They are like fog that is blown away by a strong wind. A very dark place has been kept to put them in.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.18'>They say big and foolish things. They fool people who have just left those who live in wrong ways. They fool them by making them want to do wrong things with their bodies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.19'>They promise them that they will be free. But they themselves are slaves of death. A man is a slave of anything that rules over him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.20'>They left the wrong ways of the world because they knew our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ. Then when they went back to the wrong ways again, they were ruled by them.  Then they will have more trouble than they had at first.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.21'>It would have been better for them if they had never known the right way! Because they knew the right way, it was very wrong for them to turn from the holy law God gave them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.22'>They show that this saying is true, The dog goes back to eat what his own stomach threw up! and, A pig that is washed rolls in the mud again!</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Pet.3'>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.1'>My dear brothers, this is my second letter to you. In both of my letters I have tried to bring some things to your good minds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.2'>I want you to remember what Gods prophets said would happen. And I want you to remember what we apostles told you that our Lord and Saviour said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.3'>Here is the first thing. In the last days, men will come who will make fun of holy things.  They will do what they themselves want to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.4'>They will say, He promised to come. Where is he? Our fathers have died. And since then everything is just the same as it has been since the world was made.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.5'>They do not want to remember that long ago God spoke and made the sky. He made the land come up from the water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.6'>But later on these same waters covered the world in a flood and the people died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.7'>The sky and the earth that are here now are being kept because God spoke. They are kept to be burned up. This will happen on the day when God judges people and they will die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.8'>My dear brothers, do not forget this one thing. One day is like a thousand years to the Lord. And a thousand years are like one day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.9'>God will do what he promised. He is not slow though, as some people think he is. But he is waiting a long time for you. He does not want anyone to die, but he wants all people to stop their wrong ways.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.10'>The day of the Lord will come like a man who wants to steal. There will be a loud noise and the sky will go away. The elements will melt with fire and they will be gone. The earth and everything on it will be burned up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.11'>That is the way the whole world will go. So think what kind of people you should be!  Think how holy and true to God your lives should be!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.12'>You should look for the day of God and do everything you can to make it come quickly.  On that day the sky will be on fire and go away. The elements will burn and melt away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.13'>But we are looking for a new sky and a new earth which God has promised. Only good things will be in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.14'>My dear brothers, you are looking for these things. So do all you can so that the Lord will find you without any bad or wrong thing in your lives. Let him find you at peace with one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.15'>Think of this. He is waiting a long time so that people will be saved. Our dear brother Paul also wrote these things to you, because God has made him wise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.16'>He also tells about them in all his letters. Some things in his letters are hard to understand. Some people do not know about these things and they are not strong in their faith. They change the meaning of the things Paul wrote. They do this to other things in the holy writings also. Because they do this, they will die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.17'>My dear brothers, you know about these things before they happen. Take care that you do not do the same things that bad people do. Take care that you do not stop believing the right way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.18'>Have more and more of Gods blessing and kindness. Learn more and more about our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ. He is great now, and he will be great for ever! Amen! Yes he will!</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>