<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText xml:lang='en' osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='ISV'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='ISV'>
        <title>ISV NT</title>
        <contributor>Sword Project</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-22</date>
        <description>The International Standard Version version 1.2.1</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>ISV</identifier>
        <source>http://www.crosswire.org/sword/servlet/</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>http://www.isv.org</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='2Thess'>
      <chapter osisID='2Thess.1'>
        <title>So then, encourage one another with these words.</title>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.1.1'>From Paul, Silvanus, and Timothy, to the church of the Thessalonians in union with God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.1.2'>May grace and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ be yours!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.1.3'>At all times we are obligated to thank God for you, brothers. It is right to do this because your faith is growing all the time and the love of every one of you for each other is increasing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.1.4'>As a result, we boast about you among God's churches—about your endurance and faith through all the persecutions and afflictions you are experiencing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.1.5'>This is evidence of God's righteous judgment and is intended to make you worthy of God's kingdom, for which you are suffering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.1.6'>Certainly it is right for God to pay back those who afflict you with affliction</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.1.7'>and to give us who are afflicted relief when the Lord Jesus is revealed from heaven with his mighty angels</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.1.8'>in blazing fire. He will take revenge on those who do not know God and on those who refuse to obey the gospel of our Lord Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.1.9'>Such people will suffer the punishment of eternal destruction by being separated from the Lord's presence and from his glorious power</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.1.10'>when he comes to be glorified by his saints and to be regarded with wonder on that day by all who have believed—including you, because you believed our testimony.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.1.11'>With this in mind, we always pray for you, asking that our God might make you worthy of his calling and that through his power he might help you accomplish every good desire and faithful work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.1.12'>That way the name of our Lord Jesus will be glorified by you, and you by him, according to the grace of our God and Lord, Jesus Christ.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Thess.2'>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.1'>Now we ask you, brothers, regarding the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ and our gathering together to him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.2'>not to be so quickly upset or alarmed when someone claims that we said either by some spirit, conversation, or letter that the Day of the Lord has already come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.3'>Do not let anyone deceive you in any way, for that day cannot come unless the rebellion takes place first and the man of sin, who is destined for destruction, is revealed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.4'>He opposes and exalts himself above every so-called god and object of worship. As a result, he seats himself in the sanctuary of God and declares himself to be God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.5'>Don't you remember that I repeatedly told you about these things when I was still with you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.6'>You know what it is that is now holding him back, so that he will be revealed when his time comes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.7'>For the secret of this lawlessness is already at work, but only until the person now holding it back gets out of the way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.8'>Then the lawless one will be revealed, whom the Lord will destroy with the breath of his mouth, rendering him powerless by the manifestation of his coming.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.9'>The coming of the lawless one will be accompanied by the power of Satan. He will use every kind of power, including miraculous signs, lying wonders,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.10'>and every type of evil to deceive those who are dying, those who refused to love the truth that would save them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.11'>For this reason, God will send them a powerful delusion so that they will believe the lie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.12'>Then all who have not believed the truth but have taken pleasure in unrighteousness will be condemned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.13'>At all times we are obligated to thank God for you, brothers who are loved by the Lord, because God chose you to be the first fruits for salvation through sanctification by the Spirit and through faith in the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.14'>With this purpose in mind, he called you through our proclamation of the gospel so that you would obtain the glory of our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.15'>So then, brothers, stand firm, and cling to the traditions that you were taught by us, either by word of mouth or by our letter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.16'>May our Lord Jesus Christ himself and God our Father, who loved us and by his grace gave us eternal comfort and good hope,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.2.17'>encourage your hearts and strengthen you in every good work and word.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Thess.3'>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.1'>Finally, brothers, pray for us—that the word of the Lord may spread rapidly, and that it may be honored the way it is among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.2'>Also pray that we may be rescued from worthless and evil people, since not everyone holds to the faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.3'>But the Lord is faithful and will strengthen you and protect you from the evil one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.4'>We have confidence in the Lord that you are doing and will continue to do what we command.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.5'>May the Lord direct your hearts to the love of God and to the endurance of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.6'>In the name of our Lord Jesus Christ we command you, brothers, to keep away from every brother who is living in idleness and not living according to the tradition that they received from us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.7'>For you yourselves know what you must do to imitate us. We did not live in idleness among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.8'>We did not eat anyone's food without paying for it. Instead, with toil and labor we worked night and day in order not to be a burden to any of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.9'>It is not as though we did not have that right, but, we wanted to give you an example to follow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.10'>While we were with you, we gave this order: “If anyone doesn't want to work, he shouldn't eat.”</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.11'>We hear that some of you are living in idleness. You are not busy working—you are busy interfering in other people's lives!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.12'>We order and encourage such people by the Lord Jesus Christ to do their work quietly and to earn their own living.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.13'>Brothers, do not get tired of doing what is right.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.14'>If anyone does not obey what we say in this letter, take note of him. Have nothing to do with him so that he will feel ashamed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.15'>Yet, don't treat him like an enemy, but warn him like a brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.16'>Now may the Lord of peace give you his peace at all times and in every way. May the Lord be with all of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.17'>I, Paul, am writing this greeting with my own hand. This is the mark in every letter of mine. It is the way I write.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Thess.3.18'>May the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with all of you. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>