<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText xml:lang='en' osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='ISV'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='ISV'>
        <title>ISV NT</title>
        <contributor>Sword Project</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-22</date>
        <description>The International Standard Version version 1.2.1</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>ISV</identifier>
        <source>http://www.crosswire.org/sword/servlet/</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>http://www.isv.org</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='2Tim'>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.1'>
        <title>In the same way, good works are obvious, and those that are not cannot remain hidden.</title>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.1'>From Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by God's will in keeping with the promise of life that is in Christ Jesus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.2'>to Timothy, my dear child. May grace, mercy, and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord be yours!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.3'>I constantly thank my God—whom I serve with a clear conscience, as my ancestors did—when I remember you in my prayers night and day,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.4'>recalling your tears and longing to see you so that I can be filled with joy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.5'>I am reminded of your sincere faith, which lived first in your grandmother Lois and your mother Eunice, and I am convinced that this faith also lives in you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.6'>For this reason, I am reminding you to fan into flames the gift of God that is within you through the laying on of my hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.7'>For God did not give us a spirit of timidity but one of power, love, and self-discipline.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.8'>Therefore, never be ashamed of the testimony about our Lord or of me, his prisoner. Instead, by God's power, join me in suffering for the sake of the gospel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.9'>He saved us and called us with a holy calling, not according to our own works but according to his own purpose and the grace that was given to us in Christ Jesus before time began.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.10'>Now, however, it has been revealed through the coming of our Savior Christ Jesus, who has destroyed death and through the gospel has brought life and release from death into full view.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.11'>For the sake of this gospel I was appointed to be a preacher, an apostle, and a teacher of the Gentiles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.12'>That is why I suffer as I do. However, I am not ashamed, for I know the one in whom I have put my trust, and I'm convinced that he is able to protect what he has entrusted to me until that day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.13'>Hold on to the pattern of healthy teachings that you have heard from me, along with the faith and love that are in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.14'>With the help of the Holy Spirit who lives in us, protect the good treasure that has been entrusted to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.15'>You know that everyone in Asia has abandoned me, including Phygelus and Hermogenes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.16'>May the Lord grant mercy to the family of Onesiphorus, for he often took care of me and was not ashamed that I was a prisoner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.17'>Instead, when he arrived in Rome he searched diligently for me and found me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.18'>May the Lord grant that he finds mercy from the Lord on that day. You know very well how much he assisted me in Ephesus.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.2'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.1'>As for you, my child, be strong in the grace that is in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.2'>What you have heard from me through many witnesses entrust to faithful people who will be able to teach others as well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.3'>Join me in suffering like a good soldier of Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.4'>No one serving in the military gets mixed up in civilian matters, for his aim is to please his commanding officer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.5'>Moreover, no one who is an athlete wins a prize unless he competes according to the rules.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.6'>Furthermore, it is the hard working farmer who should have the first share of the crops.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.7'>Think about what I am saying. The Lord will help you to understand all these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.8'>Meditate on Jesus Christ, who was raised from the dead and is a descendant of David. This is the gospel I tell others.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.9'>Because of it I am experiencing trouble, even to the point of being chained like a criminal. However, God's word is not chained.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.10'>For that reason, I endure everything for the sake of those who have been chosen so that they, too, may receive the salvation that is in Christ Jesus, along with eternal glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.11'>This saying is trustworthy:	In dying with Christ,true life we gain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.12'>Enduring, we with him shall reign.Who him denies,he will disclaim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.13'>Our faith may fail,his never wanes—	For thus he is,he cannot change!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.14'>Remind others about these things, and warn them in the sight of God not to argue over words. Arguing does not do any good but only destroys those who are listening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.15'>Do your best to present yourself to God as an approved worker who has nothing to be ashamed of, handling the word of truth with precision.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.16'>However, avoid pointless discussions. For people will become more and more ungodly,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.17'>and what they say will spread everywhere like gangrene. Hymenaeus and Philetus are like that.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.18'>They have abandoned the truth by claiming that the resurrection has already taken place, and so they destroy the faith of others.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.19'>However, God's solid foundation still stands. It has this inscription on it: “The Lord knows those who belong to him,” and “Everyone who calls on the name of the Lord must turn away from evil.”</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.20'>In a large house there are not only utensils made of gold and silver, but also those made of wood and clay. Some are for special use, while others are for ordinary use.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.21'>Therefore, if anyone stops associating with these people, he will become a special utensil, set apart for the owner's use, prepared for every good work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.22'>Flee from youthful passions. Instead, pursue righteousness, faithfulness, love, and peace together with those who call on the Lord with a pure heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.23'>Do not have anything to do with foolish and stupid discussions, because you know they breed arguments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.24'>A servant of the Lord must not argue. Instead, he must be kind to everyone, teachable, willing to suffer wrong,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.25'>and gentle in refuting his opponents. After all, maybe God will allow them to repent and to come to a full knowledge of the truth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.26'>so that they might escape from the devil's snare, even though they've been held captive by him to do his will.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.3'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.1'>You must realize, however, that in the last days difficult times will come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.2'>People will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boastful, arrogant, abusive, disobedient to their parents, ungrateful, unholy,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.3'>unfeeling, uncooperative, slanderous, degenerate, brutal, hateful of what is good,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.4'>traitors, reckless, conceited, and lovers of pleasure rather than lovers of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.5'>They will hold to an outward form of godliness but deny its power. Stay away from such people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.6'>For some of these men go into homes and deceive foolish women who are burdened with sins and swayed by all kinds of desires.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.7'>These women are always studying but are never able to arrive at a full knowledge of the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.8'>Just as Jannes and Jambres opposed Moses, so these men oppose the truth. They are depraved in mind and their faith is a counterfeit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.9'>But they will not get very far because, as in the case of those two men, their stupidity will be plain to everyone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.10'>But you have observed my teaching, my way of life, my purpose, my faith, my patience, my love, my endurance,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.11'>and my persecutions and sufferings that happened to me in Antioch, Iconium, and Lystra. What persecutions I endured! Yet the Lord rescued me from all of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.12'>Indeed, all who want to live a godly life in union with Christ Jesus will be persecuted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.13'>But evil people and impostors will go from bad to worse as they deceive others and are themselves deceived.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.14'>But as for you, continue in what you have learned and found to be true, because you know from whom you learned it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.15'>From infancy you have known the Holy Scriptures that are able to give you the wisdom you need for salvation through faith in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.16'>All Scripture is God-breathed and is useful for teaching, for reproof, for correction, and for training in righteousness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.17'>so that the man of God may be complete and thoroughly equipped for every good work.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.4'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.1'>In the presence of God and Christ Jesus, who is going to judge those who are living and those who are dead, and in view of his appearing and his kingdom, I solemnly appeal to you</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.2'>to proclaim the message. Be ready to do this whether or not the time is convenient. Refute, warn, and encourage with the utmost patience when you teach.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.3'>For the time will come when people will not put up with healthy doctrine but with itching ears will surround themselves with teachers who cater to their own needs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.4'>They will refuse to listen to the truth and will turn to myths.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.5'>But you must be clear-headed about everything. Endure suffering. Do the work of an evangelist. Devote yourself completely to your ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.6'>For I am already being poured out as an offering, and the time for my departure has come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.7'>I have fought the good fight. I have completed the race. I have kept the faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.8'>The victor's crown of righteousness is now waiting for me, which the Lord, the righteous Judge, will give to me on that day, and not only to me but also to all who eagerly wait for his appearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.9'>Do your best to come to me soon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.10'>For Demas, having fallen in love with this present world, has abandoned me and has gone to Thessalonica. Crescens has gone to Galatia, and Titus to Dalmatia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.11'>Only Luke is with me. Get Mark and bring him with you, for he is useful in my ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.12'>I have sent Tychicus to Ephesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.13'>When you come, bring the coat I left with Carpus in Troas, as well as the scrolls and especially the parchments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.14'>Alexander the metalworker did me a great deal of harm. The Lord will pay him back for what he did.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.15'>You, too, must watch out for him, for he violently opposed our message.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.16'>At my first trial no one came to my defense. Everyone abandoned me. May it not be held against them!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.17'>However, the Lord stood by me and gave me strength so that through me the message might be fully proclaimed and all the Gentiles could hear it. I was rescued out of a lion's mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.18'>The Lord will rescue me from every evil attack and will take me safely to his heavenly kingdom. Glory belongs to him forever and ever! Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.19'>Greet Prisca and Aquila and the family of Onesiphorus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.20'>Erastus stayed in Corinth, and I left Trophimus in Miletus because he was sick.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.21'>Do your best to come to me before winter. Eubulus sends you greetings, as do Pudens, Linus, Claudia, and all the brothers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.22'>May the Lord be with your spirit. Grace be with all of you! Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>