<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='RYLT' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='RYLT'>
        <title>Revised Young's Literal Translation NT</title>
        <contributor>J.N. Young</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>Holy Bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-22</date>
        <description>[Revised Young's Literal Translation of the NT by J.N. Young,]
	1862, 1898 (Author of the Young's Analytical Concordance)</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>RYLT</identifier>
        <source>http://www.auburn.edu/~allenkc/rylt/rylt_nt.zip</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='1Tim'>
      <chapter osisID='1Tim.1'>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.1'>Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ, according to a command of God our Saviour, and of the Lord Jesus Christ our hope,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.2'>to Timothy -- genuine child in faith: Grace, kindness, peace, from God our Father, and Christ Jesus our Lord,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.3'>according as I did exhort you to remain in Ephesus -- I going on to Macedonia -- that you might charge certain not to teach any other thing,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.4'>nor to give heed to fables and endless genealogies, that cause questions rather than the building up of God that is in faith: --</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.5'>And the end of the charge is love out of a pure heart, and of a good conscience, and of faith unfeigned,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.6'>from which certain, having swerved, did turn aside to vain discourse,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.7'>willing to be teachers of law, not understanding either the things they say, nor concerning what they asseverate,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.8'>and we have known that the law is good, if any one may use it lawfully;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.9'>having known this, that for a righteous man law is not set, but for lawless and insubordinate persons, ungodly and sinners, impious and profane, parricides and matricides, men-slayers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.10'>whoremongers, sodomites, men-stealers, liars, perjured persons, and if there be any other thing that to sound doctrine is adverse,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.11'>according to the good news of the glory of the blessed God, with which I was entrusted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.12'>And I give thanks to him who enabled me -- Christ Jesus our Lord -- that he did reckon me stedfast, having put me to the ministration,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.13'>who before was speaking evil, and persecuting, and insulting, but I found kindness, because, being ignorant, I did it in unbelief,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.14'>and exceedingly abound did the grace of our Lord, with faith and love that is in Christ Jesus:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.15'>stedfast is the word, and of all acceptation worthy, that Christ Jesus came to the world to save sinners -- first of whom I am;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.16'>but because of this I found kindness, that in me first Jesus Christ might show forth all long-suffering, for a pattern of those about to believe on him to life age-during:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.17'>and to the King of the ages, the incorruptible, invisible, only wise God, is honour and glory -- to the ages of the ages! Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.18'>This charge I commit to you, child Timothy, according to the prophesies that went before upon you, that you may war in them the good warfare,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.19'>having faith and a good conscience, which certain having thrust away, concerning the faith did make shipwreck,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.20'>of whom are Hymenaeus and Alexander, whom I did deliver to the Adversary, that they might be instructed not to speak evil.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Tim.2'>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.1'>I exhort, then, first of all, there be made supplications, prayers, intercessions, thanksgivings, for all men:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.2'>for kings, and all who are in authority, that a quiet and peaceable life we may lead in all piety and gravity,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.3'>for this is right and acceptable before God our Saviour,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.4'>who does will all men to be saved, and to come to the full knowledge of the truth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.5'>for one is God, one also is mediator of God and of men, the man Christ Jesus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.6'>who did give himself a ransom for all -- the testimony in its own times --</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.7'>in regard to which I was set a preacher and apostle -- truth I say in Christ, I do not lie -- a teacher of nations, in faith and truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.8'>I wish, therefore, that men pray in every place, lifting up kind hands, apart from anger and reasoning;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.9'>in like manner also the women, in becoming apparel, with modesty and sobriety to adorn themselves, not in braided hair, or gold, or pearls, or garments of great price,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.10'>but -- which becomes women professing godly piety -- through good works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.11'>Let a woman in quietness learn in all subjection,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.12'>and a woman I do not suffer to teach, nor to rule a husband, but to be in quietness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.13'>for Adam was first formed, then Eve,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.14'>and Adam was not deceived, but the woman, having been deceived, into transgression came,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.15'>and she shall be saved through the child-bearing, if they remain in faith, and love, and sanctification, with sobriety.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Tim.3'>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.1'>Stedfast is the word: If any one the oversight does long for, a right work he desires;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.2'>it benefits, therefore, the overseer to be blameless, of one wife a husband, vigilant, sober, decent, a friend of strangers, apt to teach,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.3'>not given to wine, not a striker, not given to filthy lucre, but gentle, not contentious, not a lover of money,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.4'>his own house leading well, having children in subjection with all gravity,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.5'>(and if any one his own house how to lead has not known, how an assembly of God shall he take care of?)</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.6'>not a new convert, lest having been puffed up he may fall to a judgment of the devil;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.7'>and it benefits him also to have a good testimony from those without, that he may not fall into reproach and a snare of the devil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.8'>Ministers -- in like manner grave, not double-tongued, not given to much wine, not given to filthy lucre,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.9'>having the secret of the faith in a pure conscience,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.10'>and let these also first be proved, then let them minister, being unblameable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.11'>Women -- in like manner grave, not false accusers, vigilant, faithful in all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.12'>Ministers -- let them be of one wife husbands; the children leading well, and their own houses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.13'>for those who did minister well a good step to themselves do acquire, and much boldness in faith that is in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.14'>These things I write to you, hoping to come unto you soon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.15'>and if I delay, that you may know how it benefits you to conduct yourself in the house of God, which is an assembly of the living God -- a pillar and foundation of the truth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.16'>and, confessedly, great is the secret of piety -- God was manifested in flesh, declared righteous in spirit, seen by messengers, preached among nations, believed on in the world, taken up in glory!</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Tim.4'>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.1'>And the Spirit expressly speaks, that in latter times shall certain fall away from the faith, giving heed to seducing spirits and teachings of demons,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.2'>in hypocrisy speaking lies, being seared in their own conscience,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.3'>forbidding to marry -- to abstain from meats that God created to be received with thanksgiving by those believing and acknowledging the truth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.4'>because every creature of God is good, and nothing is to be rejected, with thanksgiving being received,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.5'>for it is sanctified through the word of God and intercession.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.6'>These things placing before the brethren, you shall be a good minister of Jesus Christ, being nourished by the words of the faith, and of the good teaching, which you did follow after,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.7'>and the profane and old women's fables reject you, and exercise yourself unto piety,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.8'>for the bodily exercise is unto little profit, and the piety is to all things profitable, a promise having of the life that now is, and of that which is coming;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.9'>stedfast is the word, and of all acceptation worthy;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.10'>for this we both labour and are reproached, because we hope on the living God, who is Saviour of all men -- especially of those believing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.11'>Charge these things, and teach;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.12'>let no one despise your youth, but a pattern become you of those believing in word, in behaviour, in love, in spirit, in faith, in purity;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.13'>till I come, give heed to the reading, to the exhortation, to the teaching;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.14'>be not careless of the gift in you, that was given you through prophecy, with laying on of the hands of the eldership;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.15'>of these things be careful; in these things be, that your advancement may be manifest in all things;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.16'>take heed to yourself, and to the teaching; remain in them, for this thing doing, both yourself you shall save, and those hearing you.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Tim.5'>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.1'>An aged person you may not rebuke, but be entreating as a father; younger persons as brethren;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.2'>aged women as mothers, younger ones as sisters -- in all purity;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.3'>honour widows who are really widows;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.4'>and if any widow has children or grandchildren, let them learn first to their own house to show piety, and to give back a recompense to the parents, for this is right and acceptable before God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.5'>And she who is really a widow and desolate, has hoped upon God, and does remain in the supplications and in the prayers night and day,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.6'>and she who is given to luxury, living -- has died;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.7'>and these things charge, that they may be blameless;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.8'>and if any one for his own -- and especially for those of the household -- does not provide, the faith he has denied, and than an unbeliever he is worse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.9'>A widow -- let her not be enrolled under sixty years of age, having been a wife of one husband,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.10'>in good works being testified to: if she brought up children, if she entertained strangers, if saints' feet she washed, if those in tribulation she relieved, if every good work she followed after;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.11'>and younger widows be refusing, for when they may revel against the Christ, they wish to marry,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.12'>having judgment, because the first faith they did cast away,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.13'>and at the same time also, they learn to be idle, going about the houses; and not only idle, but also tattlers and busybodies, speaking the things they ought not;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.14'>I wish, therefore, younger ones to marry, to bear children, to be mistress of the house, to give no occasion to the opposer to reviling;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.15'>for already certain did turn aside after the Adversary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.16'>If any believing man or believing woman have widows, let them relieve them, and let not the assembly be burdened, that those really widows it may relieve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.17'>The well-leading elders of double honour let them be counted worthy, especially those labouring in word and teaching,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.18'>for the Writing says, 'An ox treading out you shall not muzzle,' and 'Worthyis the workman of his reward.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.19'>Against an elder an accusation receive not, except upon two or three witnesses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.20'>Those sinning, reprove before all, that the others also may have fear;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.21'>I testify fully, before God and the Lord Jesus Christ, and the choice messengers, that these things you may keep, without forejudging, doing nothing by partiality.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.22'>Be laying hands quickly on no one, nor be having fellowship with sins of others; be keeping yourself pure;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.23'>no longer be drinking water, but a little wine be using, because of your stomach and of your often infirmities;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.24'>of certain men the sins are manifest beforehand, leading before to judgment, and certain also they follow after;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.25'>in like manner also the right works are manifest beforehand, and those that are otherwise are not able to be hid.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Tim.6'>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.1'>As many as are servants under a yoke, their own masters worthy of all honour let them reckon, that the name of God and the teaching may not be evil spoken of;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.2'>and those having believing masters, let them not slight them, because they are brethren, but rather let them serve, because they are stedfast and beloved, who of the benefit are partaking. These things be teaching and exhorting;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.3'>if any one be teaching otherwise, and do not consent to sound words -- those of our Lord Jesus Christ -- and to the teaching according to piety,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.4'>he is proud, knowing nothing, but doting about questions and word-striving, out of which does come envy, strife, evil-speakings, evil-surmisings,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.5'>wranglings of men wholly corrupted in mind, and destitute of the truth, supposing the piety to be gain; depart from such;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.6'>but it is great gain -- the piety with contentment;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.7'>for nothing did we bring into the world -- it is manifest that we are able to carry nothing out;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.8'>but having food and raiment -- with these we shall suffice ourselves;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.9'>and those wishing to be rich, do fall into temptation and a snare, and many desires, foolish and hurtful, that sink men into ruin and destruction,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.10'>for a root of all the evils is the love of money, which certain longing for did go astray from the faith, and themselves did pierce through with many sorrows;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.11'>and you, O man of God, these things flee, and pursue righteousness, piety, faith, love, endurance, meekness;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.12'>be striving the good strife of the faith, be laying hold on the life age-during, to which also you wast called, and did profess the right profession before many witnesses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.13'>I charge you, before God, who is making all things alive, and of Christ Jesus, who did testify before Pontius Pilate the right profession,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.14'>that you keep the command unspotted, unblameable, till the manifestation of our Lord Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.15'>which in His own times He shall show -- the blessed and only potentate, the King of the kings and Lord of the lords,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.16'>who only is having immortality, dwelling in light unapproachable, whom no one of men did see, nor is able to see, to whom is honour and might age-during! Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.17'>Those rich in the present age charge you not to be high-minded, nor to hope in the uncertainty of riches, but in the living God, who is giving to us all things richly for enjoyment; --</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.18'>to do good, to be rich in good works, to be ready to impart, willing to communicate,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.19'>treasuring up to themselves a right foundation for the time to come, that they may lay hold on the life age-during.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.20'>O Timothy, the thing entrusted guard you, avoiding the profane vain-words and opposition of the falsely-named knowledge,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.21'>which certain professing -- concerning the faith did swerve; the grace is with you. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>