<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='RYLT' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='RYLT'>
        <title>Revised Young's Literal Translation NT</title>
        <contributor>J.N. Young</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>Holy Bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-22</date>
        <description>[Revised Young's Literal Translation of the NT by J.N. Young,]
	1862, 1898 (Author of the Young's Analytical Concordance)</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>RYLT</identifier>
        <source>http://www.auburn.edu/~allenkc/rylt/rylt_nt.zip</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='2Cor'>
      <chapter osisID='2Cor.1'>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.1'>Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ, through the will of God, and Timotheus the brother, to the assembly of God that is in Corinth, with all the saints who are in all Achaia:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.2'>Grace to you and peace from God our Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.3'>Blessed is God, even the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of the mercies, and God of all comfort,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.4'>who is comforting us in all our tribulation, for our being able to comfort those in any tribulation through the comfort with which we are comforted ourselves by God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.5'>because, as the sufferings of the Christ do abound to us, so through the Christ does abound also our comfort;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.6'>and whether we be in tribulation, it is for your comfort and salvation, that is wrought in the enduring of the same sufferings that we also suffer; whether we are comforted, it is for your comfort and salvation;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.7'>and our hope is stedfast for you, knowing that even as you are partakers of the sufferings -- so also of the comfort.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.8'>For we do not wish you to be ignorant, brethren, of our tribulation that happened to us in Asia, that we were exceedingly burdened above our power, so that we despaired even of life;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.9'>but we ourselves in ourselves the sentence of the death have had, that we may not be trusting on ourselves, but on God, who is raising the dead,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.10'>who out of so great a death did deliver us, and does deliver, in whom we have hoped that even yet He will deliver;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.11'>you working together also for us by your supplication, that the gift through many persons to us, through many may be thankfully acknowledged for us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.12'>For our glorying is this: the testimony of our conscience, that in simplicity and sincerity of God, not in fleshly wisdom, but in the grace of God, we did conduct ourselves in the world, and more abundantly toward you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.13'>for no other things do we write to you, but what you either do read or also acknowledge, and I hope that also unto the end you shall acknowledge,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.14'>according as also you did acknowledge us in part, that your glory we are, even as also you are ours, in the day of the Lord Jesus;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.15'>and in this confidence I was purposing to come unto you before, that a second favour you might have,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.16'>and through you to pass to Macedonia, and again from Macedonia to come unto you, and by you to be sent forward to Judea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.17'>This, therefore, counselling, did I then use the lightness; or the things that I counsel, according to the flesh do I counsel, that it may be with me Yes, yes, and No, no?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.18'>and God is faithful, that our word unto you became not Yes and No,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.19'>for the Son of God, Jesus Christ, among you through us having been preached -- through me and Silvanus and Timotheus -- did not become Yes and No, but in him it has become Yes;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.20'>for as many as are promises of God, in him are the Yes, and in him the Amen, for glory to God through us;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.21'>and He who is confirming you with us into Christ, and did anoint us, is God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.22'>who also sealed us, and gave the earnest of the Spirit in our hearts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.23'>And I for a witness on God do call upon my soul, that sparing you, I came not yet to Corinth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.1.24'>not that we are lords over your faith, but we are workers together with your joy, for by the faith you stand.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Cor.2'>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.1'>And I decided this to myself, not again to come in sorrow unto you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.2'>for if I make you sorry, then who is he who is making me glad, except he who is made sorry by me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.3'>and I wrote to you this same thing, that having come, I may not have sorrow from them of whom it behoved me to have joy, having confidence in you all, that my joy is of you all,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.4'>for out of much tribulation and pressure of heart I wrote to you through many tears, not that you might be made sorry, but that you might know the love that I have more abundantly toward you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.5'>And if any one has caused sorrow, he has not caused sorrow to me, but in part, that I may not burden you all;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.6'>sufficient to such a one is this punishment, that is by the more part,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.7'>so that, on the contrary, it is rather for you to forgive and to comfort, lest by over abundant sorrow such a one may be swallowed up;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.8'>therefore, I call upon you to confirm love to him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.9'>for, for this also did I write, that I might know the proof of you, whether in regard to all things you are obedient.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.10'>And to whom you forgive anything -- I also; for I also, if I have forgiven anything, to whom I have forgiven it, because of you -- in the person of Christ -- I forgive it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.11'>that we may not be over-reached by the Adversary, for of his devices we are not ignorant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.12'>And having come to Troas for the good news of the Christ, and a door to me having been opened in the Lord,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.13'>I have not had rest to my spirit, on my not finding Titus my brother, but having taken leave of them, I went forth to Macedonia;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.14'>and to God are thanks, who at all times is leading us in triumph in the Christ, and the fragrance of His knowledge He is manifesting through us in every place,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.15'>because of Christ a sweet fragrance we are to God, in those being saved, and in those being lost;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.16'>to the one, indeed, a fragrance of death to death, and to the other, a fragrance of life to life; and for these things who is sufficient?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.2.17'>for we are not as the many, adulterating the word of God, but as of sincerity -- but as of God; in the presence of God, in Christ we do speak.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Cor.3'>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.1'>Do we begin again to recommend ourselves, except we need, as some, letters of recommendation unto you, or from you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.2'>our letter you are, having been written in our hearts, known and read by all men,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.3'>manifested that you are a letter of Christ ministered by us, written not with ink, but with the Spirit of the living God, not in the tablets of stone, but in fleshy tablets of the heart,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.4'>and such trust we have through the Christ toward God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.5'>not that we are sufficient of ourselves to think anything, as of ourselves, but our sufficiency is of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.6'>who also made us sufficient to be ministrants of a new covenant, not of letter, but of spirit; for the letter does kill, and the spirit does make alive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.7'>and if the ministration of the death, in letters, engraved in stones, came in glory, so that the sons of Israel were not able to look stedfastly to the face of Moses, because of the glory of his face -- which was being made useless,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.8'>how shall the ministration of the Spirit not be more in glory?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.9'>for if the ministration of the condemnation is glory, much more does the ministration of the righteousness abound in glory;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.10'>for also even that which has been glorious, has not been glorious -- in this respect, because of the superior glory;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.11'>for if that which is being made useless is through glory, much more that which is remaining is in glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.12'>Having, then, such hope, we use much freedom of speech,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.13'>and are not as Moses, who was putting a vail upon his own face, for the sons of Israel not stedfastly to look to the end of that which is being made useless,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.14'>but their minds were hardened, for unto this day the same vail at the reading of the Old Covenant does remain unwithdrawn -- which in Christ is being made useless --</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.15'>but till to-day, when Moses is read, a vail upon their heart does lie,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.16'>and whenever they may turn unto the Lord, the vail is taken away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.17'>And the Lord is the Spirit; and where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is liberty;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.3.18'>and we all, with unveiled face, the glory of the Lord beholding in a mirror, to the same image are being transformed, from glory to glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Cor.4'>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.1'>Because of this, having this ministration, according as we did receive kindness, we do not faint,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.2'>but did renounce for ourselves the hidden things of shame, not walking in craftiness, nor deceitfully using the word of God, but by the manifestation of the truth recommending ourselves unto every conscience of men, before God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.3'>and if also our good news is veiled, in those perishing it is veiled,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.4'>in whom the god of this age did blind the minds of the unbelieving, that there does not shine forth to them the enlightening of the good news of the glory of the Christ, who is the image of God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.5'>for not ourselves do we preach, but Christ Jesus -- Lord, and ourselves your servants because of Jesus;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.6'>because it is God who said, Out of darkness light is to shine, who did shine in our hearts, for the enlightening of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.7'>And we have this treasure in earthen vessels, that the excellency of the power may be of God, and not of us;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.8'>on every side being in tribulation, but not straitened; perplexed, but not in despair;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.9'>persecuted, but not forsaken; cast down, but not destroyed;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.10'>at all times the dying of the Lord Jesus bearing about in the body, that the life also of Jesus in our body may be manifested,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.11'>for always are we who are living delivered up to death because of Jesus, that the life also of Jesus may be manifested in our dying flesh,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.12'>so that, the death indeed in us does work, and the life in you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.13'>And having the same spirit of the faith, according to that which has been written, 'I believed, therefore I did speak;' we also do believe, therefore also do we speak;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.14'>knowing that He who did raise up the Lord Jesus, us also through Jesus shall raise up, and shall present with you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.15'>for the all things are because of you, that the grace having been multiplied, because of the thanksgiving of the more, may abound to the glory of God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.16'>therefore, we faint not, but if also our outward man does decay, yet the inward is renewed day by day;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.17'>for the momentary light matter of our tribulation, more and more exceedingly an age-during weight of glory does work out for us --</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.4.18'>we not looking to the things seen, but to the things not seen; for the things seen are temporary, but the things not seen are age-during.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Cor.5'>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.1'>For we have known that if our earthly house of the tabernacle may be thrown down, a building from God we have, an house not made with hands -- age-during -- in the heavens,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.2'>for also in this we groan, with our dwelling that is from heaven earnestly desiring to clothe ourselves,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.3'>if so be that, having clothed ourselves, we shall not be found naked,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.4'>for we also who are in the tabernacle do groan, being burdened, seeing we wish not to unclothe ourselves, but to clothe ourselves, that the mortal may be swallowed up of the life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.5'>And He who did work us to this self-same thing is God, who also did give to us the earnest of the Spirit;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.6'>having courage, then, at all times, and knowing that being at home in the body, we are away from home from the Lord, --</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.7'>for through faith we walk, not through sight --</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.8'>we have courage, and are well pleased rather to be away from the home of the body, and to be at home with the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.9'>Therefore also we are ambitious, whether at home or away from home, to be well pleasing to him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.10'>for all of us it behooves to be manifested before the tribunal of the Christ, that each one may receive the things done through the body, in reference to the things that he did, whether good or evil;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.11'>having known, therefore, the fear of the Lord, we persuade men, and to God we are manifested, and I hope also in your consciences to have been manifested;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.12'>for not again ourselves do we recommend to you, but we are giving occasion to you of glorifying in our behalf, that you may have something in reference to those glorifying in face and not in heart;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.13'>for whether we were beside ourselves, it was to God; whether we be of sound mind -- it is to you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.14'>for the love of the Christ does constrain us, having judged thus: that if one for all died, then the whole died,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.15'>and for all he died, that those living, no more to themselves may live, but to him who died for them, and was raised again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.16'>So that we henceforth have known no one according to the flesh, and even if we have known Christ according to the flesh, yet now we know him no more;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.17'>so that if any one is in Christ -- he is a new creature; the old things did pass away, lo, become new have the all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.18'>And the all things are of God, who reconciled us to Himself through Jesus Christ, and did give to us the ministration of the reconciliation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.19'>how that God was in Christ -- a world reconciling to Himself, not reckoning to them their trespasses; and having put in us the word of the reconciliation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.20'>in behalf of Christ, then, we are ambassadors, as if God were calling through us, we beseech, in behalf of Christ, 'Be you reconciled to God;'</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.5.21'>for him who did not know sin, in our behalf He did make sin, that we may become the righteousness of God in him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Cor.6'>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.1'>And working together also we call upon you that you receive not in vain the grace of God --</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.2'>for He says, 'In an acceptable time I did hear you, and in a day of salvation I did help you, lo, now is a well-accepted time; lo, now, a day of salvation,' --</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.3'>in nothing giving any cause of offence, that the ministration may be not blamed,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.4'>but in everything recommending ourselves as God's ministrants; in much patience, in tribulations, in necessities, in distresses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.5'>in stripes, in imprisonments, in insurrections, in labours, in watchings, in fastings,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.6'>in pureness, in knowledge, in long-suffering, in kindness, in the Holy Spirit, in love unfeigned,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.7'>in the word of truth, in the power of God, through the armour of the righteousness, on the right and on the left,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.8'>through glory and dishonour, through evil report and good report, as leading astray, and true;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.9'>as unknown, and recognized; as dying, and lo, we live; as chastened, and not put to death;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.10'>as sorrowful, and always rejoicing; as poor, and making many rich; as having nothing, and possessing all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.11'>Our mouth has been open unto you, O Corinthians, our heart has been enlarged!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.12'>you are not straitened in us, and you are straitened in your own bowels,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.13'>and as a recompense of the same kind, (as to children I say it,) be you enlarged -- also you!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.14'>Become not yoked with others -- unbelievers, for what partaking is there to righteousness and lawlessness?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.15'>and what fellowship to light with darkness? and what concord to Christ with Belial? or what part to a believer with an unbeliever?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.16'>and what agreement to the sanctuary of God with idols? for you are a sanctuary of the living God, according as God said -- 'I will dwell in them, and will walk among them, and I will be their God, and they shall be My people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.17'>therefore, come you forth out of the midst of them, and be separated, says the Lord, and an unclean thing do not touch, and I -- I will receive you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.6.18'>and I will be to you for a Father, and you -- you shall be to Me for sons and daughters, says the Lord Almighty.'</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Cor.7'>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.1'>Having, then, these promises, beloved, may we cleanse ourselves from every pollution of flesh and spirit, perfecting sanctification in the fear of God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.2'>receive us; no one did we wrong; no one did we waste; no one did we defraud;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.3'>not to condemn you do I say it, for I have said before that in our hearts you are to die with and to live with;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.4'>great is my freedom of speech unto you, great my glory on your behalf; I have been filled with the comfort, I overabound with the joy on all our tribulation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.5'>for also we, having come to Macedonia, no relaxation has our flesh had, but on every side we are in tribulation, without are fightings, within -- fears;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.6'>but He who is comforting the cast-down -- God -- He did comfort us in the presence of Titus;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.7'>and not only in his presence, but also in the comfort with which he was comforted over you, declaring to us your longing desire, your lamentation, your zeal for me, so that the more I did rejoice,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.8'>because even if I made you sorry in the letter, I do not repent -- if even I did repent -- for I perceive that the letter, even if for an hour, did make you sorry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.9'>I now do rejoice, not that you were made sorry, but that you were made sorry to reformation, for you were made sorry toward God, that in nothing you might receive damage from us;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.10'>for the sorrow toward God reformation to salvation not to be repented of does work, and the sorrow of the world does work death,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.11'>for, lo, this same thing -- your being made sorry toward God -- how much diligence it does work in you! but defence, but displeasure, but fear, but longing desire, but zeal, but revenge; in every thing you did approve yourselves to be pure in the matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.12'>If, then, I also wrote to you -- not for his cause who did wrong, nor for his cause who did suffer wrong, but for our diligence in your behalf being manifested unto you before God --</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.13'>because of this we have been comforted in your comfort, and more abundantly the more did we rejoice in the joy of Titus, that his spirit has been refreshed from you all;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.14'>because if anything to him in your behalf I have boasted, I was not put to shame; but as all things in truth we did speak to you, so also our boasting before Titus became truth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.15'>and his tender affection is more abundantly toward you, remembering the obedience of you all, how with fear and trembling you did receive him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.7.16'>I rejoice, therefore, that in everything I have courage in you.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Cor.8'>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.1'>And we make known to you, brethren, the grace of God, that has been given in the assemblies of Macedonia,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.2'>because in much trial of tribulation the abundance of their joy, and their deep poverty, did abound to the riches of their liberality;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.3'>because, according to their power, I testify, and above their power, they were willing of themselves,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.4'>with much entreaty calling on us to receive the favour and the fellowship of the ministration to the saints,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.5'>and not according as we expected, but themselves they did give first to the Lord, and to us, through the will of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.6'>so that we exhorted Titus, that, according as he did begin before, so also he may finish to you also this favour,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.7'>but even as in every thing you do abound, in faith, and word, and knowledge, and all diligence, and in your love to us, that also in this grace you may abound;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.8'>not according to command do I speak, but because of the diligence of others, and of your love proving the genuineness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.9'>for you know the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, that because of you he became poor -- being rich, that you by that poverty may become rich.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.10'>And an opinion in this do I give: for this to you is expedient, who not only to do, but also to will, did begin before -- a year ago,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.11'>and now also finish doing it, that even as there is the readiness of the will, so also the finishing, out of that which you have,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.12'>for if the willing mind is present, according to that which any one may have it is well-accepted, not according to that which he has not;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.13'>for not that for others release, and you pressured, do I speak,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.14'>but by equality, at the present time your abundance -- for their want, that also their abundance may be for your want, that there may be equality,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.15'>according as it has been written, 'He who did gather much, had nothing over; and he who did gather little, had no lack.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.16'>And thanks to God, who is putting the same diligence for you in the heart of Titus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.17'>because indeed the exhortation he accepted, and being more diligent, of his own accord he went forth unto you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.18'>and we sent with him the brother, whose praise in the good news is through all the assemblies,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.19'>and not only so, but who was also appointed by vote by the assemblies, our fellow-traveller, with this favour that is ministered by us, unto the glory of the same Lord, and your willing mind;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.20'>avoiding this, lest any one may blame us in this abundance that is ministered by us,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.21'>providing right things, not only before the Lord, but also before men;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.22'>and we sent with them our brother, whom we proved in many things many times being diligent, and now much more diligent, by the great confidence that is toward you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.23'>whether -- about Titus -- my partner and towards you fellow-worker, whether -- our brethren, apostles of assemblies -- glory of Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.8.24'>the shewing therefore of your love, and of our boasting on your behalf, to them shew you, even in the face of the assemblies.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Cor.9'>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.9.1'>For, indeed, concerning the ministration that is for the saints, it is superfluous for me to write to you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.9.2'>for I have known your readiness of mind, which in your behalf I boast of to Macedonians, that Achaia has been prepared a year ago, and the zeal of you did stir up the more part,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.9.3'>and I sent the brethren, that our boasting on your behalf may not be made vain in this respect; that, according as I said, you may be ready,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.9.4'>lest if Macedonians may come with me, and find you unprepared, we -- we may be put to shame (that we say not -- you) in this same confidence of boasting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.9.5'>Necessary, therefore, I thought it to exhort the brethren, that they may go before to you, and may make up before your formerly announced blessing, that this be ready, as a blessing, and not as covetousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.9.6'>And this: He who is sowing sparingly, sparingly also shall reap; and he who is sowing in blessings, in blessings also shall reap;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.9.7'>each one, according as he does purpose in heart, not out of sorrow or out of necessity, for a cheerful giver does God love,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.9.8'>and God is able all grace to cause to abound to you, that in every thing always all sufficiency having, you may abound to every good work,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.9.9'>(according as it has been written, 'He dispersed abroad, he gave to the poor, his righteousness does remain to the age,')</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.9.10'>and may He who is supplying seed to the sower, and bread for food, supply and multiply your seed sown, and increase the fruits of your righteousness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.9.11'>in every thing being enriched to all liberality, which does work through us thanksgiving to God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.9.12'>because the ministration of this service not only is supplying the wants of the saints, but is also abounding through many thanksgivings to God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.9.13'>through the proof of this ministration glorifying God for the subjection of your confession to the good news of the Christ, and for the liberality of the fellowship to them and to all,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.9.14'>and by their supplication in your behalf, longing after you because of the exceeding grace of God upon you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.9.15'>thanks also to God for His unspeakable gift!</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Cor.10'>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.1'>And I, Paul, myself, do call upon you -- through the meekness and gentleness of the Christ -- who in presence, indeed am humble among you, and being absent, have courage toward you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.2'>and I beseech you, that, being present, I may not have courage, with the confidence with which I reckon to be bold against certain reckoning us as walking according to the flesh;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.3'>for walking in the flesh, not according to the flesh do we war,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.4'>for the weapons of our warfare are not fleshly, but powerful to God for bringing down of strongholds,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.5'>reasonings bringing down, and every high thing lifted up against the knowledge of God, and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of the Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.6'>and being in readiness to avenge every disobedience, whenever your obedience may be fulfilled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.7'>The things in presence do you see? if any one has trusted in himself to be Christ's, this let him reckon again from himself, that according as he is Christ's, so also we are Christ's;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.8'>for even if also anything more abundantly I shall boast concerning our authority, that the Lord gave us for building up, and not for casting you down, I shall not be ashamed;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.9'>that I may not seem as if I would terrify you through the letters,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.10'>'because the letters indeed -- says one -- are weighty and strong, and the bodily presence weak, and the speech despicable.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.11'>This one -- let him reckon thus: that such as we are in word, through letters, being absent, such also, being present, we are in deed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.12'>For we do not make bold to rank or to compare ourselves with certain of those commending themselves, but they, among themselves measuring themselves, and comparing themselves with themselves, are not wise,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.13'>and we in regard to the unmeasured things will not boast ourselves, but after the measure of the line that the God of measure did appoint to us -- to reach even unto you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.14'>for not as not reaching to you do we stretch ourselves overmuch, for even unto you did we come in the good news of the Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.15'>not boasting of the things not measured, in other men's labours, and having hope -- your faith increasing -- in you to be enlarged, according to our line -- into abundance,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.16'>in the places beyond you to proclaim good news, not in another's line in regard to the things made ready, to boast;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.17'>and he who is boasting -- in the Lord let him boast;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.10.18'>for not he who is commending himself is approved, but he whom the Lord does commend.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Cor.11'>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.1'>O that you were bearing with me a little of the folly, but you also do bear with me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.2'>for I am zealous for you with zeal of God, for I did betroth you to one husband, a pure virgin, to present to Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.3'>and I fear, lest, as the serpent did beguile Eve in his subtilty, so your minds may be corrupted from the simplicity that is in the Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.4'>for if, indeed, he who is coming does preach another Jesus whom we did not preach, or another Spirit you receive which you did not receive, or other good news which you did not accept -- well were you bearing it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.5'>for I reckon that I have been nothing behind the very chiefest apostles,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.6'>and even if unlearned in word -- yet not in knowledge, but in every thing we were made manifest in all things to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.7'>The sin did I do -- myself humbling that you might be exalted, because freely the good news of God I did proclaim to you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.8'>other assemblies I did rob, having taken wages, for your ministration;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.9'>and being present with you, and having been in want, I was chargeable to no one, for my lack did the brethren supply -- having come from Macedonia -- and in everything burdenless to you I did keep myself, and will keep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.10'>The truth of Christ is in me, because this boasting shall not be stopped in regard to me in the regions of Achaia;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.11'>therefore? because I do not love you? God has known!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.12'>and what I do, I also will do, that I may cut off the occasion of those wishing an occasion, that in that which they boast they may be found according as we also;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.13'>for those such are false apostles, deceitful workers, transforming themselves into apostles of Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.14'>and no wonder -- for even the Adversary does transform himself into a messenger of light;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.15'>no great thing, then, if also his ministrants do transform themselves as ministrants of righteousness -- whose end shall be according to their works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.16'>Again I say, may no one think me to be a fool; and if otherwise, even as a fool receive me, that I also a little may boast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.17'>That which I speak, I speak not according to the Lord, but as in foolishness, in this the confidence of boasting;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.18'>since many boast according to the flesh, I also will boast:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.19'>for gladly do you bear with the fools -- being wise,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.20'>for you bear, if any one is bringing you under bondage, if any one does devour, if any one does take away, if any one does exalt himself, if any one on the face does smite you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.21'>in reference to dishonour I speak, how that we were weak, and in whatever any one is bold -- in foolishness I say it -- I also am bold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.22'>Hebrews are they? I also! Israelites are they? I also! seed of Abraham are they? I also!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.23'>ministrants of Christ are they? -- as beside myself I speak -- I more; in labours more abundantly, in stripes above measure, in prisons more frequently, in deaths many times;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.24'>from Jews five times forty stripes save one I did receive;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.25'>thrice was I beaten with rods, once was I stoned, thrice was I shipwrecked, a night and a day in the deep I have passed;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.26'>journeyings many times, perils of rivers, perils of robbers, perils from kindred, perils from nations, perils in city, perils in wilderness, perils in sea, perils among false brethren;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.27'>in laboriousness and painfulness, in watchings many times, in hunger and thirst, in fastings many times, in cold and nakedness;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.28'>apart from the things without -- the crowding upon me that is daily -- the care of all the assemblies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.29'>Who is infirm, and I am not infirm? who is stumbled, and I am not fired;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.30'>if to boast it behooves me, of the things of my infirmity I will boast;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.31'>the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ -- who is blessed to the ages -- has known that I do not lie! --</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.32'>In Damascus the ethnarch of Aretas the king was watching the city of the Damascenes, wishing to seize me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.11.33'>and through a window in a rope basket I was let down, through the wall, and fled out of his hands.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Cor.12'>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.1'>To boast, really, is not profitable for me, for I will come to visions and revelations of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.2'>I have known a man in Christ, fourteen years ago -- whether in the body I have not known, whether out of the body I have not known, God has known -- such an one being caught away unto the third heaven;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.3'>and I have known such a man -- whether in the body, whether out of the body, I have not known, God has known, --</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.4'>that he was caught away to the paradise, and heard unutterable sayings, that it is not possible for man to speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.5'>Of such an one I will boast, and of myself I will not boast, except in my infirmities,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.6'>for if I may wish to boast, I shall not be a fool, for truth I will say; but I forebear, lest any one in regard to me may think anything above what he does see me, or does hear anything of me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.7'>and that by the exceeding greatness of the revelations I might not be exalted overmuch, there was given to me a thorn in the flesh, a messenger of the Adversary, that he might buffet me, that I might not be exalted overmuch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.8'>Concerning this thing thrice the Lord did I call upon, that it might depart from me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.9'>and He said to me, 'Sufficient for you is My grace, for My power in infirmity is perfected;' most gladly, therefore, will I rather boast in my infirmities, that the power of the Christ may rest on me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.10'>therefore I am well pleased in infirmities, in damages, in necessities, in persecutions, in distresses -- for Christ; for whenever I am infirm, then I am powerful;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.11'>I have become a fool -- boasting; you -- you did compel me; for I ought by you to have been commended, for in nothing was I behind the very chiefest apostles -- even if I am nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.12'>The signs, indeed, of the apostle were wrought among you in all patience, in signs, and wonders, and mighty deeds,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.13'>for what is there in which you were inferior to the rest of the assemblies, except that I myself was not a burden to you? forgive me this injustice!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.14'>Lo, a third time I am ready to come unto you, and I will not be a burden to you, for I seek not yours, but you, for the children ought not for the parents to lay up, but the parents for the children,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.15'>and I most gladly will spend and be entirely spent for your souls, even if, more abundantly loving you, less I am loved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.16'>And be it so, I -- I did not burden you, but being crafty, with guile I did take you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.17'>any one of those whom I have sent unto you -- by him did I take advantage of you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.18'>I entreated Titus, and did send with him the brother; did Titus take advantage of you? in the same spirit did we not walk? -- did we not in the same steps?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.19'>Again, think you that to you we are making defence? before God in Christ do we speak; and the all things, beloved, are for your up-building,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.20'>for I fear lest, having come, not such as I wish I may find you, and I -- I may be found by you such as you do not wish, lest there be strifes, envyings, wraths, revelries, evil-speakings, whisperings, puffings up, insurrections,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.12.21'>lest again having come, my God may humble me in regard to you, and I may bewail many of those having sinned before, and not having reformed concerning the uncleanness, and whoredom, and lasciviousness, that they did practise.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Cor.13'>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.13.1'>This third time do I come unto you; on the mouth of two witnesses or three shall every saying be established;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.13.2'>I have said before, and I say it before, as being present, the second time, and being absent, now, do I write to those having sinned before, and to all the rest, that if I come again, I will not spare,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.13.3'>since a proof you seek of the Christ speaking in me, who to you is not infirm, but is powerful in you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.13.4'>for even if he was crucified from infirmity, yet he does live from the power of God; for we also are weak in him, but we shall live with him from the power of God toward you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.13.5'>Your ownselves try you, if you are in the faith; your ownselves prove you; do you not know your ownselves, that Jesus Christ is in you, if you be not in some respect disapproved of?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.13.6'>and I hope that you shall know that we -- we are not disapproved of;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.13.7'>and I pray before God that you do no evil, not that we may appear approved, but that you may do that which is right, and we may be as disapproved;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.13.8'>for we are not able to do anything against the truth, but for the truth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.13.9'>for we rejoice when we may be infirm, and you may be powerful; and this also we pray for -- your perfection!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.13.10'>because of this, these things -- being absent -- I write, that being present, I may not treat any sharply, according to the authority that the Lord did give me for building up, and not for casting down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.13.11'>Henceforth, brethren, rejoice; be made perfect, be comforted, be of the same mind, be at peace, and the God of the love and peace shall be with you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.13.12'>salute one another in an holy kiss;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.13.13'>salute you do all the saints;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Cor.13.14'>the grace of the Lord Jesus Christ, and the love of God, and the fellowship of the Holy Spirit, is with you all! Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>