<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='RWebster' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='RWebster'>
        <title>Revised 1833 Webster Version</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>
Revised 1833 Webster Version                                 Oct. 95
====================================================================

Scripture quoted by permission. (RWEBSTER) Version is THE REVISED 
WEBSTER VERSION OF THE HOLY BIBLE. This English text is in the Public
Domain.
      </description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>RWebster</identifier>
        <source>http://www.answersingenesis.org/OnlineBible/files/rwebster.exe</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage/>
        <rights>This English text is in the Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Acts'>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.1'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.1'>The former treatise have I made, O Theophilus, of all that Jesus began both to do and teach,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.2'>Until the day when he was taken up, after that he through the Holy Spirit had given commandments to the apostles whom he had chosen:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.3'>To whom also he showed himself alive after his passion by many infallible proofs, being seen by them forty days, and speaking of the things pertaining to the kingdom of God:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.4'>And, being assembled with them, commanded them that they should not depart from Jerusalem, but wait for the promise of the Father, which, saith he, ye have heard from me. <note>being…: or, eating together</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.5'>For John truly baptized in water; but ye shall be baptized in the Holy Spirit not many days from now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.6'>When they therefore were come together, they asked of him, saying, Lord, wilt thou at this time restore again the kingdom to Israel?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.7'>And he said to them, It is not for you to know the times or the seasons, which the Father hath put in his own power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.8'>But ye shall receive power, after the Holy Spirit is come upon you: and ye shall be witnesses to me both in Jerusalem, and in all Judaea, and in Samaria, and to the uttermost part of the earth. <note>power…: or, the power of the Holy Ghost coming upon you</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.9'>And when he had spoken these things, while they beheld, he was taken up; and a cloud received him out of their sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.10'>And while they looked steadfastly toward heaven as he went up, behold, two men stood by them in white apparel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.11'>Who also said, Ye men of Galilee, why stand ye gazing up to heaven? this same Jesus, who is taken from you into heaven, shall so come in like manner as ye have seen him go into heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.12'>Then they returned to Jerusalem from the mount called Olivet, which is from Jerusalem a sabbath day’s journey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.13'>And when they had come in, they went into an upper room, where abode both Peter, and James, and John, and Andrew, Philip, and Thomas, Bartholomew, and Matthew, James the son of Alphaeus, and Simon Zelotes, and Judas the brother of James.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.14'>These all continued with one accord in prayer and supplication, with the women, and Mary the mother of Jesus, and with his brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.15'>And in those days Peter stood up in the midst of the disciples, and said, (the number of the names together were about an hundred and twenty,)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.16'>Men, brethren, this scripture must needs have been fulfilled, which the Holy Spirit by the mouth of David spoke before concerning Judas, who was guide to them that took Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.17'>For he was numbered with us, and had obtained part of this ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.18'>Now this man purchased a field with the reward of iniquity; and falling headlong, he burst asunder in the midst, and all his bowels gushed out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.19'>And it was known to all the dwellers at Jerusalem; therefore that field is called in their proper tongue, Aceldama, that is to say, The field of blood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.20'>For it is written in the book of Psalms, Let his habitation be desolate, and let no man dwell in it: and his office let another take. <note>bishoprick: or, office, or, charge</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.21'>Therefore of these men who accompanied us all the time that the Lord Jesus went in and out among us,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.22'>Beginning from the baptism of John, to that same day that he was taken up from us, must one be ordained to be a witness with us of his resurrection.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.23'>And they appointed two, Joseph called Barsabas, who was surnamed Justus, and Matthias.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.24'>And they prayed, and said, Thou, Lord, who knowest the hearts of all men, show which of these two thou hast chosen,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.25'>That he may take part of this ministry and apostleship, from which Judas by transgression fell, that he might go to his own place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.1.26'>And they gave forth their lots; and the lot fell upon Matthias; and he was numbered with the eleven apostles.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.2'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.1'>And when the day of Pentecost was fully come, they were all with one accord in one place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.2'>And suddenly there came a sound from heaven as of a rushing mighty wind, and it filled all the house where they were sitting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.3'>And there appeared to them cloven tongues as of fire, and it sat upon each of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.4'>And they were all filled with the Holy Spirit, and began to speak in other tongues, as the Spirit gave them utterance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.5'>And there were dwelling at Jerusalem Jews, devout men, from every nation under heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.6'>Now when this was noised abroad, the multitude came together, and were confounded, because every man heard them speak in his own language. <note>was…: Gr. voice was made confounded: or, troubled in mind</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.7'>And they were all amazed and marvelled, saying one to another, Behold, are not all these who speak Galilaeans?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.8'>And how do we hear every man in our own language, in which we were born?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.9'>Parthians, and Medes, and Elamites, and the dwellers in Mesopotamia, and in Judaea, and Cappadocia, in Pontus, and Asia,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.10'>Phrygia, and Pamphylia, in Egypt, and in the parts of Libya about Cyrene, and strangers of Rome, Jews and proselytes,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.11'>Cretes and Arabians, we hear them speak in our tongues the wonderful works of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.12'>And they were all amazed, and were perplexed, saying one to another, What meaneth this?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.13'>Others mocking said, These men are full of new wine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.14'>But Peter, standing up with the eleven, lifted up his voice, and said to them, Ye men of Judaea, and all ye that dwell at Jerusalem, be this known to you, and hearken to my words:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.15'>For these are not drunk, as ye suppose, seeing it is but the third hour of the day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.16'>But this is that which was spoken by the prophet Joel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.17'>And it shall come to pass in the last days, saith God, I will pour out of my Spirit upon all flesh: and your sons and your daughters shall prophesy, and your young men shall see visions, and your old men shall dream dreams:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.18'>And on my servants and on my handmaidens I will, in those, days pour out of my Spirit; and they shall prophesy:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.19'>And I will show wonders in heaven above, and signs on the earth beneath; blood, and fire, and vapour of smoke:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.20'>The sun shall be turned into darkness, and the moon into blood, before that great and notable day of the Lord come:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.21'>And it shall come to pass, that whoever shall call on the name of the Lord shall be saved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.22'>Ye men of Israel, hear these words; Jesus of Nazareth, a man approved by God among you by miracles and wonders and signs, which God did by him in the midst of you, as ye yourselves also know:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.23'>Him, being delivered by the determinate counsel and foreknowledge of God, ye have taken, and by wicked hands have crucified and slain:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.24'>Whom God hath raised up, having loosed the pains of death: because it was not possible that he should be held by it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.25'>For David speaketh concerning him, I saw the Lord always before my face, for he is on my right hand, that I should not be moved:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.26'>Therefore did my heart rejoice, and my tongue was glad; moreover also my flesh shall rest in hope:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.27'>Because thou wilt not leave my soul in hell, neither wilt thou allow thy Holy One to see corruption.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.28'>Thou hast made known to me the ways of life; thou shalt make me full of joy with thy countenance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.29'>Men, brethren, let me freely speak to you concerning the patriarch David, that he is both dead and buried, and his sepulchre is with us to this day. <note>let me: or, I may</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.30'>Therefore being a prophet, and knowing that God had sworn to him with an oath, that from the fruit of his loins, according to the flesh, he would raise up Christ to sit on his throne;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.31'>He seeing this before spoke of the resurrection of Christ, that his soul was not left in hell, neither did his flesh see corruption.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.32'>This Jesus hath God raised up, of which we all are witnesses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.33'>Therefore being by the right hand of God exalted, and having received from the Father the promise of the Holy Spirit, he hath shed forth this, which ye now see and hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.34'>For David did not ascend into the heavens: but he saith himself, The LORD said to my Lord, Sit thou on my right hand,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.35'>Until I make thy foes thy footstool.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.36'>Therefore let all the house of Israel know assuredly, that God hath made that same Jesus, whom ye have crucified, both Lord and Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.37'>Now when they heard this, they were pricked in their heart, and said to Peter and to the rest of the apostles, Men, brethren, what shall we do?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.38'>Then Peter said to them, Repent ye, and each one of you be baptized in the name of Jesus Christ for the remission of sins, and ye shall receive the gift of the Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.39'>For the promise is to you, and to your children, and to all that are afar off, even as many as the Lord our God shall call.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.40'>And with many other words did he testify and exhort, saying, Save yourselves from this perverse generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.41'>Then they that gladly received his word were baptized: and the same day there were added to them about three thousand souls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.42'>And they continued steadfastly in the apostles’ doctrine and fellowship, and in breaking of bread, and in prayers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.43'>And fear came upon every soul: and many wonders and signs were done by the apostles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.44'>And all that believed were together, and had all things in common;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.45'>And sold their possessions and goods, and parted them to all men, as every man had need.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.46'>And they, continuing daily with one accord in the temple, and breaking bread from house to house, ate their food with gladness and singleness of heart, <note>from…: or, at home</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.2.47'>Praising God, and having favour with all the people. And the Lord added to the church daily such as should be saved.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.3'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.1'>Now Peter and John went up together into the temple at the hour of prayer, being the ninth hour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.2'>And a certain man lame from his mother’s womb was carried, whom they laid daily at the gate of the temple which is called Beautiful, to ask alms of them that entered into the temple;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.3'>Who seeing Peter and John about to go into the temple asked alms.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.4'>And Peter, fastening his eyes upon him with John, said, Look on us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.5'>And he gave heed to them, expecting to receive something from them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.6'>Then Peter said, Silver and gold have I none; but such as I have I give thee: In the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth rise up and walk.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.7'>And he took him by the right hand, and lifted him up: and immediately his feet and ankle bones received strength.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.8'>And he leaping up stood, and walked, and entered with them into the temple, walking, and leaping, and praising God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.9'>And all the people saw him walking and praising God:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.10'>And they knew that it was he who sat for alms at the Beautiful gate of the temple: and they were filled with wonder and amazement at that which had happened to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.11'>And as the lame man who was healed held Peter and John, all the people ran together to them in the porch that is called Solomon’s, greatly wondering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.12'>And when Peter saw it, he answered to the people, Ye men of Israel, why marvel ye at this? or why look ye so earnestly on us, as though by our own power or holiness we had made this man to walk?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.13'>The God of Abraham, and of Isaac, and of Jacob, the God of our fathers, hath glorified his Son Jesus; whom ye delivered up, and denied him in the presence of Pilate, when he was determined to let him go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.14'>But ye denied the Holy One and the Just, and desired a murderer to be granted to you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.15'>And killed the Prince of life, whom God hath raised from the dead; to which we are witnesses. <note>Prince: or, Author</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.16'>And his name through faith in his name hath made this man strong, whom ye see and know: yea, the faith which is by him hath given him this perfect soundness in the presence of you all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.17'>And now, brethren, I know that through ignorance ye did it, as did also your rulers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.18'>But those things, which God before had shown by the mouth of all his prophets, that Christ should suffer, he hath so fulfilled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.19'>Repent ye therefore, and be converted, that your sins may be blotted out, when the times of refreshing shall come from the presence of the Lord;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.20'>And he shall send Jesus Christ, who before was preached to you:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.21'>Whom the heaven must receive until the times of restitution of all things, which God hath spoken by the mouth of all his holy prophets since the world began.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.22'>For Moses truly said to the fathers, A prophet shall the Lord your God raise up to you of your brethren, like me; him shall ye hear in all things whatever he shall say to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.23'>And it shall come to pass, that every soul, who will not hear that prophet, shall be destroyed from among the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.24'>Yea, and all the prophets also from Samuel and those that follow, as many as have spoken, have likewise foretold these days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.25'>Ye are the children of the prophets, and of the covenant which God made with our fathers, saying to Abraham, And in thy seed shall all the kindreds of the earth be blessed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.3.26'>To you first God, having raised up his Son Jesus, sent him to bless you, in turning away each one of you from his iniquities.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.4'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.1'>And as they were speaking to the people, the priests, and the captain of the temple, and the Sadducees, came upon them, <note>captain: or, ruler</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.2'>Being grieved that they taught the people, and preached through Jesus the resurrection from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.3'>And they laid hands on them, and put them in custody to the next day: for it was now evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.4'>But many of them who heard the word believed; and the number of the men was about five thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.5'>And it came to pass on the next day, that their rulers, and elders, and scribes,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.6'>And Annas the high priest, and Caiaphas, and John, and Alexander, and as many as were of the kindred of the high priest, were gathered together at Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.7'>And when they had set them in the midst, they asked, By what power, or by what name, have ye done this?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.8'>Then Peter, filled with the Holy Spirit, said to them, Ye rulers of the people, and elders of Israel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.9'>If we this day are examined concerning the good deed done to the impotent man, by what means he is made well;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.10'>Be it known to you all, and to all the people of Israel, that by the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth, whom ye crucified, whom God raised from the dead, even by him doth this man stand here before you in good health.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.11'>This is the stone which was rejected by you builders, which is become the head of the corner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.12'>Neither is there salvation in any other: for there is no other name under heaven given among men, by which we must be saved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.13'>Now when they saw the boldness of Peter and John, and perceived that they were unlearned and ignorant men, they marvelled; and they took knowledge of them, that they had been with Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.14'>And beholding the man who was healed standing with them, they could say nothing against it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.15'>But when they had commanded them to go aside out of the council, they conferred among themselves,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.16'>Saying, What shall we do to these men? for that indeed a notable miracle hath been done by them is apparent to all them that dwell in Jerusalem; and we cannot deny it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.17'>But that it may spread no further among the people, let us strictly threaten them, that they speak henceforth to no man in this name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.18'>And they called them, and commanded them not to speak at all nor teach in the name of Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.19'>But Peter and John answered and said to them, Whether it is right in the sight of God to hearken to you rather than to God, judge ye.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.20'>For we cannot but speak the things which we have seen and heard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.21'>So when they had further threatened them, they let them go, finding nothing how they might punish them, because of the people: for all men glorified God for that which was done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.22'>For the man was over forty years old, on whom this miracle of healing was performed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.23'>And being released, they went to their own company, and reported all that the chief priests and elders had said to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.24'>And when they heard that, they lifted up their voice to God with one accord, and said, Lord, thou art God, who hast made heaven, and earth, and the sea, and all that is in them:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.25'>Who by the mouth of thy servant David hast said, Why did the heathen rage, and the people imagine vain things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.26'>The kings of the earth stood up, and the rulers were gathered together against the Lord, and against his Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.27'>For in truth against thy holy child Jesus, whom thou hast anointed, both Herod, and Pontius Pilate, with the Gentiles, and the people of Israel, were gathered together,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.28'>To do whatever thy hand and thy counsel determined before to be done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.29'>And now, Lord, behold their threatenings: and grant to thy servants, that with all boldness they may speak thy word,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.30'>By stretching forth thy hand to heal; and that signs and wonders may be done by the name of thy holy child Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.31'>And when they had prayed, the place was shaken where they were assembled; and they were all filled with the Holy Spirit, and they spoke the word of God with boldness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.32'>And the multitude of them that believed were of one heart and of one soul: neither said any of them that any of the things which he possessed was his own; but they had all things in common.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.33'>And with great power the apostles gave witness of the resurrection of the Lord Jesus: and great grace was upon them all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.34'>Neither was there any among them that was needy: for as many as were possessors of lands or houses sold them, and brought the prices of the things that were sold,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.35'>And laid them down at the apostles’ feet: and distribution was made to every man according as he had need.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.36'>And Joses, who by the apostles was surnamed Barnabas, (which is, being interpreted, The son of consolation,) a Levite, and of the country of Cyprus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.4.37'>Having land, sold it, and brought the money, and laid it at the apostles’ feet.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.5'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.1'>But a certain man named Ananias, with Sapphira his wife, sold a possession,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.2'>And kept back part of the price, his wife also knowing of it, and brought a certain part, and laid it at the apostles’ feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.3'>But Peter said, Ananias, why hath Satan filled thy heart to lie to the Holy Spirit, and to keep back part of the price of the land? <note>to lie to: or, to deceive</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.4'>While it remained, was it not thy own? and after it was sold, was it not in thy own power? why hast thou conceived this thing in thy heart? thou hast not lied to men, but to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.5'>And Ananias hearing these words fell down, and died: and great fear came on all them that heard these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.6'>And the young men arose, wrapped him up, and carried him out, and buried him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.7'>And it was about the space of three hours after, when his wife, not knowing what was done, came in.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.8'>And Peter answered to her, Tell me whether ye sold the land for so much? And she said, Yea, for so much.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.9'>Then Peter said to her, How is it that ye have agreed together to tempt the Spirit of the Lord? behold, the feet of them who have buried thy husband are at the door, and shall carry thee out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.10'>Then she fell down immediately at his feet, and died: and the young men came in, and found her dead, and, carrying her forth, buried her by her husband.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.11'>And great fear came upon all the church, and upon as many as heard these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.12'>And by the hands of the apostles were many signs and wonders wrought among the people; (and they were all with one accord in Solomon’s porch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.13'>And of the rest dared no man join himself to them: but the people magnified them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.14'>And believers were the more added to the Lord, multitudes both of men and women.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.15'>So that they brought forth the sick into the streets, and laid them on beds and couches, that at the least the shadow of Peter passing by might overshadow some of them. <note>into…: or, in every street</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.16'>There came also a multitude out of the surrounding cities to Jerusalem, bringing sick persons, and them who were afflicted with unclean spirits: and they were healed every one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.17'>Then the high priest rose up, and all they that were with him, (which is the sect of the Sadducees,) and were filled with indignation, <note>indignation: or, envy</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.18'>And laid their hands on the apostles, and put them in the common prison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.19'>But the angel of the Lord by night opened the prison doors, and brought them forth, and said,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.20'>Go, stand and speak in the temple to the people all the words of this life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.21'>And when they heard that, they entered into the temple early in the morning, and taught. But the high priest came, and they that were with him, and called the council together, and all the elders of the children of Israel, and sent to the prison to have them brought.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.22'>But when the officers came, and found them not in the prison, they returned, and told,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.23'>Saying, The prison truly we found shut with all safety, and the keepers standing outside before the doors: but when we had opened, we found no man within.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.24'>Now when the high priest and the captain of the temple and the chief priests heard these things, they were greatly perplexed about them as to what would come of this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.25'>Then came one and told them, saying, Behold, the men whom ye put in prison are standing in the temple, and teaching the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.26'>Then went the captain with the officers, and brought them without violence: for they feared the people, lest they should have been stoned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.27'>And when they had brought them, they set them before the council: and the high priest asked them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.28'>Saying, Did we not strictly command you that ye should not teach in this name? and, behold, ye have filled Jerusalem with your doctrine, and intend to bring this man’s blood upon us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.29'>Then Peter and the other apostles answered and said, We ought to obey God rather than men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.30'>The God of our fathers raised up Jesus, whom ye slew and hanged on a tree.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.31'>Him hath God exalted with his right hand to be a Prince and a Saviour, to give repentance to Israel, and forgiveness of sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.32'>And we are his witnesses of these things; and so is also the Holy Spirit, whom God hath given to them that obey him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.33'>When they heard that, they were cut to the heart, and took counsel to slay them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.34'>Then stood up one in the council, a Pharisee, named Gamaliel, a teacher of the law, had in reputation among all the people, and commanded to put the apostles forth a little time;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.35'>And said to them, Ye men of Israel, take heed to yourselves what ye intend to do concerning these men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.36'>For before these days rose Theudas, boasting himself to be somebody; to whom a number of men, about four hundred, joined themselves: who was slain; and all, as many as obeyed him, were scattered, and brought to nought. <note>obeyed: or, believed</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.37'>After this man rose Judas of Galilee in the days of the taxing, and drew away many people after him: he also perished; and all, even as many as obeyed him, were dispersed. <note>obeyed: or, believed</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.38'>And now I say to you, Stay away from these men, and let them alone: for if this counsel or this work is from men, it will come to nothing:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.39'>But if it is from God, ye cannot overthrow it; lest perhaps ye be found even to fight against God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.40'>And to him they assented: and when they had called the apostles, and beaten them, they commanded that they should not speak in the name of Jesus, and let them go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.41'>And they departed from the presence of the council, rejoicing that they were counted worthy to suffer shame for his name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.5.42'>And daily in the temple, and in every house, they ceased not to teach and preach Jesus Christ.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.6'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.6.1'>And in those days, when the number of the disciples was multiplied, there arose a murmuring of the Grecians against the Hebrews, because their widows were neglected in the daily ministration.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.6.2'>Then the twelve called the multitude of the disciples, and said, It is not desirable that we should leave the word of God, and serve tables.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.6.3'>Therefore, brethren, look ye out among you seven men of honest report, full of the Holy Spirit and wisdom, whom we may appoint over this business.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.6.4'>But we will give ourselves continually to prayer, and to the ministry of the word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.6.5'>And the saying pleased the whole multitude: and they chose Stephen, a man full of faith and of the Holy Spirit, and Philip, and Prochorus, and Nicanor, and Timon, and Parmenas, and Nicolas a proselyte of Antioch:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.6.6'>Whom they set before the apostles: and when they had prayed, they laid their hands on them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.6.7'>And the word of God increased; and the number of the disciples multiplied in Jerusalem greatly; and a great company of the priests were obedient to the faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.6.8'>And Stephen, full of faith and power, performed great wonders and miracles among the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.6.9'>Then there arose certain of the synagogue, which is called the synagogue of the Libertines, and Cyrenians, and Alexandrians, and of them of Cilicia and of Asia, disputing with Stephen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.6.10'>And they were not able to resist the wisdom and the spirit by which he spoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.6.11'>Then they secretly induced men, who sayd, We have heard him speak blasphemous words against Moses, and against God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.6.12'>And they stirred up the people, and the elders, and the scribes, and came upon him, and caught him, and brought him to the council,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.6.13'>And set up false witnesses, who said, This man ceaseth not to speak blasphemous words against this holy place, and the law:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.6.14'>For we have heard him say, that this Jesus of Nazareth shall destroy this place, and shall change the customs which Moses delivered to us. <note>customs: or, rites</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.6.15'>And all that sat in the council, looking steadfastly on him, saw his face as it had been the face of an angel.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.7'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.1'>Then said the high priest, Are these things so?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.2'>And he said, Men, brethren, and fathers, hearken; The God of glory appeared to our father Abraham, when he was in Mesopotamia, before he dwelt in Haran,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.3'>And said to him, Depart from thy country, and from thy kindred, and come into the land which I shall show thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.4'>Then he came from the land of the Chaldeans, and dwelt in Haran: and from there, when his father was dead, he removed him into this land, in which ye now dwell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.5'>And he gave him no inheritance in it, no, not so much as to set his foot on: yet he promised that he would give it to him for a possession, and to his offspring after him, when as yet he had no child.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.6'>And God spoke in this way, That his offspring should sojourn in a foreign land; and that they should bring them into bondage, and oppress them four hundred years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.7'>And the nation to whom they shall be in bondage will I judge, said God: and after that they shall come forth, and serve me in this place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.8'>And he gave him the covenant of circumcision: and so Abraham begat Isaac, and circumcised him the eighth day; and Isaac begat Jacob; and Jacob begat the twelve patriarchs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.9'>And the patriarchs, moved with envy, sold Joseph into Egypt: but God was with him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.10'>And delivered him from all his afflictions, and gave him favour and wisdom in the sight of Pharaoh king of Egypt; and he made him governor over Egypt and all his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.11'>Now there came a famine over all the land of Egypt and Canaan, and great affliction: and our fathers found no sustenance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.12'>But when Jacob heard that there was grain in Egypt, he sent out our fathers first.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.13'>And at the second time Joseph was made known to his brethren; and Joseph’s kindred was made known to Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.14'>Then Joseph sent, and called his father Jacob to him, and all his kindred, seventy and five souls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.15'>So Jacob went down into Egypt, and died, he, and our fathers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.16'>And were carried over into Shechem, and laid in the sepulchre that Abraham bought for a sum of money of the sons of Emmor the father of Shechem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.17'>But when the time of the promise drew near, which God had sworn to Abraham, the people grew and multiplied in Egypt,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.18'>Till another king arose, who knew not Joseph.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.19'>The same dealt treacherously with our kindred, and oppressed our fathers, so that they cast out their young children, to the end they might not live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.20'>In which time Moses was born, and was exceeding fair, and nourished in his father’s house three months: <note>exceeding fair: or, fair to God</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.21'>And when he was cast out, Pharaoh’s daughter took him up, and nourished him for her own son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.22'>And Moses was learned in all the wisdom of the Egyptians, and was mighty in words and in deeds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.23'>And when he was full forty years old, it came into his heart to visit his brethren the children of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.24'>And seeing one of them suffer wrong, he defended him, and avenged him that was oppressed, and smote the Egyptian:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.25'>For he supposed his brethren to understand that God by his hand would deliver them: but they understood not. <note>For: or, Now</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.26'>And the next day he showed himself to them as they were fighting, and would have constrained them to be at peace again, saying, Sirs, ye are brethren; why do ye wrong one to another?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.27'>But he that did his neighbour wrong thrust him away, saying, Who made thee a ruler and a judge over us?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.28'>Wilt thou kill me, as thou didst the Egyptian yesterday?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.29'>Then Moses fled at this saying, and was a stranger in the land of Midian, where he begat two sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.30'>And when forty years had passed, there appeared to him in the wilderness of mount Sinai an angel of the Lord in a flame of fire in a bush.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.31'>When Moses saw it, he wondered at the sight: and as he drew near to behold it, the voice of the Lord came to him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.32'>Saying, I am the God of thy fathers, the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob. Then Moses trembled, and dared not behold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.33'>Then said the Lord to him, Put off thy shoes from thy feet: for the place where thou standest is holy ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.34'>I have seen, I have seen the affliction of my people who are in Egypt, and I have heard their groaning, and am come down to deliver them. And now come, I will send thee into Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.35'>This Moses whom they refused, saying, Who made thee a ruler and a judge? the same did God send to be a ruler and a deliverer by the hand of the angel who appeared to him in the bush.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.36'>He brought them out, after he had showed wonders and signs in the land of Egypt, and in the Red sea, and in the wilderness forty years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.37'>This is that Moses, who said to the children of Israel, A prophet shall the Lord your God raise up to you of your brethren, like me; him shall ye hear. <note>like…: or, as myself</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.38'>This is he, that was in the church in the wilderness with the angel who spoke to him on the mount Sinai, and with our fathers: who received the living oracles to give to us:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.39'>Whom our fathers would not obey, but thrust him from them, and in their hearts turned back again into Egypt,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.40'>Saying to Aaron, Make us gods to go before us: for as for this Moses, who brought us out of the land of Egypt, we know not what is become of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.41'>And they made a calf in those days, and offered sacrifice to the idol, and rejoiced in the works of their own hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.42'>Then God turned, and gave them up to worship the host of heaven; as it is written in the book of the prophets, O ye house of Israel, have ye offered to me slain beasts and sacrifices for forty years in the wilderness?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.43'>Yea, ye took up the tabernacle of Molech, and the star of your god Remphan, figures which ye made to worship them: and I will carry you away beyond Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.44'>Our fathers had the tabernacle of testimony in the wilderness, as he had appointed, speaking to Moses, that he should make it according to the fashion that he had seen. <note>speaking: or, who spake</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.45'>Which also our fathers that came after brought in with Joshua into the possession of the Gentiles, whom God drove out before the face of our fathers, to the days of David; <note>that…: or, having received</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.46'>Who found favour before God, and desired to find a tabernacle for the God of Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.47'>But Solomon built for him an house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.48'>Yet the most High dwelleth not in temples made with hands; as saith the prophet,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.49'>Heaven is my throne, and earth is my footstool: what house will ye build for me? saith the Lord: or what is the place of my rest?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.50'>Hath not my hand made all these things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.51'>Ye stiffnecked and uncircumcised in heart and ears, ye do always resist the Holy Spirit: as your fathers did, so do ye.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.52'>Which of the prophets have not your fathers persecuted? and they have slain them who showed before of the coming of the Just One; of whom ye have been now the betrayers and murderers:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.53'>Who have received the law by the disposition of angels, and have not kept it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.54'>When they heard these things, they were cut to the heart, and they gnashed on him with their teeth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.55'>But he, being full of the Holy Spirit, looked up steadfastly into heaven, and saw the glory of God, and Jesus standing on the right hand of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.56'>And said, Behold, I see the heavens opened, and the Son of man standing on the right hand of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.57'>Then they cried out with a loud voice, and stopped their ears, and ran upon him with one accord,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.58'>And cast him out of the city, and stoned him: and the witnesses laid down their clothes at a young man’s feet, whose name was Saul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.59'>And they stoned Stephen, calling upon God, and saying, Lord Jesus, receive my spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.7.60'>And he kneeled down, and cried with a loud voice, Lord, lay not this sin to their charge. And when he had said this, he fell asleep.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.8'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.1'>And Saul was consenting to his death. And at that time there was a great persecution against the church which was at Jerusalem; and they were all scattered throughout the regions of Judaea and Samaria, except the apostles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.2'>And devout men carried Stephen to his burial, and made great lamentation over him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.3'>As for Saul, he made havoc of the church, entering into every house, and dragging off men and women committed them to prison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.4'>Therefore they that were scattered went every where preaching the word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.5'>Then Philip went down to the city of Samaria, and preached Christ to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.6'>And the people with one accord gave heed to those things which Philip spoke, hearing and seeing the miracles which he was performing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.7'>For unclean spirits, crying with loud voice, came out of many that were possessed and many sick with palsies, and that were lame, were healed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.8'>And there was great joy in that city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.9'>But there was a certain man, called Simon, who before in the same city used sorcery, and bewitched the people of Samaria, saying that he was some great person:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.10'>To whom they all gave heed, from the least to the greatest, saying, This man is the great power of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.11'>And to him they had regard, because that for a long time he had bewitched them with sorceries.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.12'>But when they believed Philip preaching the things concerning the kingdom of God, and the name of Jesus Christ, they were baptized, both men and women.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.13'>Then Simon himself believed also: and when he was baptized, he continued with Philip, and was amazed, beholding the miracles and signs which were done. <note>miracles…: Gr. signs and great miracles</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.14'>Now when the apostles who were at Jerusalem heard that Samaria had received the word of God, they sent to them Peter and John:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.15'>Who, when they had come down, prayed for them, that they might receive the Holy Spirit:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.16'>(For as yet he had fallen upon none of them: only they were baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.17'>Then they laid their hands on them, and they received the Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.18'>And when Simon saw that through laying on of the apostles’ hands the Holy Spirit was given, he offered them money,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.19'>Saying, Give me also this power, that on whomever I lay hands, he may receive the Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.20'>But Peter said to him, Thy money perish with thee, because thou hast thought that the gift of God may be purchased with money.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.21'>Thou hast neither part nor lot in this matter: for thy heart is not right in the sight of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.22'>Repent therefore of this thy wickedness, and pray God, if perhaps the thought of thy heart may be forgiven thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.23'>For I perceive that thou art in the gall of bitterness, and in the bond of iniquity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.24'>Then answered Simon, and said, Pray ye to the Lord for me, that none of these things which ye have spoken come upon me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.25'>And they, when they had testified and preached the word of the Lord, returned to Jerusalem, and preached the gospel in many villages of the Samaritans.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.26'>And the angel of the Lord spoke to Philip, saying, Arise, and go toward the south to the way that goeth down from Jerusalem to Gaza, which is desert.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.27'>And he arose and went: and, behold, a man of Ethiopia, an eunuch of great authority under Candace queen of the Ethiopians, who had the charge of all her treasure, and had come to Jerusalem to worship,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.28'>Was returning, and sitting in his chariot read Isaiah the prophet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.29'>Then the Spirit said to Philip, Go near, and join thyself to this chariot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.30'>And Philip ran to him, and heard him reading the prophet Isaiah, and said, Understandest thou what thou readest?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.31'>And he said, How can I, except some man should guide me? And he besought Philip that he would come up and sit with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.32'>The place of the scripture which he read was this, He was led as a sheep to the slaughter; and like a lamb dumb before his shearer, so he opened not his mouth:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.33'>In his humiliation his judgment was taken away: and who shall declare his generation? for his life is taken from the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.34'>And the eunuch answered Philip, and said, I pray thee, of whom speaketh the prophet this? of himself, or of some other man?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.35'>Then Philip opened his mouth, and began at the same scripture, and preached to him Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.36'>And as they went on their way, they came to a certain water: and the eunuch said, See, here is water; what doth hinder me to be baptized?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.37'>And Philip said, If thou believest with all thy heart, thou mayest. And he answered and said, I believe that Jesus Christ is the Son of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.38'>And he commanded the chariot to stand still: and they both went down into the water, both Philip and the eunuch; and he baptized him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.39'>And when they had come up out of the water, the Spirit of the Lord caught away Philip, that the eunuch saw him no more: and he went on his way rejoicing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.8.40'>But Philip was found at Azotus: and passing through he preached in all the cities, till he came to Caesarea.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.9'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.1'>And Saul, yet breathing out threatenings and slaughter against the disciples of the Lord, went to the high priest,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.2'>And desired from him letters to Damascus to the synagogues, that if he found any of this way, whether they were men or women, he might bring them bound to Jerusalem. <note>of this way: Gr. of the way</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.3'>And as he journeyed, he came near Damascus: and suddenly there shone around him a light from heaven:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.4'>And he fell to the earth, and heard a voice saying to him, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.5'>And he said, Who art thou, Lord? And the Lord said, I am Jesus whom thou persecutest: it is hard for thee to kick against the goads.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.6'>And he trembling and astonished said, Lord, what wilt thou have me to do? And the Lord said to him, Arise, and go into the city, and it shall be told thee what thou must do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.7'>And the men who journeyed with him stood speechless, hearing a voice, but seeing no man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.8'>And Saul arose from the earth; and when his eyes were opened, he saw no man: but they led him by the hand, and brought him into Damascus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.9'>And he was three days without sight, and neither ate nor drank.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.10'>And there was a certain disciple at Damascus, named Ananias; and to him said the Lord in a vision, Ananias. And he said, Behold, I am here, Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.11'>And the Lord said to him, Arise, and go into the street which is called Straight, and enquire in the house of Judas for one called Saul, of Tarsus: for, behold, he prayeth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.12'>And hath seen in a vision a man named Ananias coming in, and putting his hand on him, that he might receive his sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.13'>Then Ananias answered, Lord, I have heard by many of this man, how much evil he hath done to thy saints at Jerusalem:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.14'>And here he hath authority from the chief priests to bind all that call on thy name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.15'>But the Lord said to him, Go: for he is a chosen vessel to me, to bear my name before the Gentiles, and kings, and the children of Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.16'>For I will show him what great things he must suffer for my name’s sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.17'>And Ananias went, and entered into the house; and putting his hands on him said, Brother Saul, the Lord, even Jesus, that appeared to thee in the way as thou camest, hath sent me, that thou mayest receive thy sight, and be filled with the Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.18'>And immediately there fell from his eyes as it had been scales: and he received sight immediately, and arose, and was baptized.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.19'>And when he had received food, he was strengthened. Then was Saul certain days with the disciples who were at Damascus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.20'>And immediately he preached Christ in the synagogues, that he is the Son of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.21'>But all that heard him were amazed, and said; Is not this he that destroyed them who called on this name in Jerusalem, and came here for that intent, that he might bring them bound to the chief priests?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.22'>But Saul increased the more in strength, and confounded the Jews who dwelt at Damascus, proving that this is very Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.23'>And after many days were fulfilled, the Jews took counsel to kill him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.24'>But their laying in wait was known to Saul. And they watched the gates day and night to kill him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.25'>Then the disciples took him by night, and let him down by the wall in a basket.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.26'>And when Saul had come to Jerusalem, he tried to join himself to the disciples: but they were all afraid of him, and believed not that he was a disciple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.27'>But Barnabas took him, and brought him to the apostles, and declared to them how he had seen the Lord in the way, and that he had spoken to him, and how he had preached boldly at Damascus in the name of Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.28'>And he was with them coming in and going out at Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.29'>And he spoke boldly in the name of the Lord Jesus, and disputed against the Grecians: but they went about to slay him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.30'>Which when the brethren knew, they brought him down to Caesarea, and sent him forth to Tarsus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.31'>Then had the churches rest throughout all Judaea and Galilee and Samaria, and were edified; and walking in the fear of the Lord, and in the comfort of the Holy Spirit, were multiplied.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.32'>And it came to pass, as Peter passed throughout all quarters, he came down also to the saints who dwelt at Lydda.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.33'>And there he found a certain man named Æneas, who had kept his bed eight years, and was sick with the palsy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.34'>And Peter said to him, Æneas, Jesus Christ healeth thee: arise, and make thy bed. And he arose immediately.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.35'>And all that dwelt at Lydda and Saron saw him, and turned to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.36'>Now there was at Joppa a certain disciple named Tabitha, who by interpretation is called Dorcas: this woman was full of good works and almsdeeds which she did. <note>Dorcas: or, Doe, or, Roe</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.37'>And it came to pass in those days, that she was sick, and died: whom when they had washed, they laid in an upper chamber.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.38'>And as Lydda was near to Joppa, and the disciples had heard that Peter was there, they sent to him two men, desiring him that he would not delay to come to them. <note>delay: or, be grieved</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.39'>Then Peter arose and went with them. When he had come, they brought him into the upper chamber: and all the widows stood by him weeping, and showing the coats and garments which Dorcas made, while she was with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.40'>But Peter put them all out, and kneeled down, and prayed; and turning to the body said, Tabitha, arise. And she opened her eyes: and when she saw Peter, she sat up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.41'>And he gave her his hand, and lifted her up, and when he had called the saints and widows, presented her alive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.42'>And it was known throughout all Joppa; and many believed in the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.9.43'>And it came to pass, that he tarried many days in Joppa with one Simon a tanner.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.10'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.1'>There was a certain man in Caesarea called Cornelius, a centurion of the band called the Italian band,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.2'>A devout man, and one that feared God with all his house, who gave much alms to the people, and prayed to God always.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.3'>He saw in a vision evidently about the ninth hour of the day an angel of God coming in to him, and saying to him, Cornelius.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.4'>And when he looked on him, he was afraid, and said, What is it, Lord? And he said to him, Thy prayers and thy alms are come up for a memorial before God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.5'>And now send men to Joppa, and call for one Simon, whose surname is Peter:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.6'>He lodgeth with one Simon a tanner, whose house is by the sea side: he shall tell thee what thou oughtest to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.7'>And when the angel who spoke to Cornelius had departed, he called two of his household servants, and a devout soldier of them that waited on him continually;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.8'>And when he had declared all these things to them, he sent them to Joppa.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.9'>On the next day, as they were going on their journey, and drew near to the city, Peter went up upon the housetop to pray about the sixth hour:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.10'>And he became very hungry, and would have eaten: but while they made ready, he fell into a trance,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.11'>And saw heaven opened, and a certain vessel descending to him, as it had been a great sheet knit at the four corners, and let down to the earth:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.12'>In which were all manner of fourfooted beasts of the earth, and wild beasts, and creeping things, and fowls of the air.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.13'>And there came a voice to him, Rise, Peter; kill, and eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.14'>But Peter said, Not so, Lord; for I have never eaten any thing that is common or unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.15'>And the voice spoke to him again the second time, What God hath cleansed, that call not thou common.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.16'>This was done three times: and the vessel was received up again into heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.17'>Now while Peter greatly perplexed in himself what this vision which he had seen should mean, behold, the men who were sent from Cornelius had made enquiry for Simon’s house, and stood before the gate,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.18'>And called, and asked whether Simon, who was surnamed Peter, lodged there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.19'>While Peter thought on the vision, the Spirit said to him, Behold, three men seek thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.20'>Arise therefore, and go down, and go with them, doubting nothing: for I have sent them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.21'>Then Peter went down to the men who were sent to him from Cornelius; and said, Behold, I am he whom ye seek: what is the cause for which ye have come?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.22'>And they said, Cornelius the centurion, a just man, and one that feareth God, and of good report among all the nation of the Jews, was warned from God by an holy angel to send for thee into his house, and to hear words from thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.23'>Then he called them in, and lodged them. And on the next day Peter went with them, and certain brethren from Joppa accompanied him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.24'>And on the next day they entered into Caesarea. And Cornelius waited for them, and had called together his kinsmen and near friends.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.25'>And as Peter was coming in, Cornelius met him, and fell down at his feet, and worshipped him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.26'>But Peter took him up, saying, Stand up; I myself also am a man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.27'>And as he talked with him, he went in, and found many that had come together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.28'>And he said to them, Ye know that it is an unlawful thing for a man that is a Jew to keep company, or come to one of another nation; but God hath shown me that I should not call any man common or unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.29'>Therefore I came to you willingly, as soon as I was sent for: I ask therefore for what intent ye have sent for me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.30'>And Cornelius said, Four days ago I was fasting until this hour; and at the ninth hour I prayed in my house, and, behold, a man stood before me in bright clothing,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.31'>And said, Cornelius, thy prayer is heard, and thy alms are had in remembrance in the sight of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.32'>Send therefore to Joppa, and call here Simon, whose surname is Peter; he lodgeth in the house of one Simon a tanner by the sea side: who, when he cometh, shall speak to thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.33'>Immediately therefore I sent to thee; and thou hast well done that thou hast come. Now therefore we are all here present before God, to hear all things that are commanded thee from God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.34'>Then Peter opened his mouth, and said, In truth I perceive that God is no respecter of persons:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.35'>But in every nation he that feareth him, and worketh righteousness, is accepted with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.36'>The word which God sent to the children of Israel, preaching peace by Jesus Christ: (he is Lord of all:)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.37'>That word, I say, ye know, which was proclaimed throughout all Judaea, and began from Galilee, after the baptism which John preached;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.38'>That God anointed Jesus of Nazareth with the Holy Spirit and with power: who went about doing good, and healing all that were oppressed by the devil; for God was with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.39'>And we are witnesses of all things which he did both in the land of the Jews, and in Jerusalem; whom they slew and hanged on a tree:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.40'>Him God raised the third day, and showed him openly;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.41'>Not to all the people, but to witnesses chosen before by God, even to us, who ate and drank with him after he rose from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.42'>And he commanded us to preach to the people, and to testify that it is he who was ordained by God to be the Judge of the living and the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.43'>To him give all the prophets witness, that through his name whoever believeth in him shall receive remission of sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.44'>While Peter was yet speaking these words, the Holy Spirit fell on all them who heard the word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.45'>And they of the circumcision who believed were astonished, as many as came with Peter, because that on the Gentiles also was poured out the gift of the Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.46'>For they heard them speak in tongues, and magnify God. Then answered Peter,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.47'>Can any man forbid water, that these should not be baptized, who have received the Holy Spirit as well as we?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.10.48'>And he commanded them to be baptized in the name of the Lord. Then they requested him to tarry certain days.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.11'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.1'>And the apostles and brethren that were in Judaea heard that the Gentiles also had received the word of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.2'>And when Peter had come to Jerusalem, they that were of the circumcision contended with him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.3'>Saying, Thou wentest in to men uncircumcised, and didst eat with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.4'>But Peter went over the matter from the beginning, and expounded it by order to them, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.5'>I was in the city of Joppa praying: and in a trance I saw a vision, A certain vessel descend, like a great sheet, let down from heaven by four corners; and it came even to me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.6'>Upon which when I had fastened my eyes, I considered, and saw fourfooted beasts of the earth, and wild beasts, and creeping things, and fowls of the air.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.7'>And I heard a voice saying to me, Arise, Peter; slay and eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.8'>But I said, Not so, Lord: for nothing common or unclean hath at any time entered into my mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.9'>But the voice answered me again from heaven, What God hath cleansed, that call not thou common.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.10'>And this was done three times: and all were drawn up again into heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.11'>And, behold, immediately there were three men already come to the house where I was, sent from Caesarea to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.12'>And the Spirit bade me go with them, nothing doubting. Moreover these six brethren accompanied me, and we entered into the man’s house:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.13'>And he showed us how he had seen an angel in his house, who stood and said to him, Send men to Joppa, and call for Simon, whose surname is Peter;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.14'>Who shall tell thee words, by which thou and all thy house shall be saved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.15'>And as I began to speak, the Holy Spirit fell on them, as on us at the beginning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.16'>Then I remembered the word of the Lord, how he said, John indeed baptized in water; but ye shall be baptized in the Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.17'>Forasmuch then as God gave them the same gift as he did to us, who believed on the Lord Jesus Christ; what was I, that I could withstand God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.18'>When they heard these things, they held their peace, and glorified God, saying, Then hath God also to the Gentiles granted repentance to life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.19'>Now they who were dispersed upon the persecution that arose about Stephen travelled as far as Phenice, and Cyprus, and Antioch, preaching the word to none but to the Jews only.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.20'>And some of them were men of Cyprus and Cyrene, who, when they had come to Antioch, spoke to the Grecians, preaching the Lord Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.21'>And the hand of the Lord was with them: and a great number believed, and turned to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.22'>Then tidings of these things came to the ears of the church which was in Jerusalem: and they sent forth Barnabas, that he should go as far as Antioch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.23'>Who, when he came, and had seen the grace of God, was glad, and exhorted them all, that with purpose of heart they would continue with the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.24'>For he was a good man, and full of the Holy Spirit and of faith: and many people were added to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.25'>Then Barnabas departed to Tarsus, to seek Saul:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.26'>And when he had found him, he brought him to Antioch. And it came to pass, that a whole year they assembled themselves with the church, and taught many people. And the disciples were first called Christians in Antioch. <note>with…: or, in the church</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.27'>And in these days came prophets from Jerusalem to Antioch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.28'>And there stood up one of them named Agabus, and signified by the Spirit that there should be a great famine throughout all the world: which came to pass in the days of Claudius Caesar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.29'>Then the disciples, every man according to his ability, determined to send relief to the brethren who dwelt in Judaea:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.11.30'>Which also they did, and sent it to the elders by the hands of Barnabas and Saul.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.12'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.1'>Now about that time Herod the king stretched forth his hands to afflict certain of the church. <note>stretched…: or, began</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.2'>And he killed James the brother of John with the sword.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.3'>And because he saw it pleased the Jews, he proceeded further to take Peter also. (Then were the days of unleavened bread.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.4'>And when he had apprehended him, he put him in prison, and delivered him to four quaternions of soldiers to keep him; intending after the Passover to bring him forth to the people. <note>quaternions: a file of four soldiers</note><note>Easter: Gr. Passover</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.5'>Peter therefore was kept in prison: but prayer was made without ceasing by the church to God for him. <note>prayer…: or, instant and earnest prayer was made</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.6'>And when Herod would have brought him forth, the same night Peter was sleeping between two soldiers, bound with two chains: and the keepers before the door kept the prison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.7'>And, behold, the angel of the Lord came upon him, and a light shone in the prison: and he smote Peter on the side, and raised him up, saying, Arise quickly. And his chains fell off from his hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.8'>And the angel said to him, Gird thyself, and bind on thy sandals. And so he did. And he saith to him, Cast thy garment about thee, and follow me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.9'>And he went out, and followed him; and knew not that it was true which was done by the angel; but thought he saw a vision.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.10'>When they were past the first and the second guard, they came to the iron gate that leadeth to the city; which opened to them of its own accord: and they went out, and passed on through one street; and immediately the angel departed from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.11'>And when Peter had come to himself, he said, Now I know with certainty, that the Lord hath sent his angel, and hath delivered me out of the hand of Herod, and from all the expectation of the people of the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.12'>And when he had considered the thing, he came to the house of Mary the mother of John, whose surname was Mark; where many were gathered together praying.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.13'>And as Peter knocked at the door of the gate, a maid came to answer, named Rhoda. <note>to hearken: or, to ask who was there</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.14'>And when she knew Peter’s voice, she opened not the gate for gladness, but ran in, and told that Peter stood before the gate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.15'>And they said to her, Thou art mad. But she constantly affirmed that it was even so. Then they said, It is his angel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.16'>But Peter continued knocking: and when they had opened the door, and saw him, they were astonished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.17'>But he, beckoning to them with the hand to hold their peace, declared to them how the Lord had brought him out of the prison. And he said, Go show these things to James, and to the brethren. And he departed, and went into another place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.18'>Now as soon as it was day, there was no small stir among the soldiers, what was become of Peter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.19'>And when Herod had sought for him, and found him not, he examined the keepers, and commanded that they should be put to death. And he went down from Judaea to Caesarea, and there abode.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.20'>And Herod was highly displeased with them of Tyre and Sidon: but they came with one accord to him, and, having made Blastus the king’s chamberlain their friend, desired peace; because their country was nourished by the king’s country. <note>was highly…: or, bare an hostile mind, intending war</note><note>the king’s chamberlain: Gr. that was over the king’s bedchamber</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.21'>And upon a set day Herod, arrayed in royal apparel, sat upon his throne, and made an oration to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.22'>And the people gave a shout, saying, It is the voice of a god, and not of a man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.23'>And immediately the angel of the Lord smote him, because he gave not God the glory: and he was eaten by worms, and died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.24'>But the word of God grew and multiplied.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.12.25'>And Barnabas and Saul returned from Jerusalem, when they had fulfilled their ministry, and took with them John, whose surname was Mark. <note>ministry: or, charge</note></verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.13'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.1'>Now there were in the church that was at Antioch certain prophets and teachers; as Barnabas, and Simeon that was called Niger, and Lucius of Cyrene, and Manaen, who had been brought up with Herod the tetrarch, and Saul. <note>which…: or, Herod’s foster brother</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.2'>As they ministered to the Lord, and fasted, the Holy Spirit said, Separate for me Barnabas and Saul for the work to which I have called them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.3'>And when they had fasted and prayed, and laid their hands on them, they sent them away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.4'>So they, being sent forth by the Holy Spirit, departed to Seleucia; and from there they sailed to Cyprus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.5'>And when they were at Salamis, they preached the word of God in the synagogues of the Jews: and they had also John as their helper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.6'>And when they had gone through the isle to Paphos, they found a certain sorcerer, a false prophet, a Jew, whose name was Barjesus:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.7'>Who was with the deputy of the country, Sergius Paulus, a prudent man; who called for Barnabas and Saul, and desired to hear the word of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.8'>But Elymas the sorcerer (for so is his name by interpretation) withstood them, seeking to turn away the deputy from the faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.9'>Then Saul, (who also is called Paul,) filled with the Holy Spirit, set his eyes on him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.10'>And said, O full of all deceit and all mischief, thou child of the devil, thou enemy of all righteousness, wilt thou not cease to pervert the right ways of the Lord?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.11'>And now, behold, the hand of the Lord is upon thee, and thou shalt be blind, not seeing the sun for a season. And immediately there fell on him a mist and a darkness; and he went about seeking some to lead him by the hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.12'>Then the deputy, when he saw what was done, believed, being astonished at the doctrine of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.13'>Now when Paul and his company loosed from Paphos, they came to Perga in Pamphylia: and John departing from them returned to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.14'>But when they departed from Perga, they came to Antioch in Pisidia, and went into the synagogue on the sabbath day, and sat down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.15'>And after the reading of the law and the prophets the rulers of the synagogue sent to them, saying, Men, brethren, if ye have any word of exhortation for the people, say on.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.16'>Then Paul stood up, and beckoning with his hand said, Men of Israel, and ye that fear God, listen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.17'>The God of this people Israel chose our fathers, and exalted the people when they dwelt as strangers in the land of Egypt, and with an high arm he brought them out of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.18'>And about the time of forty years he bore their manners in the wilderness. <note>suffered…: or bore, or fed them as a nurse beareth, or feedeth, her child</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.19'>And when he had destroyed seven nations in the land of Canaan, he divided their land to them by lot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.20'>And after these things, which took about four hundred and fifty years, he gave to them judges, until Samuel the prophet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.21'>And afterward they desired a king: and God gave to them Saul the son of Kish, a man of the tribe of Benjamin, by the space of forty years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.22'>And when he had removed him, he raised up to them David to be their king; to whom also he gave testimony, and said, I have found David the son of Jesse, a man after my own heart, who shall fulfil all my will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.23'>Of this man’s seed hath God according to his promise raised up to Israel a Saviour, Jesus:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.24'>After John had first preached before his coming the baptism of repentance to all the people of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.25'>And as John fulfilled his course, he said, Whom think ye that I am? I am not he. But, behold, there cometh one after me, whose shoes of his feet I am not worthy to loose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.26'>Men, brethren, children of the stock of Abraham, and whoever among you feareth God, to you is the word of this salvation sent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.27'>For they that dwell at Jerusalem, and their rulers, because they knew him not, nor yet the words of the prophets which are read every sabbath, they have fulfilled them in condemning him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.28'>And though they found no cause of death in him, yet they desired Pilate that he should be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.29'>And when they had fulfilled all that was written concerning him, they took him down from the tree, and laid him in a sepulchre.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.30'>But God raised him from the dead:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.31'>And he was seen many days by them who came up with him from Galilee to Jerusalem, who are his witnesses to the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.32'>And we declare to you the glad tidings, that the promise which was made to the fathers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.33'>God hath fulfilled the same to us their children, in that he hath raised up Jesus again; as it is also written in the second psalm, Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.34'>And as concerning that he raised him from the dead, now no more to return to corruption, he said in this way, I will give you the sure mercies of David. <note>mercies: Gr. holy, or just things: which word the Septuagint in many places, uses for that which is in the Hebrew, mercies</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.35'>Therefore he saith also in another psalm, Thou shalt not allow thy Holy One to see corruption.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.36'>For David, after he had served his own generation by the will of God, fell asleep, and was laid to his fathers, and saw corruption: <note>after…: or, after he had in his own age served the will of God</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.37'>But he, whom God raised again, saw no corruption.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.38'>Be it known to you therefore, men, brethren, that through this man is preached to you the forgiveness of sins:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.39'>And by him all that believe are justified from all things, from which ye could not be justified by the law of Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.40'>Beware therefore, lest that come upon you, which is spoken in the prophets;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.41'>Behold, ye despisers, and wonder, and perish: for I work a work in your days, a work which ye shall by no means believe, though a man declare it to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.42'>And when the Jews had gone out of the synagogue, the Gentiles besought that these words might be preached to them the next sabbath. <note>the next…: Gr. in the week between, or, in the sabbath between</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.43'>Now when the congregation was broken up, many of the Jews and religious proselytes followed Paul and Barnabas: who, speaking to them, persuaded them to continue in the grace of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.44'>And the next sabbath came almost the whole city together to hear the word of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.45'>But when the Jews saw the multitudes, they were filled with envy, and spoke against those things which were spoken by Paul, contradicting and blaspheming.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.46'>Then Paul and Barnabas became bold, and said, It was necessary that the word of God should first be spoken to you: but seeing ye reject it, and judge yourselves unworthy of everlasting life, lo, we turn to the Gentiles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.47'>For so hath the Lord commanded us, saying, I have set thee to be a light of the Gentiles, that thou shouldest be for salvation to the ends of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.48'>And when the Gentiles heard this, they were glad, and glorified the word of the Lord: and as many as were ordained to eternal life believed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.49'>And the word of the Lord was proclaimed throughout all the region.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.50'>But the Jews stirred up the devout and honourable women, and the chief men of the city, and raised persecution against Paul and Barnabas, and drove them out of their land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.51'>But they shook off the dust of their feet against them, and came to Iconium.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.13.52'>And the disciples were filled with joy, and with the Holy Spirit.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.14'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.1'>And it came to pass in Iconium, that they went both together into the synagogue of the Jews, and so spoke, that a great multitude both of the Jews and also of the Greeks believed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.2'>But the unbelieving Jews stirred up the Gentiles, and made their minds evil affected against the brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.3'>A long time therefore they abode speaking boldly in the Lord, who gave testimony to the word of his grace, and granted signs and wonders to be done by their hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.4'>But the multitude of the city was divided: and part held with the Jews, and part with the apostles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.5'>And when there was an assault made both of the Gentiles, and also of the Jews with their rulers, to use them despitefully, and to stone them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.6'>Being aware of it, they fled to Lystra and Derbe, cities of Lycaonia, and to the surrounding region:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.7'>And there they preached the gospel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.8'>And there sat a certain man at Lystra, impotent in his feet, being a cripple from his mother’s womb, who had never walked:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.9'>The same heard Paul speak: who steadfastly beholding him, and perceiving that he had faith to be healed,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.10'>Said with a loud voice, Stand upright on thy feet. And he leaped and walked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.11'>And when the people saw what Paul had done, they lifted up their voices, saying in the speech of Lycaonia, The gods have come down to us in the likeness of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.12'>And they called Barnabas, Jupiter; and Paul, Mercury, because he was the chief speaker.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.13'>Then the priest of Jupiter, who was before their city, brought oxen and garlands to the gates, and would have done sacrifice with the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.14'>Which when the apostles, Barnabas and Paul, heard of, they tore their clothes, and ran in among the people, crying out,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.15'>And saying, Sirs, why do ye these things? We also are men of like passions with you, and preach to you that ye should turn from these vanities to the living God, who made heaven, and earth, and the sea, and all things that are in them:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.16'>Who in times past allowed all nations to walk in their own ways.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.17'>Nevertheless he left not himself without witness, in that he did good, and gave us rain from heaven, and fruitful seasons, filling our hearts with food and gladness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.18'>And with these sayings they scarce restrained the people, from doing sacrifice to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.19'>And there came there certain Jews from Antioch and Iconium, who persuaded the people, and, having stoned Paul, drew him out of the city, supposing him to be dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.20'>But, as the disciples stood around him, he rose, and came into the city: and the next day he departed with Barnabas to Derbe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.21'>And when they had preached the gospel to that city, and had taught many, they returned again to Lystra, and to Iconium, and to Antioch, <note>had taught many: Gr. had made many disciples</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.22'>Confirming the souls of the disciples, exhorting them to continue in the faith, and that we must through much tribulation enter into the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.23'>And when they had ordained for them elders in every church, and had prayed with fasting, they commended them to the Lord, on whom they believed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.24'>And after they had passed throughout Pisidia, they came to Pamphylia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.25'>And when they had preached the word in Perga, they went down into Attalia:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.26'>And from there sailed to Antioch, where they had been commended from to the grace of God for the work which they fulfilled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.27'>And when they had come, and had gathered the church together, they reported all that God had done with them, and that he had opened the door of faith to the Gentiles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.14.28'>And there they abode a long time with the disciples.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.15'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.1'>And certain men who came down from Judaea taught the brethren, and said, Except ye be circumcised after the manner of Moses, ye cannot be saved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.2'>When therefore Paul and Barnabas had no small dissension and disputation with them, they determined that Paul and Barnabas, and certain others of them, should go to Jerusalem to the apostles and elders about this question.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.3'>And being brought on their way by the church, they passed through Phenice and Samaria, declaring the conversion of the Gentiles: and they caused great joy to all the brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.4'>And when they had come to Jerusalem, they were received by the church, and by the apostles and elders, and they declared all things that God had done with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.5'>But there rose certain of the sect of the Pharisees who believed, saying, That it was needful to circumcise them, and to command them to keep the law of Moses. <note>rose…: or, rose up, said they, certain</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.6'>And the apostles and elders came together to consider of this matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.7'>And when there had been much disputing, Peter rose, and said to them, Men, brethren, ye know that a good while ago God made choice among us, that the Gentiles by my mouth should hear the word of the gospel, and believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.8'>And God, who knoweth the hearts, bore them witness, giving to them the Holy Spirit, even as he did to us;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.9'>And put no difference between us and them, purifying their hearts by faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.10'>Now therefore why tempt ye God, to put a yoke upon the neck of the disciples, which neither our fathers nor we were able to bear?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.11'>But we believe that through the grace of the Lord Jesus Christ we shall be saved, even as they.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.12'>Then all the multitude kept silence, and hearkened to Barnabas and Paul, declaring what miracles and wonders God had wrought by them among the Gentiles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.13'>And after they held their peace, James answered, saying, Men, brethren, hearken to me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.14'>Simeon hath declared how God at the first visited the Gentiles, to take from among them a people for his name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.15'>And to this agree the words of the prophets; as it is written,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.16'>After this I will return, and will build again the tabernacle of David, which is fallen down; and I will build again its ruins, and I will set it up:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.17'>That the rest of men may seek after the Lord, and all the Gentiles, upon whom my name is called, saith the Lord, who doeth all these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.18'>Known to God are all his works from the beginning of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.19'>Therefore my judgment is, that we trouble not them, who from among the Gentiles are turned to God:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.20'>But that we write to them, that they abstain from pollutions of idols, and from immorality, and from things strangled, and from blood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.21'>For Moses of old time hath in every city them that preach him, being read in the synagogues every sabbath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.22'>Then it pleased the apostles and elders, with the whole church, to send chosen men of their own company to Antioch with Paul and Barnabas; namely, Judas surnamed Barsabas, and Silas, chief men among the brethren:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.23'>And they wrote letters by them after this manner; The apostles and elders and brethren send greeting to the brethren who are of the Gentiles in Antioch and Syria and Cilicia:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.24'>Forasmuch as we have heard, that certain who went out from us have troubled you with words, subverting your souls, saying, Ye must be circumcised, and keep the law: to whom we gave no such commandment:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.25'>It seemed good to us, being assembled with one accord, to send chosen men to you with our beloved Barnabas and Paul,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.26'>Men that have risked their lives for the name of our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.27'>We have sent therefore Judas and Silas, who shall also tell you the same things by mouth. <note>mouth: Gr. word</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.28'>For it seemed good to the Holy Spirit, and to us, to lay upon you no greater burden than these necessary things;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.29'>That ye abstain from things offered to idols, and from blood, and from things strangled, and from immorality: from which if ye keep yourselves, ye shall do well. Fare ye well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.30'>So when they were dismissed, they came to Antioch: and when they had gathered the multitude together, they delivered the epistle:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.31'>Which when they had read, they rejoiced for the consolation. <note>consolation: or, exhortation</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.32'>And Judas and Silas, being prophets also themselves, exhorted the brethren with many words, and confirmed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.33'>And after they had tarried there a time, they were sent away in peace from the brethren to the apostles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.34'>However it pleased Silas to abide there still.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.35'>Paul also and Barnabas continued in Antioch, teaching and preaching the word of the Lord, with many others also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.36'>And some days after Paul said to Barnabas, Let us go again and visit our brethren in every city where we have preached the word of the Lord, and see how they do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.37'>And Barnabas determined to take with them John, whose surname was Mark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.38'>But Paul thought not good to take him with them, who departed from them from Pamphylia, and went not with them to the work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.39'>And the contention was so sharp between them, that they departed one from the other: and so Barnabas took Mark, and sailed to Cyprus;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.40'>And Paul chose Silas, and departed, being commended by the brethren to the grace of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.15.41'>And he went through Syria and Cilicia, confirming the churches.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.16'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.1'>Then he came to Derbe and Lystra: and, behold, a certain disciple was there, named Timothy, the son of a certain woman, who was a Jewess, and believed; but his father was a Greek:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.2'>Who was well reported of by the brethren that were at Lystra and Iconium.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.3'>Him would Paul have to go forth with him; and took and circumcised him because of the Jews who were in those quarters: for they all knew that his father was a Greek.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.4'>And as they went through the cities, they delivered to them the decrees to keep, that were ordained by the apostles and elders who were at Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.5'>And so were the churches established in the faith, and increased in number daily.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.6'>Now when they had gone throughout Phrygia and the region of Galatia, and were forbidden by the Holy Spirit to preach the word in Asia,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.7'>After they had come to Mysia, they tried to go into Bithynia: but the Spirit allowed them not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.8'>And they passing by Mysia came down to Troas.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.9'>And a vision appeared to Paul in the night; There stood a man of Macedonia, beseeching him, saying, Come over into Macedonia, and help us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.10'>And after he had seen the vision, immediately we endeavoured to go into Macedonia, assuredly gathering that the Lord had called us to preach the gospel to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.11'>Therefore loosing from Troas, we came with a straight course to Samothracia, and the next day to Neapolis;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.12'>And from there to Philippi, which is the chief city of that part of Macedonia, and a colony: and we were in that city abiding certain days. <note>the chief: or, the first</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.13'>And on the sabbath day we went out of the city by a river side, where prayer was accustomed to be made; and we sat down, and spoke to the women who resorted there. <note>sabbath: Gr. sabbath day</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.14'>And a certain woman named Lydia, a seller of purple, of the city of Thyatira, who worshipped God, heard us: whose heart the Lord opened, that she attended to the things which were spoken by Paul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.15'>And when she was baptized, and her household, she besought us, saying, If ye have judged me to be faithful to the Lord, come into my house, and abide there. And she constrained us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.16'>And it came to pass, as we went to prayer, a certain maid possessed with a spirit of divination met us, who brought her masters much gain by soothsaying: <note>of divination: or, of Python</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.17'>The same followed Paul and us, and cried, saying, These men are the servants of the most high God, who show to us the way of salvation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.18'>And this she did many days. But Paul, being grieved, turned and said to the spirit, I command thee in the name of Jesus Christ to come out of her. And he came out the same hour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.19'>And when her masters saw that the hope of their gains was gone, they caught Paul and Silas, and drew them into the marketplace to the rulers, <note>marketplace: or, court</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.20'>And brought them to the magistrates, saying, These men, being Jews, do exceedingly trouble our city,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.21'>And teach customs, which are not lawful for us to receive, neither to observe, being Romans.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.22'>And the multitude rose up together against them: and the magistrates tore off their clothes, and commanded to beat them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.23'>And when they had laid many stripes upon them, they cast them into prison, charging the jailor to keep them safely:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.24'>Who, having received such a charge, thrust them into the inner prison, and made their feet fast in the stocks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.25'>And at midnight Paul and Silas prayed, and sang praises to God: and the prisoners heard them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.26'>And suddenly there was a great earthquake, so that the foundations of the prison were shaken: and immediately all the doors were opened, and every one’s bands were loosed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.27'>And the keeper of the prison awaking out of his sleep, and seeing the prison doors open, he drew out his sword, and would have killed himself, supposing that the prisoners had fled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.28'>But Paul cried with a loud voice, saying, Do thyself no harm: for we are all here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.29'>Then he called for a light, and sprang in, and came trembling, and fell down before Paul and Silas,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.30'>And brought them out, and said, Sirs, what must I do to be saved?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.31'>And they said, Believe on the Lord Jesus Christ, and thou shalt be saved, and thy house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.32'>And they spoke to him the word of the Lord, and to all that were in his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.33'>And he took them the same hour of the night, and washed their stripes; and was baptized, he and all his, without delay.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.34'>And when he had brought them into his house, he set food before them, and rejoiced, believing in God with all his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.35'>And when it was day, the magistrates sent the officers, saying, Let those men go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.36'>And the keeper of the prison told this saying to Paul, The magistrates have sent to let you go: now therefore depart, and go in peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.37'>But Paul said to them, They have beaten us openly uncondemned, being Romans, and have cast us into prison; and now do they thrust us out privately? nay verily; but let them come themselves and bring us out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.38'>And the officers told these words to the magistrates: and they feared, when they heard that they were Romans.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.39'>And they came and besought them, and brought them out, and desired them to depart out of the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.16.40'>And they went out of the prison, and entered into the house of Lydia: and when they had seen the brethren, they comforted them, and departed.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.17'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.1'>Now when they had passed through Amphipolis and Apollonia, they came to Thessalonica, where was a synagogue of the Jews:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.2'>And Paul, as his manner was, went in to them, and on three sabbaths reasoned with them out of the scriptures,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.3'>Opening and alleging, that it was needful that Christ should suffer, and rise again from the dead; and that this Jesus, whom I preach to you, is Christ. <note>whom…: or, whom, said he, I preach</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.4'>And some of them believed, and consorted with Paul and Silas; and of the devout Greeks a great multitude, and of the chief women not a few.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.5'>But the Jews who believed not, moved with envy, took to them certain wicked fellows of the baser sort, and gathered a company, and set all the city in an uproar, and assaulted the house of Jason, and sought to bring them out to the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.6'>And when they found them not, they drew Jason and certain brethren to the rulers of the city, crying, These that have turned the world upside down have come here also;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.7'>Whom Jason hath received: and these all do contrary to the decrees of Caesar, saying that there is another king, one Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.8'>And they troubled the people and the rulers of the city, when they heard these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.9'>And when they had taken security of Jason, and of the others, they let them go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.10'>And the brethren immediately sent away Paul and Silas by night to Berea: who coming there went into the synagogue of the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.11'>These were more noble than those in Thessalonica, in that they received the word with all readiness of mind, and searched the scriptures daily, whether those things were so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.12'>Therefore many of them believed; also of honourable women who were Greeks, and of men, not a few.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.13'>But when the Jews of Thessalonica had knowledge that the word of God was preached by Paul at Berea, they came there also, and stirred up the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.14'>And then immediately the brethren sent away Paul to go as it were to the sea: but Silas and Timothy abode there still.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.15'>And they that conducted Paul brought him to Athens: and receiving a commandment to Silas and Timothy to come to him with all speed, they departed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.16'>Now while Paul waited for them at Athens, his spirit was stirred in him, when he saw the city wholly given to idolatry. <note>wholly…: or, full of idols</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.17'>Therefore he disputed in the synagogue with the Jews, and with the devout persons, and in the market daily with them that met with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.18'>Then certain philosophers of the Epicureans, and of the Stoics, encountered him. And some said, What will this babbler say? some others, He seemeth to be a setter forth of strange gods: because he preached to them Jesus, and the resurrection. <note>babbler: or, base fellow</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.19'>And they took him, and brought him to Areopagus, saying, May we know what this new doctrine is, of which thou speakest? <note>Areopagus: or, Mars’ hill: it was the highest court in Athens</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.20'>For thou bringest certain strange things to our ears: we would know therefore what these things mean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.21'>(For all the Athenians and strangers who were there spent their time in nothing else, but either to tell, or to hear some new thing.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.22'>Then Paul stood in the midst of Mars’ hill, and said, Ye men of Athens, I perceive that in all things ye are very religious. <note>Mars’ hill: or, the court of the Areopagites</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.23'>For as I passed by, and beheld your devotions, I found an altar with this inscription, TO THE UNKNOWN GOD. Whom therefore ye ignorantly worship, him declare I to you. <note>devotions: or, gods that ye worship</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.24'>God that made the world and all things in it, seeing that he is Lord of heaven and earth, dwelleth not in temples made with hands;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.25'>Neither is worshipped with men’s hands, as though he needed any thing, seeing he giveth to all life, and breath, and all things;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.26'>And hath made of one blood all nations of men to dwell on all the face of the earth, and hath determined the times before appointed, and the bounds of their habitation;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.27'>That they should seek the Lord, if perhaps they might grope after him, and find him, though he is not far from every one of us:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.28'>For in him we live, and move, and have our being; as certain also of your own poets have said, For we are also his offspring.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.29'>Being then the offspring of God, we ought not to think that the Godhead is like gold, or silver, or stone, formed by art and man’s device.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.30'>And the times of this ignorance God overlooked; but now commandeth all men every where to repent:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.31'>Because he hath appointed a day, when he will judge the world in righteousness by that man whom he hath ordained; of which he hath given assurance to all men, in that he hath raised him from the dead. <note>hath given…: or, offered faith</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.32'>And when they heard of the resurrection of the dead, some mocked: and others said, We will hear thee again concerning this matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.33'>So Paul departed from among them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.17.34'>But certain men joined themselves to him, and believed: among whom was Dionysius the Areopagite, and a woman named Damaris, and others with them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.18'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.1'>After these things Paul departed from Athens, and came to Corinth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.2'>And found a certain Jew named Aquila, born in Pontus, lately come from Italy, with his wife Priscilla; (because that Claudius had commanded all Jews to depart from Rome:) and he came to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.3'>And because he was of the same trade, he abode with them, and worked: for by their occupation they were tentmakers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.4'>And he reasoned in the synagogue every sabbath, and persuaded the Jews and the Greeks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.5'>And when Silas and Timothy had come from Macedonia, Paul was pressed in spirit, and testified to the Jews that Jesus was Christ. <note>was Christ: or, is the Christ</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.6'>And when they opposed them, and blasphemed, he shook his raiment, and said to them, Your blood be upon your own heads; I am clean: from henceforth I will go to the Gentiles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.7'>And he departed from there, and entered into the house of a certain man named Justus, one that worshipped God, whose house was next to the synagogue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.8'>And Crispus, the chief ruler of the synagogue, believed on the Lord with all his house; and many of the Corinthians hearing believed, and were baptized.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.9'>Then the Lord spoke to Paul in the night by a vision, Be not afraid, but speak, and hold not thy peace:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.10'>For I am with thee, and no man shall lay hands on thee to hurt thee: for I have many people in this city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.11'>And he continued there a year and six months, teaching the word of God among them. <note>continued there: Gr. sat there</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.12'>And when Gallio was the deputy of Achaia, the Jews made insurrection with one accord against Paul, and brought him to the judgment seat,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.13'>Saying, This man persuadeth men to worship God contrary to the law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.14'>And when Paul was now about to open his mouth, Gallio said to the Jews, If it were a matter of wrong or wicked crimes, O ye Jews, reason would that I should bear with you:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.15'>But if it is a question of words and names, and of your law, look ye to it; for I will be no judge of such matters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.16'>And he drove them from the judgment seat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.17'>Then all the Greeks took Sosthenes, the chief ruler of the synagogue, and beat him before the judgment seat. And Gallio cared for none of those things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.18'>And Paul after this tarried there yet a good while, and took his leave of the brethren, and sailed from there into Syria, and with him Priscilla and Aquila; having shorn his head in Cenchrea: for he had a vow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.19'>And he came to Ephesus, and left them there: but he himself entered into the synagogue, and reasoned with the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.20'>When they desired him to tarry longer time with them, he consented not;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.21'>But bade them farewell, saying, I must by all means keep this feast that cometh in Jerusalem: but I will return to you, if God will. And he sailed from Ephesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.22'>And when he had landed at Caesarea, and gone up, and greeted the church, he went down to Antioch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.23'>And after he had spent some time there, he departed, and went over all the country of Galatia and Phrygia in order, strengthening all the disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.24'>And a certain Jew named Apollos, born at Alexandria, an eloquent man, and mighty in the scriptures, came to Ephesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.25'>This man was instructed in the way of the Lord; and being fervent in the spirit, he spoke and taught diligently the things of the Lord, knowing only the baptism of John.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.26'>And he began to speak boldly in the synagogue: whom when Aquila and Priscilla had heard, they took him, and expounded to him the way of God more perfectly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.27'>And when he was disposed to pass into Achaia, the brethren wrote, exhorting the disciples to receive him: who, when he had come, helped them much who had believed through grace:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.18.28'>For he mightily convinced the Jews, and that publicly, showing by the scriptures that Jesus was Christ. <note>Christ: or, is the Christ</note></verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.19'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.1'>And it came to pass, that, while Apollos was at Corinth, Paul having passed through the upper regions came to Ephesus: and finding certain disciples,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.2'>He said to them, Have ye received the Holy Spirit since ye believed? And they said to him, We have not so much as heard whether there is any Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.3'>And he said to them, Into what then were ye baptized? And they said, Into John’s baptism.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.4'>Then said Paul, John verily baptized with the baptism of repentance, saying to the people, that they should believe on him who should come after him, that is, on Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.5'>When they heard this, they were baptized into the name of the Lord Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.6'>And when Paul had laid his hands upon them, the Holy Spirit came on them; and they spoke with tongues, and prophesied.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.7'>And all the men were about twelve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.8'>And he went into the synagogue, and spoke boldly for the space of three months, disputing and persuading the things concerning the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.9'>But when some were hardened, and believed not, but spoke evil of that way before the multitude, he departed from them, and separated the disciples, disputing daily in the school of one Tyrannus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.10'>And this continued for the space of two years; so that all they who dwelt in Asia heard the word of the Lord Jesus, both Jews and Greeks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.11'>And God wrought special miracles by the hands of Paul:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.12'>So that from his body were brought to the sick, handkerchiefs or aprons, and the diseases departed from them, and the evil spirits went out of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.13'>Then certain of the vagabond Jews, exorcists, took upon them to call over them who had evil spirits the name of the Lord Jesus, saying, We adjure you by Jesus whom Paul preacheth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.14'>And there were seven sons of one Sceva, a Jew, and chief of the priests, who did so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.15'>And the evil spirit answered and said, Jesus I know, and Paul I know; but who are ye?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.16'>And the man in whom the evil spirit was leaped on them, and overcame them, and prevailed against them, so that they fled out of that house naked and wounded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.17'>And this was known to all the Jews and Greeks also dwelling at Ephesus; and fear fell on them all, and the name of the Lord Jesus was magnified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.18'>And many that believed came, and confessed, and showed their deeds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.19'>Many also of them who practised magic brought their books together, and burned them before all men: and they counted the price of them, and found it fifty thousand pieces of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.20'>So mightily grew the word of God and prevailed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.21'>After these things were ended, Paul purposed in the spirit, when he had passed through Macedonia and Achaia, to go to Jerusalem, saying, After I have been there, I must also see Rome.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.22'>So he sent into Macedonia two of them that ministered to him, Timothy and Erastus; but he himself stayed in Asia for a season.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.23'>And the same time there arose no small stir about that way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.24'>For a certain man named Demetrius, a silversmith, who made silver shrines for Diana, brought no small gain to the craftsmen;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.25'>Whom he called together with the workmen of like occupation, and said, Sirs, ye know that by this craft we have our wealth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.26'>Moreover ye see and hear, that not alone at Ephesus, but almost throughout all Asia, this Paul hath persuaded and turned away many people, saying that they are no gods, which are made with hands:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.27'>So that not only this our craft is in danger to be set at nought; but also that the temple of the great goddess Diana should be despised, and her magnificence should be destroyed, whom all Asia and the world worshippeth. <note>set at nought: or, brought into disrepute, or, contempt</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.28'>And when they heard these sayings, they were full of wrath, and cried out, saying, Great is Diana of the Ephesians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.29'>And the whole city was filled with confusion: and having caught Gaius and Aristarchus, men of Macedonia, Paul’s companions in travel, they rushed with one accord into the theatre.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.30'>And when Paul would have entered in to the people, the disciples permitted him not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.31'>And certain of the chief of Asia, who were his friends, sent to him, beseeching him that he would not venture himself into the theatre.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.32'>Some therefore cried one thing, and some another: for the assembly was confused; and the greater part knew not why they had come together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.33'>And they drew Alexander out of the multitude, the Jews putting him forward. And Alexander beckoned with the hand, and would have made his defence to the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.34'>But when they knew that he was a Jew, all with one voice about the space of two hours cried out, Great is Diana of the Ephesians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.35'>And when the townclerk had quieted the people, he said, Ye men of Ephesus, what man is there that knoweth not that the city of the Ephesians is a worshipper of the great goddess Diana, and of the image which fell down from Jupiter? <note>a worshipper: Gr. the temple keeper</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.36'>Seeing then that these things cannot be denied, ye ought to be quiet, and to do nothing rashly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.37'>For ye have brought here these men, who are neither robbers of temples, nor yet blasphemers of your goddess.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.38'>Therefore if Demetrius, and the craftsmen who are with him, have a matter against any man, the law is open, and there are deputies: let them accuse one another. <note>the law…: or, the court days are kept</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.39'>But if ye enquire any thing concerning other matters, it shall be determined in a lawful assembly. <note>lawful: or, ordinary</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.40'>For we are in danger to be called in question for this day’s uproar, there being no cause by which we may give an account of this riotous gathering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.19.41'>And when he had thus spoken, he dismissed the assembly.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.20'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.1'>And after the uproar had ceased, Paul called to him the disciples, and embraced them, and departed to go into Macedonia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.2'>And when he had gone over those parts, and had given them much exhortation, he came into Greece,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.3'>And there abode three months. And when the Jews laid wait for him, as he was about to sail into Syria, he purposed to return through Macedonia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.4'>And there accompanied him into Asia Sopater of Berea; and of the Thessalonians, Aristarchus and Secundus; and Gaius of Derbe, and Timothy; and of Asia, Tychicus and Trophimus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.5'>These going before tarried for us at Troas.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.6'>And we sailed away from Philippi after the days of unleavened bread, and came to them to Troas in five days; where we abode seven days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.7'>And upon the first day of the week, when the disciples came together to break bread, Paul preached to them, ready to depart on the next day; and continued his speech until midnight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.8'>And there were many lights in the upper chamber, where they were gathered together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.9'>And there sat in a window a certain young man named Eutychus, having fallen into a deep sleep: and as Paul was long preaching, he sunk down with sleep, and fell from the third loft, and was taken up dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.10'>And Paul went down, and fell on him, and embracing him said, Trouble not yourselves; for his life is in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.11'>When he had come up again, and had broken bread, and eaten, and talked a long while, even till break of day, so he departed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.12'>And they brought the young man alive, and were not a little comforted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.13'>And we went before to a ship, and sailed to Assos, there intending to take in Paul: for so he had appointed, intending himself to go on foot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.14'>And when he met with us at Assos, we took him in, and came to Mitylene.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.15'>And we sailed from there, and came the next day opposite Chios; and the next day we arrived at Samos, and tarried at Trogyllium; and the next day we came to Miletus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.16'>For Paul had determined to sail by Ephesus, because he would not spend the time in Asia: for he hastened, if it were possible for him, to be at Jerusalem the day of Pentecost.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.17'>And from Miletus he sent to Ephesus, and called the elders of the church.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.18'>And when they had come to him, he said to them, Ye know, from the first day that I came into Asia, after what manner I have been with you at all seasons,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.19'>Serving the Lord with all humility of mind, and with many tears, and trials, which befell me by the lying in wait of the Jews:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.20'>And how I kept back nothing that was profitable to you, but have shown you, and have taught you publicly, and from house to house,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.21'>Testifying both to the Jews, and also to the Greeks, repentance toward God, and faith toward our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.22'>And now, behold, I go bound in the spirit to Jerusalem, not knowing the things that shall befall me there:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.23'>Except that the Holy Spirit testifieth in every city, saying that bonds and afflictions await me. <note>abide me: or, wait for me</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.24'>But none of these things move me, neither count I my life dear to myself, so that I may finish my course with joy, and the ministry, which I have received from the Lord Jesus, to testify the gospel of the grace of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.25'>And now, behold, I know that ye all, among whom I have gone preaching the kingdom of God, shall see my face no more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.26'>Therefore I testify to you this day, that I am pure from the blood of all men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.27'>For I have not shunned to declare to you all the counsel of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.28'>Take heed therefore to yourselves, and to all the flock, over which the Holy Spirit hath made you overseers, to feed the church of God, which he hath purchased with his own blood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.29'>For I know this, that after my departure grievous wolves shall enter in among you, not sparing the flock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.30'>Also from your own selves shall men arise, speaking perverse things, to draw away disciples after them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.31'>Therefore watch, and remember, that by the space of three years I ceased not to warn every one night and day with tears.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.32'>And now, brethren, I commend you to God, and to the word of his grace, which is able to build you up, and to give you an inheritance among all them who are sanctified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.33'>I have coveted no man’s silver, or gold, or apparel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.34'>Yea, ye yourselves know, that these hands have ministered to my necessities, and to them that were with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.35'>I have shown you all things, that so labouring ye ought to support the weak, and to remember the words of the Lord Jesus, that he said, It is more blessed to give than to receive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.36'>And when he had thus spoken, he kneeled down, and prayed with them all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.37'>And they all wept bitterly, and fell on Paul’s neck, and kissed him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.20.38'>Sorrowing most of all for the words which he spoke, that they should see his face no more. And they accompanied him to the ship.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.21'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.1'>And it came to pass, that after we were separated from them, and had launched, we came with a straight course to Coos, and the day following to Rhodes, and from there to Patara:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.2'>And finding a ship sailing over to Phenicia, we went aboard, and set forth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.3'>Now when we had come in sight of Cyprus, we left it on the left hand, and sailed into Syria, and landed at Tyre: for there the ship was to unload her cargo.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.4'>And finding disciples, we tarried there seven days: who said to Paul through the Spirit, that he should not go up to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.5'>And when we had come to the end of those days, we departed and went on our way; and they all accompanied us on our way, with wives and children, till we were out of the city: and we kneeled down on the shore, and prayed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.6'>And when we had taken our leave one of another, we took ship; and they returned home again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.7'>And when we had finished our course from Tyre, we came to Ptolemais, and greeted the brethren, and abode with them one day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.8'>And the next day we that were of Paul’s company departed, and came to Caesarea: and we entered into the house of Philip the evangelist, who was one of the seven; and abode with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.9'>And the same man had four daughters, virgins, who prophesied.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.10'>And as we tarried there many days, there came down from Judaea a certain prophet, named Agabus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.11'>And when he had come to us, he took Paul’s belt, and bound his own hands and feet, and said, Thus saith the Holy Spirit, So shall the Jews at Jerusalem bind the man that owneth this belt, and shall deliver him into the hands of the Gentiles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.12'>And when we heard these things, both we, and they of that place, besought him not to go up to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.13'>Then Paul answered, What mean ye to weep and to break my heart? for I am ready not to be bound only, but also to die at Jerusalem for the name of the Lord Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.14'>And when he would not be persuaded, we ceased, saying, The will of the Lord be done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.15'>And after those days we got ready, and went up to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.16'>There went with us also certain of the disciples of Caesarea, and brought with them one Mnason of Cyprus, an early disciple, with whom we should lodge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.17'>And when we had come to Jerusalem, the brethren received us gladly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.18'>And the day following Paul went in with us to James; and all the elders were present.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.19'>And when he had greeted them, he declared particularly what things God had wrought among the Gentiles by his ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.20'>And when they heard it, they glorified the Lord, and said to him, Thou seest, brother, how many thousands of Jews there are who believe; and they are all zealous of the law:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.21'>And they are informed concerning thee, that thou teachest all the Jews who are among the Gentiles to forsake Moses, saying that they ought not to circumcise their children, neither to walk after the customs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.22'>What is it therefore? the multitude must needs come together: for they will hear that thou art come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.23'>Do therefore this that we say to thee: We have four men who have a vow on them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.24'>Take them and purify thyself with them, and pay their expenses that they may shave their heads: and all may know that those things, of which they were informed concerning thee, are nothing; but that thou thyself also walkest orderly, and keepest the law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.25'>As concerning the Gentiles who believe, we have written and concluded that they observe no such thing, except that they keep themselves from things offered to idols, and from blood, and from strangled, and from immorality.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.26'>Then Paul took the men, and the next day purifying himself with them entered into the temple, to signify the accomplishment of the days of purification, until an offering should be offered for every one of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.27'>And when the seven days were almost ended, the Jews who were from Asia, when they saw him in the temple, stirred up all the people, and laid hands on him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.28'>Crying out, Men of Israel, help: This is the man, that teacheth all men every where against the people, and the law, and this place: and further hath brought Greeks also into the temple, and hath polluted this holy place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.29'>(For they had seen before with him in the city Trophimus an Ephesian, whom they supposed that Paul had brought into the temple.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.30'>And all the city was moved, and the people ran together: and they took Paul, and drew him out of the temple: and immediately the doors were shut.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.31'>And as they went about to kill him, tidings came to the chief captain of the band, that all Jerusalem was in an uproar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.32'>Who immediately took soldiers and centurions, and ran down to them: and when they saw the chief captain and the soldiers, they stopped beating Paul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.33'>Then the chief captain came near, and took him, and commanded him to be bound with two chains; and demanded who he was, and what he had done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.34'>And some cried one thing, some another, among the multitude: and when he could not know the certainty for the tumult, he commanded him to be carried into the barracks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.35'>And when he came upon the stairs, so it was, that he was borne by the soldiers for the violence of the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.36'>For the multitude of the people followed, crying, Away with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.37'>And as Paul was to be led into the barracks, he said to the chief captain, May I speak to thee? Who said, Canst thou speak Greek?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.38'>Art not thou that Egyptian, who before these days madest an uproar, and leddest out into the wilderness four thousand men that were murderers?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.39'>But Paul said, I am a man who is a Jew of Tarsus, a city of Cilicia, a citizen of no mean city: and, I beseech thee, permit me to speak to the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.21.40'>And when he had given him permission, Paul stood on the stairs, and beckoned with the hand to the people. And when there was made a great silence, he spoke to them in the Hebrew language, saying,</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.22'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.1'>Men, brethren, and fathers, hear ye my defence which I make now to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.2'>(And when they heard that he spoke to them in the Hebrew language, they kept the more silence: and he saith,)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.3'>I am verily a man who is a Jew, born in Tarsus, a city in Cilicia, yet brought up in this city at the feet of Gamaliel, and taught according to the perfect manner of the law of the fathers, being zealous toward God, as ye all are this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.4'>And I persecuted this way to the death, binding and delivering into prisons both men and women.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.5'>As also the high priest doth bear me witness, and all the council of the elders: from whom also I received letters to the brethren, and went to Damascus, to bring them who were there bound to Jerusalem, to be punished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.6'>And it came to pass, that, as I was on my journey, and had come near to Damascus about noon, suddenly there shone from heaven a great light around me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.7'>And I fell to the ground, and heard a voice saying to me, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.8'>And I answered, Who art thou, Lord? And he said to me, I am Jesus of Nazareth, whom thou persecutest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.9'>And they that were with me saw indeed the light, and were afraid; but they heard not the voice of him that spoke to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.10'>And I said, What shall I do, Lord? And the Lord said to me, Arise, and go into Damascus; and there it shall be told thee concerning all things which are appointed for thee to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.11'>And when I could not see for the glory of that light, being led by the hand of them that were with me, I came into Damascus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.12'>And one Ananias, a devout man according to the law, having a good report of all the Jews who dwelt there,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.13'>Came to me, and stood, and said to me, Brother Saul, receive thy sight. And the same hour I looked up upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.14'>And he said, The God of our fathers hath chosen thee, that thou shouldest know his will, and see that Just One, and shouldest hear the voice of his mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.15'>For thou shalt be his witness to all men of what thou hast seen and heard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.16'>And now why tarriest thou? arise, and be baptized, and wash away thy sins, calling on the name of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.17'>And it came to pass, that, when I had come again to Jerusalem, even while I prayed in the temple, I was in a trance;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.18'>And saw him saying to me, Make haste, and depart quickly from Jerusalem: for they will not receive thy testimony concerning me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.19'>And I said, Lord, they know that I imprisoned and beat in every synagogue them that believed on thee:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.20'>And when the blood of thy martyr Stephen was shed, I also was standing by, and consenting to his death, and kept the raiment of them that slew him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.21'>And he said to me, Depart: for I will send thee far away to the Gentiles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.22'>And they hearkened to him until this word, and then lifted up their voices, and said, Away with such a fellow from the earth: for it is not fit that he should live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.23'>And as they cried out, and cast off their clothes, and threw dust into the air,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.24'>The chief captain commanded him to be brought into the barracks, and bade that he should be examined by scourging; that he might know for what cause they cried so against him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.25'>And as they bound him with thongs, Paul said to the centurion that stood by, Is it lawful for you to scourge a man that is a Roman, and uncondemned?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.26'>When the centurion heard that, he went and told the chief captain, saying, Take heed what thou doest: for this man is a Roman.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.27'>Then the chief captain came, and said to him, Tell me, art thou a Roman? He said, Yea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.28'>And the chief captain answered, With a great sum I obtained this freedom. And Paul said, But I was free born.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.29'>Then immediately they departed from him who were about to examine him: and the chief captain also was afraid, after he knew that he was a Roman, and because he had bound him. <note>examined him: or, tortured him</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.22.30'>On the next day, because he would have known the certainty why he was accused by the Jews, he loosed him from his bands, and commanded the chief priests and all their council to appear, and brought Paul down, and set him before them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.23'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.1'>And Paul, earnestly beholding the council, said, Men, brethren, I have lived in all good conscience before God until this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.2'>And the high priest Ananias commanded them that stood by him to strike him on the mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.3'>Then said Paul to him, God shall smite thee, thou whitewashed wall: for sittest thou to judge me according to the law, and commandest me to be smitten contrary to the law?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.4'>And they that stood by said, Revilest thou God’s high priest?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.5'>Then said Paul, I knew not, brethren, that he is the high priest: for it is written, Thou shalt not speak evil of the ruler of thy people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.6'>But when Paul perceived that the one part were Sadducees, and the other Pharisees, he cried out in the council, Men, brethren, I am a Pharisee, the son of a Pharisee: concerning the hope and resurrection of the dead I am called in question.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.7'>And when he had so said, there arose a dissension between the Pharisees and the Sadducees: and the multitude was divided.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.8'>For the Sadducees say that there is no resurrection, neither angel, nor spirit: but the Pharisees confess both.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.9'>And there arose a great cry: and the scribes that were of the Pharisees’ part arose, and contended, saying, We find no evil in this man: but if a spirit or an angel hath spoken to him, let us not fight against God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.10'>And when there arose a great dissension, the chief captain, fearing lest Paul should have been pulled in pieces by them, commanded the soldiers to go down, and to take him by force from among them, and to bring him into the barracks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.11'>And the night following the Lord stood by him, and said, Be of good cheer, Paul: for as thou hast testified concerning me in Jerusalem, so must thou bear testimony also at Rome.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.12'>And when it was day, certain of the Jews banded together, and bound themselves under a curse, saying that they would neither eat nor drink till they had killed Paul. <note>under a curse: or, with an oath of execration</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.13'>And they were more than forty who had made this conspiracy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.14'>And they came to the chief priests and elders, and said, We have bound ourselves under a great curse, that we will eat nothing until we have slain Paul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.15'>Now therefore ye with the council signify to the chief captain that he bring him down to you to morrow, as though ye would enquire something more perfectly concerning him: and we, before he shall come near, are ready to kill him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.16'>And when the son of Paul’s sister heard of their lying in wait, he went and entered into the barracks, and told Paul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.17'>Then Paul called one of the centurions to him, and said, Bring this young man to the chief captain: for he hath a certain thing to tell him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.18'>So he took him, and brought him to the chief captain, and said, Paul the prisoner called me to him, and asked me to bring this young man to thee, who hath something to say to thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.19'>Then the chief captain took him by the hand, and went with him aside privately, and asked him, What is that thou hast to tell me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.20'>And he said, The Jews have agreed to desire thee that thou wouldest bring down Paul to morrow into the council, as though they would enquire somewhat concerning him more perfectly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.21'>But do not thou yield to them: for there are of them who lie in wait for him more than forty men, who have bound themselves with an oath, that they will neither eat nor drink till they have killed him: and now they are ready, looking for a promise from thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.22'>So the chief captain then let the young man depart, and charged him, See thou tell no man that thou hast shown these things to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.23'>And he called to him two centurions, saying, Make ready two hundred soldiers to go to Caesarea, and seventy horsemen, and spearmen two hundred, at the third hour of the night;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.24'>And provide for them beasts, that they may set Paul on, and bring him safe to Felix the governor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.25'>And he wrote a letter after this manner:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.26'>Claudius Lysias to the most excellent governor Felix sendeth greeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.27'>This man was taken by the Jews, and should have been killed by them: then I came with a body of soldiers, and rescued him, having understood that he was a Roman.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.28'>And when I would have known the cause for which they accused him, I brought him forth into their council:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.29'>Whom I perceived to be accused of questions of their law, but to have nothing laid to his charge worthy of death or of bonds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.30'>And when it was told to me that the Jews laid wait for the man, I sent immediately to thee, and gave commandment to his accusers also to say before thee what they had against him. Farewell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.31'>Then the soldiers, as it was commanded them, took Paul, and brought him by night to Antipatris.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.32'>On the next day they left the horsemen to go with him, and returned to the barracks:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.33'>Who, when they came to Caesarea, and delivered the epistle to the governor, presented Paul also before him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.34'>And when the governor had read the letter, he asked of what province he was. And when he understood that he was of Cilicia;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.23.35'>I will hear thee, said he, when thy accusers also have come. And he commanded him to be kept in Herod’s judgment hall.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.24'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.1'>And after five days Ananias the high priest descended with the elders, and with a certain orator named Tertullus, who informed the governor against Paul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.2'>And when he was called forth, Tertullus began to accuse him, saying, Seeing that by thee we enjoy great quietness, and that very worthy deeds are done to this nation by thy providence,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.3'>We accept it always, and in all places, most noble Felix, with all thankfulness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.4'>However, that I may not be further tedious to thee, I beseech thee that thou wouldest of thy clemency hear us a few words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.5'>For we have found this man a pestilent fellow, and a mover of sedition among all the Jews throughout the world, and a ringleader of the sect of the Nazarenes:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.6'>Who also hath gone about to profane the temple: whom we took, and would have judged according to our law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.7'>But the chief captain Lysias came, and with great violence took him out of our hands,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.8'>Commanding his accusers to come to thee: by examining whom thou thyself mayest take knowledge of all these things, of which we accuse him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.9'>And the Jews also assented, saying that these things were so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.10'>Then Paul, after the governor had beckoned to him to speak, answered, Forasmuch as I know that thou hast been for many years a judge to this nation, I do the more cheerfully answer for myself:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.11'>That thou mayest understand, that there are yet but twelve days since I went up to Jerusalem to worship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.12'>And they neither found me in the temple disputing with any man, neither provoking the people to sedition, neither in the synagogues, nor in the city:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.13'>Neither can they prove the things of which they now accuse me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.14'>But this I confess to thee, that after the way which they call heresy, so I worship the God of my fathers, believing all things which are written in the law and in the prophets:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.15'>And have hope toward God, which they themselves also allow, that there shall be a resurrection of the dead, both of the just and unjust.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.16'>And in this I exercise myself, to have always a conscience void of offence toward God, and toward men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.17'>Now after many years I came to bring alms to my nation, and offerings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.18'>Upon which certain Jews from Asia found me purified in the temple, neither with multitude, nor with tumult.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.19'>Who ought to have been here before thee, and object, if they had any thing against me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.20'>Or else let these same here say, if they have found any evil doing in me, while I stood before the council,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.21'>Except it is for this one thing, that I cried standing among them, Concerning the resurrection of the dead I am called in question by you this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.22'>And when Felix heard these things, having more perfect knowledge of that way, he deferred them, and said, When Lysias the chief captain shall come down, I will make a decision on your case.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.23'>And he commanded a centurion to keep Paul, and to let him have liberty, and that he should forbid none of his acquaintance to minister or come to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.24'>And after certain days, when Felix came with his wife Drusilla, who was a Jewess, he sent for Paul, and heard him concerning the faith in Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.25'>And as he reasoned of righteousness, self–control, and judgment to come, Felix trembled, and answered, Go thy way for this time; when I have a convenient season, I will call for thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.26'>He hoped also that money should have been given him by Paul, that he might loose him: therefore he sent for him the oftener, and communed with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.24.27'>But after two years Porcius Festus came in place of Felix: and Felix, willing to show the Jews a favour, left Paul bound.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.25'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.1'>Now when Festus had come into the province, after three days he went up from Caesarea to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.2'>Then the high priest and the chief of the Jews informed him against Paul, and besought him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.3'>And desired favour against him, that he would send for him to Jerusalem, laying wait in the way to kill him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.4'>But Festus answered, that Paul should be kept at Caesarea, and that he himself would depart shortly there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.5'>Let them therefore, said he, who among you are able, go down with me, and accuse this man, if there is any wickedness in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.6'>And when he had tarried among them more than ten days, he went down to Caesarea; and the next day sitting on the judgment seat commanded Paul to be brought. <note>more…: or, as some copies read, no more than eight or ten days</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.7'>And when he had come, the Jews who came down from Jerusalem stood around, and laid many and grievous complaints against Paul, which they could not prove.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.8'>While he answered for himself, Neither against the law of the Jews, neither against the temple, nor yet against Caesar, have I committed any offence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.9'>But Festus, willing to do the Jews a favour, answered Paul, and said, Wilt thou go to Jerusalem, and there be judged concerning these things before me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.10'>Then said Paul, I stand at Caesar’s judgment seat, where I ought to be judged: to the Jews have I done no wrong, as thou very well knowest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.11'>For if I am an offender, or have committed any thing worthy of death, I refuse not to die: but if there is none of these things of which these accuse me, no man may deliver me to them. I appeal to Caesar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.12'>Then Festus, when he had conferred with the council, answered, Hast thou appealed to Caesar? to Caesar thou shalt go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.13'>And after certain days king Agrippa and Bernice came to Caesarea to greet Festus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.14'>And when they had been there many days, Festus declared Paul’s cause to the king, saying, There is a certain man left in bonds by Felix:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.15'>About whom, when I was at Jerusalem, the chief priests and the elders of the Jews informed me, desiring to have judgment against him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.16'>To whom I answered, It is not the manner of the Romans to deliver any man to die, before he who is accused hath the accusers face to face, and hath opportunity to answer for himself concerning the charge laid against him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.17'>Therefore, when they had come here, without any delay on the next day I sat on the judgment seat, and commanded the man to be brought forth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.18'>Against whom when the accusers stood up, they brought no accusation of such things as I supposed:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.19'>But had certain questions against him of their own religion, and of one Jesus, who was dead, whom Paul affirmed to be alive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.20'>And because I was perplexed concerning such manner of questions, I asked him whether he would go to Jerusalem, and there be judged concerning these matters. <note>I doubted…: or, I was doubtful how to enquire hereof</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.21'>But when Paul had appealed to be reserved to the hearing of Augustus, I commanded him to be kept till I might send him to Caesar. <note>hearing: or, judgment</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.22'>Then Agrippa said to Festus, I would also hear the man myself. To morrow, said he, thou shalt hear him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.23'>And on the next day, when Agrippa had come, and Bernice, with great pomp, and had entered into the place of hearing, with the chief captains, and principal men of the city, at the command of Festus Paul was brought forth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.24'>And Festus said, King Agrippa, and all men who are here present with us, ye see this man, about whom all the multitude of the Jews have dealt with me, both at Jerusalem, and also here, crying that he ought not to live any longer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.25'>But when I found that he had committed nothing worthy of death, and that he himself hath appealed to Augustus, I have determined to send him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.26'>Of whom I have no certain thing to write to my lord. Therefore I have brought him forth before you, and especially before thee, O king Agrippa, that, after examination had, I may have somewhat to write.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.25.27'>For it seemeth to me unreasonable to send a prisoner, and not also to signify the charges laid against him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.26'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.1'>Then Agrippa said to Paul, Thou art permitted to speak for thyself. Then Paul stretched forth the hand, and answered for himself:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.2'>I think myself happy, king Agrippa, because I shall answer for myself this day before thee concerning all the things of which I am accused by the Jews:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.3'>Especially because I know thee to be expert in all customs and questions which are among the Jews: therefore I beseech thee to hear me patiently.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.4'>My manner of life from my youth, which was at the first among my own nation at Jerusalem, know all the Jews;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.5'>Who knew me from the beginning, if they would testify, that after the most strict sect of our religion I lived a Pharisee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.6'>And now I stand and am judged for the hope of the promise made by God to our fathers:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.7'>To which promise our twelve tribes, earnestly serving God day and night, hope to come. For which hope’s sake, king Agrippa, I am accused by the Jews. <note>day and night: Gr. night and day</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.8'>Why should it be thought a thing incredible with you, that God should raise the dead?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.9'>I verily thought with myself, that I ought to do many things contrary to the name of Jesus of Nazareth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.10'>Which thing I also did in Jerusalem: and many of the saints did I shut up in prison, having received authority from the chief priests; and when they were put to death, I gave my voice against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.11'>And I punished them often in every synagogue, and compelled them to blaspheme; and being exceedingly mad against them, I persecuted them even to foreign cities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.12'>Upon which as I went to Damascus with authority and commission from the chief priests,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.13'>At noon, O king, I saw in the way a light from heaven, beyond the brightness of the sun, shining around me and them who journeyed with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.14'>And when we had all fallen to the earth, I heard a voice speaking to me, and saying in the Hebrew language, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me? it is hard for thee to kick against the goads.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.15'>And I said, Who art thou, Lord? And he said, I am Jesus whom thou persecutest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.16'>But rise, and stand upon thy feet: for I have appeared to thee for this purpose, to make thee a minister and a witness both of the things which thou hast seen, and of the things in which I will appear to thee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.17'>Delivering thee from the people, and from the Gentiles, to whom now I send thee,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.18'>To open their eyes, and to turn them from darkness to light, and from the power of Satan to God, that they may receive forgiveness of sins, and inheritance among them who are sanctified by faith that is in me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.19'>Upon which, O king Agrippa, I was not disobedient to the heavenly vision:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.20'>But showed first to them of Damascus, and at Jerusalem, and throughout all the region of Judaea, and then to the Gentiles, that they should repent and turn to God, and do works fit for repentance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.21'>For these causes the Jews caught me in the temple, and went about to kill me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.22'>Having therefore obtained help from God, I continue to this day, witnessing both to small and great, saying no other things than those which the prophets and Moses did say should come:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.23'>That Christ should suffer, and that he should be the first that should rise from the dead, and should show light to the people, and to the Gentiles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.24'>And as he was thus speaking for himself, Festus said with a loud voice, Paul, thou art beside thyself; much learning doth make thee mad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.25'>But he said, I am not mad, most noble Festus; but speak forth the words of truth and soberness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.26'>For the king knoweth of these things, before whom also I speak freely: for I am persuaded that none of these things are hidden from him; for this thing was not done in a corner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.27'>King Agrippa, believest thou the prophets? I know that thou believest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.28'>Then Agrippa said to Paul, Almost thou persuadest me to be a Christian.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.29'>And Paul said, I would to God, that not only thou, but also all that hear me this day, were both almost, and altogether such as I am, except these bonds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.30'>And when he had thus spoken, the king rose, and the governor, and Bernice, and they that sat with them:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.31'>And when they had gone aside, they talked between themselves, saying, This man doeth nothing worthy of death or of bonds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.26.32'>Then said Agrippa to Festus, This man might have been set at liberty, if he had not appealed to Caesar.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.27'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.1'>And when it was determined that we should sail into Italy, they delivered Paul and certain other prisoners to one named Julius, a centurion of Augustus’ band.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.2'>And entering into a ship of Adramyttium, we launched, meaning to sail by the coasts of Asia; one Aristarchus, a Macedonian of Thessalonica, being with us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.3'>And the next day we touched at Sidon. And Julius courteously treated Paul, and gave him liberty to go to his friends to refresh himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.4'>And when we had launched from there, we sailed under Cyprus, because the winds were contrary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.5'>And when we had sailed over the sea of Cilicia and Pamphylia, we came to Myra, a city of Lycia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.6'>And there the centurion found a ship of Alexandria sailing into Italy; and he put us on board.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.7'>And when we had sailed slowly many days, and scarce had come off Cnidus, the wind did not permit us, we sailed under Crete, off Salmone; <note>Crete: or, Candy</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.8'>And, scarcely passing it, came to a place which is called The fair havens; near which was the city of Lasea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.9'>Now when much time was spent, and when sailing was now dangerous, because the fast was now already past, Paul admonished them, <note>the fast: the fast was on the tenth day of the seventh month</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.10'>And said to them, Sirs, I perceive that this voyage will be with harm and much damage, not only of the cargo and ship, but also of our lives. <note>hurt: or, injury</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.11'>Nevertheless the centurion believed the master and the owner of the ship, more than the things which were spoken by Paul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.12'>And because the haven was not suitable to winter in, the greater part advised to depart from there also, if by any means they might attain to Phenice, and there to winter; which is an haven of Crete, and lieth toward the south west and north west.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.13'>And when the south wind blew softly, supposing that they had obtained their purpose, loosing from there, they sailed close by Crete.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.14'>But not long after there arose against it a tempestuous wind, called Euroclydon. <note>arose: or, beat</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.15'>And when the ship was caught, and could not bear up into the wind, we let her drive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.16'>And running under a certain isle which is called Clauda, we had much work to secure the boat:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.17'>Which when they had taken it up, they used cables, undergirding the ship; and, fearing lest they should fall into the quicksands, struck sail, and so were driven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.18'>And we being exceedingly tossed with a tempest, the next day they lightened the ship;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.19'>And the third day we cast out with our own hands the tackling of the ship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.20'>And when neither sun nor stars in many days appeared, and no small tempest lay on us, all hope that we should be saved was then taken away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.21'>But after being long without food Paul stood forth in the midst of them, and said, Sirs, ye should have hearkened to me, and not have loosed from Crete, and to have gained this harm and loss.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.22'>And now I exhort you to be of good cheer: for there shall be no loss of life among you, but of the ship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.23'>For there stood by me this night the angel of God, whose I am, and whom I serve,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.24'>Saying, Fear not, Paul; thou must be brought before Caesar: and, lo, God hath given thee all them that sail with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.25'>Therefore, sirs, be of good cheer: for I believe God, that it shall be even as it was told to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.26'>But we must be cast upon a certain isle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.27'>But when the fourteenth night was come, as we were driven up and down in Adria, about midnight the shipmen thought that they drew near to some country;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.28'>And sounded, and found it twenty fathoms: and when they had gone a little further, they sounded again, and found it fifteen fathoms.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.29'>Then fearing lest we should fall upon rocks, they cast four anchors out of the stern, and wished for the day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.30'>And as the shipmen were about to flee out of the ship, when they had let down the boat into the sea, under pretence as though they would cast anchors out of the foreship,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.31'>Paul said to the centurion and to the soldiers, Except these abide in the ship, ye cannot be saved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.32'>Then the soldiers cut off the ropes of the boat, and let her fall off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.33'>And while the day was coming on, Paul besought them all to take food, saying, This day is the fourteenth day that ye have tarried and continued fasting, having taken nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.34'>Therefore I beseech you to take some food: for this is for your health: for there shall not an hair fall from the head of any of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.35'>And when he had thus spoken, he took bread, and gave thanks to God in presence of them all: and when he had broken it, he began to eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.36'>Then they were all of good cheer, and they also took food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.37'>And we were in all in the ship two hundred and seventy and six souls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.38'>And when they had eaten enough, they lightened the ship, and cast the wheat into the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.39'>And when it was day, they knew not the land: but they discovered a certain creek with a shore, into which they purposed, if it were possible, to thrust in the ship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.40'>And when they had taken up the anchors, they committed themselves to the sea, and loosed the rudder bands, and hoisted the mainsail to the wind, and made toward the shore. <note>taken…: or, cut the anchors, they left them in the sea</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.41'>And falling into a place where two seas met, they ran the ship aground; and the bow stuck fast, and remained unmoveable, but the stern was broken with the violence of the waves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.42'>And the soldiers’ counsel was to kill the prisoners, lest any of them should swim out, and escape.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.43'>But the centurion, willing to save Paul, kept them from their purpose; and commanded that they who could swim should cast themselves first into the sea, and get to land:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.27.44'>And the rest, some on boards, and some on broken pieces of the ship. And so it came to pass, that they all escaped safe to land.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Acts.28'>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.1'>And when they had escaped, then they knew that the isle was called Melita.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.2'>And the barbarous people showed us no little kindness: for they kindled a fire, and received us every one, because of the present rain, and because of the cold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.3'>And when Paul had gathered a bundle of sticks, and laid them on the fire, there came a viper out of the heat, and fastened on his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.4'>And when the barbarians saw the venomous creature hanging from his hand, they said among themselves, No doubt this man is a murderer, whom, though he hath escaped the sea, yet Vengeance alloweth not to live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.5'>And he shook off the creature into the fire, and felt no harm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.6'>Yet they looked when he should have swollen, or fallen down dead suddenly: but after they had looked a great while, and saw no harm come to him, they changed their minds, and said that he was a god.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.7'>In the same quarters were possessions of the chief man of the isle, whose name was Publius; who received us, and lodged us three days courteously.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.8'>And it came to pass, that the father of Publius lay sick with a fever and a bloody flux: to whom Paul entered in, and prayed, and laid his hands on him, and healed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.9'>So when this was done, others also, who had diseases in the isle, came, and were healed:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.10'>Who also honoured us with many honours; and when we departed, they supplied us with such things as were necessary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.11'>And after three months we departed in a ship of Alexandria, which had wintered in the isle, whose sign was Castor and Pollux.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.12'>And landing at Syracuse, we tarried there three days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.13'>And from there we sailed around, and came to Rhegium: and after one day the south wind blew, and we came the next day to Puteoli:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.14'>Where we found brethren, and were desired to tarry with them seven days: and so we went toward Rome.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.15'>And from there, when the brethren heard of us, they came to meet us as far as Appii forum, and The three taverns: whom when Paul saw, he thanked God, and took courage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.16'>And when we came to Rome, the centurion delivered the prisoners to the captain of the guard: but Paul was permitted to dwell by himself with a soldier that kept him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.17'>And it came to pass, that after three days Paul called together the chief of the Jews: and when they were assembled, he said to them, Men, brethren, though I have committed nothing against the people, or customs of our fathers, yet I was delivered prisoner from Jerusalem into the hands of the Romans.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.18'>Who, when they had examined me, would have let me go, because there was no cause of death in me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.19'>But when the Jews spoke against it, I was constrained to appeal to Caesar; not that I had any thing to accuse my nation of.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.20'>For this cause therefore have I called for you, to see you, and to speak with you: because that for the hope of Israel I am bound with this chain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.21'>And they said to him, We have neither received letters from Judaea concerning thee, neither have any of the brethren that came shown or spoken any harm of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.22'>But we desire to hear from thee what thou thinkest: for as concerning this sect, we know that every where it is spoken against.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.23'>And when they had appointed him a day, there came many to him into his lodging; to whom he expounded and testified the kingdom of God, persuading them concerning Jesus, both out of the law of Moses, and out of the prophets, from morning till evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.24'>And some believed the things which were spoken, and some believed not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.25'>And when they agreed not among themselves, they departed, after Paul had spoken one word, Well spoke the Holy Spirit by Isaiah the prophet to our fathers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.26'>Saying, Go to this people, and say, Hearing ye shall hear, and shall not understand; and seeing ye shall see, and not perceive:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.27'>For the heart of this people has become dull, and their ears are hard of hearing, and their eyes have they closed; lest they should see with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and understand with their heart, and should be converted, and I should heal them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.28'>Be it known therefore to you, that the salvation of God is sent to the Gentiles, and they will hear it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.29'>And when he had said these words, the Jews departed, and had great dispute among themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.30'>And Paul dwelt two whole years in his own hired house, and received all that came in to him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Acts.28.31'>Preaching the kingdom of God, and teaching those things which concern the Lord Jesus Christ, with all confidence, no man forbidding him.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>