<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='RWebster' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='RWebster'>
        <title>Revised 1833 Webster Version</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>
Revised 1833 Webster Version                                 Oct. 95
====================================================================

Scripture quoted by permission. (RWEBSTER) Version is THE REVISED 
WEBSTER VERSION OF THE HOLY BIBLE. This English text is in the Public
Domain.
      </description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>RWebster</identifier>
        <source>http://www.answersingenesis.org/OnlineBible/files/rwebster.exe</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage/>
        <rights>This English text is in the Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Col'>
      <chapter osisID='Col.1'>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.1'>Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, and Timothy our brother,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.2'>To the saints and faithful brethren in Christ who are at Colosse: Grace be to you, and peace, from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.3'>We give thanks to God and the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, praying always for you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.4'>Since we heard of your faith in Christ Jesus, and of the love which ye have to all the saints,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.5'>For the hope which is laid up for you in heaven, of which ye have heard before in the word of the truth of the gospel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.6'>Which is come to you, as it is in all the world; and bringeth forth fruit, as it doth also in you, since the day ye heard of it, and knew the grace of God in truth:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.7'>As ye also learned from Epaphras our dear fellowservant, who is for you a faithful minister of Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.8'>Who also declared to us your love in the Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.9'>For this cause we also, since the day we heard it, do not cease to pray for you, and to desire that ye may be filled with the knowledge of his will in all wisdom and spiritual understanding;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.10'>That ye may walk worthy of the Lord to all pleasing, being fruitful in every good work, and increasing in the knowledge of God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.11'>Strengthened with all might, according to his glorious power, to all patience and longsuffering with joyfulness;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.12'>Giving thanks to the Father, who hath made us qualified to be partakers of the inheritance of the saints in light:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.13'>Who hath delivered us from the power of darkness, and hath translated us into the kingdom of his beloved Son: <note>his…: Gr. the Son of his love</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.14'>In whom we have redemption through his blood, even the forgiveness of sins:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.15'>Who is the image of the invisible God, the firstborn of all creation:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.16'>For by him were all things created, that are in heaven, and that are upon earth, visible and invisible, whether thrones, or dominions, or principalities, or powers: all things were created by him, and for him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.17'>And he is before all things, and by him all things consist.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.18'>And he is the head of the body, the church: who is the beginning, the firstborn from the dead; that in all things he may have the preeminence. <note>in…: or, among all</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.19'>For it pleased the Father that in him should all fulness dwell;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.20'>And, having made peace through the blood of his cross, by him to reconcile all things to himself; by him, I say, whether they are things on earth, or things in heaven. <note>having…: or, making</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.21'>And you, that were once alienated and enemies in your mind by wicked works, yet now hath he reconciled <note>in…: or, by your mind in</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.22'>In the body of his flesh through death, to present you holy and unblameable and unreproveable in his sight:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.23'>If ye continue in the faith grounded and settled, and are not moved away from the hope of the gospel, which ye have heard, and which was preached to every creature which is under heaven; of which I Paul am made a minister;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.24'>Who now rejoice in my sufferings for you, and fill up that which is behind of the afflictions of Christ in my flesh for his body’s sake, which is the church:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.25'>Of which I am made a minister, according to the dispensation of God which is given to me for you, to fulfil the word of God; <note>to fulfil…: or, fully to preach the word</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.26'>Even the mystery which hath been hid from ages and from generations, but now is revealed to his saints:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.27'>To whom God would make known what is the riches of the glory of this mystery among the Gentiles; which is Christ in you, the hope of glory: <note>in: or, among</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.28'>Whom we preach, warning every man, and teaching every man in all wisdom; that we may present every man perfect in Christ Jesus:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.1.29'>For which I also labour, striving according to his working, which worketh in me mightily.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Col.2'>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.1'>For I would that ye knew what great conflict I have for you, and for them at Laodicea, and for as many as have not seen my face in the flesh; <note>conflict: or, fear, or, care</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.2'>That their hearts may be comforted, being knit together in love, and to all riches of the full assurance of understanding, to the acknowledgement of the mystery of God, and of the Father, and of Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.3'>In whom are hid all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge. <note>In whom: or, Wherein</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.4'>And this I say, lest any man should deceive you with enticing words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.5'>For though I am absent in the flesh, yet I am with you in the spirit, joying and beholding your order, and the steadfastness of your faith in Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.6'>As ye have therefore received Christ Jesus the Lord, so walk ye in him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.7'>Rooted and built up in him, and established in the faith, as ye have been taught, abounding in it with thanksgiving.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.8'>Beware lest any man make a prey of you through philosophy and vain deceit, after the tradition of men, after the rudiments of the world, and not after Christ. <note>make a prey: or, seduce you, or, lead you astray</note><note>rudiments: or, elements</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.9'>For in him dwelleth all the fulness of the Godhead bodily.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.10'>And ye are complete in him, who is the head of all principality and power:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.11'>In whom also ye are circumcised with the circumcision made without hands, in putting off the body of the sins of the flesh by the circumcision of Christ:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.12'>Buried with him in baptism, in which also ye are risen with him through the faith of the operation of God, who hath raised him from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.13'>And you, being dead in your sins and the uncircumcision of your flesh, hath he made alive together with him, having forgiven you all trespasses;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.14'>Blotting out the handwriting of ordinances that was against us, which was contrary to us, and took it out of the way, nailing it to his cross;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.15'>And having disarmed principalities and powers, he made a show of them openly, triumphing over them in it. <note>in it: or, in himself</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.16'>Let no man therefore judge you in food, or in drink, or in respect of a feast day, or of the new moon, or of the sabbaths: <note>in meat…: or, for eating and drinking</note><note>respect: or, part</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.17'>Which are a shadow of things to come; but the body is of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.18'>Let no man beguile you of your reward in a voluntary humility and worshipping of angels, intruding into those things which he hath not seen, vainly puffed up by his fleshly mind, <note>beguile…: or, judge against you</note><note>in a…: Gr. being a voluntary in humility</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.19'>And not holding the Head, from which all the body by joints and bands having nourishment ministered, and knit together, increaseth with the increase of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.20'>Therefore if ye are dead with Christ from the rudiments of the world, why, as though living in the world, are ye subject to ordinances, <note>rudiments: or, elements</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.21'>(Touch not; taste not; handle not;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.22'>Which all are to perish with the using;) according to the commandments and doctrines of men?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.2.23'>These things have indeed a show of wisdom in will worship, and humility, and neglecting of the body; not in any honour to the satisfying of the flesh. <note>neglecting: or, punishing, or, not sparing</note></verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Col.3'>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.1'>If ye then were raised with Christ, seek those things which are above, where Christ sitteth on the right hand of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.2'>Set your affection on things above, not on things on the earth. <note>affection: or, mind</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.3'>For ye are dead, and your life is hid with Christ in God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.4'>When Christ, who is our life, shall appear, then shall ye also appear with him in glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.5'>Mortify therefore your members which are upon the earth; immorality, uncleanness, inordinate affection, evil desire, and covetousness, which is idolatry:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.6'>For which things’ the wrath of God cometh on the children of disobedience:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.7'>In which ye also walked once, when ye lived with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.8'>But now ye also put off all these; anger, wrath, malice, blasphemy, filthy communication out of your mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.9'>Lie not one to another, seeing ye have put off the old man with his deeds;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.10'>And have put on the new man, which is renewed in knowledge after the image of him that created him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.11'>Where there is neither Greek nor Jew, circumcision nor uncircumcision, Barbarian, Scythian, bond nor free: but Christ is all, and in all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.12'>Put on therefore, as the elect of God, holy and beloved, tender mercies, kindness, humbleness of mind, meekness, longsuffering;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.13'>Forbearing one another, and forgiving one another, if any man hath a quarrel against any: even as Christ forgave you, so also do ye. <note>quarrel: or, complaint</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.14'>And above all these things put on charity, which is the bond of perfectness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.15'>And let the peace of God rule in your hearts, to which also ye are called in one body; and be ye thankful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.16'>Let the word of Christ dwell in you richly in all wisdom; teaching and admonishing one another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing with grace in your hearts to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.17'>And whatever ye do in word or deed, do all in the name of the Lord Jesus, giving thanks to God and the Father by him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.18'>Wives, submit yourselves to your own husbands, as it is fit in the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.19'>Husbands, love your wives, and be not bitter against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.20'>Children, obey your parents in all things: for this is well pleasing to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.21'>Fathers, provoke not your children to anger, lest they be discouraged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.22'>Servants, obey in all things your masters according to the flesh; not with eyeservice, as menpleasers; but in singleness of heart, fearing God:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.23'>And whatever ye do, do it heartily, as to the Lord, and not to men;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.24'>Knowing that from the Lord ye shall receive the reward of the inheritance: for ye serve the Lord Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.3.25'>But he that doeth wrong shall receive for the wrong which he hath done: and there is no respect of persons.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Col.4'>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.1'>Masters, give to your servants that which is just and equal; knowing that ye also have a Master in heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.2'>Continue in prayer, and watch in the same with thanksgiving;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.3'>At the same time praying also for us, that God would open to us a door of utterance, to speak the mystery of Christ, for which I am also in bonds:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.4'>That I may make it clear, as I ought to speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.5'>Walk in wisdom toward them that are outside the church, redeeming the time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.6'>Let your speech be always with grace, seasoned with salt, that ye may know how ye ought to answer every man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.7'>All my state shall Tychicus declare to you, who is a beloved brother, and a faithful minister and fellowservant in the Lord:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.8'>Whom I have sent to you for the same purpose, that he may know your circumstances, and comfort your hearts;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.9'>With Onesimus, a faithful and beloved brother, who is one of you. They shall make known to you all things which are done here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.10'>Aristarchus my fellowprisoner greeteth you, and Mark, sister’s son to Barnabas, (concerning whom ye received commandments: if he should come to you, receive him;)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.11'>And Jesus, who is called Justus, who are of the circumcision. These only are my fellowworkers to the kingdom of God, who have been a comfort to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.12'>Epaphras, who is one of you, a servant of Christ, greeteth you, always labouring fervently for you in prayers, that ye may stand perfect and complete in all the will of God. <note>labouring…: or, striving</note><note>complete: or, filled</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.13'>For I bear him witness, that he hath a great zeal for you, and them that are in Laodicea, and them in Hierapolis.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.14'>Luke, the beloved physician, and Demas, greet you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.15'>Greet the brethren who are in Laodicea, and Nymphas, and the church which is in his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.16'>And when this epistle is read among you, cause that it be read also in the church of the Laodiceans; and that ye likewise read the epistle from Laodicea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.17'>And say to Archippus, Take heed to the ministry which thou hast received in the Lord, that thou fulfil it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Col.4.18'>The salutation by the hand of me Paul. Remember my bonds. Grace be with you. Amen. <note>Written from Rome to Colossians by Tychicus and Onesimus.</note></verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>