<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='RWebster' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='RWebster'>
        <title>Revised 1833 Webster Version</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>
Revised 1833 Webster Version                                 Oct. 95
====================================================================

Scripture quoted by permission. (RWEBSTER) Version is THE REVISED 
WEBSTER VERSION OF THE HOLY BIBLE. This English text is in the Public
Domain.
      </description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>RWebster</identifier>
        <source>http://www.answersingenesis.org/OnlineBible/files/rwebster.exe</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage/>
        <rights>This English text is in the Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Jas'>
      <chapter osisID='Jas.1'>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.1'>James, a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ, to the twelve tribes who are scattered abroad, greeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.2'>My brethren, count it all joy when ye fall into various temptations; <note>temptations: or, trials</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.3'>Knowing this, that the trying of your faith worketh patience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.4'>But let patience have her perfect work, that ye may be perfect and complete, lacking nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.5'>If any of you lacketh wisdom, let him ask of God, who giveth to all men liberally, and upbraideth not; and it shall be given to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.6'>But let him ask in faith, nothing wavering. For he that wavereth is like a wave of the sea driven with the wind and tossed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.7'>For let not that man think that he shall receive any thing from the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.8'>A double minded man is unstable in all his ways.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.9'>Let the brother of low degree rejoice in that he is exalted: <note>rejoice: or, glory</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.10'>But the rich, in that he is made low: because as the flower of the grass he shall pass away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.11'>For the sun hath no sooner risen with a burning heat, but it withereth the grass, and its flower falleth, and the grace of its fashion perisheth: so also shall the rich man fade away in his ways.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.12'>Blessed is the man that endureth temptation: for when he is tried, he shall receive the crown of life, which the Lord hath promised to them that love him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.13'>Let no man say when he is tempted, I am tempted by God: for God cannot be tempted with evil, neither tempteth he any man: <note>evil: or, evils</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.14'>But every man is tempted, when he is drawn away by his own lust, and enticed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.15'>Then when lust hath conceived, it bringeth forth sin: and sin, when it is finished, bringeth forth death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.16'>Do not err, my beloved brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.17'>Every good gift and every perfect gift is from above, and cometh down from the Father of lights, with whom is no variableness, neither shadow of turning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.18'>Of his own will he hath begotten us with the word of truth, that we should be a kind of firstfruits of his creatures.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.19'>Therefore, my beloved brethren, let every man be swift to hear, slow to speak, slow to wrath:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.20'>For the wrath of man worketh not the righteousness of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.21'>Therefore put away all filthiness and all that remains of wickedness, and receive with meekness the engrafted word, which is able to save your souls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.22'>But be ye doers of the word, and not hearers only, deceiving your own selves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.23'>For if any is a hearer of the word, and not a doer, he is like a man beholding his natural face in a mirror:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.24'>For he beholdeth himself, and goeth away, and immediately forgetteth what manner of man he was.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.25'>But he who looketh into the perfect law of liberty, and continueth in it, he being not a forgetful hearer, but a doer of the work, this man shall be blessed in his deed. <note>deed: or, doing</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.26'>If any man among you seemeth to be religious, and bridleth not his tongue, but deceiveth his own heart, this man’s religion is vain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.27'>Pure religion and undefiled before God and the Father is this, To visit the fatherless and widows in their affliction, and to keep himself unspotted from the world.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jas.2'>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.1'>My brethren, have not the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Lord of glory, with respect of persons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.2'>For if there come into your assembly a man with a gold ring, in fine apparel, and there come in also a poor man in vile raiment; <note>assembly: Gr. synagogue</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.3'>And ye have respect to him that weareth the fine clothing, and say to him, Sit thou here in a good place; and say to the poor, Stand thou there, or sit here under my footstool: <note>in…: or, well, or, seemly</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.4'>Are ye not then partial in yourselves, and are become judges of evil thoughts?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.5'>Hearken, my beloved brethren, Hath not God chosen the poor of this world rich in faith, and heirs of the kingdom which he hath promised to them that love him? <note>of the: or, of that</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.6'>But ye have despised the poor. Do not rich men oppress you, and draw you before the judgment seats?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.7'>Do they not blaspheme that worthy name by the which ye are called? <note>blaspheme: or, revile, or, slander</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.8'>If ye fulfil the royal law according to the scripture, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself, ye do well:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.9'>But if ye have respect to persons, ye commit sin, and are convicted by the law as transgressors.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.10'>For whoever shall keep the whole law, and yet offend in one point, he is guilty of all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.11'>For he that said, Do not commit adultery, said also, Do not kill. Now if thou committest no adultery, yet if thou killest, thou art become a transgressor of the law. <note>he that: or, that law which</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.12'>So speak ye, and so do, as they that shall be judged by the law of liberty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.13'>For he shall have judgment without mercy, that hath shown no mercy; and mercy rejoiceth against judgment. <note>rejoiceth: or, glorieth</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.14'>What doth it profit, my brethren, though a man saith he hath faith, and hath not works? can faith save him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.15'>If a brother or sister is naked, and destitute of daily food,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.16'>And one of you saith to them, Depart in peace, be ye warmed and filled; but ye give them not those things which are needful to the body; what doth it profit?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.17'>Even so faith, if it hath not works, is dead, being alone. <note>alone: Gr. by itself</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.18'>But, a man may say, Thou hast faith, and I have works: show me thy faith without thy works, and I will show thee my faith by my works. <note>without: some copies read, by</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.19'>Thou believest that there is one God; thou doest well: the demons also believe, and tremble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.20'>But wilt thou know, O vain man, that faith without works is dead?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.21'>Was not Abraham our father justified by works, when he had offered Isaac his son upon the altar?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.22'>Seest thou how faith wrought with his works, and by works was faith made perfect? <note>Seest…: or, Thou seest</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.23'>And the scripture was fulfilled which saith, Abraham believed God, and it was imputed to him for righteousness: and he was called the Friend of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.24'>Ye see then that by works a man is justified, and not by faith only.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.25'>Likewise also was not Rahab the harlot justified by works, when she had received the messengers, and had sent them out another way?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.26'>For as the body without the spirit is dead, so faith without works is dead also. <note>spirit: or, breath</note></verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jas.3'>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.1'>My brethren, be not many teachers, knowing that we shall receive the greater judgment. <note>condemnation: or, judgment</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.2'>For in many things we all offend. If any man stumble not in word, the same is a perfect man, able also to bridle the whole body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.3'>Behold, we put bits in the horses’ mouths, that they may obey us; and we turn about their whole body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.4'>Behold also the ships, which though they are so great, and are driven by fierce winds, yet they are turned about with a very small helm, wherever the pilot willeth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.5'>Even so the tongue is a little member, and boasteth great things. Behold, how great a matter a little fire kindleth! <note>a matter: or, wood</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.6'>And the tongue is a fire, a world of iniquity: so is the tongue among our members, that it defileth the whole body, and setteth on fire the course of nature; and it is set on fire from hell. <note>course: Gr. wheel</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.7'>For every kind of beasts, and of birds, and of serpents, and of creatures in the sea, is tamed, and hath been tamed by mankind: <note>kind: Gr. nature</note><note>mankind: Gr. nature of man</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.8'>But the tongue can no man tame; it is an unruly evil, full of deadly poison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.9'>With it we bless God, even the Father; and with it we curse men, who are made after the similitude of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.10'>Out of the same mouth proceedeth blessing and cursing. My brethren, these things ought not so to be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.11'>Doth a fountain send forth at the same place sweet water and bitter? <note>place: or, hole</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.12'>Can the fig tree, my brethren, bear olive berries? or a vine, figs? so no fountain can yield both salt water and fresh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.13'>Who is a wise man and endued with knowledge among you? let him show by a good behaviour his works with meekness of wisdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.14'>But if ye have bitter envying and strife in your hearts, glory not, and lie not against the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.15'>This wisdom descendeth not from above, but is earthly, sensual, demonic. <note>sensual: or, natural</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.16'>For where envying and strife is, there is confusion and every evil work. <note>confusion: Gr. tumult, or, unquietness</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.17'>But the wisdom that is from above is first pure, then peaceable, gentle, and reasonable, full of mercy and good fruits, without partiality, and without hypocrisy. <note>partiality: or, wrangling</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.18'>And the fruit of righteousness is sown in peace by them that make peace.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jas.4'>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.1'>From where come wars and fightings among you? come they not from this, even from your lusts that war in your members? <note>fightings: or, brawlings</note><note>lusts: or, pleasures</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.2'>Ye lust, and have not: ye kill, and desire to have, and cannot obtain: ye fight and war, yet ye have not, because ye ask not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.3'>Ye ask, and receive not, because ye ask amiss, that ye may consume it upon your lusts. <note>lusts: or, pleasures</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.4'>Ye adulterers and adulteresses, know ye not that the friendship of the world is enmity with God? whoever therefore will be a friend of the world is the enemy of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.5'>Do ye think that the scripture saith in vain, The spirit that dwelleth in us lusteth to envy? <note>to envy: or, enviously?</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.6'>But he giveth more grace. Therefore he saith, God resisteth the proud, but giveth grace to the humble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.7'>Submit yourselves therefore to God. Resist the devil, and he will flee from you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.8'>Draw near to God, and he will draw near to you. Cleanse your hands, ye sinners; and purify your hearts, ye double minded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.9'>Be afflicted, and mourn, and weep: let your laughter be turned to mourning, and your joy to heaviness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.10'>Humble yourselves in the sight of the Lord, and he shall lift you up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.11'>Speak not evil one of another, brethren. He that speaketh evil of his brother, and judgeth his brother, speaketh evil of the law, and judgeth the law: but if thou judgest the law, thou art not a doer of the law, but a judge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.12'>There is one lawgiver, who is able to save and to destroy: who art thou that judgest another?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.13'>Come now, ye that say, To day or to morrow we will go into such a city, and continue there a year, and buy and sell, and get gain:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.14'>Though ye know not what shall be to morrow. For what is your life? It is even a vapour, that appeareth for a little time, and then vanisheth away. <note>It…: or, For it is</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.15'>Instead of that ye ought to say, If the Lord will, we shall live, and do this, or that.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.16'>But now ye rejoice in your boastings: all such rejoicing is evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.17'>Therefore to him that knoweth to do good, and doeth it not, to him it is sin.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jas.5'>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.1'>Come now, ye rich men, weep and wail for your miseries that shall come upon you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.2'>Your riches are corrupted, and your garments are motheaten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.3'>Your gold and silver is rusted; and its rust shall be a witness against you, and shall eat your flesh as it were fire. Ye have heaped up treasure for the last days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.4'>Behold, the hire of the labourers who have reaped your fields, which is by you kept back by fraud, crieth: and the cries of them who have reaped have entered into the ears of the Lord of Hosts. <note>sabaoth: Heb. hosts</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.5'>Ye have lived in pleasure on the earth, and been wanton; ye have nourished your hearts, as in a day of slaughter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.6'>Ye have condemned and killed the just; and he doth not resist you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.7'>Be patient therefore, brethren, until the coming of the Lord. Behold, the farmer waiteth for the precious fruit of the earth, and hath long patience for it, until he receiveth the early and the latter rain. <note>Be…: or, Be long patient, or, Suffer with long patience</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.8'>Be ye also patient; establish your hearts: for the coming of the Lord draweth near.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.9'>Murmur not one against another, brethren, lest ye be condemned: behold, the judge standeth before the door. <note>Grudge not: or, Groan, or, Grieve not</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.10'>Take, my brethren, the prophets, who have spoken in the name of the Lord, for an example of suffering affliction, and of patience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.11'>Behold, we count them happy who endure. Ye have heard of the patience of Job, and have seen the end of the Lord; that the Lord is very pitiful, and of tender mercy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.12'>But above all things, my brethren, swear not, neither by heaven, neither by the earth, neither by any other oath: but let your yea be yea; and your nay, nay; lest ye fall into condemnation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.13'>Is any among you afflicted? let him pray. Is any cheerful? let him sing psalms.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.14'>Is any sick among you? let him call for the elders of the church; and let them pray over him, anointing him with oil in the name of the Lord:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.15'>And the prayer of faith shall save the sick, and the Lord shall raise him up; and if he hath committed sins, they shall be forgiven him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.16'>Confess your faults one to another, and pray one for another, that ye may be healed. The effectual fervent prayer of the righteous man availeth much.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.17'>Elijah was a man subject to like passions as we are, and he prayed earnestly that it might not rain: and it rained not on the earth by the space of three years and six months. <note>subject…: of the same nature, that is, a fellow mortal</note><note>earnestly: or, in his prayer</note></verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.18'>And he prayed again, and the heaven gave rain, and the earth brought forth its fruit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.19'>Brethren, if any one of you should err from the truth, and one should convert him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.20'>Let him know, that he who converteth a sinner from the error of his way shall save a soul from death, and shall hide a multitude of sins.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>