<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisIDWork='OEB' osisRefWork='Bible' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2012-08-08</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='OEB'>
        <title>Open English Bible (US Spelling)</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Mod2Zef (7)</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject/>
        <date>2012-08-08</date>
        <description>The Open English Bible is the anticipated end product of a project intended to create an English translation of the Bible that is:   under a licence enabling the maximum reuse, remixing and sharing without requiring the payment of royalties or the obtaining of permission from copyright holders; and a translation reflecting modern English usage and Biblical scholarship.   The OEB is being formed by editing the public domain Twentieth Century New Testament, which was a new translation of the New Testament published in the early twentieth century, based on the Greek text of Westcott and Hort.   As such, the OEB as a translation does not stand within the Tyndale tradition but has a separate tradition in a similar manner to the NIV and New English Bible.    Our website is at http://openenglishbible.org</description>
        <publisher/>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>OEB</identifier>
        <source>http://openenglishbible.org/</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>Creative Commons: CC0</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Jas'>
      <chapter osisID='Jas.1'>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.1'>James, a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ, greets the twelve tribes that are living abroad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.2'>My friends, whatever may be the temptations that beset you from time to time, always regard them as a reason for rejoicing,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.3'>knowing, as you do, that the testing of your faith develops endurance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.4'>And let endurance do its work perfectly, so that you may be altogether perfect, and in no respect deficient.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.5'>If one of you is deficient in wisdom, let them ask wisdom from the God who gives freely to everyone without reproaches, and it will be given to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.6'>But let them ask with confidence, never doubting; for the person who doubts is like a wave of the sea driven here and there at the mercy of the wind —</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.7'>Such a person must not expect that they will receive anything from the Lord,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.8'>vacillating as they are, irresolute at every turn.  [crosswire  amateurish codings versifikation may be wrong here ]</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.9'>Let a follower in humble circumstances be proud of their exalted position, but a rich follower of their humiliation;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.10'>for the rich will pass away ‘like the flower of the grass.’</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.11'>As the sun rises, and the hot wind blows, ‘the grass withers, its flower fades,’ and all its beauty is gone. So is it with the rich . In the midst of their pursuits they will come to an untimely end.  [crosswire  amateurish codings versifikation may be wrong here ]</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.12'>Blessed is the person who remains firm under temptation, for, when they have stood the test, they will receive the crown of life, which the Lord has promised to those who love him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.13'>Let no one say, when they are tempted, “It is God who is tempting me!” For God, who cannot be tempted to do wrong, does not himself tempt anyone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.14'>A person is in every case tempted by their own passions — allured and enticed by them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.15'>Then passion conceives and gives birth to sin, and sin, on reaching maturity, brings forth death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.16'>Do not be deceived, my dear friends.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.17'>Every good thing given us, and every perfect gift, is from above, and comes down to us from the Maker of the lights in the heavens, who is himself never subject to change or to eclipse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.18'>Because he so willed, he gave us life, through the message of the truth, so that we should be, as it were, an earnest of still further creations.  [crosswire  amateurish codings versifikation may be wrong here ]</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.19'>Mark this, my dear friends — Let everyone be quick to listen, slow to speak, and slow to get angry;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.20'>for human anger does not forward the righteous purpose of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.21'>Therefore, have done with all filthiness and whatever wickedness still remains, and in a humble spirit receive that message which has been planted in your hearts and is able to save your souls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.22'>Put that message into practice, and do not merely listen to it — deceiving yourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.23'>For, when anyone listens to it and does not practice it, they like a person looking at their own face in a mirror.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.24'>They look at themselves, then go on their way,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.25'>but the person who looks carefully into the perfect law, the law of freedom, and continues to do so, not listening to it and then forgetting it, but putting it into practice — that person will be blessed in what they do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.26'>When a person appears to be religious, yet does not bridle their tongue, but imposes on their own conscience, that person’s religious observances are valueless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.1.27'>That religious observance which is pure and spotless in the eyes of God our Father is this — to visit orphans and widows in their trouble, and to keep oneself uncontaminated by the world.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jas.2'>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.1'>My friends, are you really trying to combine faith in Jesus Christ, our glorified Lord, with the worship of rank?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.2'>Suppose a visitor should enter your synagogue, with gold rings and in grand clothes, and suppose a poor man should come in also, in shabby clothes,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.3'>and you are deferential to the visitor who is wearing grand clothes, and say — “There is a good seat for you here,” but to the poor man — “You must stand; or sit down there by my footstool,”</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.4'>Is not that to make distinctions among yourselves, and show yourselves prejudiced judges?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.5'>Listen, my dear friends. Has not God chosen those who are poor in the things of this world to be rich through their faith, and to possess the kingdom which he has promised to those who love him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.6'>But you — you insult the poor man! Is not it the rich who oppress you? Is not it they who drag you into law courts?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.7'>Is not it they who malign that honorable name which has been bestowed on you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.8'>Yet, if you keep the royal law which runs — ‘You must love your neighbor as you love yourself,’ you are doing right;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.9'>but, if you worship rank, you commit a sin, and stand convicted by that same law of being offenders against it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.10'>For a person who has laid the law, as a whole, to heart, but has failed in one particular, is accountable for breaking all its provisions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.11'>He who said ‘You must not commit adultery’ also said ‘You must not murder.’ If, then, you commit murder but not adultery, you are still an offender against the law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.12'>Therefore, speak and act as people who are to be judged by the ‘law of freedom.’</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.13'>For there will be justice without mercy for the person who has not acted mercifully. Mercy triumphs over Justice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.14'>My friends, what is the good of a person’s saying that they have faith, if they do not prove it by actions? Can such faith save them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.15'>Suppose some brother or sister should be in need of clothes and of daily bread,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.16'>and one of you were to say to them — “Go, and peace be with you; find warmth and food for yourselves,” and yet you were not to give them the necessaries of life, what good would it be to them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.17'>In just the same way faith, if not followed by actions, is, by itself, a lifeless thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.18'>Some one, indeed, may say — “You are a man of faith, and I am a man of action.” [crosswire  amateurish codings versifikation may be wrong here ] “Then show me your faith,” I reply, “apart from any actions, and I will show you my faith by my actions.”</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.19'>It is a part of your faith, is it not, that there is one God? Good; yet even the demons have that faith, and tremble at the thought.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.20'>Now do you really want to understand, fool, how it is that faith without actions leads to nothing?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.21'>Look at our ancestor, Abraham. Was not it the result of his actions that he was pronounced righteous after he had offered his son, Isaac, on the altar?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.22'>You see how, in his case, faith and actions went together; that his faith was perfected as the result of his actions;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.23'>and that in this way the words of scripture came true — “Abraham believed God, and that was regarded by God as righteousness,” and “He was called the friend of God.”</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.24'>You see, then, that it is as the result of their actions that a person is pronounced righteous, and not of their faith only.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.25'>Was not it the same with the prostitute, Rahab? Was not it as the result of her actions that she was pronounced righteous, after she had welcomed the messengers and helped them escape by?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.2.26'>Exactly as a body is dead without a spirit, so faith is dead without actions.  [crosswire  amateurish codings versifikation may be wrong here ]</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jas.3'>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.1'>I do not want many of you, my friends, to become teachers, knowing, as you do, that we who teach will be judged by a more severe standard than others.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.2'>We often make mistakes, every one of us. Anyone who does not make mistakes when speaking is indeed a perfect person, able to bridle their whole body as well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.3'>When we put bits into horses’ mouths, to make them obey us, we control the rest of their bodies so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.4'>Again, think of ships. Large as they are, and even when driven by fierce winds, they are controlled by a very small rudder and steered in whatever direction the man at the helm may determine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.5'>So is it with the tongue. Small as it is, it is a great boaster. Think how tiny a spark may set the largest forest ablaze!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.6'>And the tongue is like a spark. Among the members of our body it proves itself a world of mischief; it contaminates the whole body; it sets the wheels of life on fire, and is itself set on fire by the flames of Gehenna.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.7'>For while all sorts of beasts and birds, and of reptiles and creatures in the sea, are tameable, and actually have been tamed by man,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.8'>no human being can tame the tongue. It is a restless plague! It is charged with deadly poison!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.9'>With it we bless our Lord and Father, and with it we curse people who are made ‘in God’s likeness.’</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.10'>From the very same mouth come blessings and curses! My friends, it is not right that this should be so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.11'>Does a spring give both good and bad water from the same source?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.12'>Can a fig tree, my friends, bear olives? Or a vine bear figs? No, nor can a brackish well give good water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.13'>Who among you claims to be wise and intelligent? Let them show that their actions are the outcome of a good life lived in the humility of true wisdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.14'>But, while you harbor envy and bitterness and a spirit of rivalry in your hearts, do not boast or lie to the detriment of the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.15'>That is not the wisdom which comes from above; no, it is earthly, animal, devilish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.16'>For, where envy and rivalry exist, there you will also find disorder and all kinds of base actions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.17'>But the wisdom from above is, before every thing else, pure; then peace-loving, gentle, open to conviction, rich in compassion and good deeds, and free from partiality and insincerity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.3.18'>And righteousness, its fruit, is sown in peace by those who work for peace.  [crosswire  amateurish codings versifikation may be wrong here ]</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jas.4'>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.1'>What is the cause of the fighting and quarreling that goes on among you? Is not it to be found in the desires which are always at war within you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.2'>You crave, yet do not obtain. You murder and rage, yet cannot gain your end. You quarrel and fight. You do not obtain, because you do not ask.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.3'>You ask, yet do not receive, because you ask for a wrong purpose — to spend what you get on your pleasures.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.4'>Unfaithful people! Do not you know that to be friends with the world means to be at enmity with God? Therefore whoever chooses to be friends with the world makes himself an enemy to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.5'>Do you suppose there is no meaning in the passage of scripture which asks — ‘Is envy to result from the longings of the Spirit which God has implanted within you?’</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.6'>No; the gift that God gives is for a nobler end; and that is why it is said — ‘God is opposed to the haughty, but gives help to the humble.’</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.7'>Therefore submit to God; but resist the devil, and he will flee from you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.8'>Draw near to God, and he will draw near to you. Make your hands clean, you sinners; and your hearts pure, you vacillator!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.9'>Grieve, mourn, and lament! Let your laughter be turned to mourning, and your happiness to gloom!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.10'>Humble yourselves before the Lord, and he will exalt you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.11'>Do not disparage one another, friends. The person who disparages others, or passes judgment on them, disparages the law and passes judgment on the law. But, if you pass judgment on the law, you are not obeying it, but judging it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.12'>There is only one lawgiver and judge — he who has the power both to save and to destroy. But who are you that pass judgment on your neighbor?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.13'>Listen to me, you who say ‘Today or tomorrow we will go to such and such a town, spend a year there, and trade, and make money,’</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.14'>And yet you do not know what your life will be like tomorrow! For you are but a mist appearing for a little while and then disappearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.15'>You ought, rather, to say ‘If the Lord wills, we will live and do this or that.’</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.16'>But, as it is, you are constantly boasting presumptuously! All such boasting is wicked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.4.17'>The person, then, who knows what is right but fails to do it — that is sin in them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Jas.5'>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.1'>Listen to me, you rich people, weep and wail for the miseries that are coming upon you!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.2'>Your riches have wasted away, and your clothes have become moth-eaten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.3'>Your gold and silver are rusted; and the rust on them will be evidence against you, and will eat into your flesh. It was fire, so to speak, that you stored up for yourselves in these last days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.4'>I tell you, the wages of the laborers who mowed your fields, which you have been fraudulently keeping back, are crying out against you, and the outcries of your reapers have reached the ears of the Lord of Hosts!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.5'>You have lived on earth a life of extravagance and luxury; you have indulged your fancies in a time of bloodshed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.6'>You have condemned, you have murdered, the righteous one! Must not God be opposed to you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.7'>Be patient, then, friends, until the coming of the Lord. Even the farmer has to wait for the precious fruit of the earth, watching over it patiently, until it has had the spring and summer rains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.8'>And you must be patient also, and not be discouraged; for the Lord’s coming is near.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.9'>Do not make complaints against one another, friends, or judgment will be passed on you. The judge is already standing at the door!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.10'>Friends, as an example of the patient endurance of suffering, take the prophets who spoke in the name of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.11'>We count those who displayed such endurance blessed! You have heard, too, of Job’s endurance, and have seen what the Lord’s purpose was, for ‘the Lord is full of pity and compassion.’</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.12'>Above all things, my friends, never take an oath, either by heaven, or by earth, or by anything else. With you let ‘Yes’ suffice for yes, and ‘No’ for no, so that you may escape condemnation.  [crosswire  amateurish codings versifikation may be wrong here ]</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.13'>If any of you is in trouble, let them pray; if anyone is happy, let them sing hymns.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.14'>If anyone of you is ill, let him send for the officers of the church, and let them pray over them, after anointing them with oil in the name of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.15'>The prayer offered in faith will save the person who is sick, and the Lord will raise them from their bed; and if they have committed sins, they will be forgiven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.16'>Therefore, confess your sins to one another and pray for one another, so that you may be cured. Great is the power of a good person’s fervent prayer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.17'>Elijah was only human like ourselves, but, when he prayed fervently that it might not rain, no rain fell on the land for three years and a half.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.18'>And, when he prayed again, the clouds brought rain, and the land bore crops.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.19'>My friends, should one of you be led astray from the truth, and someone bring them back again,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jas.5.20'>be sure that the person who brings a sinner back from their mistaken ways will save that person’s soul from death, and throw a veil over countless sins.  [crosswire  amateurish codings versifikation may be wrong here ]</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>