<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='WEB' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='WEB'>
        <title>World English Bible</title>
        <contributor>Rainbow Missions  PO BOX 1151  LONGMONT CO 80502-1151  USA</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>The WEB Bible as it might apear by the name is being translated specifically for the purpose of being distrubuted over the WEB.</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBEL SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>WEB</identifier>
        <source>ftp://unboundftp.biola.edu/pub/web.zip</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div osisID='John' type='book'>
      <chapter osisID='John.1'>
        <verse osisID='John.1.1'>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.2'>The same was in the beginning with God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.3'>All things were made through him. Without him was not anything made that has been made.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.4'>In him was life, and the life was the light of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.5'>The light shines in the darkness, and the darkness hasn`t overcome it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.6'>There came a man, sent from God, whose name was John.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.7'>The same came as a witness, that he might testify about the light, that all might believe through him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.8'>He was not the light, but was sent that he might testify about the light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.9'>The true light that enlightens everyone was coming into the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.10'>He was in the world, and the world was made through him, and the world didn`t recognize him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.11'>He came to his own, and those who were his own didn`t receive him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.12'>But as many as received him, to them he gave the right to become God`s children, to those who believe in his name:</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.13'>who were born, not of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.14'>The Word became flesh, and lived among us. We saw his glory, such glory as of the only Son of the Father, full of grace and truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.15'>John testified about him. He cried out, saying, "This was he of whom I said, `He who comes after me has surpassed me, for he was before me.`"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.16'>From his fullness we all received grace upon grace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.17'>For the law was given through Moses. Grace and truth came through Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.18'>No one has seen God at any time. The only conceived Son, who is in the bosom of the Father, he has declared him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.19'>This is John`s testimony, when the Jews sent priests and Levites from Jerusalem to ask him, "Who are you?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.20'>He confessed, and didn`t deny, but he confessed, "I am not the Christ."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.21'>They asked him, "What then? Are you Elijah?"     He said, "I am not."     "Are you the prophet?"     He answered, "No."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.22'>They said therefore to him, "Who are you? Give us an answer to take back to those who sent us. What do you say about yourself?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.23'>He said, "I am the voice of one crying in the wilderness, `Make straight the way of the Lord,` as Isaiah the prophet said."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.24'>The ones who had been sent were from the Pharisees.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.25'>They asked him, "Why then do you baptize, if you are not the Christ, nor Elijah, nor the Prophet?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.26'>John answered them, "I baptize in water, but among you stands one whom you don`t know,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.27'>he who comes after me, whose sandal strap I`m not worthy to untie."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.28'>These things were done in Bethany beyond the Jordan, where John was baptizing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.29'>On the next day, he saw Jesus coming to him, and said, "Behold, the Lamb of God, who takes away the sin of the world!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.30'>This is he of whom I said, `After me comes a man who is preferred before me, for he was before me.`</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.31'>I didn`t know him, but for this reason I came baptizing in water: that he would be revealed to Israel."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.32'>John testified, saying, "I have seen the Spirit descending like a dove out of heaven, and it remained on him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.33'>I didn`t recognize him, but he who sent me to baptize in water, he said to me, `On whoever you will see the Spirit descending, and remaining on him, the same is he who baptizes in the Holy Spirit.`</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.34'>I have seen, and have testified that this is the Son of God."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.35'>Again, on the next day, John was standing with two of his disciples,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.36'>and he looked at Jesus as he walked, and said, "Behold, the Lamb of God!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.37'>The two disciples heard him speak, and they followed Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.38'>Jesus turned, and saw them following, and said to them, "What are you looking for?"     They said to him, "Rabbi" (which is to say, being interpreted, Teacher), "where are you staying?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.39'>He said to them, "Come, and see."     They came and saw where he was staying, and they stayed with him that day. It was about the tenth hour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.40'>One of the two who heard John, and followed him, was Andrew, Simon Peter`s brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.41'>He first found his own brother, Simon, and said to him, "We have found the Messiah!" (which is, being interpreted, Christ).</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.42'>He brought him to Jesus. Jesus looked at him, and said, "You are Simon the son of Jonah. You shall be called Cephas" (which is by interpretation, Peter).</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.43'>On the next day, he was determined to go forth into Galilee, and he found Philip. Jesus said to him, "Follow me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.44'>Now Philip was from Bethsaida, of the city of Andrew and Peter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.45'>Philip found Nathanael, and said to him, "We have found him, of whom Moses in the law, and the prophets, wrote: Jesus of Nazareth, the son of Joseph."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.46'>Nathanael said to him, "Can any good thing come out of Nazareth?"     Philip said to him, "Come and see."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.47'>Jesus saw Nathanael coming to him, and said about him, "Behold, an Israelite indeed, in whom is no deceit!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.48'>Nathanael says to him, "How do you know me?"     Jesus answered him, "Before Philip called you, when you were under the fig tree, I saw you."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.49'>Nathanael answered him, "Rabbi, you are the Son of God! You are King of Israel!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.50'>Jesus answered him, "Because I told you, `I saw you underneath the fig tree,` do you believe? You will see greater things than these."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.51'>He said to him, "Most assuredly, I tell you, hereafter you will see heaven opened, and the angels of God ascending and descending on the Son of Man."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.2'>
        <verse osisID='John.2.1'>The third day, there was a marriage in Cana of Galilee. Jesus` mother was there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.2'>Jesus also was invited, with his disciples, to the marriage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.3'>When the wine ran out, Jesus` Mother said to him, "They have no wine."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.4'>Jesus said to her, "Woman, what does that have to do with you and me? My hour has not yet come."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.5'>His mother said to the servants, "Whatever he says to you, do it."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.6'>Now there were six water pots of stone set there after the Jews` manner of purifying, containing two or three metretes apiece.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.7'>Jesus said to them, "Fill the water pots with water." They filled them up to the brim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.8'>He said to them, "Now draw some out, and take it to the ruler of the feast." They took it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.9'>When the ruler of the feast tasted the water now become wine, and didn`t know where it came from (but the servants who had drawn the water knew), the ruler of the feast called the bridegroom,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.10'>and said to him, "Everyone serves the good wine first, and when the guests have drunk freely, then that which is worse. You have kept the good wine until now!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.11'>This beginning of his signs Jesus did in Cana of Galilee, and revealed his glory. His disciples believed in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.12'>After this, he went down to Capernaum, he, and his mother, his brothers, and his disciples; and there they stayed not many days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.13'>The Passover of the Jews was at hand, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.14'>He found in the temple those who sold oxen, sheep, and doves, and the changers of money sitting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.15'>He made a whip of cords, and threw all out of the temple, both the sheep and the oxen; and he poured out the changers` money, and overthrew their tables.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.16'>To those who sold the doves, he said, "Take these things out of here! Don`t make my Father`s house a marketplace!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.17'>His disciples remembered that it was written, "Zeal for your house will eat me up."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.18'>The Jews therefore answered him, "What sign do you show to us, seeing that you do these things?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.19'>Jesus answered them, "Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.20'>The Jews therefore said, "Forty-six years was this temple in building, and will you raise it up in three days?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.21'>But he spoke of the temple of his body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.22'>When therefore he was raised from the dead, his disciples remembered that he said this, and they believed the scripture, and the word which Jesus had said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.23'>Now when he was in Jerusalem at the Passover, during the feast, many believed in his name, observing his signs which he did.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.24'>But Jesus didn`t trust himself to them, because he knew all people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.25'>and because he didn`t need for anyone to testify concerning man; for he himself knew what was in man.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.3'>
        <verse osisID='John.3.1'>Now there was a man of the Pharisees named Nicodemus, a ruler of the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.2'>The same came to him by night, and said to him, "Rabbi, we know that you are a teacher come from God, for no one can do these signs that you do, unless God is with him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.3'>Jesus answered him, "Most assuredly, I tell you, unless one is born anew, he can`t see the kingdom of God."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.4'>Nicodemus said to him, "How can a man be born when he is old? Can he enter a second time into his mother`s womb, and be born?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.5'>Jesus answered, "Most assuredly I tell you, unless one is born of water and the Spirit, he can`t enter into the kingdom of God!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.6'>That which is born of the flesh is flesh. That which is born of the Spirit is spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.7'>Don`t marvel that I said to you, `You must be born anew.`</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.8'>The wind blows where it wants to, and you hear its sound, but don`t know where it comes from and where it is going. So is everyone who is born of the Spirit."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.9'>Nicodemus answered him, "How can these things be?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.10'>Jesus answered him, "Are you the teacher of Israel, and don`t understand these things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.11'>Most assuredly I tell you, we speak that which we know, and testify of that which we have seen, and you don`t receive our witness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.12'>If I told you earthly things and you don`t believe, how will you believe if I tell you heavenly things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.13'>No one has ascended into heaven, but he who descended out of heaven, the Son of Man, who is in heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.14'>As Moses lifted up the serpent in the wilderness, even so must the Son of Man be lifted up,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.15'>that whoever believes in him should not perish, but have eternal life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.16'>For God so loved the world, that he gave his one and only Son, that whoever believes in him should not perish, but have eternal life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.17'>For God didn`t send his Son into the world to judge the world, but that the world should be saved through him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.18'>He who believes in him is not judged. He who doesn`t believe has been judged already, because he has not believed in the name of the only born Son of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.19'>This is the judgment, that the light has come into the world, and men loved the darkness rather than the light; for their works were evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.20'>For everyone who does evil hates the light, and doesn`t come to the light, for fear that his works would be reproved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.21'>But he who does the truth comes to the light, that his works may be revealed, that they have been done with God."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.22'>After these things, Jesus came with his disciples into the land of Judea. He stayed there with them, and baptized.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.23'>John also was baptizing in Enon near Salim, because there was much water there. They came, and were baptized.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.24'>For John was not yet thrown into prison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.25'>There arose therefore a questioning on the part of John`s disciples with some Jews about purification.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.26'>They came to John, and said to him, "Rabbi, he who was with you beyond the Jordan, to whom you have testified, behold, the same baptizes, and all men come to him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.27'>John answered, "A man can receive nothing, unless it has been given him from heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.28'>You yourselves testify about me, that I said, `I am not the Christ,` but, `I have been sent before him.`</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.29'>He who has the bride is the bridegroom; but the friend of the bridegroom, who stands and hears him, rejoices greatly because of the bridegroom`s voice. This, my joy, therefore is made full.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.30'>He must increase, but I must decrease.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.31'>He who comes from above is above all. He who is from the Earth belongs to the Earth, and speaks of the Earth. He who comes from heaven is above all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.32'>What he has seen and heard, of that he testifies; and no one receives his witness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.33'>He who has received his witness has set his seal to this, that God is true.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.34'>For he whom God has sent speaks the words of God; for God gives the Spirit without measure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.35'>The Father loves the Son, and has given all things into his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.36'>He who believes in the Son has eternal life, but he who disobeys the Son won`t see life, but the wrath of God remains on him."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.4'>
        <verse osisID='John.4.1'>Therefore when the Lord knew that the Pharisees had heard that Jesus was making and baptizing more disciples than John</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.2'>(although Jesus himself didn`t baptize, but his disciples),</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.3'>he left Judea, and departed again into Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.4'>He needed to pass through Samaria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.5'>So he came to a city of Samaria, called Sychar, near the parcel of ground that Jacob gave to his son, Joseph.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.6'>Jacob`s well was there. Jesus therefore, being tired from his journey, sat down by the well. It was about the sixth hour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.7'>A woman of Samaria came to draw water. Jesus said to her, "Give me a drink."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.8'>For his disciples had gone away into the city to buy food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.9'>The Samaritan woman therefore said to him, "How is it that you, being a Jew, ask for a drink from me, a Samaritan woman?" (For Jews have no dealings with Samaritans.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.10'>Jesus answered her, "If you knew the gift of God, and who it is who says to you, `Give me a drink,` you would have asked him, and he would have given you living water."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.11'>The woman said to him, "Sir, you have nothing to draw with, and the well is deep. From where then have you that living water?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.12'>Are you greater than our father, Jacob, who gave us the well, and drank of it himself, as did his sons, and his cattle?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.13'>Jesus answered her, "Everyone who drinks of this water will thirst again,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.14'>but whoever drinks of the water that I will give him will never thirst; but the water that I will give him will become in him a well of water springing up to eternal life."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.15'>The woman said to him, "Sir, give me this water, so that I don`t get thirsty, neither come all the way here to draw."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.16'>Jesus said to her, "Go, call your husband, and come here."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.17'>The woman answered, "I have no husband."     Jesus said to her, "You said well, `I have no husband,`</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.18'>for you have had five husbands; and he whom you now have is not your husband. This you have said truly."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.19'>The woman said to him, "Sir, I perceive that you are a prophet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.20'>Our fathers worshipped in this mountain, and you Jews say that in Jerusalem is the place where people ought to worship."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.21'>Jesus said to her, "Woman, believe me, the hour comes, when neither in this mountain, nor in Jerusalem, will you worship the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.22'>You worship that which you don`t know. We worship that which we know; for salvation is from the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.23'>But the hour comes, and now is, when the true worshippers will worship the Father in spirit and truth, for the Father seeks such to be his worshippers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.24'>God is a Spirit, and those who worship him must worship in spirit and truth."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.25'>The woman said to him, "I know that Messiah comes," (he who is called Christ). "When he has come, he will declare to us all things."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.26'>Jesus said to her, "I who speak to you am he."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.27'>At this, his disciples came. They marveled that he was speaking with a woman; yet no one said, "What are you looking for?" or, "Why do you speak with her?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.28'>So the woman left her water pot, and went away into the city, and said to the people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.29'>"Come, see a man who told me everything that I did. Can this be the Christ?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.30'>They went out of the city, and were coming to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.31'>In the meanwhile, the disciples urged him, saying, "Rabbi, eat."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.32'>But he said to them, "I have food to eat that you don`t know about."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.33'>The disciples therefore said one to another, "Has anyone brought him something to eat?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.34'>Jesus said to them, "My food is to do the will of him who sent me, and to accomplish his work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.35'>Don`t you say, `There are yet four months until the harvest?` Behold, I tell you, lift up your eyes, and look at the fields, that they are white already to harvest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.36'>He who reaps receives wages, and gathers fruit to eternal life; that both he who sows and he who reaps may rejoice together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.37'>For in this the saying is true, `One sows, and another reaps.`</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.38'>I sent you to reap that for which you haven`t labored. Others have labored, and you have entered into their labor."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.39'>From that city many of the Samaritans believed in him because of the word of the woman, who testified, `He told me everything that I did."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.40'>So when the Samaritans came to him, they begged him to stay with them. He stayed there two days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.41'>Many more believed because of his word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.42'>They said to the woman, "Now we believe, not because of your speaking; for we have heard for ourselves, and know that this is indeed the Christ, the Savior of the world."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.43'>After the two days he went forth from there and went into Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.44'>For Jesus himself testified that a prophet has no honor in his own country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.45'>So when he came into Galilee, the Galilaeans received him, having seen all the things that he did in Jerusalem at the feast, for they also went to the feast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.46'>He came therefore again to Cana of Galilee, where he made the water into wine. There was a certain nobleman whose son was sick at Capernaum.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.47'>When he heard that Jesus had come out of Judea into Galilee, he went to him, and begged him that he would come down and heal his son, for he was at the point of death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.48'>Jesus therefore said to him, "Unless you see signs and wonders, you will in no way believe."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.49'>The nobleman said to him, "Sir, come down before my child dies."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.50'>Jesus said to him, "Go your way. Your son lives." The man believed the word that Jesus spoke to him, and he went his way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.51'>As he was now going down, his servants met him and reported, saying "your child lives!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.52'>So he inquired of them the hour when he began to get better. They said therefore to him, "Yesterday at the seventh hour, the fever left him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.53'>So the father knew that it was at that hour in which Jesus said to him, "Your son lives." He believed, as did his whole house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.54'>This is again the second sign that Jesus did, having come out of Judea into Galilee.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.5'>
        <verse osisID='John.5.1'>After these things, there was a feast of the Jews, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.2'>Now in Jerusalem by the sheep gate, there is a pool, which is called in Hebrew, "Bethesda," having five porches.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.3'>In these lay a great multitude of those who were sick, blind, lame, or paralyzed, waiting for the moving of the water;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.4'>for an angel of the Lord went down at certain times into the pool, and stirred up the water. Whoever stepped in first after the stirring of the water was made whole of whatever disease he was afflicted with.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.5'>A certain man was there, who had been sick for thirty-eight years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.6'>When Jesus saw him lying there, and knew that he had been sick for a long time, he asked him, "Do you want to be made well?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.7'>The sick man answered him, "Sir, I have no one to put me into the pool when the water is stirred up, but while I`m coming, another steps down before me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.8'>Jesus said to him, "Arise, take up your mat, and walk."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.9'>Immediately, the man was made well, and took up his mat and walked.     Now it was the Sabbath on that day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.10'>So the Jews said to him who was cured, "It is the Sabbath. It is not lawful for you to carry your mat."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.11'>He answered them, "He who made me well, the same said to me, `Take up your mat, and walk.`"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.12'>Then they asked him, "Who is the man who said to you, `Take up your mat, and walk`?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.13'>But he who was healed didn`t know who it was, for Jesus had withdrawn, a crowd being in the place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.14'>Afterward Jesus found him in the temple, and said to him, "Behold, you are made well. Sin no more, so that nothing worse happens to you."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.15'>The man went away, and told the Jews that it was Jesus who had made him well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.16'>For this cause the Jews persecuted Jesus, and sought to kill him, because he did these things on the Sabbath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.17'>But Jesus answered them, "My Father is still working, so I am working, too."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.18'>For this cause therefore the Jews sought the more to kill him, because he not only broke the Sabbath, but also called God his own Father, making himself equal with God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.19'>Jesus therefore answered them, "Most assuredly, I tell you, the Son can do nothing of himself, but what he sees the Father doing. For whatever things he does, these the Son also does likewise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.20'>For the Father loves the Son, and shows him all things that he himself does. He will show him greater works than these, that you may marvel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.21'>For as the Father raises the dead and gives them life, even so the Son also gives life to whom he desires.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.22'>For neither does the Father judge any man, but he has given all judgment to the Son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.23'>that all may honor the Son, even as they honor the Father. He who doesn`t honor the Son doesn`t honor the Father who sent him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.24'>Most assuredly I tell you, he who hears my word, and believes him who sent me, has eternal life, and doesn`t come into judgment, but has passed out of death into life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.25'>Most assuredly, I tell you, the hour comes, and now is, when the dead will hear the Son of God`s voice; and those who hear will live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.26'>For as the Father has life in himself, even so he gave to the Son also to have life in himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.27'>He also gave him authority to execute judgment, because he is a son of man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.28'>Don`t marvel at this, for the hour comes, in which all that are in the tombs will hear his voice,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.29'>and will come forth; those who have done good, to the resurrection of life; and those who have done evil, to the resurrection of judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.30'>I can of myself do nothing. As I hear, I judge, and my judgment is righteous; because I don`t seek my own will, but the will of my Father who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.31'>"If I testify about myself, my witness is not valid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.32'>It is another who testifies about me. I know that the testimony which he testifies about me is true.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.33'>You have sent to John, and he has testified to the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.34'>But the testimony which I receive is not from man. However, I say these things that you may be saved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.35'>He was the lamp that burns and shines, and you were willing to rejoice for a while in his light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.36'>But the testimony which I have is greater than that of John, for the works which the Father has given me to accomplish, the very works that I do, testify about me, that the Father has sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.37'>The Father himself, who sent me, has testified about me. You have neither heard his voice at any time, nor seen his form.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.38'>You don`t have his word living in you; for whom he sent, him you don`t believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.39'>You search the scriptures, because you think that in them you have eternal life; and these are they which testify about me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.40'>Yet you will not come to me, that you may have life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.41'>I don`t receive glory from men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.42'>But I know you, that you don`t have God`s love in yourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.43'>I have come in my Father`s name, and you don`t receive me. If another comes in his own name, you will receive him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.44'>How can you believe, who receive glory from one another, and you don`t seek the glory that comes from the only God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.45'>"Don`t think that I will accuse you to the Father. There is one who accuses you, even Moses, on whom you have set your hope.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.46'>For if you believed Moses, you would believe me; for he wrote about me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.47'>But if you don`t believe his writings, how will you believe my words?"</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.6'>
        <verse osisID='John.6.1'>After these things, Jesus went away to the other side of the sea of Galilee, which is also called the Sea of Tiberias.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.2'>A great multitude followed him, because they saw the signs which he did on those who were sick.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.3'>Jesus went up into the mountain, and he sat there with his disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.4'>Now the Passover, the feast of the Jews, was at hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.5'>Jesus therefore lifting up his eyes, and seeing that a great multitude was coming to him, said to Philip, "Where are we to buy bread, that these may eat?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.6'>This he said to test him, for he himself knew what he would do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.7'>Philip answered him, "Two hundred denarii worth of bread is not sufficient for them, that everyone of them may receive a little."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.8'>One of his disciples, Andrew, Simon Peter`s brother, said to him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.9'>"There is a boy here who has five barley loaves and two fish, but what are these among so many?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.10'>Jesus said, "Have the people sit down." Now there was much grass in that place. So the men sat down, in number about five thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.11'>Jesus took the loaves; and having given thanks, he distributed to the disciples, and the disciples to those who were sitting down; likewise also of the fish as much as they desired.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.12'>When they were filled, he said to his disciples, "Gather up the broken pieces which are left over, that nothing be lost."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.13'>So they gathered them up, and filled twelve baskets with broken pieces from the five barley loaves, which were left over by those who had eaten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.14'>When therefore the people saw the sign which Jesus did, they said, "This is truly the prophet who comes into the world."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.15'>Jesus therefore, perceiving that they were about to come and take him by force, to make him king, withdrew again into the mountain by himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.16'>When evening came, his disciples went down to the sea,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.17'>and they entered into the boat, and were going over the sea to Capernaum. It was now dark, and Jesus had not come to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.18'>The sea was rising by reason of a great wind that blew.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.19'>When therefore they had rowed about twenty-five or thirty stadia, they saw Jesus walking on the sea, and drawing near to the boat; and they were afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.20'>But he said to them, "It is I. Don`t be afraid."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.21'>They were willing therefore to receive him into the boat. Immediately the boat was at the land where they were going.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.22'>On the next day, the multitude that stood on the other side of the sea saw that there was no other boat there, except the one which his disciples had entered, and that Jesus hadn`t entered with his disciples into the boat, but his disciples went away alone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.23'>However boats from Tiberias came near to the place where they ate the bread after the Lord had given thanks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.24'>When the multitude therefore saw that Jesus wasn`t there, neither his disciples, they themselves got into the boats, and came to Capernaum, seeking Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.25'>When they found him on the other side of the sea, they asked him, "Rabbi, when did you come here?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.26'>Jesus answered them, "Most assuredly I tell you, you seek me, not because you saw signs, but because you ate of the loaves, and were filled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.27'>Don`t work for the food which perishes, but for the food which remains to eternal life, which the Son of Man will give to you. For the Father, even God, has sealed him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.28'>They said therefore to him, "What must we do, that we may work the works of God?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.29'>Jesus answered them, "This is the work of God, that you believe in him whom he has sent."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.30'>They said therefore to him, "What then do you do for a sign, that we may see, and believe you? What work do you do?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.31'>Our fathers ate the manna in the wilderness. As it is written, `He gave them bread out of the sky to eat.`"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.32'>Jesus therefore said to them, "Most assuredly, I tell you, it wasn`t Moses who gave you the bread out of heaven, but my Father gives you the true bread out of heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.33'>For the bread of God is that which comes down out of heaven, and gives life to the world."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.34'>They said therefore to him, "Lord, always give us this bread."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.35'>Jesus said to them. "I am the bread of life. He who comes to me will not be hungry, and he who believes in me will never be thirsty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.36'>But I told you that you have seen me, and yet don`t believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.37'>All that which the Father gives me will come to me. Him who comes to me I will in no way throw out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.38'>For I have come down from heaven, not to do my own will, but the will of him who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.39'>This is the will of my Father who sent me, that of all who he has given to me I should lose nothing, but should raise them up at the last day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.40'>This is the will of the one who sent me, that everyone who sees the Son, and believes in him, should have eternal life; and I will raise him up at the last day."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.41'>The Jews therefore murmured concerning him, because he said, "I am the bread which came down out of heaven."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.42'>They said, "Isn`t this Jesus, the son of Joseph, whose father and mother we know? How then does he say, `I have come down out of heaven?`"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.43'>Therefore Jesus answered them, "Don`t murmur among yourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.44'>No one can come to me unless the Father who sent me draws him, and I will raise him up in the last day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.45'>It is written in the prophets, `They will all be taught by God.` Everyone who hears from the Father, and has learned, comes to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.46'>Not that any man has seen the Father, except he who is from God. He has seen the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.47'>Most assuredly, I tell you, he who believes in me has eternal life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.48'>I am the bread of life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.49'>Your fathers ate the manna in the wilderness, and they died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.50'>This is the bread which comes down out of heaven, that a man may eat of it, and not die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.51'>I am the living bread which came down out of heaven. If anyone eats of this bread, he will live forever. Yes, the bread which I will give is my flesh, for the life of the world."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.52'>The Jews therefore contended with one another, saying, "How can this man give us his flesh to eat?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.53'>Jesus therefore said to them, "Most assuredly I tell you, unless you eat the flesh of the Son of Man and drink his blood, you don`t have life in yourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.54'>He who eats my flesh and drinks my blood has eternal life, and I will raise him up at the last day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.55'>For my flesh is food indeed, and my blood is drink indeed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.56'>He who eats my flesh and drinks my blood lives in me, and I in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.57'>As the living Father sent me, and I live because of the Father; so he who feeds on me, he will also live because of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.58'>This is the bread which came down out of heaven -- not as our fathers ate the manna, and died. He who eats this bread will live forever."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.59'>These things he said in the synagogue, as he taught in Capernaum.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.60'>Therefore many of his disciples, when they heard this, said, "This is a hard saying! Who can hear it?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.61'>But Jesus knowing in himself that his disciples murmured at this, said to them, "Does this cause you to stumble?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.62'>What if you would see the Son of Man ascending to where he was before?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.63'>It is the spirit who gives life. The flesh profits nothing. The words that I speak to you are spirit, and are life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.64'>But there are some of you who don`t believe." For Jesus knew from the beginning who they were who didn`t believe, and who it was who would betray him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.65'>He said, "For this cause have I said to you that no one can come to me, except it be given to him by my Father."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.66'>At this, many of his disciples went back, and walked no more with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.67'>Jesus said therefore to the twelve, "You don`t also want to go away, do you?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.68'>Simon Peter answered him, "Lord, to whom would we go? You have the words of eternal life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.69'>We have come to believe and know that you are the Christ, the Son of the living God."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.70'>Jesus answered them, "Didn`t I choose you, the twelve, and one of you is a devil?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.71'>Now he spoke of Judas, the son of Simon Iscariot, for it was he who would betray him, being one of the twelve.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.7'>
        <verse osisID='John.7.1'>After these things, Jesus walked in Galilee, for he would not walk in Judea, because the Jews sought to kill him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.2'>Now the feast of the Jews, the Feast of Booths, was at hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.3'>His brothers therefore said to him, "Depart from here, and go into Judea, that your disciples also may see your works which you do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.4'>For no man does anything in secret, and himself seeks to be known openly. If you do these things, reveal yourself to the world."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.5'>For even his brothers didn`t believe in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.6'>Jesus therefore said to them, "My time has not yet come, but your time is always ready.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.7'>The world can`t hate you, but it hates me, because I testify about it, that its works are evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.8'>You go up to the feast. I am not yet going up to this feast, because my time is not yet fulfilled."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.9'>Having said these things to them, he stayed in Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.10'>But when his brothers had gone up to the feast, then he also went up, not publicly, but as it were in secret.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.11'>The Jews therefore sought him at the feast, and said, "Where is he?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.12'>There was much murmuring among the multitudes concerning him. Some said, "He is a good man." Others said, "Not so, but he leads the multitude astray."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.13'>Yet no one spoke openly of him for fear of the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.14'>But when it was now the midst of the feast, Jesus went up into the temple and taught.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.15'>The Jews therefore marveled, saying, "How does this man know letters, having never been educated?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.16'>Jesus therefore answered them, "My teaching is not mine, but his who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.17'>If anyone desires to do his will, he will know of the teaching, whether it is from God, or if I speak from myself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.18'>He who speaks from himself seeks his own glory, but he who seeks the glory of him who sent him, the same is true, and no unrighteousness is in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.19'>Didn`t Moses give you the law, and yet none of you keeps the law? Why do you seek to kill me?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.20'>The multitude answered, "You have a demon! Who seeks to kill you?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.21'>Jesus answered them, "I did one work, and you all marvel because of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.22'>Moses has given you circumcision (not that it is of Moses, but of the fathers), and on the Sabbath you circumcise a boy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.23'>If a boy receives circumcision on the Sabbath, that the law of Moses may not be broken, are you angry with me, because I made a man every bit whole on the Sabbath?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.24'>Don`t judge according to appearance, but judge righteous judgment."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.25'>Some therefore of them of Jerusalem said, "Isn`t this he whom they seek to kill?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.26'>Behold, he speaks openly, and they say nothing to him. Can it be that the rulers indeed know that this is truly the Christ?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.27'>However we know where this man comes from, but when the Christ comes, no one will know where he comes from."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.28'>Jesus therefore cried out in the temple, teaching and saying, "You both know me, and know where I am from. I have not come of myself, but he who sent me is true, whom you don`t know.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.29'>I know him, because I am from him, and he sent me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.30'>They sought therefore to take him. No one laid a hand on him, because his hour was not yet come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.31'>But of the multitude, many believed in him. They said, "When the Christ comes, will he do more signs than those which this man has done?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.32'>The Pharisees heard the multitude murmuring these things concerning him, and the chief priests and the Pharisees sent officers to take him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.33'>Then Jesus said, "Yet a little while, am I with you, then I go to him who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.34'>You will seek me, and won`t find me; and where I am, you can`t come."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.35'>The Jews therefore said among themselves, "Where will this man go that we won`t find him? Will he go to the Dispersion among the Greeks, and teach the Greeks?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.36'>What is this word that he said, `You will seek me, and won`t find me; and where I am, you can`t come?`"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.37'>Now on the last and greatest day of the feast, Jesus stood and cried out, "If anyone is thirsty, let him come to me and drink!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.38'>He who believes in me, as the scripture has said, from within him will flow rivers of living water."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.39'>But he said this about the Spirit, which those believing in him were to receive. For the Holy Spirit was not yet given, because Jesus wasn`t yet glorified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.40'>Many of the multitude therefore, when they heard these words, said, "This is truly the prophet."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.41'>Others said, "This is the Christ." But some said, "What, does the Christ come out of Galilee?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.42'>Hasn`t the scripture said that the Christ comes of the seed of David, and from Bethlehem, the village where David was?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.43'>So there arose a division in the multitude because of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.44'>Some of them would have taken him, but no one laid hands on him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.45'>The officers therefore came to the chief priests and Pharisees, and they said to them, "Why didn`t you bring him?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.46'>The officers answered, "No man ever spoke like this man!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.47'>The Pharisees therefore answered them, "Are you also led astray?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.48'>Has any of the rulers believed in him, or of the Pharisees?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.49'>But this cursed multitude doesn`t know the law."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.50'>Nicodemus (he who came to him by night, being one of them) said to them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.51'>"Does our law judge a man, unless it first hears from him personally and knows what he does?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.52'>They answered him, "Are you also from Galilee? Search, and see that no prophet has arisen out of Galilee."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.53'>Everyone went to his own house,</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.8'>
        <verse osisID='John.8.1'>but Jesus went to the Mount of Olives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.2'>At dawn, he came again into the temple, and all the people came to him. He sat down, and taught them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.3'>The scribes and the Pharisees brought a woman taken in adultery. Having set her in the midst,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.4'>they told him, "Teacher, we found this woman in adultery, in the very act.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.5'>Now in our law, Moses commanded us to stone such. What then do you say about her?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.6'>They said this testing him, that they might have something to accuse him of.     But Jesus stooped down, and wrote on the ground with his finger, as if he didn`t hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.7'>But when they continued asking him, he lifted himself up, and said to them, "He who is without sin among you, let him throw the first stone at her."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.8'>Again he stooped down, and with his finger wrote on the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.9'>They, when they heard it, being convicted by their conscience, went out one by one, beginning from the oldest, even to the last. Jesus was left alone with the woman where she was, in the midst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.10'>Jesus lifted himself up, and seeing no one but the woman, said to her, "Woman, where are they? Did no one condemn you?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.11'>She said, "No one, Lord."     Jesus said, "Neither do I condemn you. Go your way. From now on, sin no more."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.12'>Again, therefore, Jesus spoke to them, saying, "I am the light of the world. He who follows me will not walk in the darkness, but will have the light of life."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.13'>The Pharisees therefore said to him, "You testify about yourself. Your witness is not valid."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.14'>Jesus answered them, "Even if I testify about myself, my witness is true, for I know where I came from, and where I am going; but you don`t know where I came from, or where I am going.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.15'>You judge according to the flesh. I judge no one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.16'>Even if I do judge, my judgment is true, for I am not alone, but I am with the Father who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.17'>It`s also written in your law that the testimony of two men is valid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.18'>I am he who testifies about myself, and the Father who sent me testifies about me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.19'>They said therefore to him, "Where is your Father?"     Jesus answered, "You know neither me, nor my Father. If you knew me, you would know my Father also."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.20'>Jesus spoke these words in the treasury, as he taught in the temple. No one took him, because his hour had not yet come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.21'>Jesus said therefore again to them, "I am going away, and you will seek me, and will die in your sins. Where I go, you can`t come."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.22'>The Jews therefore said, "Will he kill himself, that he says, `Where I am going, you can`t come?`"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.23'>He said to them, "You are from beneath. I am from above. You are of this world. I am not of this world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.24'>I said therefore to you that you will die in your sins; for unless you believe that I am he, you will die in your sins."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.25'>They said therefore to him, "Who are you?"     Jesus said to them, "Just what I have been saying to you from the beginning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.26'>I have many things to speak and to judge concerning you. However he who sent me is true; and the things which I heard from him, these I say to the world."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.27'>They didn`t perceive that he spoke to them about the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.28'>Jesus therefore said to them, "When you have lifted up the Son of Man, then will you know that I am he, and that I do nothing of myself, but as my Father taught me, I say these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.29'>He who sent me is with me. The Father hasn`t left me alone, for I always do the things that are pleasing to him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.30'>As he spoke these things, many believed in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.31'>Jesus therefore said to those Jews who had believed him, "If you remain in my word, then you are truly my disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.32'>You will know the truth, and the truth will make you free."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.33'>They answered him, "We are Abraham`s seed, and have never yet been in bondage to anyone. How do you say, `You will be made free?`"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.34'>Jesus answered them, "Most assuredly I tell you, everyone who commits sin is the bondservant of sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.35'>A bondservant doesn`t live in the house forever. A son remains forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.36'>If therefore the Son makes you free, you will be free indeed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.37'>I know that you are Abraham`s seed, yet you seek to kill me, because my word finds no place in you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.38'>I say the things which I have seen with my Father; and you also do the things which you have seen with your father."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.39'>They answered him, "Our father is Abraham."     Jesus said to them, "If you were Abraham`s children, you would do the works of Abraham.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.40'>But now you seek to kill me, a man who has told you the truth, which I heard from God. Abraham didn`t do this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.41'>You do the works of your father."     They said to him, "We were not born of sexual immorality. We have one Father, God."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.42'>Therefore Jesus said to them, "If God were your Father, you would love me, for I came forth and have come from God. For neither have I come of myself, but he sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.43'>Why don`t you understand my speech? Because you can`t hear my word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.44'>You are of your Father, the devil, and it is your desire to do the lusts of your father. He was a murderer from the beginning, and doesn`t stand in the truth, because there is no truth in him. When he speaks a lie, he speaks of his own; for he is a liar, and the father of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.45'>But because I tell the truth, you don`t believe me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.46'>Which of you convicts me of sin? If I tell the truth, why do you not believe me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.47'>He who is of God hears the words of God. For this cause you don`t hear, because you are not of God."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.48'>Then the Jews answered him, "Don`t we say well that you are a Samaritan, and have a demon?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.49'>Jesus answered, "I don`t have a demon, but I honor my Father, and you dishonor me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.50'>But I don`t seek my own glory. There is one who seeks and judges.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.51'>Most assuredly, I tell you, if a person keeps my word, he will never see death."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.52'>Then the Jews said to him, "Now we know that you have a demon. Abraham died, and the prophets; and you say, `If a man keeps my word, he will never taste of death.`</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.53'>Are you greater than our father, Abraham, who died? The prophets died. Who do you make yourself out to be?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.54'>Jesus answered, "If I glorify myself, my glory is nothing. It is my Father who glorifies me, of whom you say that he is our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.55'>You have not known him, but I know him. If I said, `I don`t know him,` I would be like you, a liar. But I know him, and keep his word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.56'>Your father Abraham rejoiced to see my day. He saw it, and was glad."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.57'>The Jews therefore said to him, "You are not yet fifty years old, and have you seen Abraham?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.58'>Jesus said to them, "Most assuredly, I tell you, before Abraham was born, I AM."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.59'>They took up stones therefore to throw at him, but Jesus hid himself, and went out of the temple, going through the midst of them, and so passed by.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.9'>
        <verse osisID='John.9.1'>As he passed by, he saw a man blind from his birth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.2'>His disciples asked him, "Rabbi, who sinned, this man or his parents, that he was born blind?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.3'>Jesus answered, "Neither did this man sin, nor his parents. But, that the works of God might be revealed in him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.4'>I must work the works of him who sent me, while it is day. The night is coming, when no one can work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.5'>When I am in the world, I am the light of the world."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.6'>When he had said this, he spat on the ground, made mud with the saliva, anointed the blind man`s eyes with the mud,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.7'>and said to him, "Go, wash in the pool of Siloam" (which means "Sent"). So he went away, washed, and came seeing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.8'>The neighbors therefore, and those who saw that he was blind, before, said, "Isn`t this he who sat and begged?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.9'>Others said, "It is he." Still others said, "He is like him."     He said, "I am he."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.10'>They said therefore to him, "How were your eyes opened?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.11'>He answered, "A man called Jesus made mud, anointed my eyes, and said to me, "Go to the pool of Siloam, and wash." So I went away and washed, and I received sight."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.12'>Then they asked him, "Where is he?"     He said, "I don`t know."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.13'>They brought him who before was blind to the Pharisees.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.14'>It was a Sabbath when Jesus made the mud and opened his eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.15'>Again therefore the Pharisees also asked him how he received his sight. He said to them, "He put mud on my eyes, I washed, and I see."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.16'>Some therefore of the Pharisees said, "This man is not from God, because he doesn`t keep the Sabbath." Others said, "How can a man who is a sinner do such signs?" There was division among them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.17'>Therefore they asked the blind man again, "What do you say about him, in that he opened your eyes?"     He said, "He is a prophet."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.18'>The Jews therefore did not believe concerning him, that he had been blind, and had received his sight, until they called the parents of him who had received his sight,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.19'>and asked them, "Is this your son, who you say was born blind? How then does he now see?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.20'>His parents answered them, "We know that this is our son, and that he was born blind;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.21'>but how he now sees, we don`t know; or who opened his eyes, we don`t know. He is of age. Ask him. He will speak for himself."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.22'>His parents said these things because they feared the Jews; for the Jews had already agreed that if any man would confess him as Christ, he would be put out of the synagogue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.23'>Therefore his parents said, "He is of age. Ask him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.24'>So they called the man who was blind a second time, and said to him, "Give glory to God. We know that this man is a sinner."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.25'>He therefore answered, "I don`t know if he is a sinner. One thing I know: that though I was blind, now I see."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.26'>They said to him again, "What did he do to you? How did he open your eyes?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.27'>He answered them, "I told you already, and you didn`t listen. Why do you want to hear it again? Do you also want to become his disciples?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.28'>They became abusive towards him and said, "You are his disciple, but we are disciples of Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.29'>We know that God has spoken to Moses. But as for this man, we don`t know where he comes from."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.30'>The man answered them, "How amazing! You don`t know where he comes from, yet he opened my eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.31'>We know that God doesn`t listen to sinners, but if anyone is a worshipper of God, and does his will, he listens to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.32'>Since the world began it has never been heard of that anyone opened the eyes of a man born blind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.33'>If this man were not from God, he could do nothing."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.34'>They answered him, "You were altogether born in sins, and do you teach us?" They threw him out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.35'>Jesus heard that they had thrown him out, and finding him, he said, "Do you believe in the Son of God?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.36'>He answered, "Who is he, Lord, that I may believe in him?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.37'>Jesus said to him, "You have both seen him, and it is he who speaks with you."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.38'>He said, "Lord, I believe!" and he worshipped him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.39'>Jesus said, "I came into this world for judgment, that those who don`t see may see; and that those who see may become blind."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.40'>Those of the Pharisees who were with him heard these things, and said to him, "Are we also blind?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.41'>Jesus said to them, "If you were blind, you would have no sin; but now you say, `We see.` Therefore your sin remains.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.10'>
        <verse osisID='John.10.1'>"Most assuredly, I tell you, he who doesn`t enter by the door into the sheep fold, but climbs up some other way, the same is a thief and a robber.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.2'>But he who enters in by the door is the shepherd of the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.3'>The gatekeeper opens the gate for him, and the sheep listen to his voice. He calls his own sheep by name, and leads them out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.4'>Whenever he brings out his own sheep, he goes before them, and the sheep follow him, for they know his voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.5'>They will by no means follow a stranger, but will flee from him; for they don`t know the voice of strangers."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.6'>Jesus spoke this parable to them, but they didn`t understand what he was telling them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.7'>Jesus therefore said to them again, "Most assuredly, I tell you, I am the sheep`s door.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.8'>All who came before me are thieves and robbers, but the sheep didn`t listen to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.9'>I am the door. If anyone enters in by me, he will be saved, and will go in and go out, and will find pasture.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.10'>The thief only comes to steal, kill, and destroy. I came that they may have life, and may have it abundantly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.11'>I am the good shepherd. The good shepherd lays down his life for the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.12'>He who is a hired hand, and not a shepherd, who doesn`t own the sheep, sees the wolf coming, leaves the sheep, and flees. The wolf snatches the sheep, and scatters them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.13'>The hired hand flees because he is a hired hand, and doesn`t care for the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.14'>I am the good shepherd. I know my own, and I`m known by my own;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.15'>even as the Father knows me, and I know the Father. I lay down my life for the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.16'>I have other sheep, which are not of this fold. I must bring them also, and they will hear my voice. They will become one flock with one shepherd.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.17'>Therefore the Father loves me, because I lay down my life, that I may take it again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.18'>No one takes it away from me, but I lay it down by myself. I have power to lay it down, and I have power to take it again. I received this commandment from my Father."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.19'>Therefore a division arose again among the Jews because of these words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.20'>Many of them said, "He has a demon, and is mad! Why do you listen to him?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.21'>Others said, "These are not the sayings of one possessed with a demon. Can a demon open the eyes of the blind?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.22'>It was the Feast of the Dedication at Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.23'>It was winter, and Jesus was walking in the temple, in Solomon`s porch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.24'>The Jews therefore came around him and said to him, "How long will you hold us in suspense? If you are the Christ, tell us plainly."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.25'>Jesus answered them, "I told you, and you don`t believe. The works that I do in my Father`s name, these testify about me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.26'>But you don`t believe, because you are not of my sheep, as I told you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.27'>My sheep hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.28'>I give eternal life to them. They will never perish, and no one will snatch them out of my hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.29'>My Father, who has given them to me, is greater than all. No one is able to snatch them out of my Father`s hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.30'>I and the Father are one."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.31'>Therefore Jews took up stones again to stone him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.32'>Jesus answered them, "I have shown you many good works from my Father. For which of those works do you stone me?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.33'>The Jews answered him, "We don`t stone you for a good work, but for blasphemy: because you, being a man, make yourself God."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.34'>Jesus answered them, "Isn`t it written in your law, `I said, you are gods?`</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.35'>If he called them gods, to whom the word of God came (and the scripture can`t be broken),</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.36'>Do you say of him whom the Father sanctified and sent into the world, `You blaspheme,` because I said, `I am the Son of God?`</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.37'>If I don`t do the works of my Father, don`t believe me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.38'>But if I do them, though you don`t believe me, believe the works; that you may know and believe that the Father is in me, and I in the Father."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.39'>They sought again to seize him, and he went forth out of their hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.40'>He went away again beyond the Jordan into the place where John was at the first baptizing, and there he stayed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.41'>Many came to him. They said, "John indeed did no sign, but everything whatever that John said about this man is true."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.42'>Many believed in him there.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.11'>
        <verse osisID='John.11.1'>Now a certain man was sick, Lazarus of Bethany, of the village of Mary and her sister, Martha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.2'>It was that Mary who anointed the Lord with ointment, and wiped his feet with her hair, whose brother, Lazarus, was sick.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.3'>The sisters therefore sent to him, saying, "Lord, behold, he for whom you have great affection is sick."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.4'>But when Jesus heard it, he said, "This sickness is not to death, but for the glory of God, that God`s Son may be glorified by it."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.5'>Now Jesus loved Martha, and her sister, and Lazarus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.6'>When therefore he heard that he was sick, he stayed at that time two days in the place where he was.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.7'>Then after this he said to the disciples, "Let`s go into Judea again."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.8'>The disciples told him, "Rabbi, the Jews were just trying to stone you, and are you going there again?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.9'>Jesus answered, "Aren`t there twelve hours of daylight? If a man walks in the day, he doesn`t stumble, because he sees the light of this world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.10'>But if a man walks in the night, he stumbles, because the light isn`t in him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.11'>He said these things, and after that, he said to them, "Our friend, Lazarus, has fallen asleep, but I am going so that I may awake him out of sleep."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.12'>The disciples therefore said to him, "Lord, if he has fallen asleep, he will recover."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.13'>Now Jesus had spoken of his death, but they thought that he spoke of taking rest in sleep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.14'>So Jesus said to them plainly then, "Lazarus is dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.15'>I am glad for your sakes that I was not there, so that you may believe. Nevertheless, let`s go to him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.16'>Thomas therefore, who is called Didymus, said to his fellow disciples, "Let`s go also, that we may die with him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.17'>So when Jesus came, he found that he had been in the tomb four days already.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.18'>Now Bethany was near Jerusalem, about fifteen stadia away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.19'>Many of the Jews had come to Martha and Mary, to console them concerning their brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.20'>Therefore Martha, when she heard that Jesus was coming, went and met him, but Mary stayed in the house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.21'>Therefore Martha said to Jesus, "Lord, if you would have been here, my brother wouldn`t have died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.22'>Even now I know that, whatever you ask of God, God will give you."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.23'>Jesus said to her, "Your brother will rise again."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.24'>Martha said to him, "I know that he will rise again in the resurrection at the last day."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.25'>Jesus said to her, "I am the resurrection and the life. He who believes in me, though he die, yet will he live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.26'>Whoever lives and believes in me will never die. Do you believe this?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.27'>She said to him, "Yes, Lord. I have come to believe that you are the Christ, God`s Son, he who comes into the world."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.28'>When she had said this, she went away, and called Mary, her sister, secretly, saying, "The Teacher is here, and is calling you."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.29'>She, when she heard this, arose quickly, and went to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.30'>Now Jesus had not yet come into the village, but was in the place where Martha met him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.31'>Then the Jews who were with her in the house, and were consoling her, when they saw Mary, that she rose up quickly and went out, followed her, saying, "She is going to the tomb to weep there."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.32'>Mary therefore, when she came to where Jesus was, and saw him, fell down at his feet, saying to him, "Lord, if you would have been here, my brother wouldn`t have died."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.33'>When Jesus therefore saw her weeping, and the Jews weeping who came with her, he groaned in the spirit, and was troubled,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.34'>and said, "Where have you laid him?"     They told him, "Lord, come and see."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.35'>Jesus wept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.36'>The Jews therefore said, "See how much affection he had for him!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.37'>Some of them said, "Couldn`t this man, who opened the eyes of him who was blind, have also caused that this man wouldn`t die?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.38'>Jesus therefore, again groaning in himself, came to the tomb. Now it was a cave, and a stone lay against it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.39'>Jesus said, "Take away the stone."     Martha, the sister of him who was dead, said to him, "Lord, by this time there is a stench, for he has been dead four days."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.40'>Jesus said to her, "Didn`t I tell you that if you believed, you would see God`s glory?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.41'>So they took away the stone from the place where the dead man was lying. Jesus lifted up his eyes, and said, "Father, I thank you that you listened to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.42'>I know that you always listen to me, but because of the multitude that stands around I said this, that they may believe that you sent me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.43'>When he had said this, he cried with a loud voice, "Lazarus, come out!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.44'>He who was dead came out, bound hand and foot with wrappings, and his face was wrapped around with a cloth.     Jesus said to them, "Free him, and let him go."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.45'>Therefore many of the Jews, who came to Mary and saw that which Jesus did, believed in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.46'>But some of them went away to the Pharisees, and told them the things which Jesus had done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.47'>The chief priests therefore and the Pharisees gathered a council, and said, "What are we doing? For this man does many signs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.48'>If we leave him alone like this, everyone will believe in him, and the Romans will come and take away both our place and our nation."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.49'>But a certain one of them, Caiaphas, being high priest that year, said to them, "You know nothing at all,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.50'>nor do you take account that it is advantageous for us that one man should die for the people, and that the whole nation not perish."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.51'>Now he didn`t say this of himself, but being high priest that year, he prophesied that Jesus would die for the nation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.52'>and not for the nation only, but that he might also gather together into one the children of God who are scattered abroad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.53'>So from that day forth they took counsel that they might put him to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.54'>Jesus therefore walked no more openly among the Jews, but departed from there into the country near the wilderness, into a city called Ephraim. He stayed there with his disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.55'>Now the Passover of the Jews was at hand. Many went up to Jerusalem out of the country before the Passover, to purify themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.56'>Then they sought for Jesus and spoke one with another, as they stood in the temple, "What do you think? Isn`t he coming to the feast?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.57'>Now the chief priests and the Pharisees had commanded that if anyone knew where he was, he should report it, that they might seize him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.12'>
        <verse osisID='John.12.1'>Therefore six days before the Passover, Jesus came to Bethany, where Lazarus was, who had been dead, whom he raised from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.2'>So they made him a supper there. Martha served, but Lazarus was one of those who sat at the table with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.3'>Mary, therefore, took a pound of ointment of pure nard, very precious, and anointed the feet of Jesus, and wiped his feet with her hair. The house was filled with the fragrance of the ointment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.4'>Then Judas Iscariot, Simon`s son, one of his disciples, who would betray him, said,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.5'>"Why wasn`t this ointment sold for three hundred denarii, and given to the poor?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.6'>Now he said this, not because he cared for the poor, but because he was a thief, and having the money box, used to steal what was put into it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.7'>But Jesus said, "Leave her alone. She has kept this for the day of my burial.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.8'>For you always have the poor with you, but you don`t always have me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.9'>A large crowd therefore of the Jews learned that he was there, and they came, not for Jesus` sake only, but that they might see Lazarus also, whom he had raised from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.10'>But the chief priests conspired to also put Lazarus to death,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.11'>because on account of him many of the Jews went away and believed in Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.12'>On the next day a great multitude had come to the feast. When they heard that Jesus was coming to Jerusalem,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.13'>they took the branches of the palm trees, and went out to meet him, and cried out, "Hosanna! Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord, the King of Israel!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.14'>Jesus, having found a young donkey, sat on it. As it is written,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.15'>"Don`t be afraid, daughter of Zion. Behold, your King comes, sitting on a donkey`s colt."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.16'>His disciples didn`t understand these things at first, but when Jesus was glorified, then they remembered that these things were written about him, and that they had done these things to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.17'>The multitude therefore that was with him when he called Lazarus out of the tomb, and raised him from the dead, was testifying.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.18'>For this cause also the multitude went and met him, because they heard that he had done this sign.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.19'>The Pharisees therefore said among themselves, "See how you accomplish nothing. Behold, the world has gone after him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.20'>Now there were certain Greeks among those that went up to worship at the feast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.21'>These, therefore, came to Philip, who was from Bethsaida of Galilee, and asked him, saying, "Sir, we want to see Jesus."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.22'>Philip came and told Andrew, and in turn, Andrew came with Philip, and they told Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.23'>Jesus answered them, "The time has come for the Son of Man to be glorified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.24'>Most assuredly I tell you, unless a grain of wheat falls into the earth and dies, it remains by itself alone. But if it dies, it bears much fruit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.25'>He who loves his life will lose it. He who hates his life in this world will keep it to eternal life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.26'>If anyone serves me, let him follow me. Where I am, there will my servant also be. If anyone serves me, the Father will honor him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.27'>"Now my soul is troubled. What will I say? `Father, save me from this time?` But for this cause I came to this time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.28'>Father, glorify your name!"     Then there came a voice out of the sky, saying, "I have both glorified it, and will glorify it again."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.29'>The multitude therefore, who stood by and heard it, said that it had thundered. Others said, "An angel has spoken to him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.30'>Jesus answered, "This voice hasn`t come for my sake, but for your sakes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.31'>Now is the judgment of this world. Now the prince of this world will be cast out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.32'>I, if I am lifted up from the earth, will draw all men to myself."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.33'>But he said this, signifying by what kind of death he should die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.34'>The multitude answered him, "We have heard out of the law that the Christ remains forever. How do you say, `The Son of Man must be lifted up?` Who is this Son of Man?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.35'>Jesus therefore said to them, "Yet a little while the light is with you. Walk while you have the light, that darkness doesn`t overtake you. He who walks in the darkness doesn`t know where he is going.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.36'>While you have the light, believe in the light, that you may become sons of light." Jesus said these things, and he departed and hid himself from them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.37'>But though he had done so many signs before them, yet they didn`t believe in him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.38'>that the word of Isaiah the prophet might be fulfilled, which he spoke, "Lord, who has believed our report? To whom has the arm of the Lord been revealed?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.39'>For this cause they couldn`t believe, for Isaiah said again,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.40'>"He has blinded their eyes and he hardened their heart, Lest they should see with their eyes, And perceive with their heart, And would turn, And I would heal them."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.41'>Isaiah said these things when he saw his glory, and he spoke of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.42'>Nevertheless even of the rulers many believed in him, but because of the Pharisees they didn`t confess it, so that they wouldn`t be put out of the synagogue,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.43'>for they loved men`s approval more than God`s approval.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.44'>Jesus cried out and said, "Whoever believes in me, believes not in me, but in him who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.45'>He who sees me sees him who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.46'>I have come as a light into the world, that whoever believes in me may not remain in the darkness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.47'>If anyone listens to my sayings, and doesn`t believe, I don`t judge him. For I came not to judge the world, but to save the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.48'>He who rejects me, and doesn`t receive my sayings, has one who judges him. The word that I spoke, the same will judge him in the last day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.49'>For I spoke not from myself, but the Father who sent me, he gave me a commandment, what I should say, and what I should speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.50'>I know that his commandment is eternal life. The things therefore which I speak, even as the Father has said to me, so I speak."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.13'>
        <verse osisID='John.13.1'>Now before the feast of the Passover, Jesus knowing that his time had come that he would depart out of this world to his Father, having loved his own who were in the world, he loved them to the end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.2'>After supper, the devil having already put into the heart of Judas Iscariot, Simon`s son, to betray him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.3'>Jesus, knowing that the Father had given all things into his hands, and that he came forth from God, and was going to God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.4'>arose from supper, and laid aside his outer garments. He took a towel, and wrapped a towel around his waist.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.5'>Then he poured water into the basin, and began to wash the disciples` feet, and to wipe them with the towel that was wrapped around him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.6'>Then he came to Simon Peter. He said to him, "Lord, do you wash my feet?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.7'>Jesus answered him, "You don`t know what I am doing now, but you will understand later."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.8'>Peter said to him, "You will never wash my feet!"     Jesus answered him, "If I don`t wash you, you have no part with me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.9'>Simon Peter said to him, "Lord, not my feet only, but also my hands and my head!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.10'>Jesus said to him, "Someone who has bathed only needs to have their feet washed, but is completely clean. You are clean, but not all of you."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.11'>For he knew him who would betray him, therefore he said, "You are not all clean."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.12'>So when he had washed their feet, put his outer garment back on, and sat down again, he said to them, "Do you know what I have done to you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.13'>You call me, `Teacher` and `Lord.` You say so correctly, for so I am.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.14'>If I then, the Lord and the Teacher, have washed your feet, you also ought to wash one another`s feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.15'>For I have given you an example, that you also should do as I have done to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.16'>Most assuredly I tell you, a servant is not greater than his lord, neither one who is sent greater than he who sent him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.17'>If you know these things, blessed are you if you do them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.18'>I speak not of you all. I know whom I have chosen. But that the scripture may be fulfilled, `He who eats bread with me has lifted up his heel against me.`</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.19'>From now on, I tell you before it happens, that when it happens, you may believe that I AM.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.20'>Most assuredly I tell you, he who receives whoever I send, receives me; and he who receives me, receives him who sent me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.21'>When Jesus had said this, he was troubled in the spirit, and testified, "Most assuredly I tell you that one of you will betray me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.22'>The disciples looked at one another, perplexed about whom he spoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.23'>One of his disciples, whom Jesus loved, was at the table, leaning against Jesus` breast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.24'>Simon Peter therefore beckoned to him, and said to him, "Tell us who it is of whom he speaks."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.25'>He, leaning back, as he was, on Jesus` breast, asked him, "Lord, who is it?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.26'>Jesus therefore answered, "It is he who I will give this morsel to when I have dipped it." So when he had dipped the morsel, he gave it to Judas, the son of Simon Iscariot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.27'>After the morsel, then Satan entered into him.     Jesus therefore said to him, "What you do, do quickly."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.28'>Now no man at the table knew why he said this to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.29'>For some thought, because Judas had the money box, that Jesus said to him, "Buy what things we need for the feast," or that he should give something to the poor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.30'>Therefore, having received that morsel, he went out immediately. It was night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.31'>When he had gone out, Jesus said, "Now the Son of Man is  glorified, and God is glorified in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.32'>If God is glorified in him, God will also glorify him in himself, and he will glorify him immediately.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.33'>Little children, yet a little while I am with you. You will seek me, and as I said to the Jews, `Where I am going, you can`t come,` so now I tell you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.34'>A new commandment I give to you, that you love one another, just like I have loved you; that you also love one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.35'>By this everyone will know that you are my disciples, if you have love for one another."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.36'>Simon Peter said to him, "Lord, where are you going?"     Jesus answered, "Where I am going, you can`t follow now, but you will follow afterwards."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.37'>Peter said to him, "Lord, why can`t I follow you even now? I will lay down my life for you."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.38'>Jesus answered him, "Will you lay down your life for me? Most assuredly I tell you, the rooster won`t crow until you have denied me three times.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.14'>
        <verse osisID='John.14.1'>"Don`t let your heart be troubled. Believe in God. Believe also in me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.2'>In my Father`s house are many mansions. If it weren`t so, I would have told you. I am going to prepare a place for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.3'>If I go and prepare a place for you, I will come again, and will receive you to myself; that where I am, you may be there also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.4'>Where I go, you know, and you know the way."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.5'>Thomas says to him, "Lord, we don`t know where you are going. How can we know the way?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.6'>Jesus said to him, "I am the way, the truth, and the life. No one comes to the Father, but by me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.7'>If you had known me, you would have known my Father also. From now on, you know him, and have seen him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.8'>Philip said to him, "Lord, show us the Father, and that will be enough for us."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.9'>Jesus said to him, "Have I been with you such a long time, and do you not know me, Philip? He who has seen me has seen the Father. How do you say, `Show us the Father?`</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.10'>Don`t you believe that I am in the Father, and the Father in me? The words that I tell you, I speak not from myself; but the Father living in me does his works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.11'>Believe me that I am in the Father, and the Father in me; or else believe me for the very works` sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.12'>Most assuredly I tell you, he who believes in me, the works that I do, he will do also; and greater works than these will he do; because I am going to my Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.13'>Whatever you will ask in my name, that will I do, that the Father may be glorified in the Son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.14'>If you will ask anything in my name, that will I do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.15'>If you love me, keep my commandments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.16'>I will pray to the Father, and he will give you another Counselor, that he may be with you forever,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.17'>-- the Spirit of truth, whom the world can`t receive; for it doesn`t see him, neither knows him. You know him, for he lives with you, and will be in you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.18'>I will not leave you orphans. I will come to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.19'>Yet a little while, and the world will see me no more; but you will see me. Because I live, you will live also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.20'>In that day you will know that I am in my Father, and you in me, and I in you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.21'>Someone who has my commandments, and keeps them, that person is one who loves me. One who loves me will be loved by my Father, and I will love him, and will reveal myself to him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.22'>Judas (not Iscariot) said to him, "Lord, what will happen that you will reveal yourself to us, and not to the world?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.23'>Jesus answered him, "If a man loves me, he will keep my word. My Father will love him, and we will come to him, and make our home with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.24'>He who doesn`t love me doesn`t keep my words. The word which you hear isn`t mine, but the Father`s who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.25'>I have said these things to you, while still living with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.26'>But the Counselor, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name, he will teach you all things, and bring to your memory all that I said to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.27'>Peace I leave with you. My peace I give to you; not as the world gives, give I to you. Don`t let your heart be troubled, neither let it be fearful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.28'>You heard how I told you, `I go away, and I come to you.` If you loved me, you would have rejoiced, because I said `I am going to my Father;` for the Father is greater than I.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.29'>Now I have told you before it happens so that, when it happens, you may believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.30'>I will no more speak much with you, for the prince of the world comes, and he has nothing in me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.31'>But that the world may know that I love the Father, and as the Father commanded me, even so I do. Arise, let us go from here.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.15'>
        <verse osisID='John.15.1'>"I am the true vine, and my Father is the farmer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.2'>Every branch in me that doesn`t bear fruit, he takes away. Every branch that bears fruit, he prunes, that it may bear more fruit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.3'>You are already pruned clean because of the word which I have spoken to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.4'>Remain in me, and I in you. As the branch can`t bear fruit by itself, unless it remains in the vine, so neither can you, unless you remain in me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.5'>I am the vine. You are the branches. He who remains in me, and I in him, the same bears much fruit, for apart from me you can do nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.6'>If a man doesn`t remain in me, he is thrown out as a branch, and is withered; and they gather them, throw them into the fire, and they are burned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.7'>If you remain in me, and my words remain in you, you will ask whatever you desire, and it will be done to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.8'>In this is my Father glorified, that you bear much fruit; and so you will be my disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.9'>Even as the Father has loved me, I also have loved you. Remain in my love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.10'>If you keep my commandments, you will remain in my love; even as I have kept my Father`s commandments, and remain in his love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.11'>I have spoken these things to you, that my joy may be in you, and that your joy may be made full.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.12'>This is my commandment, that you love one another, even as I have loved you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.13'>Greater love has no one than this, that a man lay down his life for his friends.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.14'>You are my friends, if you do whatever I command you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.15'>No longer do I call you servants, for the servant doesn`t know what his lord does. But I have called you friends, for everything that I heard from my Father, I have made known to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.16'>You didn`t choose me, but I chose you, and appointed you, that you should go and bear fruit, and that your fruit should remain; that whatever you will ask of the Father in my name, he may give it to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.17'>I command these things to you, that you may love one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.18'>If the world hates you, you know that it has hated me before it hated you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.19'>If you were of the world, the world would love its own. But because you are not of the world, since I chose you out of the world, therefore the world hates you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.20'>Remember the word that I said to you: `A servant is not greater than his lord.` If they persecuted me, they will also persecute you. If they kept my word, they will keep yours also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.21'>But all these things will they do to you for my name`s sake, because they don`t know him who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.22'>If I had not come and spoken to them, they would not have had sin; but now they have no excuse for their sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.23'>He who hates me, hates my Father also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.24'>If I hadn`t done among them the works which none other did, they wouldn`t have had sin. But now have they seen and also hated both me and my Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.25'>But that the word may be fulfilled that is written in their law, `They hated me without a cause.`</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.26'>When the Counselor has come, whom I will send to you from the Father, the Spirit of truth, who proceeds from the Father, he will testify about me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.27'>You will also testify, because you have been with me from the beginning.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.16'>
        <verse osisID='John.16.1'>"These things have I spoken to you, so that you wouldn`t be caused to stumble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.2'>They will put you out of the synagogues. Yes, the time comes that whoever kills you will think that he offers service to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.3'>They will do these things because they have not known the Father, nor me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.4'>But I have told you these things, so that when the time comes, you may remember that I told you about them. I didn`t tell you these things from the beginning, because I was with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.5'>But now I am going to him who sent me, and none of you asks me, `Where are you going?`</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.6'>But because I have told you these things, sorrow has filled your heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.7'>Nevertheless I tell you the truth: It is to your advantage that I go away, for if I don`t go away, the Counselor won`t come to you. But if I go, I will send him to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.8'>When he has come, he will convict the world in respect to sin, and righteousness, and judgment;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.9'>of sin, because they don`t believe in me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.10'>of righteousness, because I am going to my Father, and you see me no more;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.11'>of judgment, because the prince of this world has been judged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.12'>I have yet many things to tell you, but you can`t bear them now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.13'>However when he, the Spirit of truth, has come, he will guide you into all the truth, for he will not speak from himself; but whatever things he hears, he will speak. He will declare to you the things that are to come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.14'>He will glorify me, for he will take from what is mine, and will declare it to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.15'>All things whatever the Father has are mine; therefore I said that he takes of mine, and will declare it to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.16'>A little while, and you will not see me. Again a little while, and you will see me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.17'>Some of his disciples therefore said to one another, "What is this that he says to us, `A little while, and you won`t see me, and again a little while, and you will see me;` and, `Because I go to the Father?`"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.18'>They said therefore, "What is this that he says, `A little while?` We don`t know what he is saying."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.19'>Therefore Jesus perceived that they wanted to ask him, and he said to them, "Do you inquire among yourselves concerning this, that I said, `A little while, and you won`t see me, and again a little while, and you will see me?`</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.20'>Most assuredly I tell you, that you will weep and lament, but the world will rejoice. You will be sorrowful, but your sorrow will be turned into joy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.21'>A woman, when she is in travail, has sorrow, because her time has come. But when she has delivered the child, she doesn`t remember the anguish any more, for the joy that a child is born into the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.22'>You therefore now have sorrow, but I will see you again, and your heart will rejoice, and no one will take your joy away from you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.23'>In that day you will ask me no question. Most assuredly I tell you, whatever you may ask of the Father, he will give it to you in my name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.24'>Until now, you have asked nothing in my name. Ask, and you will receive, that your joy may be made full.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.25'>I have spoken these things to you in figures of speech. But the time comes when I will no more speak to you in figures of speech, but will tell you plainly about the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.26'>In that day you will ask in my name; and I don`t say to you, that I will pray to the Father for you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.27'>for the Father himself loves you, because you have loved me, and have believed that I came forth from God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.28'>I came out from the Father, and have come into the world. Again, I leave the world, and go to the Father."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.29'>His disciples said to him, "Behold, now you speak plainly, and speak no figures of speech.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.30'>Now we know that you know all things, and don`t need for anyone to question you. By this we believe that you came forth from God."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.31'>Jesus answered them, "Do you now believe?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.32'>Behold, the time comes, yes, has now come, that you will be scattered, everyone to his own place, and will leave me alone. Yet I am not alone, because the Father is with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.33'>I have told you these things, that in me you may have peace. In the world you have oppression; but cheer up! I have overcome the world."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.17'>
        <verse osisID='John.17.1'>Jesus said these things, and lifting up his eyes to heaven, he said, "Father, the time has come. Glorify your Son, that your Son may also glorify you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.2'>even as you gave him authority over all flesh, that to all whom you have given him, he will give eternal life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.3'>This is eternal life, that they should know you, the only true God, and him whom you sent, Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.4'>I glorified you on the earth. I have accomplished the work which you have given me to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.5'>Now, Father, glorify me with your own self with the glory which I had with you before the world existed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.6'>I revealed your name to the people whom you have given me out of the world. They were yours, and you have given them to me. They have kept your word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.7'>Now they know that all things whatever you have given me are from you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.8'>for the words which you have given me I have given to them, and they received them, and knew for sure that I came forth from you, and they believed that you sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.9'>I pray for them. I don`t pray for the world, but for those whom you have given me, for they are yours.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.10'>All things that are mine are yours, and yours are mine, and I am glorified in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.11'>I am no more in the world, and these are in the world, and I am coming to you. Holy Father, keep them through your name which you have given me, that they may be one, even as we are.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.12'>While I was with them in the world, I kept them in your name. Those whom you have given me I have kept. None of them is lost, except the son of perdition, that the Scripture might be fulfilled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.13'>But now I come to you, and I say these things in the world, that they may have my joy made full in themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.14'>I have given them your word. The world hated them, because they are not of the world, even as I am not of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.15'>I pray not that you would take them from the world, but that you would keep them from the evil one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.16'>They are not of the world even as I am not of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.17'>Sanctify them in your truth. Your word is truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.18'>As you sent me into the world, even so I sent them into the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.19'>For their sakes I sanctify myself, that they themselves also may be sanctified in truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.20'>Neither for these only do I pray, but for those also who believe in me through their word,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.21'>that they may all be one; even as you, Father, are in me, and I in you, that they also may be one in us; that the world may believe that you sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.22'>The glory which you have given me, I have given to them; that they may be one, even as we are one;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.23'>I in them, and you in me, that they may be perfected into one; that the world may know that you sent me, and loved them, even as you loved me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.24'>Father, I desire that they also whom you have given me be with me where I am, that they may see my glory, which you have given me, for you loved me before the foundation of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.25'>Righteous Father, the world didn`t know you, but I knew you; and these knew that you sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.26'>I made known to them your name, and will make it known; that the love with which you loved me may be in them, and I in them."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.18'>
        <verse osisID='John.18.1'>When Jesus had spoken these words, he went forth with his disciples over the brook Kidron, where was a garden, into which he entered, himself and his disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.2'>Now Judas, who betrayed him, also knew the place, for Jesus often resorted there with his disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.3'>Judas then, having taken a detachment of soldiers and officers from the chief priests and the Pharisees, came there with lanterns, torches, and weapons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.4'>Jesus therefore, knowing all the things that were coming on him, went forth, and said to them, "Who are you looking for?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.5'>They answered him, "Jesus of Nazareth."     Jesus said to them, "I AM."     Judas also, who betrayed him, was standing with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.6'>When therefore he said to them, "I AM," they went backward, and fell to the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.7'>Again therefore he asked them, "Who are you looking for?"     They said, "Jesus of Nazareth."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.8'>Jesus answered, "I told you that I AM. If therefore you seek me, let these go their way,"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.9'>that the word might be fulfilled which he spoke, "Of those whom you have given me, I have lost none."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.10'>Simon Peter therefore, having a sword, drew it, and struck the high priest`s servant, and cut off his right ear. The servant`s name was Malchus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.11'>Jesus therefore said to Peter, "Put up the sword into its sheath. The cup which the Father has given me, shall I not drink it?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.12'>So the detachment, the commanding officer, and the officers of the Jews, seized Jesus and bound him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.13'>and led him to Annas first, for he was father-in-law to Caiaphas, who was high priest that year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.14'>Now it was Caiaphas who gave counsel to the Jews, that it was expedient that one man should die for the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.15'>Simon Peter followed Jesus, as did another disciple. Now that disciple was known to the high priest, and entered in with Jesus into the court of the high priest;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.16'>but Peter was standing at the door outside. So the other disciple, who was known to the high priest, went out and spoke to her who kept the door, and brought in Peter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.17'>Then the maid who kept the door said to Peter, "Are you also one of this man`s disciples?"     He said, "I am not."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.18'>Now the servants and the officers were standing there, having made a fire of coals, for it was cold. They were warming themselves. Peter was with them, standing and warming himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.19'>The high priest therefore asked Jesus of his disciples, and of his teaching.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.20'>Jesus answered him, "I spoke openly to the world. I always taught in synagogues, and in the temple, where the Jews always meet. I said nothing in secret.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.21'>Why do you ask me? Ask those who have heard me what I said to them. Behold, these know the things which I said."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.22'>When he had said this, one of the officers standing by slapped Jesus with his hand, saying, "Do you answer the high priest like that?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.23'>Jesus answered him, "If I have spoken evil, testify of the evil; but if well, why do you beat me?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.24'>Annas sent him bound to Caiaphas, the high priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.25'>Now Simon Peter was standing and warming himself. They said therefore to him, "Are you also one of his disciples?"     He denied it, and said, "I am not."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.26'>One of the servants of the high priest, being a relative of him whose ear Peter cut off, said, "Didn`t I see you in the garden with him?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.27'>Peter therefore denied again, and immediately the rooster crowed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.28'>They led Jesus therefore from Caiaphas into the Praetorium. It was early, and they themselves didn`t enter into the Praetorium, that they might not be defiled, but might eat the Passover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.29'>Pilate therefore went out to them, and said, "What accusation do you bring against this man?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.30'>They answered him, "If this man weren`t an evildoer, we wouldn`t have delivered him up to you."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.31'>Pilate therefore said to them, "Take him yourselves, and judge him according to your law."     Therefore the Jews said to him, "It is not lawful for us to put anyone to death,"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.32'>that the word of Jesus might be fulfilled, which he spoke, signifying by what kind of death he should die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.33'>Pilate therefore entered again into the Praetorium, called Jesus, and said to him, "Are you the King of the Jews?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.34'>Jesus answered him, "Do you say this of yourself, or did others tell it to you concerning me?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.35'>Pilate answered, "Am I a Jew? Your own nation and the chief priests delivered you to me. What have you done?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.36'>Jesus answered, "My kingdom is not of this world. If my kingdom were of this world, then my servants would fight, that I wouldn`t be delivered to the Jews. But now my kingdom is not from here."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.37'>Pilate therefore said to him, "Are you a king then?"     Jesus answered, "You say that I am a king. To this end have I been born, and to this end I have come into the world, that I should testify to the truth. Everyone who is of the truth listens to my voice."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.38'>Pilate said to him, "What is truth?"     When he had said this, he went out again to the Jews, and said to them, "I find no basis for a charge against him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.39'>But you have a custom, that I should release to you one at the Passover. Therefore do you desire that I release to you the King of the Jews?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.40'>Then they all cried out again, saying, "Not this man, but Barabbas!" Now Barabbas was a robber.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.19'>
        <verse osisID='John.19.1'>Then Pilate therefore took Jesus, and flogged him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.2'>The soldiers twisted thorns into a crown, and put it on his head, and dressed him in a purple garment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.3'>They said, "Hail, King of the Jews!" and they struck him with their hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.4'>Then Pilate went out again, and said to them, "Behold, I bring him out to you, that you may know that I find no basis for a charge against him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.5'>Jesus therefore came out, wearing the crown of thorns and the purple garment. Pilate said to them, "Behold, the man!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.6'>When therefore the chief priests and the officers saw him, they cried out, saying, "Crucify! Crucify!"     Pilate said to them, "Take him yourselves, and crucify him, for I find no basis for a charge against him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.7'>The Jews answered him, "We have a law, and by our law he ought to die, because he made himself the Son of God."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.8'>When therefore Pilate heard this saying, he was more afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.9'>He entered into the Praetorium again, and said to Jesus, "Where are you from?" But Jesus gave him no answer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.10'>Pilate therefore said to him, "Aren`t you speaking to me? Don`t you know that I have power to release you, and have power to crucify you?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.11'>Jesus answered, "You would have no power at all against me, unless it were given to you from above. Therefore he who delivered me to you has greater sin."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.12'>At this, Pilate sought to release him, but the Jews cried out, saying, "If you release this man, you aren`t Caesar`s friend! Everyone who makes himself a king speaks against Caesar!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.13'>When Pilate therefore heard these words, he brought Jesus out, and sat down on the judgment seat at a place called "The Pavement," but in Hebrew, "Gabbatha."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.14'>Now it was the Preparation of the Passover, at about the sixth hour. He said to the Jews, "Behold, your King!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.15'>They cried out, "Away with him! Away with him! Crucify him!"     Pilate said to them, "Shall I crucify your King?"     The chief priests answered, "We have no king but Caesar!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.16'>Then therefore he delivered him to them to be crucified. So they took Jesus and led him away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.17'>He went out, bearing his cross, to the place called "The place of a skull," which is called in Hebrew, "Golgotha,"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.18'>where they crucified him, and with him two others, on either side one, and Jesus in the middle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.19'>Pilate wrote a title also, and put it on the cross. There was written, "JESUS OF NAZARETH, THE KING OF THE JEWS."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.20'>Therefore many of the Jews read this title, for the place where Jesus was crucified was near the city; and it was written in Hebrew, in Latin, and in Greek.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.21'>The chief priests of the Jews therefore said to Pilate, "Don`t write, `The King of the Jews,` but that, `he said, I am King of the Jews.`"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.22'>Pilate answered, "What I have written, I have written."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.23'>Then the soldiers, when they had crucified Jesus, took his garments and made four parts, to every soldier a part; and also the coat. Now the coat was without seam, woven from the top throughout.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.24'>Then they said to one another, "Let`s not tear it, but cast lots for it, whose it will be," that the scripture might be fulfilled, which says, "They parted my garments among them, For my cloak they cast lots."     Therefore the soldiers did these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.25'>But there were standing by the cross of Jesus his mother, and his mother`s sister, Mary the wife of Clopas, and Mary Magdalene.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.26'>Therefore when Jesus saw his mother, and the disciple whom he loved standing there, he said to his mother, "Woman, behold your son!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.27'>Then he said to the disciple, "Behold, your mother!" From that hour, the disciple took her to his own home.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.28'>After this, Jesus, seeing that all things were now finished, that the scripture might be fulfilled, said, "I am thirsty."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.29'>Now a vessel full of vinegar was set there; so they put a sponge full of the vinegar on hyssop, and brought it to his mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.30'>When Jesus therefore had received the vinegar, he said, "It is finished." He bowed his head, and gave up his spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.31'>Therefore the Jews, because it was the Preparation, so that the bodies wouldn`t remain on the cross on the Sabbath (for that Sabbath was a special one), asked of Pilate that their legs might be broken, and that they might be taken away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.32'>Therefore the soldiers came, and broke the legs of the first, and of the other who was crucified with him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.33'>but when they came to Jesus, and saw that he was already dead, they didn`t break his legs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.34'>However one of the soldiers pierced his side with a spear, and immediately blood and water came out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.35'>He who has seen has testified, and his testimony is true. He knows that he tells the truth, that you also may believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.36'>For these things happened, that the scripture might be fulfilled, "A bone of him will not be broken."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.37'>Again another scripture says, "They will look on him whom they pierced."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.38'>After these things, Joseph of Arimathaea, being a disciple of Jesus, but secretly for fear of the Jews, asked of Pilate that he might take away Jesus` body. Pilate gave him permission. He came therefore, and took away his body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.39'>Nicodemus also came, he who at first came to Jesus by night, bringing a mixture of myrrh and aloes, about a hundred Roman pounds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.40'>So they took Jesus` body, and bound it in linen cloths with the spices, as the custom of the Jews is to bury.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.41'>Now in the place where he was crucified there was a garden. In the garden a new tomb in which no man had ever yet been laid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.42'>Then because of the Jews` Preparation (for the tomb was near at hand) they laid Jesus there.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.20'>
        <verse osisID='John.20.1'>Now on the first day of the week, Mary Magdalene came early, while it was yet dark, to the tomb, and saw the stone taken away from the tomb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.2'>She ran therefore, and came to Simon Peter, and to the other disciple whom Jesus loved, and said to them, "They have taken away the Lord out of the tomb, and we don`t know where they have laid him!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.3'>Peter therefore went forth, and the other disciple, and they went toward the tomb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.4'>They both ran together. The other disciple outran Peter, and came to the tomb first.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.5'>Stooping and looking in, he saw the linen cloths lying, yet he didn`t enter in.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.6'>Then Simon Peter came, following him, and entered into the tomb. He saw the linen cloths lying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.7'>and the cloth that was on his head, not lying with the linen cloths, but rolled up in a place by itself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.8'>Then the other disciple also entered in therefore, who came first to the tomb, and he saw, and believed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.9'>For as yet they didn`t know the scripture, that he must rise from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.10'>So the disciples went away again to their own homes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.11'>But Mary was standing outside at the tomb weeping. So, as she wept, she stooped and looked into the tomb,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.12'>and she saw two angels in white sitting, one at the head, and one at the feet, where the body of Jesus had lain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.13'>They told her, "Woman, why are you weeping?"     She said to them, "Because they have taken away my Lord, and I don`t know where they have laid him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.14'>When she had said this, she turned herself back, and saw Jesus standing, and didn`t know that it was Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.15'>Jesus said to her, "Woman, why are you weeping? Who are you looking for?"     She, supposing him to be the gardener, said to him, "Sir, if you have carried him away, tell me where you have laid him, and I will take him away."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.16'>Jesus said to her, "Mary."     She turned herself, and said to him, "Rhabbouni!" which is to say, "Teacher!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.17'>Jesus said to her, "Don`t touch me, for I haven`t yet ascended to my Father; but go to my brothers, and tell them, `I am ascending to my Father and your Father, and my God and your God.`"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.18'>Mary Magdalene came and told the disciples that she had seen the Lord, and that he had said these things to her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.19'>When therefore it was evening, on that day, the first day of the week, and when the doors were locked where the disciples were assembled, for fear of the Jews, Jesus came and stood in the midst, and said to them, "Peace be to you."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.20'>When he had said this, he showed to them his hands and his side. The disciples therefore were glad when they saw the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.21'>Jesus therefore said to them again, "Peace be to you. As the Father has sent me, even so I send you."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.22'>When he had said this, he breathed on them, and said to them, "Receive the Holy Spirit!</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.23'>Whoever`s sins you forgive, they are forgiven to them. Whoever`s sins you retain, they are retained."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.24'>But Thomas, one of the twelve, called Didymus, wasn`t with them when Jesus came.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.25'>The other disciples therefore said to him, "We have seen the Lord!"     But he said to them, "Unless I see in his hands the print of the nails, and put my hand into his side, I will not believe."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.26'>After eight days again his disciples were within, and Thomas with them. Jesus came, the doors being locked, and stood in the midst, and said, "Peace be to you."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.27'>Then he said to Thomas, "Reach here your finger, and see my hands. Reach here your hand, and put it into my side. Don`t be faithless, but believing."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.28'>Thomas answered him, "My Lord and my God!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.29'>Jesus said to him, "Because you have seen me, you have believed. Blessed are those who have not seen, and have believed."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.30'>Therefore Jesus did many other signs in the presence of his disciples, which are not written in this book;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.31'>but these are written, that you may believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God, and that believing you may have life in his name.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.21'>
        <verse osisID='John.21.1'>After these things, Jesus revealed himself again to the disciples at the sea of Tiberias. He revealed himself this way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.2'>Simon Peter, Thomas called Didymus, Nathanael of Cana in Galilee, and the sons of Zebedee, and two others of his disciples were together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.3'>Simon Peter said to them, "I`m going fishing."     They told him, "We are also coming with you." They immediately went forth, and entered into the boat. That night, they caught nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.4'>But when day was now breaking, Jesus stood on the beach, yet the disciples didn`t know that it was Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.5'>Jesus therefore said to them, "Children, have you anything to eat?"     They answered him, "No."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.6'>He said to them, "Cast the net on the right side of the boat, and you will find some."     They cast therefore, and now they were not able to draw it in for the multitude of fish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.7'>That disciple therefore whom Jesus loved said to Peter, "It`s the Lord!"     So when Simon Peter heard that it was the Lord, he wrapped his coat around him (for he was naked), and threw himself into the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.8'>But the other disciples came in the little boat (for they were not far from the land, but about two hundred cubits away), dragging the net full of fish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.9'>So when they got out on the land, they saw a fire of coals there, and fish laid on it, and bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.10'>Jesus said to them, "Bring some of the fish which you have just caught."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.11'>Simon Peter went up, and drew the net to land, full of great fish, one hundred fifty-three; and even though there were so many, the net wasn`t torn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.12'>Jesus said to them, "Come and eat breakfast."     None of the disciples dared inquire of him, "Who are you?" knowing that it was the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.13'>Then Jesus came and took the bread, gave it to them, and the fish likewise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.14'>This is now the third time that Jesus was revealed to his disciples, after he had risen from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.15'>So when they had eaten their breakfast, Jesus said to Simon Peter, "Simon, son of Jonah, do you love me more than these?"     He said to him, "Yes, Lord; you know that I have affection for you."     He said to him, "Feed my lambs."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.16'>He said to him again a second time, "Simon, son of Jonah, do you love me?"     He said to him, "Yes, Lord; you know that I have affection for you."     He said to him, "Tend my sheep."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.17'>He says to him the third time, "Simon, son of Jonah, do you have affection for me?"     Peter was grieved because he asked him the third time, "Do you have affection for me?" He said to him, "Lord, you know everything. You know that I have affection for you."     Jesus said to him, "Feed my sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.18'>Most assuredly I tell you, when you were young, you dressed yourself, and walked where you wanted to. But when you are old, you will stretch out your hands, and another will dress you, and carry you where you don`t want to go."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.19'>Now he said this, signifying by what kind of death he would glorify God. When he had said this, he said to him, "Follow me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.20'>Then Peter, turning around, saw a disciple following. This was the disciple whom Jesus sincerely loved, the one who had also leaned on Jesus` breast at the supper and asked, "Lord, who is going to betray You?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.21'>Peter seeing him, said to Jesus, "Lord, and what will this man do?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.22'>Jesus said to him, "If I desire that he stay until I come, what is that to you? You follow me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.23'>This saying therefore went forth among the brothers, that that disciple wouldn`t die. Yet Jesus didn`t say to him that he wouldn`t die, but, "If I desire that he stay until I come, what is that to you?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.24'>This is the disciple who testifies about these things, and wrote these things. We know that his witness is true.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.25'>There are also many other things which Jesus did, which if they would all be written, I suppose that even the world itself wouldn`t contain the books that would be written.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>