<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='LONT' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='LONT'>
        <title>Living Oracles NT</title>
        <contributor>George Campbell, James Macknight, Philip Doddridge. Ed. Alexander Campbell.</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>Holy Bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>[Alexander Campbell's Living Oracles,]
The Sacred Writings of the Apostles and Evangelists of Jesus Christ, Commonly Styled the New Testament. 
Translated from the Original Greek.
MDCCCXXXV. 1835</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>LONT</identifier>
        <source>http://www.e-sword.net/usermods/bbl/Living%20Oracles%20New%20Testament%20(LONT)%20(1835).exe</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='1Cor'>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.1'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.1'>Paul, a called Apostle of Jesus Christ, by the will of God, and Sosthenes, the brother,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.2'>to the congregation of God which is in Corinth, sanctified by Christ Jesus, called saints; with all, in every place, who invoke the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, both their Lord and ours:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.3'>favor and peace be with you from God our Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.4'>I give thanks to my God always in respect of you; on account of the favor of God, which was given to you through Jesus Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.5'>that you were enriched with every gift, by him; even with all speech, and all knowledge,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.6'>just as the testimony of Christ was confirmed among you:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.7'>so that you come behind in no gift, waiting for the full manifestation of our Lord Jesus Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.8'>who will confirm you till the end, without accusation in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.9'>God is faithful, by whom you have been called into the fellowship of his Son Jesus Christ our Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.10'>Now, brethren, I beseech you by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that you all speak the same thing, and that there be no schisms among you; but that you be perfectly united in the same mind, and in the same judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.11'>For it has been declared to me concerning you, my brethren, by some of the family of Chloe, that there are contentions among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.12'>And I mention this, that each of you says, I, indeed, am of Paul, and I of Apollos, and I of Cephas, and I of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.13'>Is Christ divided? Was Paul crucified for you? or were you immersed into the name of Paul?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.14'>I give thanks to God that I immersed none of you except Crispus and Gaius;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.15'>lest any one should say that I immersed into my own name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.16'>And I immersed also the family of Stephanus: besides, I know not whether I immersed any other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.17'>For Christ did not send me to immerse, but to proclaim the glad tidings; not, however, with wisdom of speech, that the cross of Christ might not be deprived of its efficacy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.18'>For this doctrine (the doctrine of the cross) is, indeed, foolishness to the destroyed; but to us, who are saved, it is the power of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.19'>«Therefore, it is written,» 'I will destroy the wisdom of the wise, and will set aside the knowledge of the prudent.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.20'>Where is the wise man? where the scribe? where the disputers of this world? Has not God shown the wisdom of this world to be folly?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.21'>For, when, in the wisdom of God, the world, through wisdom, knew not God, it pleased God, through the foolishness of this proclamation, to save them who believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.22'>And though the Jews demand a sign, and the Greeks seek wisdom;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.23'>yet we proclaim a crucified Christ: to the Jews, indeed, a stumbling block, and to the Greeks foolishness:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.24'>but to them who are called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ, the power of God and the wisdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.25'>Because the foolishness of God is wiser than men, and the weakness of God is stronger than men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.26'>For you see the calling of you, brethren, that not many wise men after the flesh, not many mighty, not many noble;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.27'>but God has chosen the foolish of the world to put the wise to shame; and the weak God has chosen to put the strong to shame;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.28'>the ignoble of the world, and the despised, God has chosen; nay, those that are nothing, to reduce to nothing those that are;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.29'>that not flesh might boast in his presence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.30'>Of him, therefore, you are in Christ Jesus, who is become to us wisdom from God, justification, also, and sanctification, and redemption.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.1.31'>«So that, as it is written,» 'Let him who boasts, boast in the Lord.'</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.2'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.1'>Now, when I cam to you, brethren, I came not with excellency of speech, and of wisdom, declaring to you the testimony of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.2'>For I determined to make known nothing among you but Jesus Christ, and him crucified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.3'>And I, in weakness and in fear, and in much trembling, was with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.4'>My discourse, also, and my proclamation, were not with persuasive words of human wisdom; but with the demonstration of the Spirit, and of power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.5'>That your faith might not stand in the wisdom of men, but in the power of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.6'>However, we speak wisdom among the perfect: but not the wisdom of this world; neither of the rulers of this world, who are to be brought to nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.7'>But we speak the mysterious wisdom of God, which has been till now concealed; which God declared before the time of the ages, should be spoken to our glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.8'>Which none of the rulers of this world knew: for if they had known it, they would not have crucified the Lord of glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.9'>«For, as it is written,» 'Those things eye has not seen, and ear has not heard, and into the heart of man have not entered, which God has prepared for them who love him.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.10'>But God has revealed them to us by his Spirit; for the Spirit searches all things, even the deep things of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.11'>For who, of men, knows the thoughts of a man, except the spirit of man which is in him: so, also, the thoughts of God no man knows, but the Spirit of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.12'>Now, we have received, not the spirit of the world, but the Spirit which comes from God, that we might know the things which are gifted to us by God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.13'>Which things, also, we speak, not in words, taught by human wisdom; but in words taught by the Spirit, explaining spiritual things in spiritual words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.14'>Now, an animal man receives not the thing of the Spirit of God: for they are foolishness to him; neither can he know them, because they are spiritually examined.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.15'>But the spiritual man examines, indeed, all things, yet he is examined by no one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.2.16'>For what animal man has known the mind of the Lord, who will instruct him? But we have the mind of Christ.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.3'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.1'>Now, I, brethren, could not speak to you as to spiritual, but as to fleshly men, even as to babes in Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.2'>Milk I gave you-not meat; for you were not then able to receive it: nay, neither yet now are you able, because you are still fleshly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.3'>For, whereas, among you, envying, and strife, and divisions subsist; are you not fleshly, and walk after the manner of men?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.4'>Besides, while one says, I, indeed, am of Paul; and another, I of Apollos, are you not fleshly?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.5'>For who is Paul, and who is Apollos; but ministers, by whom you have believed, even as the Lord has given to each?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.6'>I have planted, Apollos has watered; but God has made to grow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.7'>So that neither the planter is anything, nor the waterer; but God, who makes to grow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.8'>However, the planter and the waterer are one, and each shall receive his proper reward, according to his proper labor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.9'>Wherefore, we are joint laborers, employed by God. You are God's field; you are God's building.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.10'>According to the favor of God, which is given to me as a skillful architect, I have laid the foundation, and another builds upon it. But let every one take heed how he builds on it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.11'>For other foundation no one can lay, except what is laid, which is Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.12'>Now if any one build on this foundation, gold, silver, precious stones, wood, hay, stubble;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.13'>every one's work shall be made manifest: for the say will make it plain, because it is revealed by fire; and so the fire will try every one's work, of what sort it is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.14'>If the work of any one remain, which he has built upon the foundation: he shall receive a reward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.15'>If the work of any one shall be burnt, he will suffer loss: himself, however, shall be saved, yet so as through a fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.16'>Do you not know that you are the temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwells among you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.17'>If any one destroy the temple of God, him will God destroy; for the temple of God is holy, which temple you are.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.18'>Let no one deceive himself. If any one among you think to be wise in this age, let him become a fool, that he may be wise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.19'>«For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God; for it is written,» 'He entangled the wise in their own craftiness.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.20'>«And again,» 'The Lord knows the reasonings of the wise, that they are vain.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.21'>Wherefore, let no man boast in men; for all things are yours:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.22'>whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or things present, or things to come-all are yours;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.3.23'>and you are Christ's, and Christ is God's.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.4'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.1'>So, then, let a man consider us as servants only of Christ, and stewards of the secrets of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.2'>Now, it is required in stewards, that every one be found faithful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.3'>Therefore, to me it is a very small matter that I be condemned by you, or by human judgment, seeing I do not condemn myself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.4'>For I am conscious to myself of no fault. However, I am not by this justified; but he who judges me is the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.5'>Wherefore, do not, before the time, pass any judgment, till the Lord come; who both will bring to light the hidden things of darkness, and lay open the counsels of the hearts; and then praise shall be to every one from God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.6'>Now, these things, brethren, I have figuratively applied to myself, and Apollos, for your sakes, that by us you may learn not to esteem teachers above what has been written, that no one of you may, on account of one teacher, be puffed up against another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.7'>Besides, who makes you to differ? For what have you which you did not receive? And now, if you did receive it, why do you boast as not receiving it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.8'>Now you are filled! now you are become rich! you have reigned without it! and I wish, indeed, you had reigned, that we also might reign with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.9'>For I think that God has set forth us, the Apostles, last, as persons appointed to death; because we are made a spectacle to the world, even to angels, and to men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.10'>We are fools on account of Christ; but you are wise in Christ: we are weak, but you are strong: you are honored, but we are despised.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.11'>To the present hour we both hunger and thirst, and are naked, and are buffeted, and have no certain dwelling place,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.12'>and labor, working with our own hands: when reviled, we bless: when persecuted, we bear:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.13'>when defamed, we beseech: when we are become as the purgations of the world, the filth of all things until now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.14'>I write not these things to shame you; but, as my beloved children, I instruct you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.15'>For, though you have ten thousand teachers in Christ, yet you have not many fathers; for, to Christ Jesus, through the gospel, I have begotten you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.16'>Wherefore, I beseech you, be imitators of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.17'>For this purpose I have sent to you Timothy, who is my beloved son, and faithful in the Lord: he will put you in mind of my ways, which are in Christ, even as I teach everywhere, in every congregation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.18'>Now, some are puffed up, as if I were not coming to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.19'>But I will come to you soon, if the Lord will, and shall know, not the speech of them who are puffed up, but the power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.20'>For the Reign of God is not in word, but in power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.4.21'>What do you incline? Shall I come to you with a rod, or in love, and in the spirit of meekness?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.5'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.1'>It is generally reported that there is incest among you; and such incest as is not even among the heathens-that one has his father's wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.2'>And you are puffed up, and have not rather bewailed, so that he who has done this work might be taken from among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.3'>Wherefore, I, indeed, as absent in the body yet present in spirit, have already, as present, judged him who committed this act.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.4'>My sentence is this: You being assembled, my spirit also being with you; in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ, with the power of the Lord Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.5'>deliver this very person up to Satan for the destruction of the flesh, that the spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.6'>Your boasting is not becoming. Do you not know, that a little leaven leavens the whole mass?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.7'>Cleanse out, therefore, the old leaven, that you may be a new lump, seeing you are without leaven; for even our passover, Christ is sacrificed for us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.8'>Therefore, let us keep the feast, not with old leaven, neither with the leaven of malice and wickedness: but with unleavened sincerity and truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.9'>I wrote you, in that epistle, not to associate with the vicious;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.10'>but I did not mean in general the fornicators of this world, the avaricious, the rapacious, or the idolaters; seeing, then, indeed, you must go out of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.11'>But now I write to you, if any one, called a brother, be a fornicator, or a covetous person, or an idolater, or a reviler, or a drunkard, or an extortioner; not to associate, not even to eat, with such a person.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.12'>For what have I to do to pronounce sentence on them also who are without? Do not you judge them who are within?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.5.13'>But them are without, God judges. Therefore, put away from among yourselves the wicked person.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.6'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.1'>Dare any of you, having a matter against another, be judged by the unrighteous, and not by the saints?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.2'>Do you not know that the saints are to judge with world? And if the world is to be judged by you, are you unworthy to decide your petty causes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.3'>Do you not know that we are to judge messengers? Why not, then, things pertaining to this life?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.4'>If, then, you have the cognizance of such matters, why do you set those to judge who are of no account in the congregation?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.5'>For shame to you I say it! So, then, there is not among you a wise man; not even one, who shall be able to decide between his brethren!</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.6'>But brother with brother is judged, and that by infidels!</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.7'>Now, therefore, indeed, there is plainly a fault in you, that you have law-suits with one another. Why do you not rather bear the being defrauded?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.8'>But you injure and defraud; and that, too, your own brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.9'>Do you not know that the unrighteous shall not inherit the kingdom of God? Be not deceived: neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor catamites, nor sodomites,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.10'>nor thieves, nor misers, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor extortioners, shall inherit the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.11'>And such were some of you; but you are washed, but you are sanctified, but you are justified, by the name of the Lord Jesus, and by the Spirit of our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.12'>All meats are lawful for me to eat, but all are not proper: all meats are lawful for me to eat; but I will not be enslaved by any meat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.13'>Meats for the belly, and the belly for meats; however, God will destroy both it and them. Now, the body was not made for uncleanness, but for the Lord, and the Lord for the body:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.14'>and God has both raised the Lord, and will raise up us by his own power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.15'>Do you not know that your bodies are members of Christ? Shall, I, then, take the members of Christ and make them the members of a harlot? By no means.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.16'>«What! do you not know that he who is strongly attached to a harlot is one body? for he says,» 'The two shall be one flesh.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.17'>But he, who is strongly attached to the Lord, is one spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.18'>Flee uncleanness. Every sin which a man commits, is without the body: but he who commits uncleanness, sins against his own body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.19'>What! do you not know that your body is the temple of the Holy Spirit, who is in you, whom you have from God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.6.20'>Besides, you are not your own; for you are bought with a price: therefore, with your body glorify God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.7'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.1'>Now, concerning the things of which you wrote me: It is good for a man not to marry a woman.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.2'>Nevertheless, on account of uncleanness, let every man have a wife of his own, and let every woman have her own husband.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.3'>Let the husband fulfill his obligations to his wife: and in like manner, also, the wife to the husband.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.4'>The wife has not the command of her own person, but the husband: and in like manner, also, the husband has not the command of his own person, but the wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.5'>Deprive not one another, unless, perhaps, by consent, for a time, that you may devote yourselves to prayer; and do you come again together, that Satan may not tempt you through your incontinency.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.6'>But this which follows I speak as an advice, and not as an injunction,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.7'>that I wish all men to be as I myself am. However, each has a proper gift from God; one, indeed, after this manner, and another after that.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.8'>I say, to the unmarried men, and to the widows, it is good for them if they can remain even as I do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.9'>Yet, if they can not live continently, let them marry; for it is better to marry than to be in pain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.10'>Now, those who have married I charge, (yet not I, but the Lord;) let not a wife depart from her husband:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.11'>but if she even depart, let her remain unmarried, or be reconciled to her husband; and a husband must not put away his wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.12'>But the rest I command, not the Lord; if any brother have an infidel wife, who herself is well pleased to dwell with him, let him not put her away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.13'>And a woman who has an infidel husband, who himself is well pleased to dwell with her, let her not put him away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.14'>For the infidel husband is sanctified by the wife, and the infidel wife is sanctified by the husband; otherwise, certainly, your children were unclean; whereas, indeed, they are holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.15'>But if the infidel depart, let him depart: the brother or the sister is not in bondage with such; but God has called us to peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.16'>For how do you know, O wife! whether you shall save your husband? And how do you know, O husband! whether you shall save your wife?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.17'>But as God has distributed to every one, and as the Lord has called every one, so let him walk; and so, in all the congregations, I ordain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.18'>Has any circumcised one been called? Let him not be uncircumcised. Has any one been called in uncircumcision? Let him not be circumcised.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.19'>Circumcision is nothing, and uncircumcision is nothing, but the keeping of the commandments of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.20'>Let every one remain in the same calling in which he was called.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.21'>Were you called, being a bondman? Be not careful to be made free. Yet, if you can be made free, prefer it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.22'>For a bondman, who is called by the Lord, is the Lord's freedman. In like manner, also, a freedman who is called, is Christ's bondman.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.23'>You were bought with a price: become not the slaves of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.24'>Brethren, in what state each one was called, in that let him remain with God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.25'>Now, concerning virgins, I have not a commandment of the Lord: but, I give my judgment, as having obtained mercy of the Lord, to be faithful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.26'>I declare this, then, to be good, on account of the present distress; namely, that it is good for a man who is unmarried, to continue so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.27'>Are you bound to a wife? seek not to be loosed. Are you loosed from a wife? seek not a wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.28'>And yet, if you marry, you have not sinned; and if a virgin marry, she has not sinned: nevertheless, affliction in the flesh such shall have; but I spare you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.29'>Now, this I say, brethren, the time being short, it remains that both they who have wives, should be as not having wives;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.30'>and they who weep, as not weeping; and they who rejoice, as not rejoicing; and they who buy, as not possessing;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.31'>and they who use this world, as not abusing it: for the form of this world passes by.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.32'>Besides, I would have you without anxious care. The unmarried man anxiously cares for the things of the Lord; how he shall please the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.33'>But he who is married, anxiously cares for the things of the world; how he shall please his wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.34'>There is the like difference between the wife and the virgin. The unmarried woman anxiously cares for the things of the Lord; that she may be holy, both in body and spirit: but she who is married, anxiously cares for the things of the world; how she shall please her husband.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.35'>Now, this I say, for your own benefit; not with a view to lay a snare for you, but for that which is becoming, and best adapted to a steady, uninterrupted adherence to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.36'>But if any one thinks he acts improperly toward his virgin, if she be above age, unmarried, and so needs to be married; let him do what she inclines, he does not sin: let such marry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.37'>But he who stands firm in his heart; not having necessity, and has power concerning his own will; and has determined this in his own heart, to keep his virgin, does well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.38'>So, then, even he who gives her in marriage, does well; but he who gives her not in marriage, does better.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.39'>A wife is bound, as long as her husband lives; but if her husband be dead, she is at liberty to be married to whom she pleases; only in the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.7.40'>But she is happier if she continue as she is. This is my opinion; and I think I have the Spirit of God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.8'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.1'>Now, concerning things sacrificed to idols, we know, (for we all have knowledge. Knowledge puffs up, but love builds up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.2'>However, if any one is confident of knowing anything, he has known nothing, yet, as he ought to know.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.3'>But, if any one love God, the same is acknowledged by him.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.4'>Concerning, then, the eating of things sacrificed to idols, we know that an idol is nothing in the world; and that there is no other God but one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.5'>For though, indeed, there are nominal gods, whether in heaven or on earth; (as, indeed, there are many gods, and many lords;)</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.6'>yet, to us, there is but one God, the Father; of whom all things are, and we for him: and one Lord Jesus Christ; by whom all things are, and we by him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.7'>However, this knowledge is not in all: for some, till this hour, in the conscience of the idol, eat it, as a thing sacrificed to the idol; and their conscience, being weak, is defiled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.8'>But meat does not recommend us to God: for neither, if we eat, are we the better; neither, if we do not eat, are we the worse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.9'>Nevertheless, take heed, lest, perhaps, this liberty of yours become a stumbling block to the weak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.10'>For if any one see you, who have knowledge, at table in an idol's temple, will not the conscience of him that is weak, be encouraged to eat things sacrificed to idols?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.11'>and through this, your knowledge, shall the weak brother perish, for whom Christ died?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.12'>And, by thus sinning against the brethren, and wounding their conscience, you sin against Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.8.13'>Wherefore, if meat make my brother stumble, I will never eat flesh, lest I make my brother stumble.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.9'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.1'>Am I not an Apostle? Am I not a freeman? Have I not seen Jesus Christ, our Lord? Are you not my work in the Lord?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.2'>If to others I am not an Apostle, yet, to you, at least, I am; for the seal of my apostleship, are you, in the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.3'>My answer to them who condemn me, is this:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.4'>Have we not liberty to eat, and to drink?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.5'>Have we not liberty to lead about a sister wife, as the other Apostles, and the brethren of the Lord, and Cephas?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.6'>Or, have I, only, and Barnabas, not liberty to forbear working?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.7'>Who, at any time, serves in the wars, on his own charges? Who plants a vineyard, and does not eat the fruit of it? Or who feeds a flock, and does not eat of the milk of the flock?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.8'>Do I speak these things as a man? Or does not the law also say these things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.9'>«For, in the law of Moses it is written,» 'You shall not muzzle the ox treading out the corn.' 'Does God take care of the oxen?'</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.10'>Or, does he command this chiefly for our sakes? For our sakes, certainly, it is written: because, he who plows, ought to plough in hope; and he who threshes in hope, ought to partake of his own hope.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.11'>If we have sown for you spiritual things, is it a great matter, if we shall reap your carnal things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.12'>If others partake of this authority over you, ought not we, rather? Nevertheless, we have not used this power; but we bear all things, that we may not give any hindrance to the gospel of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.13'>Do you not know that they who perform sacred offices, eat from the temple? Do not they who wait at the altar share with the altar?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.14'>So also, the Lord has appointed them who announce the gospel, to live by the gospel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.15'>But I have used none of these privileges; neither have I written these things that it should be done to me: for it were good for me rather to die, than that any one should make my boasting void.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.16'>For when I declared the gospel, I have nothing to boast of; because necessity is laud upon me: yes, woe awaits me if I declare not the gospel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.17'>Now, if I do this willingly, I have a reward; but, if against my will, still I am entrusted with the stewardship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.18'>What, then, is my reward? that, when declaring the gospel, I shall exhibit the gospel of Christ without charge, in order that I may not abuse my power in the gospel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.19'>For, though I be a freeman, with respect to all; I have made myself a servant to all, that I might gain the more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.20'>So, to the Jews, I became as a Jew, that I might gain the Jews: to those under the law, (though not under the law) as under the law, that I might gain those under the law:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.21'>to those without law, as without law, (not being without law to God, but under law to Christ,) that I might gain those that are without law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.22'>To the weak, I became as weak, that I might gain the weak. To all, I have become all things, that, by all means, I might same some.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.23'>Now, this I do for the sake of the gospel, and that I may become a joint partaker of its rewards.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.24'>Do you not know that they who run a race, all run, but one only receives the prize? So run, that you may lay hold of the prize?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.25'>Now, every one who contends is temperate in all things: they, indeed, that they may receive a fading crown; but we, one that does not fade.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.26'>I, therefore, so run, as not out of view. So I fight, not as beating the air:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.9.27'>but, I mortify my body, and keep it in subjection; lest, perhaps, having proclaimed to others, I myself should not be accepted.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.10'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.1'>Now, I would not have you ignorant, brethren, that our fathers were all under the cloud, and all passed through the sea:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.2'>and all were immersed into Moses, in the cloud and in the sea;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.3'>and all did eat the same spiritual meat;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.4'>and all did drink the same spiritual drink; (for they drank of the spiritual rock, which followed them, and that rock was Christ.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.5'>Nevertheless, with the greater part of them, God was not well pleased; for they were cast down in the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.6'>Now, these things have become types to us, in order that we should not be lusters after evil things, even as they lusted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.7'>«Neither be you idolaters, as some of them were; as it is written,» 'The people sat down to eat, and to drink, and rose up to dance.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.8'>Neither let us commit whoredom, as some of them committed whoredom, and fell, in one day, twenty-three thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.9'>Neither let us grievously tempt Christ, as some of them tempted, and perished by serpents.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.10'>Neither murmur you, as even some of the murmured, and perished by the destroyer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.11'>Now, all these things happened to them as types; and are written for our admonition, on whom the ends of the ages are come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.12'>Wherefore, let him who thinks he stands, take heed, lest he fall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.13'>No trial has come upon you but such as belongs to man; and God is faithful, who will not suffer you to be tried above what you are able, but will, with the trial, also make a way to escape, that you may be able to bear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.14'>Wherefore, my beloved, fly from idolatry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.15'>I speak as to wise men; judge you what I say.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.16'>The cup of blessing, which we bless; is it not the joint participation of the blood of Christ? The loaf, which we break; is it not the joint participation of the body of Christ?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.17'>Because there is one loaf, we, the many, are one body: for we all participate of that one loaf.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.18'>Look at Israel after the flesh. Are not they, who eat of the sacrifices, joint partakers of the altar?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.19'>What, then, do I affirm? that an idol is anything, or than an idol sacrifice is anything?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.20'>No. But, that what the heathens sacrifice, they sacrifice to demons, and not to God. Now, I would not have you become joint partakers with the demons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.21'>You can not drink the cup of the Lord and the cup of demons: you can not partake of the table of the Lord, and of the table of demons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.22'>Do we provoke the Lord to jealousy? Are we stronger than he?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.23'>All things are lawful, but all are not expedient; all are lawful, but all do not edify.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.24'>Let no one seek his own, but that of his neighbor, also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.25'>Whatever is sold in the shambles, eat, asking no question on account of conscience;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.26'>«for the earth is the Lord's, and the fullness thereof.»</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.27'>And if any of the unbelievers invite you, and you incline to go, whatever is set before you, eat; asking no question on account of conscience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.28'>But if any one say to you, This is a thing sacrificed to an idol; do not eat, on account of him who showed it, and of conscience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.29'>Now, I say conscience, not your own, but that of the other. But why is my liberty judged by another's conscience?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.30'>But if, by favor, I be a partaker, why am I evil spoken of, for that for which I give thanks?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.31'>Whether, then, you eat or drink, or whatever you do, do all to the glory of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.32'>Be no occasion of stumbling; neither to the Jews, nor to the Greeks, nor to the congregation of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.10.33'>Even as I please all men in all things; not seeking my own advantage, but that of the many, that they may be saved.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.11'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.1'>Become imitators of me, even as I also am of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.2'>Now I praise you, brethren; because, in all things you remember me, and hold fast the traditions as I delivered them to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.3'>But I would have you know, that the head of every man is Christ; and the head of the woman is the man; and the head of Christ is God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.4'>Every man who prays, or prophesies, having his head covered, dishonors his head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.5'>And every woman who prays, or prophesies, with her head uncovered, dishonors her head. Besides, it is one and the same, with being shaved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.6'>Wherefore, if a woman be not veiled, even let her be shorn: but, if it be shame for a woman to be shorn or shaved, let her be veiled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.7'>Now, man, indeed, ought not to cover the head, being the image and glory of God, but woman is the glory of man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.8'>Besides the man is not of the woman; but the woman is of the man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.9'>And, also, the man was not created for the woman, but the woman for the man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.10'>For this reason, ought the woman to have a vail on her head, on account of the messengers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.11'>However, neither is the man, without the woman, nor the woman without the man, in the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.12'>Besides, as the woman is from the man, so also, the man is by the woman; but all from God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.13'>Judge in yourselves, is it decent that a woman pray to God unveiled?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.14'>Does not even nature itself teach you that if, indeed, a man have long hair, it is a disgrace to him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.15'>But if a woman have long hair, it is a glory to her: for her hair is given to her for a vail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.16'>However, if any one resolve to be contentious, we have no such custom; neither the congregations of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.17'>Now, in declaring this, that you come together, not for the better, but for the worse, I do not praise you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.18'>For, first, indeed, I hear, that when you come together in the congregation, there are schisms among you; and I partly believe it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.19'>For there must even be sects among you, that the approved among you may be made manifest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.20'>But your coming together into one place, is not to eat the Lord's supper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.21'>For, in eating it, every one takes first his own supper; and one, indeed, is hungry, and another is filled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.22'>What! have you not houses, to eat and to drink in? or, do you despise the congregation of God and put to shame those who have not? What shall I say to you? Shall I praise you? In this, I praise you not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.23'>For I received from the Lord what, also, I delivered to you; that the Lord Jesus, in the night in which we was betrayed, took a loaf;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.24'>and, having given thanks, he broke it; and said, Take, eat; this is my body, which is broken for you: do this in remembrance of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.25'>In like manner, also, the cup, after he had supped; saying, This cup is the new institution in my blood: do this, as often as you drink it, in remembrance of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.26'>For as often as you eat this loaf, and drink this cup, you openly publish the death of the Lord, until he come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.27'>So, then, whosoever shall eat this loaf, and drink this cup of the Lord unworthily, shall be guilty of the body and blood of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.28'>But let a man examine himself, and then let him eat of the loaf, and drink of the cup.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.29'>For he who eats and drinks unworthily, eats and drinks judgment to himself, not distinguishing the body of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.30'>For this cause, many among you are weak and sick, and a considerable number are fallen asleep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.31'>But if we would judge ourselves, we should not be judged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.32'>Yet, when we are judged by the Lord, we are corrected, that we may not be condemned with the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.33'>Wherefore, my brethren, when you come together to eat, wait for each other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.11.34'>And if any one hunger, let him eat at home, that you may not come together for judgment. And the other things I will set in order when I come.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.12'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.1'>Now, concerning spiritual gifts, brethren, I would not have you ignorant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.2'>You know that you were Gentiles, led away to dumb idols, even as you happened to be led.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.3'>Wherefore, I inform you, that no one, speaking by the Spirit of God, pronounces Jesus accursed; and, that no one can declare Jesus Lord, except by the Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.4'>Now, there are diversities of gifts, but the same spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.5'>And there are diversities of ministries, but the same Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.6'>And there are diversities of operations, but the same God, who works all in all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.7'>And to each is given this manifestation of the Spirit, for the advantage of all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.8'>For to one, indeed, is given, by the Spirit, the word of wisdom: and to another, the word of knowledge, according to the same Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.9'>And to another, faith, by the same Spirit: and to another, healing, by the same Spirit:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.10'>and to another, the operations of powers: and to another, prophecy: and to another, diverse kinds of foreign tongues: and to another, the interpretation of foreign tongues.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.11'>Now, all these does the one and the same Spirit effectively work; distributing to each, respectively, as he pleases.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.12'>For, as the body is one, although it have many members; and all the members of that one body, being many, are one body, so also is Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.13'>For, indeed, by one Spirit, we all have been immersed into one body; whether Jews or Greeks, whether slaves or freemen; and all have been made to drink of one Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.14'>Since, then, the body is not one member, but many;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.15'>if the foot shall say, Because I am not the hand, I am not of the body; is it, for this, not of the body?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.16'>And if the ear shall say, Because I am not the eye, I am not of the body; is it, for this, not of the body?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.17'>If the whole body were an eye, where were the hearing? If the whole were hearing, where were the smelling?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.18'>But, now, God has placed the members, every one of them, in the body, as he has pleased.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.19'>Besides, if all were one member, where were the body?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.20'>But now, indeed, there are many members, but one body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.21'>Therefore, the eye can not say to the hand, I have no need of you: nor, again, the head to the feet, I have no need of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.22'>Nay, those members of the body which seem to be more feeble, are necessary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.23'>And those which we think are less honorable members of the body, around them we throw more abundant honor; and so our uncomely members have more abundant comeliness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.24'>But, our comely members have no need. However, God has tempered the body together; having given to the member which wants it, more abundant honor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.25'>That there may be no schism in the body; but, that the members may have the very same anxious care, one for another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.26'>So, whether one member suffer, all the members sympathize; or, one member be honored, all the members rejoice together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.27'>Now, you are Christ's body, and members in particular.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.28'>And these, indeed, God has placed in the congregation: first, Apostles; secondly, prophets; thirdly, teachers; next, powers; then, gifts of healing; helpers, directors, kinds of foreign languages.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.29'>Are all Apostles? are all prophets? are all teachers? have all powers?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.30'>have all the gift of healing? do all speak in foreign languages? do all interpret?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.12.31'>Now, ardently desire the best gifts; and yet I show you a more excellent way.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.13'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.1'>Though I could speak with the tongues of men, of angels, but have not love, I become as sounding brass, or a noisy cymbal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.2'>And though I have prophecy, and know all secrets, and all knowledge; and though I have all faith, so as to remove mountains, but have not love, I am nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.3'>And though I spend all my goods in feeding the poor, and though I deliver my body to be burned, but have not love, I am nothing profited.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.4'>Love suffers long, and is kind. Love envies not. Love does not vaunt; is not puffed up;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.5'>does not behave itself unbecomingly; does not seek its own things; is not exasperated; does not imagine evil;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.6'>does not rejoice in iniquity, but greatly rejoices in the truth:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.7'>covers all things, believes all things, hopes all things, endures all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.8'>Love never fails: but, whether prophecies, they will be out of use: or foreign languages, they shall cease: or science, it shall be abolished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.9'>For we know only in part, and prophesy in part.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.10'>But when perfection is come, then what is in part will be done away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.11'>When I was a child, I spoke as a child, I conceived as a child, I reasoned as a child. But when I became a man, I put away childish things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.12'>For now we seek through a glass obscurely; but then, face to face: now, I know in part; but then, I shall fully know, even as I am fully known.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.13.13'>And now abide faith, hope, love, these three: but the greatest of these is love.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.14'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.1'>Pursue love, and earnestly desire spiritual gifts; but especially that you may prophesy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.2'>For he who speaks in a foreign language, speaks not to men, but to God; for no one understands him: nevertheless, by the Spirit he speaks secrets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.3'>But he who prophesies, speaks to men for edification, and exhortation, and consolation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.4'>He who speaks in a foreign language, edifies himself: but he who prophesies, edifies the congregation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.5'>I wish, indeed, that you all spoke in foreign languages; but rather that you prophesied: for greater is he who prophesies, than he who speaks in foreign languages, unless, indeed, he interpret, that the congregation may receive edification.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.6'>For now, brethren, if I should come to you speaking in foreign languages, what shall I profit you, unless I shall speak to you intelligibly; either by revelation, or by knowledge, or by prophecy, or by doctrine?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.7'>In like manner, things without life, giving sound; whether pipe, or harp; unless they give a difference to the notes, how shall it be known what is piped, or harped?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.8'>And, therefore, if the trumpet give and unintelligible sound, who will prepare himself for battle?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.9'>So, also, you, unless with the tongue you give intelligible speech, how shall it be known what is spoken? Therefore, you will be speaking to the air.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.10'>There are, perhaps, so many kinds of languages in the world, and none of them is without signification.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.11'>Yet, if I do not know the meaning of the language, I shall be to him who speaks, a foreigner; and he who speaks, will be a foreigner to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.12'>Wherefore, you, also, since you are earnestly desirous of spiritual gifts, seek them, that you may abound for the edification of the congregation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.13'>For which cause, let him who prays in a foreign language, pray that he may interpret.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.14'>For if I pray in a foreign language, my spirit prays; but my understanding is unfruitful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.15'>What, then, is to be done? I will pray with the Spirit, but I will pray also with understanding: I will sing with the Spirit; but I will sing also with understanding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.16'>Else, when you shall bless with the spirit, how shall he who fills up the place of the unlearned, say the Amen to your thanksgiving, since he knows not what you say?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.17'>For you, indeed, give thanks well; but the other is not edified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.18'>I give thanks to God, speaking in more foreign languages than all of you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.19'>yet, in the congregation, I would rather speak five sentences with my meaning understood, that I may instruct others, also, than ten thousand sentences in a foreign language.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.20'>Brethren, be not children in understanding; but in evil be children, and in understanding be full grown men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.21'>«In the law it is written,» 'Surely, with other tongues, and with other lips, I will speak to this people; yet not even then will they hearken to me, says the Lord.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.22'>So that foreign languages are for a sign; not to believers, but to unbelievers: but prophecy is for a sign; not to unbelievers, but to believers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.23'>If, then, the whole congregation be come together in one place, and all speak in foreign languages; and there come in unlearned persons, or unbelievers, will they not say that you are mad?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.24'>But if all prophesy, and there come in an unbeliever, or an unlearned person, he is corrected by all, he is examined by all;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.25'>the hidden things of his heart are made manifest: and so, falling on his face, he will worship God, publishing that God is actually among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.26'>What is it, then, brethren? When you are come together, each of you has a psalm, has a discourse, has a foreign language, has a revelation, has an interpretation! Let all things be done to edification.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.27'>And if any one speak in a foreign language, let it be by two, or at most by three sentences, and separately; and let one interpret.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.28'>But if there be no interpreter, let him be silent in the congregation; yet let him speak to himself and to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.29'>Now, let two or three prophets speak, and let the others judge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.30'>But, if to another, sitting by, anything be revealed, let the first be silent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.31'>For you all can prophesy, one by one, that all may learn, and all may be comforted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.32'>For the spirits of the prophets are subject to the prophets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.33'>Besides, God is not the author of confusion, but of peace. As in all the assemblies of the saints,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.34'>let your women be silent in the congregations: for it has not been permitted to them to speak, but they must be in subjection; as the law also commands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.35'>And if they wish to learn anything, let them ask their own husbands, at home: for it is an indecent thing for women to speak in the congregation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.36'>What! went the word of God forth from you? or did it come to you only?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.37'>If any one be really a prophet, or spiritual person, let him acknowledge the things I write to you, that they are the commandments of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.38'>And if any one be ignorant, let him be ignorant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.39'>Wherefore, brethren, earnestly desire to prophesy; and hinder not to speak in foreign languages.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.14.40'>Let all things be done decently and in order.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.15'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.1'>Now I declare to you, brethren, the glad tidings which I announced to; which, also, you have received, and in which you stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.2'>By which, also, you are saved, if you retain those joyful tidings which I delivered to you; unless you believed to no purpose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.3'>For I delivered to you, among the first things, what also I received first-that Christ died for our sins, according to the scriptures;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.4'>and that he was buried; and that he rose again the third day, according to the scriptures;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.5'>and that he was seen by Cephas, then by the twelve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.6'>After that, he was seen by above five hundred brethren at once; of whom the greater part remain to this present time, but some are fallen asleep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.7'>After that, he was seen by James; then, by all the Apostles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.8'>And, last of all he was seen by me, as by one born out of due time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.9'>For I am the least of the Apostles; who am not worthy to be called an Apostle, because I persecuted the congregation of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.10'>But, by the favor of God, I am what I am: and his favor which was bestowed on me, was not vain; for I have labored more abundantly than all of them; yet not I, but the favor of God, which is with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.11'>Well, then, whether I or they, so we proclaim, and so you believed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.12'>Now, if it be proclaimed that Christ was raised from the dead, how is it that some among you say, that there is no resurrection of the dead?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.13'>For if there be no resurrection of the dead, neither has Christ been raised.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.14'>And if Christ has not been raised, vain, certainly, is our proclamation, and vain, also, is your faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.15'>Besides, we are found even false witnesses concerning God; because we have witnessed, with respect to God, that he raised Christ; whom he raised not, if, indeed, the dead are not raised.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.16'>And if the dead are not raised, neither has Christ been raised,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.17'>Farther, if Christ has not been raised, your faith is useless; you are still in your sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.18'>Certainly, also, they who are fallen asleep in Christ are perished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.19'>If in this life, only, we have hope in Christ, we are, of all men, the most miserable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.20'>But now Christ is raised from the dead, -the first fruit of them who have fallen asleep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.21'>For since through a man came death, through a man also comes the resurrection of the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.22'>Therefore, as by Adam all die, so also by Christ all shall be made alive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.23'>But every one in his own rank: Christ the first fruit; they that are Christ's, afterward, at his coming.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.24'>Then comes the end, when he shall resign the kingdom to God, even the Father; when he shall have abolished all government, and all authority, and power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.25'>For he must reign till he has put all the enemies under his feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.26'>The last enemy, Death, shall be destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.27'>For he has subjected all things under his feet. Now when it says that all things are subjected, it is manifest that he is excepted, who has subjected all things to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.28'>Now, when all things are subjected to him, then even the Son himself shall be subjected to him, who subjected all things to him, that God may be all in all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.29'>Otherwise, what shall they do, who are immersed for the dead, if the dead rise not at all? why then are they immersed for them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.30'>And why do we endanger ourselves every hour?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.31'>I solemnly declare, by your rejoicing, what I also have in Christ Jesus our Lord, that every day I die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.32'>If, after the manner of men, I have fought with wild beasts at Ephesus, what is the advantage to me, if the dead rise not? Let us eat and drink, for tomorrow we die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.33'>Be not deceived: evil communications corrupt good manners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.34'>Awake up as you ought, and sin not; for some of you have not the knowledge of God. For shame to you, I say it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.35'>But some one will say, How can the dead be raised up? and with what kind of body do they come?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.36'>Simpleton! what you sow is not made alive, except it die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.37'>And as to what you sow, you do not show the body which shall be produced, but the naked grain; it may be of wheat, or of any other kind:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.38'>but God gives it a body, as it has pleased him; and to each of the seeds, its proper body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.39'>All flesh is not the same flesh: but there is, indeed, one flesh of men, and another of beasts, and another of fishes, and another of fowls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.40'>And there are bodies celestial, and bodies terrestrial: but different, indeed, is the glory of the celestial, and that of the terrestrial.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.41'>The glory of the sun is one, and the glory of the moon is another, and the glory of the stars another; moreover, star excels star in glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.42'>Just so is the resurrection of the dead. It is sown in corruption-it is raised in incorruption:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.43'>it is sown in dishonor-it is raised in glory: it is sown in weakness-it is raised in power:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.44'>it is sown an animal body-it is raised a spiritual body. There is an animal body, and there is a spiritual body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.45'>«For thus it is written,» 'The first man, Adam, was made a living soul-the last Adam, a vivifying spirit.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.46'>However, that was not first, which is spiritual; but that which is animal, and then that which is spiritual.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.47'>The first man, from the earth, was earthy; the second man is the Lord from heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.48'>As was the earthy, so also are the earthy; and as is the heavenly, such also shall be heavenly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.49'>For, as we have borne the image of the earthy, we shall also bear the image of the heavenly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.50'>And this I affirm, brethren, that flesh and blood can not inherit the kingdom of God; neither can corruption inherit incorruption.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.51'>Behold, I tell you a secret: we shall not, indeed, all die; but we shall all be changed;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.52'>in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, at the last trumpet; for it shall sound, and then the dead shall be raised incorruptible; and we shall be changed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.53'>For this corruptible body, must put on incorruption; and this mortal body must put on immortality.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.54'>«Now, when this corruptible body shall have put on incorruption, and this mortal body shall have put on immortality, then that saying of scripture shall be accomplished,» 'Death is swallowed up forever.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.55'>Death! where is thy sting? Hades! where is thy victory?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.56'>For the sting of death is sin, and the strength of sin is the law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.57'>Now thanks be to God, who gives us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.15.58'>Wherefore, my beloved brethren, be stable, unmoved; abounding in the work of the Lord at all times, knowing that your labor is not vain in the Lord.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Cor.16'>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.1'>Now, concerning the collection, which is for the saints; as I ordered the congregations of Galatia, so also so you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.2'>On the first say of the week, let each of you lay somewhat by itself, according as he may have prospered, putting it into the treasury; that when I come, there may be then no collection.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.3'>And when I come, whomsoever you shall approve by letters, them I will send to carry your gift to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.4'>Or, if it be proper that even I should go, they shall go with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.5'>Now, I will come to you, when I have passed through Macedonia, (for I do pass through Macedonia;)</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.6'>and, perhaps, I shall abide, and even winter with you, that you may send me forward, whithersoever I may go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.7'>For I will not now see you in passing; but I hope to remain with you sometime, if the Lord permit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.8'>However, I shall remain at Ephesus till Pentecost.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.9'>For a great and effectual door is opened to me, yet there are many opposers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.10'>Now, if Timothy be come, take care that he be among you without fear; for he works, even as I do, the work of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.11'>Wherefore, let no one despise him; but send him forward in peace, that he may come to me; for I expect him with the brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.12'>And with relation to our brother Apollos, I entreated him much to go to you with the brethren; but his inclination was not at all to go now, but he will go when he shall find a convenient season.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.13'>Watch; stand fast in the faith; acquit yourselves like men; be strong.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.14'>Let all things be done with love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.15'>You know the family of Stephanus, that it is the first fruit of Achaia, and that they have devoted themselves to the ministry of the saints.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.16'>I entreat you, therefore, brethren, that you submit yourselves to such, and to every joint worker and laborer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.17'>I am glad of the coming of Stephanus, and Fortunatus, and Achaicus; for they have supplied your deficiency,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.18'>and have refreshed my spirit and yours; wherefore, acknowledge such persons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.19'>The congregations of Asia salute you. Aquila and Priscilla salute you much in the Lord, with the congregation which is in their house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.20'>All the brethren salute you. Salute one another with a holy kiss.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.21'>The salutation of Paul with my own hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.22'>If any one love not the Lord Jesus Christ, he shall be accursed when the Lord comes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.23'>The favor of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Cor.16.24'>My love be with you all in Christ Jesus. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>