<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='LONT' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='LONT'>
        <title>Living Oracles NT</title>
        <contributor>George Campbell, James Macknight, Philip Doddridge. Ed. Alexander Campbell.</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>Holy Bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>[Alexander Campbell's Living Oracles,]
The Sacred Writings of the Apostles and Evangelists of Jesus Christ, Commonly Styled the New Testament. 
Translated from the Original Greek.
MDCCCXXXV. 1835</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>LONT</identifier>
        <source>http://www.e-sword.net/usermods/bbl/Living%20Oracles%20New%20Testament%20(LONT)%20(1835).exe</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='1Pet'>
      <chapter osisID='1Pet.1'>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.1'>Peter, an Apostle of Jesus Christ, to the elect sojourners of the dispersion, of Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia-</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.2'>according to the predetermination of God the Father, by a sanctification of the Spirit, in order to obedience, and sprinkling of the blood of Jesus Christ: Favor and peace be multiplied to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.3'>Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who, according to his great mercy, has regenerated us to a lively hope, through the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.4'>to an inheritance incorruptible and undefiled, and unfading, preserved in the heavens for us;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.5'>who, by the power of God, are guarded through faith, to the salvation prepared to be revealed in the last time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.6'>On account of this, be exceeding glad, though now, for a little while, (since it is needful,) you are made sorry by divers trials;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.7'>that the trying of your faith, (much more precious than of gold, which perishes, though proved by fire,) may be found to praise, and honor, and glory, at the revelation of Jesus Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.8'>whom, not having seen, you love; on whom, not now looking, but believing, you greatly rejoice, with joy unspeakable and full of glory-</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.9'>receiving the consummation of your faith, even the salvation of your souls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.10'>Concerning which salvation, the prophets inquired accurately, and searched diligently, who have prophesied concerning the favor bestowed on you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.11'>searching diligently of what things, and what kind of time, the Spirit of Christ, who was in them, did signify, when he testified before the sufferings of Christ, and the glories following these-</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.12'>to whom it was revealed, that, not for themselves, but for us, they ministered these things; which have now been reported to you, by them who have declared the glad tidings to you, with the Holy Spirit sent down from heaven: into which things, angels earnestly desire to look attentively.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.13'>Wherefore, having the loins of your mind girded, being vigilant, constantly hope for the gift to be brought to you, at the revelation of Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.14'>As obedient children, not fashioning yourselves according to the former lusts, in your ignorance;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.15'>but as he who has called you is holy, be you also holy;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.16'>«for it is written,» 'Be you holy, because I am holy.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.17'>And seeing you call on the Father, who, without respect of persons, judges according to every man's work-pass the time of your sojourning here, in fear;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.18'>knowing that, not with corruptible things, as silver and gold, you were redeemed from your foolish behavior, delivered to you by your fathers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.19'>but with the precious blood of Christ, as of a lamb without blemish, and without spot;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.20'>predetermined, indeed, before the foundation of the world, but manifested in these last times for you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.21'>who through him, believe in God, who raised him up from the dead, and gave him glory, that your faith and hope might be in God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.22'>Wherefore, having purified your souls by obeying the truth, through the Spirit, to unfeigned brotherly love, love one another, from a pure heart, fervently:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.23'>having been regenerated, not of corruptible seed, but of incorruptible, through the word of the living God, which remains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.24'>«For all flesh is as grass, and all the glory of man as the flower of grass. The grass withers, and the flower of it falls down; but the word of the Lord remains forever.»</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.25'>Now this is that word which has been proclaimed as glad tidings to you.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Pet.2'>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.1'>Wherefore, laying aside all malice, and all guile and hypocrisies, and envyings, and all evil speaking;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.2'>as newborn babes, earnestly desire the unadulterated milk of the word, that you may grow by it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.3'>Because, indeed, you have tasted that the Lord is good;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.4'>to whom coming, as to a living stone, rejected indeed by men, but chosen by God, and precious;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.5'>you, also, as living stones, are built up a spiritual temple, a holy priesthood, to offer spiritual sacrifices, most acceptable to God, through Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.6'>«Wherefore, it is contained in the scripture,» 'Behold I lay in Zion a chief corner stone, elect, precious: whoever trusts in it, shall not be ashamed.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.7'>To you, then, who trust, it is precious; but to unbelieving- a stone which the builders rejected, which has become the head of the corner-</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.8'>a stone of stumbling, and a rock of offense. Those who stumble at the word, are disobedient unbelievers, to which, therefore, they were appointed:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.9'>but you are an elect race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a purchased people; that you should declare the perfections of him who has called you from darkness into his marvelous light:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.10'>who formerly were not a people, but now are a people of God; who had not obtained mercy, but now have obtained mercy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.11'>Beloved, I beseech you, as sojourners and travelers, abstain from fleshly lusts, which war against the soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.12'>Have your behavior comely, among the Gentiles, that, whereas, they speak against you, as evil doers, having beheld your good works, they may glorify God, in the day of visitation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.13'>Be subject, therefore, to every human establishment for the Lord's sake; whether to the king, as supreme;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.14'>or to governor, as those sent by him for the punishment, indeed, of evil doers; but for the praise of them who do good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.15'>For so is the will of God, that, by doing good, you put to silence the ignorance of foolish men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.16'>Live as freemen, yet do not use your freedom as a covering of wickedness; but as the servants of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.17'>Treat all men with respect: love the brotherhood: fear God: honor the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.18'>Let household servants be subject to their masters, with all reverence; not only to the good and gentle, but also to the froward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.19'>For this is acceptable, if any one, from conscience of God, sustain sorrows, suffering unjustly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.20'>But what praise is due, if, when you commit faults and are buffeted, you bear it patiently? Yet if, when you do well, and suffer, you bear it patiently, this is acceptable with God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.21'>Besides, to this you were called; for even Christ suffered for us, leaving us a pattern, that you should follow his footsteps;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.22'>who did not sin, neither was guile found in his mouth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.23'>who, when he was reviled, did not revile in return; when he suffered he did not threaten, but committed his cause to him who judges righteously-</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.24'>who himself bore away our sins in his own body, on the tree; that we, being freed from sins, should live to righteousness; by whose stripes you are healed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.25'>For you were as sheep going astray, but are now returned to the Shepherd, and Overseer of your souls.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Pet.3'>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.1'>In like manner, let the wives be in subjection to their own husbands; that, indeed, if any obey not the word, they, without the word, may be won by the behavior of their wives,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.2'>(when they behold you chaste behavior, joined with reverence:)</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.3'>whose adorning, let it not be that which is external-the plaiting of hair, trinkets of gold, or finery of dress;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.4'>but-the hidden man of the heart, with the incorruptible ornament of a meek and quiet spirit, which, in the sight of God, is of great value.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.5'>For thus, anciently, the holy women, also, who trusted in God, adorned themselves, being in subjection to their own husbands;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.6'>even as Sarah obeyed Abraham, calling him Lord; whose daughters you are become, doing well, and not fearing any terror.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.7'>In like manner, husbands, dwell with your wives according to knowledge, giving honor to the wife, as the weaker vessel, and as joint heirs of the favor of life, that your prayers be not hindered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.8'>Finally, be all of one mind, sympathizing, lovers of the brethren, tender-hearted, courteous-</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.9'>not returning evil for evil, or railing for railing; but, on the contrary, bless: knowing that to this you were called, that you might inherit the blessing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.10'>«For he who is desirous to enjoy life, and to see good days, let him restrain his tongue from evil, and his lips from speaking deceit.»</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.11'>Let him turn away from evil, and do good; let him turn away from evil, and do good; let him seek peace, and pursue it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.12'>«For the eyes of the Lord are upon the righteous, and his ears are open to their supplication; but the face of the Lord is against the workers of iniquity.»</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.13'>Besides, who is he that will do evil to you, if you be imitators of the Good One?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.14'>Nevertheless, although you even suffer for righteousness' sake, you are happy. Therefore, do not fear their fear, neither be troubled:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.15'>but sanctify the Lord God in your hearts; and be always prepared for giving an answer, with meekness and reverence, to every one who asks of you a reason for the hope which is in you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.16'>Hold fast a good conscience, that, whereas they speak against you as evil doers, they may be put to shame who arraign your good behavior in Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.17'>For it is better to suffer as well doers, if the will of God appoints it, than as evil doers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.18'>For even Christ once suffered for sins, the just for the unjust, that he might bring us to God; being put to death, indeed, in the flesh, but made alive by the Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.19'>By which, also, he made proclamation to the spirits in prison,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.20'>who formerly were disobedient, when the patience of God once waited, in the days of Noah, while an ark was preparing, in which few, that is, eight souls, were effectually saved through water-</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.21'>the antitype, immersion, does, also, now save us, (not putting away the filth of the flesh; but seeking of a good conscience toward God,) by the resurrection of Jesus Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.22'>who, having gone into heaven, is at the right hand of God; angels, and authorities, and powers, being subjected to him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Pet.4'>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.1'>Christ, then, having suffered for us in the flesh, do you also warm yourselves with the same mind: for he who has suffered in the flesh, has ceased from sin;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.2'>so that he no longer lives his remaining time in the flesh, to the lusts of men, but to the will of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.3'>For the time which has passed of life, is sufficient to have wrought the will of the Gentiles, having walked in lasciviousness, lusts, excesses in wine, revellings, carousals, and abominable idolatries.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.4'>On which account they wonder that you do not run with them, into the same sink of debauchery, reviling you,-</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.5'>who shall give account to him who is prepared to judge the living and the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.6'>For, to this end of the gospel was preached to the dead, that they might, indeed, be judged according to men in the flesh, but live according to God in the spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.7'>Now the end of all things has approached; be, therefore, sober, and watch to prayer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.8'>And above all things, have fervent love to one another; for love will cover a multitude of sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.9'>Be hospitable to one another, without murmurings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.10'>Let every one, according as he has received a gift, minister it to the others, as good stewards of the manifold favor of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.11'>If any one speak, let him speak as the oracles of God: if any one minister, let him do it as from the strength which God supplies; that in all things God may be glorified through Jesus Christ, to whom be the glory and the power for ever and ever. Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.12'>Beloved, wonder not at the fiery trial among you, which is come upon you for a trial, as if some strange thing happened to you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.13'>but, seeing you partake of the sufferings of Christ, rejoice: that, also, at the revelation of his glory you may rejoice, with exceeding great joy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.14'>If you be reproached for the name of Christ, you are happy; because the Spirit of glory and of God rests upon you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.15'>By them, indeed, he is evil spoken of, but by you he is glorified. Wherefore, let none of you suffer as a murderer, or a thief, or a malefactor, or as a meddling person.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.16'>However, if any one suffer as a Christian, let him not be ashamed, but let him even glorify God on that account.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.17'>Indeed, the time is come that punishment must begin at the house of God; and if it begin first at us, what the end of them who do not obey the gospel of God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.18'>And, if the righteous with difficulty escape, where will the ungodly and the sinner appear!</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.19'>Wherefore, then, let those who suffer by the will of God, commit their own lives to him in well doing, as a faithful Creator.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Pet.5'>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.1'>The seniors who are among you, I exhort, who am also a senior, and a witness of the sufferings of Christ, and also a partaker of the glory which is to be revealed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.2'>Feed the flock of God, which is with you; exercising the overseer's office, not by constraint, but willingly; neither for the sake of sordid gain, but from good disposition;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.3'>neither as lording it over the heritage of God, but, being patterns to the flock:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.4'>and when the Chief Shepherd shall appear, you shall receive the crown of glory which fades not away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.5'>For the like reason, you younger persons subject yourselves to the seniors. Yes, all be subject to one another, and be clothed with humility, for God resists the proud but gives favor to the humble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.6'>Be humbled, therefore, under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt you in due time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.7'>Cast all your anxious care on him, because he cares for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.8'>Be sober, be vigilant: your adversary, the devil, is walking about as a roaring lion, seeking whom he may devour:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.9'>whom resist, steadfast in the faith, knowing that the very same sufferings are accomplished in your brethren, who are in the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.10'>And may the God of all favor, who has called us to his eternal glory, by Christ Jesus, after you have suffered a little, himself make you complete; support, strengthen, establish you:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.11'>to him be the glory and dominion for ever and ever. Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.12'>By Sylvanus, a faithful brother, (as I conclude,) I have written to you in few words, exhorting you, and strongly testifying that this is the true favor of God, in which you stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.13'>They at Babylon, elected jointly with you, and Mark, my son, salute you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.14'>Salute one another with a kiss of love. Peace to you all, who are in Christ Jesus.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>