<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='LONT' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='LONT'>
        <title>Living Oracles NT</title>
        <contributor>George Campbell, James Macknight, Philip Doddridge. Ed. Alexander Campbell.</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>Holy Bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>[Alexander Campbell's Living Oracles,]
The Sacred Writings of the Apostles and Evangelists of Jesus Christ, Commonly Styled the New Testament. 
Translated from the Original Greek.
MDCCCXXXV. 1835</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>LONT</identifier>
        <source>http://www.e-sword.net/usermods/bbl/Living%20Oracles%20New%20Testament%20(LONT)%20(1835).exe</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Mark'>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.1'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.1'>The beginning of the gospel of Jesus Christ, Son of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.2'>«As it is written in Isaiah the Prophet,» 'Behold, I send my messenger before thee, who shall prepare thy way:'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.3'>«The voice of one proclaiming in the wilderness, Prepare a way for the Lord, make for him a straight passage:»</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.4'>thus came John immersing in the wilderness, and publishing the immersion of reformation for the remission of sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.5'>And all the country of Judea, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, resorted to him, and were immersed by him in the river Jordan, confessing their sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.6'>Now John's clothing was of camel's hair, tied around his waist with a leather girdle: and he lived upon locusts and wild honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.7'>And he proclaimed, saying, One mightier than I comes after me, whose shoe-latchet I am unworthy to stoop down and untie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.8'>I, indeed, have immersed you in water; but he will immerse you in the Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.9'>At that time Jesus came from Nazareth of Galilee to the Jordan, and was immersed by John.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.10'>As soon as he arose out of the water, he saw the sky part asunder, and the Spirit descend upon him like a dove.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.11'>And a voice from heaven, which said, Thou art my Son, the beloved, in whom I delight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.12'>Immediately after this, the spirit conveyed him into the wilderness;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.13'>and he continued in the wilderness forty days tempted by Satan; and was among the wild beasts; and the heavenly messengers ministered to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.14'>But after John's imprisonment, Jesus went to Galilee, proclaiming the good tidings of the Reign of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.15'>The time, he said, is accomplished, the Reign of God approaches; reform, and believe the good tidings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.16'>Then walking by the sea of Galilee, he saw Simon, and Andrew, Simon's brother, casting a drag net into the sea, for they were fishers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.17'>Jesus said to them, Come with me, and I will cause you to be fishers of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.18'>Immediately they left their nets, and followed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.19'>Passing on a little, and seeing James, son of Zebedee, with John his brother, who were mending their nets in a bark,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.20'>he immediately called them; and leaving their father Zebedee in the bark with the hired servants, they accompanied him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.21'>And they went to Capernaum; and on the Sabbath he repaired directly to the synagogue, and instructed the people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.22'>who were filled with admiration at his manner of teaching; for he taught as one having authority, and not as the scribes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.23'>Now there was in their synagogue a man possessed with an unclean spirit, who cried out,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.24'>Ah! Jesus of Nazareth, what hast thou to do with us? Art thou come to destroy us? I know who thou art, the Holy One of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.25'>Jesus rebuking him, said, Be silent, and come out of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.26'>Then the unclean spirit threw him into convulsions; and, raising loud cried, came out of him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.27'>at which they were all so amazed, that they asked one another, What does this mean? For he commands with authority even the unclean spirits, and they obey him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.28'>And thenceforth his fame spread through all the region of Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.29'>As soon as they were come out of the synagogue, they went with James and John into the house of Simon and Andrew,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.30'>where Simon's wife's mother lay sick of a fever, of which they immediately acquainted Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.31'>And he came, and taking her by the hand, raised her; instantly the fever left her, and she entertained them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.32'>In the evening, after sunset, they brought to him all the sick, and the demoniacs;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.33'>the whole city being assembled at the door.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.34'>And he healed many persons affected with various diseases, and expelled many demons, whom he permitted not to speak, because they knew him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.35'>On the morrow, having risen before dawn, he went out, and retired to a solitary place, and prayed there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.36'>And Simon and his company went in quest of him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.37'>and having found him, said to him, Every person seeks you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.38'>Jesus said, Let us go to the neighboring boroughs, to make proclamation there also: for I came out with this design.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.39'>Accordingly he proclaimed in their synagogues throughout all Galilee, and expelled demons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.40'>And a leper came to him, and on his knees entreated him, saying, If you will, you can cleanse me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.41'>Jesus had compassion, and stretching out his hand and touching him, said, I will, be you clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.42'>This he had no sooner uttered, than the leprosy departed from the man, and he was cleansed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.43'>Then Jesus strictly charging him, and dismissing him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.44'>said, See you tell nothing of this to any man; but go, show yourself to the priest; and offer for your cleansing the things prescribed by Moses, that it may be notified to the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.45'>But the man, as soon as he was gone, began to blaze this story, talking openly everywhere, insomuch that Jesus could no longer publicly appear in the city; but remained without in solitary places, whither the people resorted to him from all parts.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.2'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.1'>After many days, he returned to Capernaum; and when it was known that he was in the house,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.2'>such a multitude flocked thither, that there was no room for them, not even near the door, and he taught them the word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.3'>A paralytic was then brought, carried by four men,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.4'>who, not being able to come nigh him for the crowd, uncovered the place where Jesus was; and, through the opening, let down the conch, on which the paralytic lay.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.5'>Jesus perceiving their faith, said to the paralytic, Son, your sins are forgiven you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.6'>But certain scribes who were present, reasoned thus within themselves:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.7'>How does this man speak such blasphemies? Who can forgive sins but God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.8'>Jesus, immediately knowing in himself that they made these reflections, said to them, Why do you reason thus within yourselves?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.9'>Which is easier, to say to the paralytic, Your sins are forgiven, or to say, with effect, Arise, take up your couch and walk?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.10'>But that you may know that the Son of Man has power upon the earth to forgive sins, rise, (he said to the paralytic,)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.11'>I command you, take up your couch, and go home.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.12'>Immediately he rose, took up the couch, and walked out before them all; insomuch that they were all amazed, and glorified God, saying, We never saw anything like this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.13'>Again, he went out toward the sea, and all the multitude repaired to him, and he taught them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.14'>Passing along, he saw Levi, son of Alpheus, sitting at the toll office, and said to him, Follow me. And he arose and followed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.15'>Now when Jesus was eating in this man's house, several publicans and sinners placed themselves at table with him and his disciples: for many of these people followed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.16'>The Scribes and the Pharisees, seeing him eat with publicans and sinners, said to his disciples, Wherefore does he eat and drink with publicans and sinners?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.17'>Jesus, hearing this, replied, The whole need not a physician, but the sick. I came not to call the righteous, but sinners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.18'>The disciples of John, and those of the Pharisees, accustomed to fasting, came to him and said, John's disciples, and those of the Pharisees, fast; why do not your disciples fast?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.19'>Jesus answered, Do the bridesmen fast while the bridegroom is with them? While the bridegroom is with them they do not fast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.20'>But the days will come when the bridegroom shall be take from them; and in those days they will fast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.21'>No person sews a piece of undressed cloth on an old garment; otherwise the new patch tears the old cloth, and makes a worse rent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.22'>No person puts new wine into old leather bottles; else the new wine bursts the bottle; and thus both the wine is split, and the bottles are rendered useless; but new wine must be put into new bottles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.23'>Once, when he was going through the corn on the Sabbath, his disciples began to pluck the ears of corn as they went.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.24'>The Pharisees said to him, Why do they that which on the Sabbath, it is unlawful to do?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.25'>He answered, Did you never read what David and his attendants did, in a strait, when they were hungry,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.26'>how he entered the tabernacle of God, in the days of Abiathar the high priest, and eat the loaves of the presence, which none but the priests could lawfully eat, and gave of them also to his attendants?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.27'>He added, The Sabbath was made for man, and not man for the Sabbath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.28'>Therefore the Son of Man is master even of the Sabbath.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.3'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.1'>At another time he entered the synagogue, when a man was there who had a withered hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.2'>And they, with a design to accuse Jesus, watched him, to see whether he would heal the man on the Sabbath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.3'>Jesus said to the man, who had the withered hand, Stand up in the midst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.4'>Then he said to them, Whether it is lawful to do good on the Sabbath, or to do evil-to save, or to kill? But they were silent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.5'>And looking around on them with anger, being grieved for the blindness of their minds, he said to the man, Stretch out your hand: and as he stretched out his hand, it was restored.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.6'>And the Pharisees went out immediately, and conspired with the Herodians against him to destroy him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.7'>But Jesus withdrew with his disciples toward the sea, whither a great multitude followed him from Galilee, from Judea,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.8'>from Jerusalem, from Idumea, and from the banks of the Jordan. They also of the territories of Tyre and Sidon, having heard what wonders he had performed, flocked to him in crowds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.9'>Then he ordered his disciples to get a boat to attend him, because of the multitude, lest they should throng him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.10'>for he had healed many, which made all, who had maladies, press upon him to touch him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.11'>And the unclean spirits, when they beheld him, prostrated themselves before him, crying, Thou art the Son of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.12'>But he strictly charged them not to make him known.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.13'>Afterward Jesus went up a mountain, and called to him whom he would, and they went to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.14'>And he selected twelve, that they might attend him, and that he might commission them to make proclamation;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.15'>empowering them to cure disease; and to expel demons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.16'>These were Simon, whom he surnamed Peter,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.17'>and James, son of Zebedee, and John, the brother of James. These he surnamed Boanerges, that is, sons of thunder;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.18'>and Andrew, and Philip, and Bartholomew, and Matthew, and Thomas, and James son of Alpheus, and Thaddeus, and Simon the Canaanite</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.19'>and Judas Iscariot, who betrayed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.20'>Then they went into a house, whither a crowd again assembled, so that Jesus and his disciples could not so such as eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.21'>His kinsmen hearing this, went out to restrain it, (for they said, He is beside himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.22'>And the scribes who came from Jerusalem, said, He is confederate with Beelzebub, and expels demons by the prince of demons.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.23'>Jesus having called them, said to them by similitudes, How can Satan expel Satan?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.24'>If a kingdom be torn by factions, that kingdom can not subsist.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.25'>And if a family be torn by factions, that family can not subsist.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.26'>Thus, if Satan fight against himself, and be divided, he can not subsist, but is near his end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.27'>No one who enters the strong one's house, can plunder his goods, unless he first overpower the strong one; then, indeed, he may plunder his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.28'>Indeed, I say to you, that though all other sins in the sons of men are pardonable, and whatever slanders they shall utter;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.29'>whosoever shall speak slanderously against the Holy Spirit, shall never be pardoned, but be liable to eternal punishment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.30'>He said this because they affirmed he was leagued with an unclean spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.31'>Meanwhile came his mother and brothers, who standing without, sent for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.32'>And the crowd who sat round him, said to him, Lo, your mother and brothers are without, and seek you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.33'>He answered them, saying, Who is my mother or my brothers?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.34'>And looking about on those who sat around him, he said, Behold my mother and my brothers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.35'>for whosoever does the will of God, is my brother, my sister, and mother.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.4'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.1'>Again, he was teaching by the sea side, when so great a multitude gathered about him, that he was obliged to go aboard a bark, and sit there, while all the people remained on shore.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.2'>Then he taught them many things by parables.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.3'>In teaching, he said to them, Attend, behold the sower went out to sow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.4'>And as he sowed, part of the seed fell by the way-side, and the birds came and picked it up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.5'>Part fell upon rocky ground, where it had little mold. This sprang sooner, because there was no depth of soil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.6'>But after the sun had beaten upon it, it was scorched, and having no root, it withered away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.7'>Part fell among thorns; and the thorns grew up and stifled it, so that it yielded nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.8'>Part fell into good ground, and sprang up, and became so fruitful, that some grains produced thirty, some sixty, and some a hundred.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.9'>He added. Whoever has ears to hear, let him hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.10'>When he was in private, those who were about him with the twelve, asked him the meaning of the parable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.11'>He said to them, It is your privilege to know the secrets of the Reign of God, but to those without everything is veiled in parables;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.12'>that they may not perceive what they look at, or understand what they hear; lest they should be reclaimed, and obtain the forgiveness of their sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.13'>He said also to them, Do you not understand this parable? How then will you understand all the parables?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.14'>The sower is he who disperses the word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.15'>The wayside on which some of the grain fell, denotes those who have no sooner heard the word, than Satan comes, and takes away that which was sown in their hearts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.16'>The rocky ground denotes those, who, hearing the word, receive it first with pleasure;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.17'>yet not having it rooted in their minds, retain it but a while; for when trouble or persecution comes because of the word, they instantly relapse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.18'>The ground overrun with thorns, denotes those hearers</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.19'>in whom worldly cares, and delusive riches, and the inordinate desire of other things, stifle the word, and render it unfruitful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.20'>The good soil on which some grains yielded thirty, some sixty, and some a hundred, denotes those who hear the word, and retain it, and produce the fruits thereof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.21'>He said further, Is a lamp brought to be put under a vessel, or under a bed, and not to be set on a stand?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.22'>For there is no secret, that is not discovered; nor has anything been concealed, which is not to be divulged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.23'>If any man have ears to hear, let him hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.24'>He said, moreover, Consider what you hear: with the measure with which you give, you shall receive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.25'>For to him who has, more shall be given; but from him who has not, even that which he has shall be taken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.26'>He said also, The kingdom of God is like seed, which a man sowed in his field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.27'>While he slept by night, and waked by day, the seed shot up, and grew without his minding it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.28'>For the earth produces of itself first the blade, then the ear; afterward the full corn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.29'>But as soon as the grain was ripe, he applied the sickle, because it was time to reap it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.30'>He said also, To what shall we compare the kingdom of God, or by what similitude shall we represent it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.31'>It is like a grain of mustard seed, which, when it is sown in the earth, is the smallest of all the seeds that are there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.32'>But after it is sown, it springs up, and becomes greater than any herb, and shoots out branches so large, that under their shades, the birds of the air may find shelter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.33'>And in many such similitudes, he conveyed instruction to the people, as he found them disposed to hear:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.34'>and without a similitude he told them nothing; but he solved all to his disciples in private.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.35'>That day, in the evening, he said to them, Let us pass to the other side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.36'>And they, leaving the people, but having him in the bark, set sail in company with other small barks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.37'>Then there arose a great storm of wind which drove the billows into the bark, which was now full.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.38'>Jesus being in the stern, asleep on a pillow, they awake him, saying, Rabbi, do you not care that we perish?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.39'>And he arose, and commanded the wind, saying to the sea, Peace! be still! Immediately the wind ceased, and great calm ensued.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.40'>And he said to them, Why are you so timorous? How is it that you have no faith?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.41'>And they were exceedingly terrified, and said one to another, Who is this, whom even the wind and the sea obey?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.5'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.1'>Then they crossed the sea, and came into the country of the Gadarenes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.2'>He was no sooner gone ashore, than there met him a man coming from the monuments, possessed of an unclean spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.3'>who made his abode in the tombs; and no man could confine him, not even with chains,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.4'>and broken the fetters, so that no person was able to tame him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.5'>He was continually, night and day, in the mountains, and in the tombs, howling, and cutting himself with flints.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.6'>But when he saw Jesus afar off, he ran, and prostrating himself before him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.7'>cried out, What hast thou to do with me, Jesus, Son of the Most High God? I conjure thee by God not to torment me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.8'>(For Jesus had said to him, Come out of the man, you unclean spirit.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.9'>Jesus asked him, What is your name? He answered, My name is Legion, for we are many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.10'>And he earnestly entreated him not to drive them out of the country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.11'>Now there was a great herd of swine feeding on the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.12'>And the fiends besought him, saying, Suffer us to go to the swine, that we may enter into them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.13'>Jesus immediately permitted them. Then the unclean spirits being gone out, entered into the swine; and the herd, in number about two thousand, rushed down a precipice into the sea, and were choked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.14'>And the swineherds fled, and told it in the city and villages. And the people flocked out to see what had happened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.15'>When they came to Jesus, and saw him who had been possessed by the legion, sitting, and clothed, and in his right mind, they were afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.16'>And those who had seen the whole, having related to them what had happened to the demoniac, and to the swine,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.17'>they entreated him to leave their territories.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.18'>As he entered the bark, the man who had been possessed, begged permission to attend him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.19'>Jesus however did not permit him, but said, Go home to your relations, and tell them what great things the Lord, in pity, has done for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.20'>Accordingly he departed, publishing in Decapolis, what great things Jesus had done for him. And they were all amazed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.21'>Jesus having repassed in the bark, a great crowd gathered round him, while he was on the shore.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.22'>Then came one of the directors of the synagogue, named Jairus, who seeing him threw himself at his feet,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.23'>and entreated him earnestly, saying, My little daughter is in extreme danger; I pray you come and lay your hands upon her and to heal her, and she will be well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.24'>And Jesus went with him, followed by a great multitude who thronged him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.25'>And a woman, who had been twelve years distressed with an issue of blood,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.26'>who had suffered much from several physicians, and spent her all without receiving any relief, but rather growing worse,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.27'>having heard of Jesus, came in the crowd, behind, and touched his mantle;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.28'>for she had said, If I but touch his cloths, I shall recover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.29'>Instantly the source of her distemper was dried up, and she felt in her body, that she was delivered from that scourge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.30'>Jesus immediately, conscious of the virtue which had issued from him, turned toward the crowd, saying, Who touched my clothes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.31'>His disciples answered, You see how the multitude throng you; yet you say, Who touched me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.32'>But he looked round him, to see her who had done it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.33'>Then the woman, knowing the change wrought upon her, came trembling with fear, threw herself prostrate before him, and confessed the whole truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.34'>But he said to her, Daughter, your faith has cured you; go in peace, released from this scourge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.35'>Before he had done speaking, messengers came from the house of the director of the synagogue, who said, Your daughter is dead, why should you trouble the teacher any further?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.36'>Jesus hearing this message delivered, said immediately to the director, Fear not; only believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.37'>And he allowed no person to follow him except Peter and James, and John, the brother of James.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.38'>Being arrived at the director's house, and seeing the tumult, and the people weeping and wailing immoderately,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.39'>he said to them, as he entered, Why do you weep and make a bustle? The child is not dead, but asleep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.40'>And they derided him. But having made them all go out, he took with him the child's father and mother, and those who came with him; and he entered the chamber where she was;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.41'>and, taking her by the hand, said to her, Talitha cumi, (which signified, Young woman, arise,) I command you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.42'>Immediately the maid arose and walked, for she was twelve years old; and they were confounded with astonishment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.43'>But he strictly enjoined them not to mention it to any person, and ordered that something should be given her to eat.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.6'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.1'>Jesus, leaving that place, went to his own country, accompanied by his disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.2'>And on the Sabbath he taught in their synagogues, and many who heard him, said with astonishment, Whence has this man these abilities? What wisdom is this which he has gotten? and how are so great miracles performed by him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.3'>Is not this the carpenter, the son of Mary, the brother of James and Joses, and Judas and Simon? Are not his sisters also here with us? And they were offended at him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.4'>But Jesus said to them, A prophet is no where disregarded, except in his own country, and amongst his own relations, and in his own house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.5'>And he could do no miracle there, excepting curing a few sick by laying his hands on them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.6'>And he wondered at their unbelief. And he went through the neighboring villages teaching.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.7'>And having called to him the twelve, he sent them out two by two, and gave them power over the unclean spirits;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.8'>and ordered them to take nothing for their journey, but a single staff; no bag, no bread, and in their girdle no money;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.9'>to be shod with sandals, and not to put on two coats.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.10'>He said also, Whatever house you enter in any place, continue in that house, till you leave the place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.11'>But wheresoever they will not receive you, nor hear you, shake off the dust under your feet at your departure, as a protestation against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.12'>And being departed, they publicly warned men to reform;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.13'>and expelled many demons, and cured many sick persons, anointing them with oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.14'>And King Herod heard of him, (for his name was become famous) and said, John the Immerser is raised from the dead; and therefore miracles are performed by him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.15'>Others said, It is Elijah. Others, It is a prophet like those of ancient times.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.16'>But when Herod heard of him, he said, This is John whom I beheaded. He is raised from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.17'>For Herod had caused John to be apprehended, and kept bound in prison, on account of Herodias, his brother Philip's wife, whom he had himself married.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.18'>For John had said to Herod, It is not lawful for you to have your brother's wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.19'>Now this roused Herodias' resentment, who would have killed John, but could not,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.20'>because Herod respected him, and knowing him to be a just and holy man, protected him; and did many things recommended by him, and heard him with pleasure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.21'>At length a favorable opportunity offered, which was Herod's birthday, when he made an entertainment for the great officers of his court and army, and the persons of distinction in Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.22'>For the daughter of Herodias came in, and danced before them, and pleased Herod and his guests so much, that the king said to the young woman, Ask whatever you will, and I will give it you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.23'>nay, he swore to her, Whatsoever you shall ask, I will give it you, were it the half of my kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.24'>And she withdrew, and said to her mother, What shall I ask? She answered, The head of John the Immerser.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.25'>Her daughter then, returning hastily to the king, made this request: I would that you give me presently in a basin, the head of John the Immerser.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.26'>And the king was much grieved; however, from a regard to his oath, and his guests, he would not refuse her,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.27'>and immediately dispatched a sentinel with orders to bring the Immerser's head. Accordingly he went, and beheaded him in the prison,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.28'>and brought his hand in a basin, and presented it to the young woman; and the young woman presented it to her mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.29'>When his disciples heard this, they went and brought his corpse, and laid it in a monument.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.30'>Now the Apostles, being assembled, related everything to Jesus, both what they had done, and what they had taught.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.31'>And he said to them, Come you apart into a desert place, and rest awhile; for there were so many coming and going, that they had not leisure so much as to eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.32'>And they retired by ship to a desert place, to be by themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.33'>But many who saw them depart, and knew whither they were sailing, ran out of all the cities, and came together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.34'>Being landed, he saw a great multitude, and had compassion on them; because they were as a flock which has no shepherd; and he taught them many things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.35'>When it grew late, his disciples came to him and said, This is a desert place, and it is now late;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.36'>dismiss the people, that they may go to the neighboring farms and villages, and buy themselves bread, for they have nothing to eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.37'>He answering, said to them, Supply them yourselves. They replied, Shall we go and give two hundred denarii for bread, in order to supply them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.38'>He said to them, How many loaves have you? Go and see. Upon inquiry, they answered, Five and two fishes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.39'>And he commanded them to make all the people recline upon the green grass in separate companies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.40'>And they formed themselves into squares, by hundred and by fifties.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.41'>Then Jesus taking the five loaves and the two fishes, and looking up to heaven, blessed and broke the loaves, and gave them to his disciples to set before the multitude. He distributed also the two fishes among them all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.42'>When they all had eat and were satisfied,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.43'>they carried off twelve baskets full of the fragments of the bread and the fishes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.44'>Now they who had eat of the loaves, were five thousand men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.45'>And immediately he obliged his disciples to embark, and pass over before, toward Bethsaida, while he dismissed the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.46'>And having sent them away, he retired to a mountain to pray.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.47'>In the evening, the bark being in the midst of the sea, and he alone on the land,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.48'>he observed them toiling at the oar, for the wind was against them: and about the fourth watch of the night, he went to them, walking on the water. and seemed intending to pass by them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.49'>When they saw him walking on the sea, they thought it was an apparition, and cried out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.50'>For they all saw him, and were terrified; but he immediately spoke to them, saying, Take courage; it is I; be not afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.51'>And having gone aboard to them, the wind ceased, which struck them still more with astonishment and admiration.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.52'>for their minds were so stupefied, that they never reflected upon the loaves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.53'>When they had crossed, they came to the territory of Gennesaret, where they landed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.54'>And being come ashore, the people knew him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.55'>and ran through all that country, carrying the sick on couches, to every place where they heard he was.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.56'>And whatever village, or city, or town he entered, they laid the diseased in the streets, and besought him, that they might touch, were it but a tuft of his mantle; and whosoever touched him, were healed.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.7'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.1'>Now the Pharisees, and some scribes who came from Jerusalem, resorted to Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.2'>And observing some of his disciples eating with impure hands, that is, unwashed hands;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.3'>(for the Pharisees, and indeed all the Jews who observed the tradition of the elders, eat not until they have washed their hands by pouring a little water upon them:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.4'>and if they be come from the market, by dipping them; and many other usages there are, which they have adopted, as immersions of cups and pots, and brazen vessels and beds:)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.5'>then the Pharisees and Scribes asked him, Whence comes it that your disciples observe not the tradition of the elders, but eat with unwashed hands?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.6'>He answering, said to them, O hypocrites! well do you suit the character, which Isaiah gave of you, when he said, This people honor me with their lips; but their heart is estranged from me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.7'>«In vain, however, they worship me, while they teach institutions merely human.»</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.8'>For laying aside the commandment of God, you retain the traditions of men, immersions of pots and cups, and many other similar practices.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.9'>You judge well, continued he, in annulling the commandment of God, to make room for your traditions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.10'>«For Moses has said,» 'Honor your father and mother' 'and '«Whosoever reviles father or mother, shall be punished with death.»</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.11'>«But you maintain, if a man say to father or mother,'Be it corban (that is, devoted) whatever of mine shall profit you';»</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.12'>he must not thenceforth do anything for his father or mother;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.13'>thus invalidating the word of God, by the tradition which you have established. And in many other instances you act thus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.14'>Then having called the whole multitude, he said to them, Hearken to me all of you, and be instructed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.15'>There is nothing from without, which entering into the man, can pollute him; but the things which proceed from within the man, are the things that pollute him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.16'>If any man has ears to hear, let him hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.17'>When he had withdrawn from the people into a house, his disciples asked him the meaning of that sentence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.18'>He answered, Are you also void of understanding? Do you not perceive, that whatsoever from without enters into the man, can not pollute him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.19'>because it enters not into his heart, but into his stomach, whence all impurities in the victuals pass into the sink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.20'>But, added he, that which proceeds out of the man, is what pollutes the man:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.21'>for from within the human heart proceed vicious machinations, adulteries, fornications, murders, thefts,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.22'>insatiable desires, malevolence, fraud, immodesty, envy, calumny, arrogance, levity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.23'>All these evils issue from within, and pollute the man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.24'>Then he arose, and went to the frontiers of Tyre and Sidon; and having entered a house, he desired that none might know of him; but he could not be concealed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.25'>For a woman whose little daughter had an unclean spirit, hearing of him, came and threw herself at his feet,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.26'>(the woman was a Greek, a native of Syrophenicia,) and entreated him that he would cast the demon out of her daughter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.27'>Jesus answered, Let the children first be satisfied; for it is not seemly to take the children bread, and throw it to the dogs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.28'>She replied, True, Sir; yet even the dogs under the table eat of the children's crumbs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.29'>He said to her, For this answer go home; the demon is gone out of your daughter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.30'>Immediately she went home, and found her daughter lying upon the bed, and freed from the demon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.31'>Then leaving the borders of Tyre and Sidon, he returned to the sea of Galilee, through the precincts of Decapolis.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.32'>And they brought to him a deaf man, who had also an impediment in his speech, and entreated him to lay his hand upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.33'>Jesus having taken him aside from the crowd, spit upon his own fingers, and put them into the man's ears, and touched his tongue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.34'>Then looking up to heaven, and sighing, he said, Ephphatha, that is, Be opened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.35'>Immediately his ears were opened, and his tongue loosed, and he spoke distinctly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.36'>He charged them to tell no person: but the more he charged them, the more they published it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.37'>saying with inexpressible amazement, He does everything well: he makes both the deaf to hear, and the dumb to speak.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.8'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.1'>At that time the crowd being very numerous, and having no food, he called his disciple, and said to them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.2'>I have compassion on the multitude; for they attend me now three days, and have nothing to eat;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.3'>and if I send them home fasting, their strength will fail by the way; for some of them have come from afar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.4'>His disciples answered, Whence can we supply these people with bread here in the desert?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.5'>He asked them, How many loaves have you? They said, Seven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.6'>Then commanding the multitude to place themselves upon the ground, he took the seven loaves, and having given thanks, broke them, and gave them to his disciples, that they might distribute them to the people, and they distributed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.7'>They had also a few small fishes, which, after blessing, he likewise ordered to be presented.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.8'>So they eat, and were satisfied; and the fragments which remained, were carried off in seven hand-baskets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.9'>Now they who had eat were about four thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.10'>Having dismissed them, he immediately embarked with his disciples, and went into the territory of Dalmanutha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.11'>Thence some Pharisees came, who began to argue with him; and in order to prove him, demanded of him a sign in the sky.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.12'>Jesus answered with a deep groan, Wherefore does this generation require a sign? Indeed, I say to you, that no sign shall be given to this generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.13'>After that, leaving them, he re-embarked and returned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.14'>Now the disciples had forgot to bring bread, having only one loaf with them in the bark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.15'>Then Jesus gave them this caution: Attend; beware of the leaven of the Pharisees, and of the leaven of Herod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.16'>They reflecting upon it, said among themselves, It is because we have no bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.17'>Jesus remarking it, said to them, Why do you make this reflection, hat you have no bread? Are you yet so thoughtless, so inattentive?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.18'>Is your understanding still blinded? Have you no us of your eyes, or of your ears? or do you not remember</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.19'>when I distributed the five loaves among five thousand, how many baskets full of fragments did you carry off? They answered, Twelve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.20'>And when the seven among four thousand, how many hand-baskets full of the fragments did you carry off? They said, Seven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.21'>How then is it, proceeded he, that you do not apprehend me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.22'>When Jesus came to Bethsaida, they brought to him a blind man, whom they entreated him to touch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.23'>He took the blind man by the hand, and led him out of the village. Then having put spittle on his eyes, and laid his hands upon him, he asked him whether he saw.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.24'>Having looked up, he said, I see men, as trees walking.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.25'>And Jesus laid his hands upon the man's eyes, and made him look again. And he was so perfectly cured, as to see every object clearly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.26'>And Jesus sent him home, saying, Neither go into the village, nor tell anything to any of the villagers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.27'>Jesus went thence with his disciples to the villages of Caesarea Philippi, and by the way asked them, saying, Who do men say that I am?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.28'>They answered, John the Immerser; but some say, Elijah; and others, One of the prophets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.29'>He said to them, But who do you say that I am? Peter answering, said to him, You are the Messiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.30'>Then he charged them to tell no person this concerning him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.31'>And he began to inform them, that the Son of Man must suffer many things, and be rejected by the elders, and the chief priests, and the scribes, and be killed, and that in three days he must rise again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.32'>This he spoke so plainly, that Peter, taking him aside, reproved him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.33'>But he turning, and looking on his disciples, rebuked Peter, saying, Get you hence, adversary, for you do not relish the things of God, but the things of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.34'>Then having called both to the people, and to his disciples, he said, Is any willing to come under my guidance? Let him renounce himself, and take up his cross, and follow me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.35'>For whosoever would save his life, shall lose it; and whosoever will lose his life, for my sake and the gospel's, shall save it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.36'>What would it profit a man, if he should gain the whole world, with the forfeit of his life?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.37'>or what will a man not give in ransom for his life?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.38'>For whosoever shall be ashamed of me, and of my words, in this adulterous and sinful generation; of him likewise the Son of man will be ashamed, when he shall come in the glory of his Father, accompanied by the holy angels.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.9'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.1'>He added, Indeed, I say to you, there are some standing here, who shall not taste death, till they see the Reign of God ushered in with power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.2'>After six days, Jesus took Peter, and James, and John, apart to the top of a high mountain, and was transfigured in their presence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.3'>His garments became glittering, and were like snow, of such whiteness as no fuller on the earth could imitate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.4'>There appeared to them also Elijah and Moses, who were conversing with Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.5'>Then Peter said to Jesus, Rabbi, it is good for us to stay here: let us make three booths, one for you, and one for Moses, and one for Elijah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.6'>for he knew not what he said, they were so terrified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.7'>And there came a cloud which covered them; and out of the cloud issued a voice, which said, This is my Son, the beloved: hear him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.8'>And instantly, looking about, they saw no person but Jesus and themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.9'>As they went down from the mountain, he charged them not to relate to any person what they had seen, till the Son of Man was risen from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.10'>And they took notice of that expression, and inquired among themselves what the rising from the dead could mean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.11'>Then they asked him, saying, Why do the scribes affirm that Elijah must come first?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.12'>He answered, Elijah, to consummate the whole, must come first; and, (as it is written of the Son of Man,) must likewise suffer many things and be condemned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.13'>But I tell you, that Elijah too is come, as was predicted, and they have treated him as they pleased.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.14'>When he returned to the other disciples, he saw a great multitude about them, and some scribes disputing with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.15'>As soon as the people saw him, they were all struck with awe, and ran to salute him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.16'>And he asked the scribes, About what do you dispute with them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.17'>One of the people answering, said, Rabbi, I have brought you my son, who has a dumb spirit;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.18'>and wheresoever it seizes him, it dashes him on the ground, where he continues foaming, and grinding his teeth, till his strength is exhausted. And I spoke to your disciples to expel the demon, but they were not able.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.19'>Jesus then said, O unbelieving generation! how long shall I be with you? how long shall I suffer you? Bring him to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.20'>Accordingly they brought him: and no sooner did he see him, than the spirit threw him into convulsions, so that he foamed, and rolled upon the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.21'>Jesus asked the father, How long is it since this first befell him? He answered, From his infancy;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.22'>and often it has thrown him both into the fire, and into the water, to destroy him; but if you can do anything, have compassion upon us and help us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.23'>Jesus replied, If you can believe; all things are practicable for him who believes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.24'>The boy's father, crying out immediately, said with tears, I believe; Master, supply the defects of my faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.25'>When Jesus saw that the people came crowding upon him, he rebuked the unclean spirit, saying to him, Dumb and deaf spirit, come out of him, I command you, and enter no more into him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.26'>Then, having cried aloud and severely convulsed him, it came out, and he appeared as one dead, insomuch that many said, He is dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.27'>But Jesus taking him by the hand, raised him, and he stood up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.28'>When Jesus was come into the house, his disciples asked him privately, Why could not we expel the demon?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.29'>He answered, This kind can not be dislodged unless by prayer and fasting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.30'>Having left that place, they pass through Galilee; and he was desirous that no person should know it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.31'>for he was instructing his disciples. And he said to them, The Son of Man will soon be delivered into the hands of men, who will kill him; and after he is killed, he will rise again the third day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.32'>But they understood not what he meant, and were afraid to ask him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.33'>When he was come to Capernaum, being in the house, he asked them, What were you debating amongst yourselves by the way?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.34'>But they were silent; for they had debated amongst themselves by the way, who should be greatest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.35'>Then having sat down, he called the twelve, and said to them, If any man would be first, he shall be the last of all, and the servant of all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.36'>And he took a child, and placed him in the midst of them, and holding him in his arms, said to them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.37'>Whosoever shall receive one such child on my account, receives me; and whosoever shall receive me, receives not me, but him who sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.38'>Then John said to him, Rabbi, we saw one expelling demons in your name, who follows not us, and we forbade him, because he does not follow us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.39'>Jesus answered, Forbid him not; for there is none that works a miracle in my name, that can readily speak evil of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.40'>For whosoever is not against you is for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.41'>For whosoever shall give you a cup of water to drink on my account, because you are Christ's; indeed, I say to you, he shall not lose his reward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.42'>But whoever shall ensnare any of the little ones, who believe in me, it were better for him that a millstone were fastened to his neck, and that he were thrown into the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.43'>Moreover, if your hand ensnare you, cut it off; it is better for you to enter maimed into life, than having two hands to go into hell, into the unquenchable fire;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.44'>where their worm dies not, and their fire is not quenched.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.45'>And if your foot ensnare you, cut it off; it is better for you to enter lame into life, than having two feet to be cast into hell, into the unquenchable fire;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.46'>where their worm dies not, and their fire is not quenched.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.47'>And if your eye ensnare you, pull it out; it is better for you to enter one-eyed into the kingdom of God, than having two eyes to be cast into hell fire;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.48'>where their worm dies not, and their fire is not quenched.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.49'>For every one shall be seasoned with fire; as every sacrifice is seasoned with salt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.50'>Salt is good; but if the salt become tasteless, with what will you season it? Preserve salt in yourselves, and maintain peace with one another.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.10'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.1'>Then he arose and came into the confines of Judea, through the country upon the Jordan. Again multitudes resorted to him; and again, as his custom was, he taught them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.2'>And some Pharisees came, who, to try him, asked him, Is it lawful for the husband to divorce his wife?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.3'>He answering, said to them, What precept has Moses given you on this subject?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.4'>They replied, Moses has permitted us to write her a bill of divorcement, and dismiss her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.5'>Jesus answering, said to them, Because of your intractable disposition, Moses gave you this permission.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.6'>But from the beginning, at the creation, God made them a male and a female.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.7'>For this reason a man shall leave his father and mother, and shall adhere to his wife,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.8'>and they two shall be one flesh. They are, therefore, not longer two, but one flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.9'>What then God has conjoined, let no man separate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.10'>And, in the house, his disciples asked him anew concerning this matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.11'>He said to them, Whosoever divorces his wife, and marries another, commits adultery against her;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.12'>and if a woman divorce her husband, and marry another, she commits adultery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.13'>Then they brought children to him, that he might touch them; but the disciples rebuked those who brought them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.14'>Jesus perceiving this, was offended, and said, Allow the children to come to me, do not hinder them; for of such is the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.15'>Indeed, I say to you, whosoever will not receive the kingdom of God as a child, shall never enter it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.16'>Then taking them up in his arms, and laying his hands upon them, he blessed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.17'>As he went out into the road, one came running to him, who, kneeling, asked him, Good Teacher, what must I do to inherit eternal life?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.18'>Jesus answered, Why do you call me good? God alone is good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.19'>Do you know the commandments? Do not commit adultery; do not commit murder; do not steal; do not give false testimony; do no injury; honor your father and mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.20'>The other replied, Rabbi, I have observed all these from my childhood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.21'>Jesus, looking upon him, loved him, and said to him, In one thing, nevertheless, you are deficient. Go, sell all that you have, and give the price to the poor, and you shall have treasure in heaven; then come, and follow me, carrying the cross.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.22'>But he was troubled at this answer, and went away sorrowful; for he had great possessions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.23'>Then Jesus looking around him, said to his disciples, How difficult it is for the wealthy to enter the kingdom of God!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.24'>The disciples were astonished at his words; but Jesus resuming the discourse, said, Children, how difficult is it for them, who confide in wealth, to enter the kingdom of God!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.25'>It is easier for a camel to pass through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.26'>At this they were still more amazed, and said one to another, Who then can be saved?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.27'>Jesus looking upon them, said, To men it is impossible, but not to God; for to God all things are possible.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.28'>Then Peter took occasion to say, As for us, we have forsaken all, and followed you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.29'>Jesus answering, said, Indeed, I say to you, there is none who shall have forsaken his house, or brothers, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, for my sake and the gospel's;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.30'>who shall not receive now, in this world, a hundred fold; houses, and brothers, and sisters, and mothers, and children, and lands, with persecutions; and in the future state, eternal life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.31'>But many shall be first, who are last, and last, who are first.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.32'>As they were on the road to Jerusalem, Jesus walking before them, a panic seized them, and they followed him with terror. Then taking the twelve aside, he told them again what would befall him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.33'>Behold, says he, we are going to Jerusalem, where the Son of Man shall be delivered to the chief priests, who will condemn him to die, and deliver him to the Gentiles,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.34'>who will mock him, and scourge him, and spit upon him, and kill him; but the third day he shall rise again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.35'>Then James and John, the sons of Zebedee, accosted him, saying, Rabbi, we beg you would grant us what we purpose to ask.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.36'>He said to them, what would you have me grant you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.37'>They answered, That when you shall have attained your glory, one of us may sit at your right hand, and the other at your left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.38'>Jesus replied, You know not what you ask. Can you drink such a cup as I am to drink; and undergo an immersion like that which I must undergo?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.39'>They answered, We can. Jesus said to them, You shall indeed drink such a cup, as I am to drink, and undergo an immersion like that which I must undergo;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.40'>but to sit at my right hand, and left, I can not give, unless to those for whom it is appointed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.41'>The ten hearing this, conceived indignation against James and John.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.42'>But Jesus having called them together, said to them, You know that those who are accounted the princes of the nations, domineer over them; and their great ones exercise authority upon them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.43'>but it must not be so amongst you. On the contrary, whosoever would be great amongst you, shall be your servant;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.44'>and whosoever would be the chief, shall be the slave of all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.45'>For even the Son of Man came not to be served, but to serve, and to give his life a ransom for many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.46'>Then they came to Jericho. Afterward, as he was departing thence, with his disciples, and a great crowd, blind Bartimeus, son of Timeus, who sat by the way-side begging,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.47'>hearing that it was Jesus the Nazarene, cried, saying, Jesus Son of David, have pity upon me!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.48'>Many charged him to be silent, but he cried still the louder, Son of David, have pity upon me!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.49'>Jesus stopping, ordered them to call him. Accordingly they called the blind man, saying to him, Take courage; arise, he calls you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.50'>Then throwing down his mantle, he sprang up, and went to Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.51'>Jesus addressing him, said, What do you wish me to do for you? Rabboni, answered the blind man, to give me my sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.52'>Jesus said to him, Go; your faith has cured you. Immediately he recovered his sight, and followed Jesus in the way.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.11'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.1'>As they approached Jerusalem, being come as far as Bethphage, and Bethany, near the Mount of Olives; he sent two of his disciples,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.2'>and said to them, Go into the village opposite you, and just as you enter it, you will find a colt tied, on which no man ever rode; loose him, and bring him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.3'>And if any person ask you, Wherefore do you this? say, The Master needs him, and he will instantly send him hither.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.4'>Accordingly they went, and finding a colt tied before a door, where two ways met, they loosed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.5'>Some of the people present said to them, Wherefore do you loose the colt?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.6'>They having answered as Jesus had commanded them, were allowed to take him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.7'>Accordingly they brought the colt to Jesus, on which having laid their mantles, he sat on him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.8'>And many spread their mantles in the way; others cut down sprays from the trees, and strowed them in the way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.9'>And they who went before, and they who followed shouted, saying, Hosanna! blessed be He that comes in the name of the Lord!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.10'>Happy be the approaching Reign of our Father David!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.11'>In this manner Jesus entered Jerusalem and the temple; where, after surveying everything around, it being late, he departed with the twelve to Bethany.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.12'>The next day, when he left Bethany, he was hungry;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.13'>and observing a fig tree at a distance, full of leaves, went to look for fruit on it, for the fig harvest was not yet. And being come, he found nothing but leaves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.14'>Then he said to it, Henceforth let no man ever eat fruit off you. And his disciples heard him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.15'>Being returned to Jerusalem, he went into the temple, and drove out them who sold, and them who bought in the temple, and overturned the tables of the money changers, and the stalls of them who sold doves;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.16'>and would suffer no person to carry vessels through the temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.17'>«He also taught them, saying, Is it not written,» 'My house shall be called a house of prayer for all nations?' 'but you have made it a den of robbers.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.18'>And the scribes and the chief priests hearing this, sought means to destroy him; for they dreaded him, because all the multitude admired his doctrine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.19'>And in the evening he went out of the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.20'>Next morning as they returned, they saw that the fig tree was dried up from the root.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.21'>Peter recollecting, said to him, Rabbi, behold the fig tree, which you devoted, already withered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.22'>Jesus answered, Have faith in God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.23'>For indeed, I say to you, Whoever shall say to this mountain, Be lifted, and thrown into the sea, and shall not in the least doubt, but shall believe that what he says shall happen; whatever he shall command, shall be done for him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.24'>for which reason I assure you, that what things soever you pray for, if you believe that you shall obtain them, they shall be yours.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.25'>And when you pray, forgive, if you have matter of complaint against any; that your Father, who is in heaven, may also forgive you your trespasses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.26'>But if you do not forgive, neither will your Father, who is in heaven, forgive your trespasses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.27'>Again, they arrived at Jerusalem; and as he was walking in the temple, the chief priests, scribes, and the elders, came,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.28'>and said to him, By what authority do you these things? and who empowered you to do them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.29'>Jesus answering, said to them, I also have a question to ask; answer me, and I will tell you by what authority I do these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.30'>Was the title which John had to immerse, from heaven, or from men? Answer me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.31'>Then they argued thus among themselves; If we say, From heaven; he will reply, Why, then, did you not believe him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.32'>But if we say, From men; we are in danger from the people, who are all convinced that John was a prophet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.33'>They therefore answering, said to Jesus, We can not tell. Jesus replied, Neither do I tell you by what authority I do these things.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.12'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.1'>Then addressing them in parables, he said, A man planted a vineyard, and hedged it about, and dug a place for a wine vat, and built a tower, and having farmed it out, went abroad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.2'>The season being come, he sent a servant to the husbandmen, to receive his portion of the fruits of the vineyard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.3'>But they seized him, beat him, and sent him away empty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.4'>Again, he sent to them another servant, whom they wounded in the head with stones, and sent back with disgrace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.5'>He sent another, whom they killed; and of many more that he sent, some they beat, and some they killed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.6'>At last, having an only son, whom he loved, he sent him also to them; for he said, They will reverence my son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.7'>But those husbandmen said among themselves, This is the heir; come, let us kill him, and the inheritance will be our own.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.8'>Then they laid hold on him, and having thrust him out of the vineyard, they killed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.9'>What, therefore, will the proprietor of the vineyard do? He will come and destroy the husbandmen, and give the vineyard to others.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.10'>«Have you not read this passage of scripture,» 'A stone which the builders rejected, is made the head of the corner:'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.11'>«this the Lord has performed, and we behold it with admiration?»</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.12'>And they desired to have seized him, but were afraid of the multitude; for they knew that he spoke the parable against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.13'>Then the chief priests, the scribes, and the elders, leaving Jesus, went away, and sent to him certain Pharisees and Herodians, to catch him in his words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.14'>These coming up, said to him, Rabbi, we know that you are upright, and stand in awe of none; for you respect not the person of men, but teach the way of God faithfully. Is it lawful to give tribute to Cesar, or not?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.15'>Shall we give, or shall we not give? He, perceiving their artifice, answered, Why would you entangle me? Bring me a denarius, that I may see it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.16'>When they had brought, he asked them, Whose is the image and inscription? They answered, Cesar's.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.17'>Jesus replied, Render to Cesar that which is Cesar's, and to God that which is God's. And they wondered at him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.18'>Then Sadducees came to him, who say that there is no future life, and proposed this questions:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.19'>Rabbi, Moses has enacted, that if a man's brother die, survived by a wife without children, he shall marry the widow, and raise issue to his brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.20'>Now there were seven brothers. The first took a wife, and dying, left no issue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.21'>The second married her, and died; neither did he leave any issue; so did also the third.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.22'>Thus all seven married her, and left no issue. Last of all, the woman also died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.23'>At the resurrection, therefore, when they are risen, to which of the seven will she belong; for she has been the wife of them all?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.24'>Jesus answering, said to them, Is not this the source of your error, your not knowing the scriptures, nor the power of God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.25'>For there will be neither marrying, nor giving in marriage, among them who rise from the dead. They will then resemble the angels.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.26'>«But as to the dead, that they are raised, have you not read in the book of Moses, how God spoke to him in the bush, saying,'I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob.'»</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.27'>God is not a God of the dead, but of the living. Therefore you greatly err.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.28'>A scribe, who had heard them dispute, perceiving the justness of his reply, came to him, and proposed this question: Which is the chief commandment of all?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.29'>«Jesus answered, The chief of all the commandments is,'Hearken, Israel, the Lord is our God. The Lord is one:'»</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.30'>«and,» 'You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart, and with all your soul, and with all your mind, and with all your strength.' 'This is the first commandment.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.31'>«The second resembles it:» 'You shall love your neighbor as yourself.' 'There is no commandment greater than these.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.32'>The scribe replied, Truly, Rabbi, you have answered well. There is one, and only one;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.33'>and to love him with all the heart, and with all the spirit, and with all the soul, and with all the strength; and to love one's self, is more than all burnt offerings and sacrifices.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.34'>Jesus observing how pertinently he had answered, said to him, You are not far from the kingdom of God. After that, no person ventured to put questions to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.35'>As Jesus was teaching in the temple, he asked them, Why do you scribes assert, that the Messiah must be a son of David?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.36'>«Yet David, himself, speaking by the Holy Spirit, says,'The Lord, said to my Lord, Sit at my right hand, until I make your foes your footstool.'»</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.37'>David himself, therefore, calls him his Lord; how then can he be his son? And the common people heard him with delight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.38'>Further, in teaching, he said to them, Beware of the scribes, who affect to walk in robes; who love salutations in public places,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.39'>and the principal seats in the synagogues, and the uppermost places at entertainments;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.40'>who devour the families of widows, and use long prayers for a disguise. They shall undergo the severest punishment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.41'>And Jesus sitting opposite the treasury, observed the people throwing money into the treasury; and many rich persons put in much.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.42'>Then the poor widow came, who threw in two mites, (which make a farthing.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.43'>Jesus having called his disciples, said to them, Indeed, I say to you, that this poor widow has given more than any of those who have thrown into the treasury;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.44'>for they all have contributed out of their superfluous stores; whereas she has given all the little she had-her whole living.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.13'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.1'>As he was going out of the temple, one of his disciples said to him, Rabbi, look what prodigious stones and stately buildings are here!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.2'>Jesus answering, said to him, You see these great buildings. They shall be so razed, that one stone will not be left upon another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.3'>Afterward, as he was sitting on the Mount of Olives, opposite the temple, Peter, and James, and John, and Andrew, asked him privately,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.4'>Tell us, when will this happen? and what will be the sign, when all this is to be accomplished?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.5'>Jesus answering them, took occasion to say, Take heed that no man seduce you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.6'>for many will assume my character, saying, I am the person, and will seduce many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.7'>But when you hear of wars and rumors of wars, be not alarmed; for this must happen, but the end is not yet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.8'>For nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom; and there will be earthquakes in sundry places, and there will be famines and commotions. These are the prelude of woes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.9'>But take heed to yourselves; for they will deliver you to councils; and you will be beaten in the synagogues, and brought before governors and kings for my sake, to bear testimony to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.10'>The good tidings, however, must first be published among all nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.11'>But when they conduct you, to deliver you up, have no anxiety beforehand, nor premeditate what you shall speak: but whatever shall be suggested to you in that moment, speak; for it is not you that shall speak, but the Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.12'>Then the brother will deliver up the brother to death; and the father the child; and children will arise against their parents, and procure their death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.13'>And on my account you shall be universally hated; but the man who perseveres to the end, shall be saved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.14'>But when you shall see standing on forbidden ground, the desolating abomination, (reader, attend!) then let those in Judea flee to the mountains;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.15'>and let not him who shall be on the roof, go down into the house, nor enter it, to carry anything out of his house:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.16'>and let not him who shall be in the field, turn back to fetch his mantle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.17'>But alas for the women with child, and for them who give suck in those days!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.18'>Pray, then, that your flight happen not in the winter;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.19'>because there shall be such affliction in those days, as has not been before, from the beginning of the world, which God created, nor shall be ever after.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.20'>Had the Lord assigned it a long duration, no soul could escape; but for the sake of the people whom he had elected, he has made its duration the shorter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.21'>Then if any one shall say to you, Lo! the Messiah is here, or Lo! he is yonder, believe it not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.22'>For false Messiahs and false prophets will arise, who will perform wonders and prodigies, in order to impose, if possible, even on the elect.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.23'>Be you, therefore, upon your guard: remember, I have warned you of everything.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.24'>But in those days, after that affliction, the sun shall be darkened, and the moon shall withhold her light,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.25'>and the stars of heaven shall fall; and the powers which are in heaven shall be shaken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.26'>Then they shall see the Son of Man coming in the clouds with great power and glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.27'>Then he will send his messengers, and assemble his elect from the four quarters of the world, from the extremities of heaven and earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.28'>Learn now a similitude from the fig tree. When its branches become tender, and put forth leaves, you know that the summer is nigh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.29'>In like manner, when you shall see these things happen, know that he is near, even at the door.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.30'>Indeed, I say to you, that this generation shall not pass, till all these things be accomplished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.31'>For heaven and earth shall fail: but my words shall not fail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.32'>But of that day, or of that hour, knows none, (not the angels; no, not the Son,) but the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.33'>Be circumspect, be vigilant, and pray; for you know not when that time will be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.34'>When a man intends to travel, he leaves his household in charge to his servants, assigns to every one his task, and orders the porter to watch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.35'>Watch you, therefore; for you know not when the master of the house will return, (whether in the evening, or at midnight, or at cock-crowing, or in the morning;)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.36'>lest coming suddenly, he find you asleep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.37'>Now what I say to you, I say to all, Watch.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.14'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.1'>After two days was the feast of the passover, and of unleavened bread. And the chief priests and the scribes were contriving how they might take Jesus by surprise, and kill him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.2'>They said, however, Not during the festival, for fear of an insurrection among the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.3'>Now being at table in Bethany, in the house of Simon, formerly a leper, there came a woman with an alabaster box of the balsam of spikenard, which was very costly; and she broken open the box, and poured the liquor upon his head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.4'>There were some present, who said with indignation, Why this profusion of the balsam?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.5'>For it could have been sold for more than three hundred denarii, which might have been given to the poor. And they murmured against her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.6'>But Jesus said, Let her alone. Why do you molest her? She has done me a good office.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.7'>For you will have the poor always amongst you, and can do them good whenever you please; but me you will not always have.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.8'>She has done what she could. She has beforehand embalmed my body for the funeral.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.9'>Indeed, I say to you, in whatsoever corner of the world the glad tidings shall be proclaimed, what this woman has now done, shall be mentioned to her honor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.10'>Then Judas Iscariot, one of the twelve, repaired to the chief priests, to betray Jesus to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.11'>And they listened to him with joy, and promised to give him money. Afterward he sought a favorable opportunity to deliver him up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.12'>Now the first day of unleavened bread, when the passover is sacrificed, his disciples said to him, Whither shall we go to prepare for your eating the passover?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.13'>Then he sent two of his disciples, saying to them, Go into the city, where you will meet a man carrying a pitcher of water; follow him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.14'>and wherever he shall enter, say to the master of the house, The Teacher says, Where is the guest chamber, in which I may eat the passover with my disciples?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.15'>And he will show you a large upper room ready furnished. There prepare for us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.16'>Accordingly, his disciples went away, and being come into the city, found everything as he had told them, and prepared the passover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.17'>In the evening he went thither with the twelve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.18'>As they were at table eating, Jesus said, Indeed, I say to you, that one of you who eats with me, will betray me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.19'>Upon this they became very sorrowful; and asked him, all of them, one after another, Is it I?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.20'>He answering, said to them, It is one of the twelve; he who dips his morsel in the dish with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.21'>The Son of Man departs in the manner foretold in the scripture concerning him; but alas for that man! by whom the Son of Man is betrayed: it had been better for that man never to have been born.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.22'>While they were at supper, Jesus took bread, and after blessing, broke it, and gave it to them, saying, Take; this is my body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.23'>Then he took the cup, and having given thanks, gave it to them; and they all drank of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.24'>And he said to them, This is my blood, the blood of the new institution, shed for many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.25'>Indeed, I say to you, that I will drink no more of the product of the vine, till that day when I shall drink it new in the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.26'>And after the hymn, they went to the Mount of Olives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.27'>«And Jesus said to them, This night I shall prove a stumbling stone to you all; for it is written,'I will smite the Shepherd, and the sheep shall be dispersed.'»</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.28'>Nevertheless, after I am raised again, I will go before you to Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.29'>Peter then said to him, Though they all should stumble, I never will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.30'>Jesus answered him, Indeed, I say to you, that today, this very night, before the cock crow twice, even you will disown me thrice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.31'>But Peter insisted on it, adding, Although I should die with you, I will never disown you. And all the rest said the same.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.32'>Then they came to a place named Gethsemane, where he said to his disciples, Stay here while I pray.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.33'>And he took with him Peter, and James, and John, and being seized with grief and horror,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.34'>said to them, My soul is overwhelmed with a deadly anguish; tarry here and watch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.35'>And going a little before, he threw himself on the ground, and prayed that, if it were possible, he might be delivered from that hour,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.36'>and said, Abba, (that is, Father,) all things are possible to thee; take this cup away from me; yet not what I would, but what thou wilt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.37'>Then he returned, and finding them asleep, said to Peter, Simon, do you sleep? Could you not keep awake a single hour?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.38'>Watch and pray, that you be not overcome by temptation: the spirit indeed is willing, but the flesh is weak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.39'>Again, he retired and prayed, using the same words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.40'>When he returned, he again found them sleeping; for their eyes were overpowered, and they knew not what to answer him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.41'>A third time he came, and said to them, Do you now sleep, and take your rest? All is over: the hour is come: and the Son of Man is delivered into the hands of sinners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.42'>Arise. Let us be going. Lo! he who betrays me is drawing near.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.43'>Immediately, before he had done speaking, appeared Judas, one of the twelve, with a great multitude armed with swords and clubs, who were sent by the chief priests, the scribes, and the elders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.44'>Now the betrayer had given them this signal: The man whom I shall kiss, is he; seize him, and lead him away safely.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.45'>He was no sooner come, than accosting Jesus, he said, Rabbi, Rabbi, and kissed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.46'>Then they laid hands on him and seized him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.47'>But one of those who were present, drew his sword, and smiting the high priest's servant, cut off his ear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.48'>Then Jesus addressing them, said, Do you come with swords and clubs to apprehend me, like people in pursuit of a robber?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.49'>I was daily amongst you, teaching in the temple, and you did not arrest me. But in this the scriptures are accomplished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.50'>Then they all forsook him and fled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.51'>Now there followed him a youth, who had only a linen cloth wrapped about his body; the soldiers having laid hold of him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.52'>he left the cloth, and fled from them naked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.53'>Then they took Jesus away to the high priest, with whom all the chief priests, the elders, and the scribes, were convened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.54'>And Peter followed him at a distance, as far as the court of the high priest's house, and sat there with the officers, warming himself at the fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.55'>Meanwhile, the chief priests, and all the Sanhedrin, sought for evidence against Jesus, in order to condemn him to die, but found none:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.56'>for many gave false testimony against him, but their testimonies were insufficient.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.57'>The some arose, who testified falsely against him, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.58'>We heard him say, I will demolish this temple made with hands, and in three days will build another without hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.59'>But even here their testimony was defective.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.60'>Then the high priest, standing up in the midst, interrogated Jesus, saying, Do you answer nothing to what these men testify against you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.61'>But he was silent, and gave no answer. Again, the high priest interrogating him, said, Are you the Messiah, the Son of the blessed One?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.62'>Jesus answered, I am; nay, you shall see the Son of Man sitting at the right hand of the Almighty, and coming in the clouds of heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.63'>Then the high priest rent his garments, saying, What further need have we of witnesses?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.64'>You have heard the blasphemy. What is your opinion? And they all pronounced him worthy of death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.65'>Then some began to spit on him; others to cover his face and buffet him, saying to him, Divine who it is. And the officers gave him blows on the cheeks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.66'>Now Peter being below in the court, one of the maids of the high priest came thither,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.67'>who seeing Peter warming himself, looked on him, and said, You also were with the Nazarene Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.68'>But he denied it, saying, I know him not: nor do I understand what you mean. Immediately he went out into the portico, and the cock crew.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.69'>The maid seeing him again, said to the bystanders, This is one of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.70'>Again he denied. And a little after, those who were present said to Peter, You are certainly one of them; for you are a Galilean, your speech shows it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.71'>Upon this he affirmed, with imprecations, and oaths, that he did not know the man of whom they spoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.72'>The cock crew the second time: and Peter recollected the word which Jesus had said to him, Before the cock crow twice, you will disown me thrice. And reflecting upon this, he wept.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.15'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.1'>Early in the morning, the chief priests, with the elders, the scribes, and all the Sanhedrin, after consulting together, bound Jesus, carried him away, and delivered him to Pilate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.2'>Pilate, asking him, said, You are the king of the Jews? He answered, You say right.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.3'>Now the chief priests accused him of many things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.4'>Again Pilate asked him, saying, Do you answer nothing? Observe how many crimes they arraign you for.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.5'>But Jesus answered no more, insomuch that Pilate was astonished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.6'>Now, at the festival, he always released to them any one prisoner, whom they desired.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.7'>And there was one Barabbas, that had been imprisoned with his seditious associates, who in their sedition had committed murder.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.8'>And, with clamor, the multitude demanded of Pilate, what he used to grant them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.9'>He answered them, saying, Shall I release to you the king of the Jews?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.10'>(For he knew that through envy, the chief priests had delivered him up.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.11'>But the chief priests incited the multitude to insist on the release of Barabbas, in preference to Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.12'>Pilate again interposed, saying, What then would you have me do with him whom you call king of the Jews?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.13'>They cried, Crucify him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.14'>Pilate asked them, Why? What evil has he done? But they cried the more vehemently, Crucify him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.15'>Then Pilate, desirous to gratify the crowd, released Barabbas to them; and having caused Jesus to be scourged, delivered him up to be crucified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.16'>And the soldiers brought him into the hall called praetorium, where, having convened all the band,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.17'>they arrayed him in purple, and crowned him with a wreath of thorns,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.18'>and saluted him, saying, Hail, King of the Jews!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.19'>Then they struck him on the head with a reed, and spit upon him, and paid him homage on their knees.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.20'>And when they had mocked him, the stripped him of the purple, and dressed him in his own clothes, and took him away to be crucified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.21'>And they constrained one Simon, a Cyrenian, who passed by, in coming from the country, the father of Alexander and Rufus, to carry the cross.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.22'>And they brought him to Golgotha, (that is to say, The Place of Skulls,)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.23'>where they gave him wine to drink, mingled with myrrh, which he would not receive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.24'>When they had nailed him to the cross, they parted his garments, dividing by lot what every man should take.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.25'>Now it was the third hour, when they nailed him to the cross.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.26'>And the inscription, bearing the cause of his death, was in these words, THE KING OF THE JEWS.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.27'>They likewise crucified two robbers with him, one at his right hand, and the other at his left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.28'>«And the scripture was fulfilled, which says,» 'He was ranked with malefactors.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.29'>Meanwhile, they who passed by reviled him, shaking their heads, and saying, Ah! you who could demolish the temple, and rebuild it in three days!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.30'>save yourself, and come down from the cross!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.31'>The chief priests likewise, with the scribes, deriding him, said among themselves, He saved others; can not he save himself?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.32'>Let the Messiah, the King of Israel, descend now from the cross, that we may see and believe! Even those who were crucified with him reproached him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.33'>Now from the sixth hour until the ninth, darkness covered all the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.34'>At the ninth hour, Jesus cried aloud saying, Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani! which signifies, My God, My God, why hast thou forsaken me!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.35'>Some who were present, hearing this, said, Hark! he calls Elijah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.36'>One at the same time ran, and dipped a sponge in vinegar, and having fastened it to a stick, presented it to him to drink, saying, Let alone, we shall see whether Elijah will come to take him down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.37'>And Jesus sending forth a cry expired.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.38'>Then was the vail of the temple rent in two, from top to bottom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.39'>And the centurion who stood opposite observing that he expired with so loud a cry, said, Surely, this man was a son of a god.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.40'>There were women also looking on at a distance, amongst whom were Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James the younger, and of Joses and Salome,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.41'>(these had followed him, and served him, when he was in Galilee,) and several others, who came with him to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.42'>When it was evening, (because it was the preparation, that is, the eve of the Sabbath,)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.43'>Joseph of Arimathea, an honorable senator, who himself also expected the Reign of God, taking courage, repaired to Pilate, and begged the body of Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.44'>Pilate, amazed that he was so soon dead, sent for the centurion, and asked him whether Jesus had been dead any time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.45'>And being informed by the centurion, he granted the body to Joseph;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.46'>who having bought linen, and taking Jesus down, wrapped him in the linen; and laid him in a tomb, hewn out of the rock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.47'>Now Mary the Magdalene, and Mary the mother of Joses, saw where he was laid.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.16'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.1'>When the Sabbath was past, Mary the Magdalene, Mary the mother of James, and Salome, bought spices that they might embalm Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.2'>And early in the morning, the first day of the week, they came to the tomb about sunrise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.3'>And they said among themselves, Who will roll away the stone for us from the entrance of the tomb? (for it was very large.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.4'>But when they looked, they saw that the stone had been rolled away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.5'>Then entering the tomb, they beheld a youth sitting on the right side, clothed in a white robe, and they were frightened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.6'>But he said to them, Be not frightened; you seek Jesus the Nazarene, who was crucified. He is risen, he is not here: behold the place where they laid him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.7'>But go, say to his disciples, and to Peter, He is gone before you to Galilee; where you shall see him, as he told you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.8'>The women then getting out, fled from the tomb, seized with trembling and consternation; but said nothing to any one, they were so terrified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.9'>Jesus having arisen early the first day of the week, appeared first to Mary the Magdalene, out of whom he had cast seven demons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.10'>She went and informed those who had attended him, who were in affliction and tears.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.11'>But when they heard that he was alive, and had been seen by her, they did not believe it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.12'>Afterward he appeared in another form to two of them, as they traveled on foot into the country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.13'>These being returned, informed the other disciples, but neither did they believe him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.14'>At length he appeared to the eleven, as they were eating, and reproached them with their incredulity and obstinacy, in disbelieving those who had seen him after his resurrection.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.15'>And he said unto them, Go throughout all the world, proclaim the glad tidings to the whole creation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.16'>He who shall believe, and be immersed, shall be saved; but he who shall not believe, shall be condemned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.17'>And these miraculous powers shall attend the believers:- In my name they shall expel demons. They shall speak in languages unknown to them before.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.18'>They shall handle serpents with safety. And if they drink poison, it shall not hurt them. They shall cure the sick by laying their hands upon them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.19'>Now, after the Lord had spoken to them, he was taken up into heaven, and sat down at the right hand of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.20'>As for them, they went out and proclaimed the tidings everywhere, the Lord co-operating with them, and confirming their doctrine by the miracles with which it was accompanied.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>