<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='LONT' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='LONT'>
        <title>Living Oracles NT</title>
        <contributor>George Campbell, James Macknight, Philip Doddridge. Ed. Alexander Campbell.</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>Holy Bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>[Alexander Campbell's Living Oracles,]
The Sacred Writings of the Apostles and Evangelists of Jesus Christ, Commonly Styled the New Testament. 
Translated from the Original Greek.
MDCCCXXXV. 1835</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>LONT</identifier>
        <source>http://www.e-sword.net/usermods/bbl/Living%20Oracles%20New%20Testament%20(LONT)%20(1835).exe</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Phlm'>
      <chapter osisID='Phlm.1'>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.1'>Paul, a prisoner of Jesus Christ, and Timothy, the brother, to Philemon, the beloved, and our fellow-laborer;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.2'>and to Apphia, the beloved; and to Archippus, our fellow-soldier, and to the congregation in your house:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.3'>Favor to you, and peace from God our Father, and from our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.4'>I give thanks to my God always, making mention of you in my prayers-</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.5'>(having heard of the faith which you have toward the Lord Jesus, and of your love to all the saints)-</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.6'>that the communication of your faith may become effectual by the acknowledgment of every good thing that is among us, toward Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.7'>For we have much joy and consolation in your love; because the souls of the saints are refreshed by you, brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.8'>Wherefore, thought I might be bold in Christ, to enjoin you what is fit;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.9'>yet, for love's sake, I rather beseech, being such a one as Paul, an old man, and now, also a prisoner of Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.10'>I beseech you for my son, whom I have begot, in my bonds, even Onesimus;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.11'>who formerly was to you unprofitable, but now will be very profitable to you, even as he has been to me-</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.12'>whom I have sent back: do you, therefore, receive him as an object of my tenderest affection;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.13'>whom I was desirous to have detained with myself, that, in your stead, he might have ministered to me, in these bonds, for the gospel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.14'>but without your mind I would do nothing, that the good derived might not be as if by constraint, but as voluntary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.15'>Perhaps, also, for this reason he was separated for a little while, that you might have him for ever:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.16'>no longer as a slave only, but above a slave, a beloved brother, especially to me-and how much more to you, both in the flesh and in the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.17'>If, then, you hold me as a partner, receive him as myself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.18'>And if he had injured you in anything, or owes you, place it to my account.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.19'>I, Paul, have written with my own hand-I will repay. I forbear to urge upon you, that you owe to me even your own self.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.20'>I beseech you brother, let me have joy of you in the Lord- gratify my tender affections for Christ's sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.21'>Having confidence in your obedience, I have written to you, knowing that you will even do more than I ask.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.22'>But at the same time, prepare me also a lodging; for I hope that through your prayers, I shall be granted to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.23'>These salute you, Epaphras, my fellow prisoner for Christ Jesus;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.24'>Mark, Aristarchus; Demas, Luke, my fellow-laborers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.25'>The favor of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>