<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='Leeser' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='Leeser'>
        <title>Leeser Old Testament</title>
        <contributor>
1853 The Twenty-Two Books of the Holy Scriptures

The first English translation of the Jewish Bible 
published in America in 1853 by Rabbi Isaac Leeser. 

Verses where the Leeser verse numbering differs from
the KJV and other English versions are prefixed with
the Leeser (chapter:verse) reference at the beginning 
of the verse. Italics are used to indicate words 
supplied by the translator.
</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description/>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>Leeser</identifier>
        <source>http://www.answersingenesis.org/OnlineBible/files/leeser.exe</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Deut'>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.1'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.1'>These are the words which Moses spoke unto all Israel on this side of the Jordan, in the wilderness, in the plain opposite Suph, between Paran, and Tophel, and Laban, and Chazeroth, and Dizahab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.2'>It is a journey of eleven days from Horeb by the way of mount Seir unto Kadeshbarnea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.3'>And it came to pass in the fortieth year, in the eleventh month, on the first day of the month, that Moses spoke unto the children of Israel, according to all that the Lord had commanded him concerning them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.4'>After he had smitten Sichon the king of the Emorites, who dwelt in Cheshbon, and Og the king of Bashan, who dwelt at Ashtaroth in Edrei.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.5'>On this side of the Jordan, in the land of Moab, began Moses to explain this law, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.6'>The Lord our God spoke unto us in Horeb, saying, Ye have tarried long enough at this mount;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.7'>Turn you, and take your journey, and go to the mountain of the Emorites, and unto all its neighboring places, in the plain, in the mountain, and in the lowlands, and in the southern country, and by the coast of the sea, to the land of the Canaanites, and unto the Lebanon, up to the great river, the river Euphrates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.8'>Behold, I have given up the land before you: go in and take possession of the land which the Lord hath sworn unto your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give it unto them and to their seed after them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.9'>And I said unto you at that time, as followeth, I am not able alone to bear you:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.10'>The Lord your God hath multiplied you, and, behold, ye are this day as the stars of heaven for multitude.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.11'>May the Lord the God of your fathers make you a thousand times as many more as ye are; and bless you, as he hath spoken unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.12'>How can I by myself alone bear your cumbrance, and your burden, and your strife!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.13'>Furnish for yourselves wise and understanding men, and those known among your tribes, and I will place them as chiefs over you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.14'>And ye answered me, and said, The thing which thou hast spoken is good to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.15'>And I took the chiefs of your tribes, wise and known men, and I set them as heads over you, captains over thousands, and captains over hundreds, and captains over fifties, and captains over tens, and as officers for your tribes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.16'>And I commanded your judges at that time, saying, Hear the causes between your brethren, and judge righteously, between a man and his brother, and between his stranger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.17'>Ye shall not respect persons in judgment; the small as well as the great shall ye hear; ye shall not be afraid of any man; for the judgment belongeth to God: and the cause that is too hard for you shall ye bring unto me, and I will hear it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.18'>And I commanded you at that time all the things which ye should do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.19'>And we departed from Horeb, and we went through all that great and terrible wilderness, which ye have seen, by the way of the mountain of the Emorites, as the Lord our God had commanded us; and we came as far as Kadeshbarnea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.20'>And I said unto you, Ye are come unto the mountain of the Emorites, which the Lord our God doth give unto us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.21'>Behold, the Lord thy God hath given up the land before thee: go up and take possession of it, as the Lord the God of thy fathers hath spoken unto thee; do not fear, and be not discouraged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.22'>And ye all came near unto me and said, Let us send out men before us, that they may search out for us the land, and bring us word again concerning the way by which we must go up, and the cities to which we shall come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.23'>And the thing was pleasing in my eyes; and I took of you twelve men, one man for every tribe:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.24'>And they turned and went up into the mountain, and came unto the valley of Eshcol, and spied it out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.25'>And they took in their hand some of the fruit of the land, and brought it down unto us; and they brought us word again, and said, The land which the Lord our God doth give us is good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.26'>But you would not go up, and ye rebelled against the order of the Lord your God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.27'>And ye murmured in your tents, and said, On account of the hatred of the Lord toward us, hath he brought us forth out of the land of Egypt, to deliver us into the hand of the Emorites, to destroy us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.28'>Whither shall we go up? our brethren have made faint our heart, saying, The people is greater and taller than we; the cities are great and fortified up to heaven; and moreover the sons of the Anakim have we seen there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.29'>And I said unto you, Have no dread, nor be ye afraid of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.30'>The Lord your God who goeth before you, he it is who will fight for you; all just as he did for you in Egypt before your eyes;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.31'>And in the wilderness which thou hast seen, where the Lord thy God bore thee, as a man doth bear his son, on all the way that ye have gone, until ye came unto this place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.32'>Yet in this thing do ye not believe in the Lord your God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.33'>Who goeth before you on the way to seek out for you a place for your encamping, in fire by night, to cause you to see on the way in which ye are to go, and in a cloud by day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.34'>And the Lord heard the voice of your words; and he was wroth, and swore, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.35'>Surely there shall not one of these men of this evil generation see that good land, which I have sworn to give unto your fathers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.36'>Save Caleb the son of Yephunneh, he shall see it, and to him will I give the land upon which he hath trodden, and to his children; because he hath wholly followed the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.37'>also with me was the Lord angry for your sakes, saying, also thou shalt not go in thither.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.38'>Joshua the son of Nun, who standeth before thee, he shall go in thither: him encourage; for he shall cause Israel to inherit it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.39'>And your little ones, of whom ye said, They will become a prey, and your children who know not this day either good or evil, these shall go in thither; and unto them will I give it, and they shall possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.40'>But as for you, turn you, and take your journey into the wilderness by the way of the Red Sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.41'>And ye answered and said unto me, We have sinned against the Lord; we indeed will go up and we will fight, according to all that the Lord our God hath commanded us; and ye girded on every man his weapons of war, and ye insisted to go up into the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.42'>And the Lord said unto me, Say unto them, Go not up, and do not fight; for I am not among you; lest ye be smitten before your enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.43'>And I spoke unto you; but ye would not hear; and ye rebelled against the order of the Lord, and you were presumptuous, and went up into the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.44'>And the Emorites, who dwelt in that mountain: came out against you, and they pursued you, as the bees do, and they overthrew you in Seir, as far as Chormah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.45'>And ye returned and wept before the Lord; but the Lord hearkened not to your voice, nor gave ear unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.1.46'>And ye tarried in Kadesh many days, according unto the days that ye tarried there.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.2'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.1'>Then we turned, and took our journey into the wilderness by the way of the Red Sea, as the Lord had spoken unto me: and we traveled around mount Seir many days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.2'>And the Lord said unto me, as followeth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.3'>Ye have traveled long enough around this mountain; turn yourselves northward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.4'>And the people command thou, saying, Ye are passing by the border of your brethren the children of Esau, who dwell in Seir; and they will be afraid of you; therefore take ye good heed unto yourselves;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.5'>Do not contend with them; for I will not give unto you of their land, even so much as a foots breadth; because unto Esau have I given mount Seir for an inheritance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.6'>Food shall ye buy of them for money, that ye may eat; and water also shall ye buy of them for money, that ye may drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.7'>For the Lord thy God hath blessed thee in all the works of thy hand; he hath provided for thy wandering through this great wilderness: these forty years the Lord thy God hath been with thee; thou hast lacked nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.8'>And we passed away from our brethren the children of Esau, who dwell in Seir, from the way through the plain, from Elath, and from Ezyongaber. And we turned and passed the way of the wilderness of Moab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.9'>And the Lord said unto me, Do not attack the Moabites, nor contend with them in battle; for I will not give thee from their land any inheritance, because unto the children of Lot have I given Ar for an inheritance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.10'>The Emim in times past dwelt therein, a people great, and numerous, and tall as the Anakim;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.11'>As Rephaim were also they accounted, equally with the Anakim; and the Moabites called the m Emim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.12'>And in Seir dwelt the Chorim in times past; but the children of Esau drove them out, and they destroyed them from before them, and dwelt in their stead; as Israel hath done unto the land of his inheritance, which the Lord hath given unto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.13'>Now rise up, and get you over the brook Zered; and we passed over the brook Zered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.14'>And the time which we came from Kadeshbarnea, until we had passed over the brook Zered, was thirty and eight years; until all the generation of the men of war were spent from out the midst of the camp, as the Lord had sworn unto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.15'>And also the hand of the Lord was against them, to destroy them from the midst of the camp; until they were spent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.16'>So it came to pass, when all the men of war were spent by, dying from the midst of the people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.17'>That the Lord spoke unto me, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.18'>Thou art passing this day by the border of Moab, by Ar,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.19'>And thou comest nigh opposite the children of Ammon: do not attack them, nor contend with them; for I will not give unto thee of the land of the children of Ammon any inheritance; because unto the children of Lot have I given it for an inheritance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.20'>As the land of Rephaim was it also accounted: Rephaim dwelt therein in times past; and the Ammonites called them Zamzummim;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.21'>A people great, and numerous, and tall, as the Anakim; but the Lord destroyed them before them; and they drove them out, and dwelt in their stead:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.22'>As he hath done to the children of Esau, who dwell in Seir, from before whom he destroyed the Chorim; and they drove them out and dwelt in their stead, even unto this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.23'>And the Avvim, who dwelt in open towns, as far as unto Gazzah,the Caphtorim, who came forth out of Caphtor, destroyed them, and dwelt in their stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.24'>Rise ye up, set forward, and pass over the brook Arnon; behold I have given into thy hand Sichon the king of Cheshbon, the Emorite, and his land: begin to drive him out, and contend with him in battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.25'>This day will I begin to put the dread of thee and the fear of thee upon the nations that are under the whole heaven; whoever will hear the report of thee, shall tremble, and shall quake because of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.26'>And I sent messengers out of the wilderness of Kedemoth unto Sichon, the king of Cheshbon, with words of peace, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.27'>Let me pass through thy land: always by the highway will I go along; I will not turn unto the right hand or unto the left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.28'>Food shalt thou sell me for money, that I may eat; and water for money shalt thou give me, that I may drink: only let me pass through on foot;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.29'>(As the children of Esau who dwell in Seir, and the Moabites who dwell in Ar, have done unto me:) until that I shall pass over the Jordan into the land which the Lord our God giveth us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.30'>But Sichon, the king of Cheshbon, would not suffer our passing by him; for the Lord thy God had hardened his spirit, and had made obstinate his heart, that he might deliver him into thy hand, as hath happened this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.31'>And the Lord said unto me, Behold, I have begun to give up Sichon and his land before thee: begin to drive him out, that thou mayest inherit his land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.32'>And Sichon came out against us, he and all his people, to the battle at Yahaz.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.33'>And the Lord our God gave him up before us; and we smote him, and his sons, and all his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.34'>And we conquered all his cities at that time, and devoted every inhabited city, and the women, and the little ones; we left none that escaped.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.35'>Only the cattle we took as booty unto ourselves, and the spoil of the cities which we had captured.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.36'>From Aroer, which is by the bank of the brook of Arnon, and the city that is in the brook, even unto Gilad, there was not one city which was too strong for us; the whole did the Lord our God give up before us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.2.37'>Only unto the land of the children of Ammon didst thou not come nigh, unto the whole margin of the brook Yabbok, and the cities in the mountain, and unto whatsoever the Lord our God had forbidden us.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.3'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.1'>And we turned, and went up the way to Bashan; and Og the king of Bashan came out against us, he and all his people, to the battle at Edrei.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.2'>And the Lord said unto me, Fear him not; for into thy hand have I given him, and all his people, and his land; and thou shalt do unto him as thou hast done unto Sichon, the king of the Emorites, who dwelt at Cheshbon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.3'>And the Lord our God gave into our hands also Og the king of Bashan, and all his people; and we smote him until none was left to him who escaped.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.4'>And we conquered all his cities at that time, there was not a city which we took not from them, sixty cities, all the region of Argob, the kingdom of Og in Bashan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.5'>all these were fortified cities, with high walls, gates, and bars; besides the unwalled towns, which were a great many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.6'>And we devoted them, as we had done unto Sichon the king of Cheshbon, devoting every inhabited city, the women, and the little ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.7'>But all the cattle, and the spoil of the cities, we took as booty to ourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.8'>And we took at that time out of the hand of the two kings of the Emorites the land which is on this side of the Jordan, from the river of Arnon unto mount Chermon;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.9'>(The Sidonians call Chermon Siryon; and the Emorites call it Senir;)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.10'>All the cities of the plain, and all Gilad, and all Bashan, unto Salchah and Edrei, the cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.11'>For only Og the king of Bashan had been left of the remnant of the Rephaim; behold, his bedstead was a bedstead of iron; lo! it is in Rabbah of the children of Ammon: nine cubits is its length, and four cubits its breadth, after the arm of a man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.12'>And of this land, of which we took possession at that time, from Aroer, which is by the river Arnon, and half mount Gilad, and the cities thereof, I gave unto the Reubenites and to the Gadites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.13'>And the rest of Gilad, and all Bashan, the kingdom of Og, I gave unto the half tribe of Menasseh: all the region of Argob, with all Bashan, this is called the land of Rephaim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.14'>Yair the son of Menasseh took all the region of Argob up to the border of the Geshurites and the Maachathites; and he called them the land of Bashan, after his own name, the villages of Yair, unto this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.15'>And unto Machir I gave Gilad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.16'>And unto the Reubenites and unto the Gadites I gave from Gilad even unto the brook Arnon, the land within the river and that adjoining, even unto the brook Yabbok, the border of the children of Ammon;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.17'>The plain also, and the Jordan, and the adjoining land, from Kinnereth even unto the sea of the plain, the Salt Sea, under the declivities of Pisgah, eastward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.18'>And I commanded you at that time, saying, The Lord your God hath given you this land to possess it: armed shall ye pass over before your brethren the children of Israel, all that are fit to bear arms.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.19'>But your wives, and your little ones, and your cattle, (I know that ye have much cattle,) shall abide in your cities which I have given you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.20'>Until that the Lord have given rest unto your brethren, as well as unto you, and they also have taken possession of the land which the Lord your God giveth them beyond the Jordan: then shall ye return every man unto his possession which I have given you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.21'>And Joshua also I commanded at that time, saying, Thy own eyes have seen all that the Lord your God hath done unto these two kings: thus will the Lord do unto all the kingdoms whither thou passest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.22'>Ye shall not fear them; for the Lord your God it is who fighteth for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.23'>And I besought the Lord at that time, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.24'>O Lord Eternal, thou hast begun to show thy servant thy greatness, and thy mighty hand; for what God is there in heaven or on earth, that can do aught like thy works, and like thy mighty deeds?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.25'>Let me go over, I pray thee, that I may see the good land which is on the other side of the Jordan, this goodly mountain, and the Lebanon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.26'>But the Lord was wroth with me for your sakes, and he would not hear me: and the Lord said unto me, Let it suffice thee; do not continue to speak unto me any more of this matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.27'>Get thee up unto the top of Pisgah, and lift up thy eyes, westward, and northward, and southward, and eastward, and behold it with thy eyes; for thou shalt not pass over this Jordan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.28'>And do thou charge Joshua, and strengthen him, and encourage him; for he shall go over before this people, and he shall divide out to them the land which thou shalt see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.3.29'>And we abode in the valley opposite Bethpeor.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.4'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.1'>And now, O Israel, hearken unto the statutes and unto the ordinances which I teach you to do; in order that ye may live, and go in and take possession of the land which the Lord, the God of your fathers, giveth unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.2'>Ye shall not add unto the word which I command you, nor shall ye diminish aught from it; that ye may keep the commandments of the Lord your God which I command you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.3'>Your own eyes have seen that which the Lord hath done because of Baalpeor; for every man that followed Baalpeor, him the Lord thy God hath destroyed from the midst of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.4'>But ye that did cleave unto the Lord your God, are alive, every one of you, this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.5'>See, I have taught you statutes and ordinances, just as the Lord my God commanded me; that ye may do so in the midst of the land whither ye go to take possession of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.6'>Keep therefore and do them; for this is your wisdom and your understanding before the eyes of the nations, that shall hear all these statutes, and they will say, Nothing but a wise and understanding people is this great nation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.7'>For what great nation is there that hath gods so nigh unto it, as is the Lord our God at all times that we call upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.8'>And what great nation is there that hath statutes and ordinances so righteous as is all this law, which I lay before you this day?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.9'>Only take heed to thyself, and guard thy soul diligently, that thou do not forget the things which thy eyes have seen, and that they depart not from thy heart all the days of thy life; but thou shalt make them known unto thy sons, and unto thy sons sons;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.10'>The day that thou stoodest before the Lord thy God at Horeb, when the Lord said unto me, Assemble for me the people, and I will cause them to hear my words, which they shall learn, to fear me all the days that they shall live upon the earth, and which they shall teach their children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.11'>And ye came near and stood at the foot of the mount; and the mount was burning with fire unto the midst of the heaven, from amidst darkness, clouds, and thick darkness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.12'>And the Lord spoke unto you out of the midst of the fire; the sound of words ye heard, but any similitude ye saw not: there was nothing but a sound.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.13'>And he told unto you his covenant, which he commanded you to perform, the ten commandments; and he wrote them upon two tables of stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.14'>And me the Lord commanded at that time to teach you statutes and ordinances, that ye might do them in the land whither ye go over to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.15'>Take ye therefore good heed of your souls; for ye saw no manner of similitude on the day that the Lord spoke unto you at Horeb out of the midst of the fire:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.16'>That ye become not corrupt, and make yourselves a graven image, the similitude of any idolfigure, the likeness of a male or of a female,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.17'>The likeness of any beast that is on the earth, the likeness of any winged fowl that flieth in the air of heaven,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.18'>The likeness of any thing that creepeth on the ground, the likeness of any fish that is in the waters beneath the earth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.19'>And that thou lift not up thy eyes unto the heavens, and thou see the sun, and the moon, and the stars, all the host of heaven, and be misled to bow down to them, and to serve them, those which the Lord thy God hath assigned unto all nations under the whole heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.20'>But you did the Lord take, and he brought you forth out of the iron furnace, out of Egypt, to be unto you a people of inheritance, as ye are this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.21'>Farthermore the Lord was angry with me for your sakes, and he swore that I should not go over the Jordan, and that I should not go in unto that good land, which the Lord thy God giveth unto thee for an inheritance;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.22'>For I must die in this land; I shall not go over the Jordan; but ye will go over and take possession of this good land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.23'>Take heed unto yourselves, that ye do not forget the covenant of the Lord your God, which he hath made with you, and make yourselves a graven image, the likeness of any thing, which the Lord thy God hath forbidden thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.24'>For the Lord thy God is a consuming fire; yea, a watchful God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.25'>When thou begettest children, and childrens children, and ye shall have remained long in the land, and ye become corrupt, and make a graven image, the likeness of any thing, and do the evil in the eyes of the Lord thy God, to provoke him to anger:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.26'>I call this day the heavens and the earth to witness against you, that ye shall soon perish from off the land whereunto ye go over the Jordan to possess it; ye shall not remain many days upon it, but ye shall surely be destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.27'>And the Lord will scatter you among the nations, and ye will be left few in number among the nations, whither the Lord will lead you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.28'>And ye will serve there gods, the work of mans hands, wood and stone, which neither can see, nor hear, nor eat, nor smell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.29'>But thou wilt seek from there the Lord thy God, and wilt find him, if thou apply to him with all thy heart and with all thy soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.30'>When thou art in tribulation, and all these things have overtaken thee, in the latter end of days: then wilt thou return to the Lord thy God, and be obedient unto his voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.31'>For a merciful God is the Lord thy God; he will not forsake thee, nor destroy thee; and he will not forget the covenant of thy fathers which he hath sworn unto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.32'>For do but ask of former days, which were before thee, since the day that God created man upon the earth, and from the one end of the heavens unto the other end of the heavens, whether there hath been the like of this great thing, or whether the like of it hath been heard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.33'>Hath ever a people heard the voice of a god, speaking out of the midst of the fire, as thou hast heard, and remained alive?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.34'>Or hath a god essayed to go to take himself a nation from the midst of a nation, by proofs, by signs, and by wonders, and by war, and by a mighty hand, and by an outstretched arm, and by great terrors, like all that which the Lord your God hath done for you in Egypt before thy eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.35'>Unto thee it was shown, that thou mightest know, that the Eternal is the God: there is none else besides him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.36'>Out of the heavens he caused thee to hear his voice, to correct thee: and upon the earth he caused thee to see his great fire; and his words didst thou hear out of the midst of the fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.37'>And therefore, because he loved thy fathers, he chose their seed after them, and brought thee out in his presence with his mighty power out of Egypt;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.38'>To drive out nations greater and mightier than thou art, from before thee, to bring thee in, to give unto thee their land for an inheritance, as it is this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.39'>Know therefore this day, and reflect in thy heart, that the Eternal is the God in the heavens above, and upon the earth beneath: there is none else.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.40'>And thou shalt keep his statutes, and his commandments, which I command thee this day, that it may go well with thee, and with thy children after thee; and that thou mayest live many days upon the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, for all times.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.41'>Then Moses set aside three cities on this side of the Jordan, toward the rising of the sun;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.42'>That thither might flee the manslayer, who should kill his neighbor unawares, when he had not been an enemy to him in times past; and that he should flee unto one of these cities and live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.43'>Bezer in the wilderness, in the plain country, for the Reubenites; and Ramoth in Gilad for the Gadites; and Golan in Bashan for the Menassites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.44'>And this is the law which Moses set before the children of Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.45'>These are the testimonies, and the statutes, and the ordinances, which Moses spoke unto the children of Israel, when they came forth out of Egypt,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.46'>On this side of the Jordan, in the valley opposite to Bethpeor, in the land of Sichon the king of the Emorites, who dwelt at Cheshbon, whom Moses and the children of Israel smote, after they were come forth out of Egypt;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.47'>And they took possession of his land, and of the land of Og the king of Bashan, the two kings of the Emorites, who were on this side of the Jordan toward the rising of the sun;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.48'>From Aroer, which is on the bank of the river Arnon, even unto mount Sion, which is Chermon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.4.49'>And all the plain on this side of the Jordan eastward, even unto the sea of the plain, under the declivities of Pisgah.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.5'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.1'>And Moses called all Israel, and said unto them, Hear, O Israel, the statutes and the ordinances which I speak in your ears this day, that ye may learn them, and that ye may observe to do them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.2'>The Lord our God made a covenant with us in Horeb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.3'>Not with our fathers did the Lord make this covenant, but with us, we who are here all of us alive this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.4'>Face to face did the Lord speak with you on the mount, out of the midst of the fire,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.5'>(I was standing between the Lord and between you at that time, to announce to you the word of the Lord; for ye were afraid by reason of the fire, and ye went not up into the mount;) saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.6'>I am the Lord thy God, who have brought thee out of the land of Egypt, from the house of slavery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.7'>Thou shalt have no other gods before me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.8'>Thou shalt not make unto thyself any graven image, any likeness of any thing that is in the heavens above, or that is on the earth beneath, or that is in the water under the earth:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.9'>Thou shalt not bow thyself down unto them, nor serve them; for I the Lord thy God am a jealous God, visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children, and upon the third and upon the fourth generation of them that hate me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.10'>And showing kindness unto the thousandth generation of them that love me, and keep my commandments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.11'>Thou shalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vain; for the Lord will not hold him guiltless that taketh his name in vain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.12'>Keep the sabbathday to sanctify it, as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.13'>Six days shalt thou labor, and do all thy work;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.14'>But the seventh day is the sabbath in honor of the Lord thy God; on it thou shalt not do any work, neither thou, nor thy son, nor thy daughter, nor thy manservant, nor thy maidservant, nor thy ox, nor thy ass, nor any of thy cattle, nor thy stranger that is within thy gates: in order that thy manservant and thy maidservant may rest as well as thou.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.15'>And thou shalt remember that thou hast been a servant in the land of Egypt, and that the Lord thy God brought thee out from there by a mighty hand and by an outstretched arm; therefore hath the Lord thy God commanded thee to observe the sabbathday.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.16'>Honor thy father and thy mother, as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee: in order that thy days may be prolonged, and in order that it may go well with thee, in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.17'>Thou shalt not kill.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.18'>
          <note>(5:17AA)</note> Neither shalt thou commit adultery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.19'>
          <note>(5:17BA)</note> Neither shalt thou steal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.20'>
          <note>(5:17CA)</note> Neither shalt thou bear false witness against thy neighbor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.21'>
          <note>(5:18)</note> Neither shalt thou covet thy neighbors wife. Neither shalt thou desire thy neighbors house, nor his field, nor his manservant, nor his maidservant, nor his ox, nor his ass, nor anything that is thy neighbors.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.22'>
          <note>(5:19)</note> These words did the Lord speak unto all your assembly on the mount out of the midst of the fire, of the cloud, and of the thick darkness, with a great voice, but he did so no more; and he wrote them on two tables of stone, and he gave them unto me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.23'>
          <note>(5:20)</note> And it came to pass, when ye heard the voice out of the midst of the darkness, while the mount was burning with fire, that ye came near unto me, even all the heads of your tribes, and your elders;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.24'>
          <note>(5:21)</note> And ye said, Behold, the Lord our God hath caused us to see his glory and his greatness, and his voice have we heard out of the midst of the fire: this day have we seen that God can speak with man, who nevertheless may live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.25'>
          <note>(5:22)</note> But now why should we die? for this great fire may consume us; if we continue to hear the voice of the Lord our God any more, then shall we die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.26'>
          <note>(5:23)</note> For where is there any flesh, that hath heard the voice of the living God speaking out of the midst of the fire, like us, and hath remained alive?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.27'>
          <note>(5:24)</note> Do thou approach, and hear all that the Lord our God may say; and thou shalt speak unto us all that the Lord our God may speak unto thee; and we will hear and do it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.28'>
          <note>(5:25)</note> And the Lord heard the voice of your words, while ye were speaking unto me; and the Lord said unto me, I have heard the voice of the words of this people, which they have spoken unto thee: they have done well in all that they have spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.29'>
          <note>(5:26)</note> Who would grant that this their heart might remain in them, to fear me, and to keep all my commandments at all times; in order that it might be well with them, and with their children for ever!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.30'>
          <note>(5:27)</note> Go, say to them, Return you unto your tents.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.31'>
          <note>(5:28)</note> But as for thee, remain thou here by me, and I will speak unto thee all the commandments, and the statutes, and the ordinances, which thou shalt teach them, that they may do them in the land which I give them to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.32'>
          <note>(5:29)</note> Observe ye then to do as the Lord your God hath commanded you: ye shall not turn aside to the right or to the left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.5.33'>
          <note>(5:30)</note> altogether in the way, which the Lord your God hath commanded you, shall ye walk; in order that ye may live, and that it may be well with you, and that ye may remain many days in the land which ye will possess.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.6'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.1'>And this is the commandment, with the statutes, and the ordinances, which the Lord your God hath commanded to teach you, to do them in the land whither ye are passing over to possess it:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.2'>In order that you mayest fear the Lord thy God, to keep all his statutes and his commandments, which I command thee, thou and thy son, and thy sons son, all the days of thy life; and in order that thy days may be prolonged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.3'>Hear, therefore, O Israel, and observe to do them; that it may be well with thee, and that ye may increase greatly, as the Lord the God of thy fathers hath spoken to thee, in the land flowing with milk and honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.4'>Hear, O Israel! The Lord, our God, is the One Eternal Being.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.5'>And thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy might.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.6'>And these words which I command thee this day, shall be in thy heart:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.7'>And thou shalt teach them diligently unto thy children, and thou shalt speak of them when thou sittest in thy house, and when thou walkest by the way, and when thou liest down, and when thou risest up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.8'>And thou shalt bind them for a sign upon thy hand, and they shall be as frontlets between thy eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.9'>And thou shalt write them upon the doorposts of thy house, and upon thy gates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.10'>And it shall be, when the Lord thy God shall bring thee into the land which he hath sworn unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give unto thee, great and goodly cities, which thou didst not build,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.11'>And houses full of all good things, which thou didst not fill, and wells hewed out which thou didst not hew, vineyards and olivetrees, which thou didst not plant; and thou hast eaten and art satisfied:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.12'>Then beware that thou do not forget the Lord, who hath brought thee forth out of the land of Egypt, from the house of slavery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.13'>The Lord thy God shalt thou fear, and him shalt thou serve, and by his name shalt thou swear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.14'>Ye shall not go after other gods, of the gods of the nations which are round about you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.15'>For the Lord thy God is a watchful God among you: so that the anger of the Lord thy God may not be kindled against thee, and he destroy thee from off the face of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.16'>Ye shall not tempt the Lord your God, as ye tempted him in Massah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.17'>Ye shall diligently keep the commandments of the Lord your God, and his testimonies, and his statutes, which he hath commanded thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.18'>And thou shalt do that which is right and good in the eyes of the Lord; in order that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayest go in and take possession of the good land which the Lord hath sworn unto thy fathers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.19'>To cast out all thy enemies from before thee; as the Lord hath spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.20'>When thy son should ask thee in time to come, saying, What mean the testimonies, and the statutes, and the ordinances, which the Lord our God hath commanded you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.21'>Then shalt thou say unto thy son, We were bondmen unto Pharaoh in Egypt; and the Lord brought us out of Egypt with a mighty hand;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.22'>And the Lord let come signs and wonders, great and sore, on Egypt, on Pharaoh, and on all his household, before our eyes;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.23'>And us he brought out from there; in order to bring us in, to give us the land which he had sworn unto our fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.24'>And the Lord commanded us to do all these statutes, to fear the Lord our God; that it might be well with us at all times, and that he might preserve us alive, as it is at this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.6.25'>And it shall be accounted righteousness unto us, if we observe to do all this commandment before the Lord our God, as he hath commanded us.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.7'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.1'>When the Lord thy God shall bring thee into the land whither thou goest to possess it, and cast out many nations before thee, the Hittites, and the Girgashites, and the Emorites, and the Canaanites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites, seven nations, greater in number and mightier than thou;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.2'>And when the Lord thy God shall give them up before thee, and thou dost smite them: thou shalt utterly destroy them; thou shalt not make any covenant with them, nor show mercy unto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.3'>Neither shalt thou make marriages with them; thy daughters shalt thou not give unto his son, and his daughter shalt thou not take unto thy son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.4'>For he would turn away thy son from following me, so that they might serve other gods; and the anger of the Lord would be kindled against you, and he would destroy thee speedily.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.5'>But thus shall ye do unto them: their altars shall ye pull down, and their statues shall ye break, and their groves shall ye cut down, and their graven images shall ye burn with fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.6'>For thou art a holy people unto the Lord thy God; of thee the Lord thy God hath made choice to be unto himself a special people, above all the nations that are upon the face of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.7'>Not because ye are more in number than all the nations, did the Lord desire you and make choice of you; for ye are the fewest of all the nations;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.8'>But on account of the love of the Lord for you, and because he keepeth the oath which he hath sworn unto your fathers, hath the Lord brought you out with a mighty hand, and redeemed you out of the house of bondmen, out of the hand of Pharaoh the king of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.9'>Know then that the Eternal thy God, is the God, the faithful God, who keepeth the covenant and the mercy with those that love him and with those that keep his commandments to the thousandth generation;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.10'>And repayeth those that hate him to their face, to destroy them; he will not delay to him that hateth him, he will repay him to his face.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.11'>Therefore shalt thou keep the commandment, and the statutes, and the ordinances, which I command thee this day, to do them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.12'>And it shall come to pass in reward for that ye will hearken to these ordinances, and keep, and do them, that the Lord thy God will keep unto thee the covenant and the kindness which he hath sworn unto thy fathers:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.13'>And he will love thee, and bless thee, and multiply thee; and he will bless the fruit of thy womb, and the fruit of thy land, thy corn, and thy wine, and thy oil, the increase of thy cattle, and the young of thy flocks, in the land which he hath sworn unto thy fathers to give unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.14'>Blessed shalt thou be above all the nations; there shall not be a barren male or female among thee, nor among thy cattle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.15'>And the Lord will take away from thee all sickness; and all the evil diseases of Egypt, which thou knowest, will he not put upon thee; but he will lay them upon all those that hate thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.16'>And thou shalt consume all the nations which the Lord thy God giveth unto thee; thy eye shall not look with pity upon them: and thou shalt not serve their gods; for that would be a snare unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.17'>If thou shouldst say in thy heart, These nations are more numerous than I: how shall I be able to dispossess them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.18'>Thou shalt not be afraid of them; but thou shalt well remember what the Lord thy God did unto Pharaoh, and unto all Egypt;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.19'>The great proofs which thy eyes have seen, and the signs, and the wonders, and the mighty hand, and the outstretched arm, whereby the Lord thy God brought thee out: in this wise will the Lord thy God do unto all the people of whom thou art afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.20'>Moreover the hornet will the Lord thy God send out against them, until they that are left, and hide themselves from thee, be destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.21'>Thou shalt not be affrighted at them; for the Lord thy God is in the midst of thee, a mighty and terrible God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.22'>And the Lord thy God will chase out these nations before thee, little by little: thou shalt not be able to make an end of them speedily, lest the beasts of the field increase upon thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.23'>And the Lord thy God will give them up before thee, and he will bring among them a mighty confusion, until they be destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.24'>And he will give their kings into thy hand, and thou shalt destroy their name from under the heavens: no man shall be able to stand up before thee, until thou have destroyed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.25'>The graven images of their gods shall ye burn with fire: thou shalt not covet the silver or gold that is on them, so that thou wouldst take it unto thyself, lest thou be ensnared thereby; for it is an abomination to the Lord thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.7.26'>And thou shalt not bring an abomination into thy house, lest thou become accursed like it: thou shalt utterly detest it, and thou shalt utterly abhor it; for it is accursed.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.8'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.1'>All the commandment which I command thee this day shall ye observe to do; in order that ye may live, and multiply, and go in and take possession of the land which the Lord hath sworn unto your fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.2'>And thou shalt remember all the way which the Lord thy God hath led thee these forty years in the wilderness, in order to afflict thee, to prove thee, to know what is in thy heart, whether thou wouldst keep his commandments, or not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.3'>And he afflicted thee, and suffered thee to hunger, and he gave thee manna to eat, which thou knewest not, and which thy fathers had not known; in order that he might make thee know that not by bread alone man doth live, but by every thing that proceedeth out of the mouth of the Lord doth man live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.4'>Thy garment did not fall worn out from thee, and thy foot did not swell, these forty years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.5'>And thou shalt consider in thy heart, that, as a man chasteneth his son, so doth the Lord thy God chasten thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.6'>And thou shalt keep the commandments of the Lord thy God, to walk in his ways, and to fear him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.7'>For the Lord thy God bringeth thee into a good land, a land of brooks of water, of fountains and depths that spring out of valleys and mountains;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.8'>A land of wheat, and barley, and of the vine, and the figtree, and the pomegranate; a land of the oilolive, and of honey;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.9'>A land wherein thou shalt eat bread without scarceness, wherein thou shalt not lack anything; a land the stones whereof are iron, and out of the mountains of which thou canst hew copper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.10'>And when thou hast eaten and art satisfied, then shalt thou bless the Lord thy God for the good land which he hath given thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.11'>Take heed unto thyself that thou forget not the Lord thy God, so as not to keep his commandments, and his ordinances, and his statutes, which I command thee this day;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.12'>That when thou hast eaten and art satisfied, and hast built goodly houses, and dwelt therein;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.13'>And when thy herds and thy flocks multiply, and thy silver and thy gold are multiplied, and all that thou hast is multiplied:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.14'>Thy heart be then not lifted up, and thou forget the Lord thy God, who hath brought thee forth out of the land of Egypt, from the house of slavery;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.15'>Who hath led thee through the great and terrible wilderness, wherein are snakes, poisonous serpents, and scorpions, and drought, where there is no water; who hath brought forth for thee water out of the flinty rock;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.16'>Who hath fed thee in the wilderness with manna, which thy fathers knew not; in order to afflict thee, and in order to prove thee, to do thee good at thy latter end;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.17'>And thou say in thy heart, My power and the strength of my hand have gotten me this wealth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.18'>But thou shalt remember the Lord thy God; for it is he that giveth thee power to get wealth; in order that he might fulfill his covenant which he hath sworn unto thy fathers, as it is this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.19'>And it shall come to pass, that, if thou shouldst forget the Lord thy God, and walk after other gods, and serve them, and bow thyself down to them, I testify against you this day that ye shall surely perish;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.8.20'>Like the nations which the Lord destroyeth from before you, so shall ye perish; in recompense of that ye would not hearken unto the voice of the Lord your God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.9'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.1'>Hear, O Israel: Thou art to pass this day over the Jordan, to go in to drive out nations greater and mightier than thou, to conquer cities great and fortified up to heaven,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.2'>A people great and tall, the children of the Anakim, whom thou knowest, and of whom thou hast heard say, Who can stand before the children of Anak!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.3'>Understand therefore this day, that the Lord thy God it is who goeth over before thee, he is a consuming fire; he will destroy them, and he will subdue them before thy face; and thou wilt drive them out, and destroy them quickly, as the Lord hath spoken unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.4'>Thou must not say in thy heart, when the Lord thy God doth cast them out from before thee, as followeth, For my righteousness hath the Lord brought me in to possess this land; and that for the wickedness of these nations the Lord doth drive them out from before thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.5'>Not for thy righteousness, nor for the uprightness of thy heart, dost thou go in to possess their land; but for the wickedness of these nations doth the Lord thy God drive them out from before thee, and in order that he may fulfill the word which the Lord hath sworn unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.6'>And thou shalt know, that not for thy righteousness doth the Lord thy God give unto thee this good land to possess it; for thou art a stiffnecked people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.7'>Remember, do not forget, how thou didst provoke the Lord thy God to wrath in the wilderness: from the day that thou wentest out of the land of Egypt, until ye came unto this place, have ye been rebellious against the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.8'>Also at Horeb ye provoked the Lord to wrath, so that the Lord was angry with you to destroy you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.9'>When I was gone up into the mount to receive the tables of stone, the tables of the covenant which the Lord had made with you, and I abode on the mount forty days and forty nights, bread did I not eat, and water did I not drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.10'>And the Lord gave unto me the two tables of stone inscribed by the finger of God; and on them was written according to all the words, which the Lord had spoken with you on the mount out of the midst of the fire on the day of the assembly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.11'>And it came to pass at the end of forty days and forty nights, that the Lord gave unto me the two tables of stone, the tables of the covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.12'>And the Lord said unto me, Arise, get thee down quickly from here; for thy people which thou hast brought forth out of Egypt have become corrupted; they have quickly turned aside out of the way which I have commanded them; they have made themselves a molten image.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.13'>And the Lord said unto me, thus, I have seen this people, and, behold, it is a stiffnecked people:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.14'>Let me alone, and I will destroy them, and blot out their name from under the heavens; and I will make of thee a nation mightier and more numerous than they.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.15'>And I turned and came down from the mount, and the mount was burning with fire; and the two tables of the covenant were upon my two hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.16'>And I looked, and, behold, ye had sinned against the Lord your God, ye had made yourselves a molten calf; ye had turned aside quickly out of the way which the Lord had commanded you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.17'>And I took hold of the two tables, and cast them out of my two hands, and I broke them before your eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.18'>And I threw myself down before the Lord, as at the first, forty days and forty nights; bread did I not eat, and water did I not drink; on account of all your sins which ye had committed, in doing what is evil in the eyes of the Lord, to provoke him to anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.19'>For I was afraid of the anger and the indignation, wherewith the Lord was wroth against you to destroy you; but the Lord hearkened unto me also at that time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.20'>And with Aaron was the Lord very angry to destroy him; and I prayed also for Aaron at the same time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.21'>And your work of sin, which ye had made, the calf, I took and burnt it in fire, and stamped it, grinding it very small, until it was as fine as dust: and I cast the dust thereof into the brook that descendeth from the mount.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.22'>And at Taberah, and at Massah and at Kibrothhattaavah, have ye been provoking the Lord to wrath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.23'>And when the Lord sent you from Kadeshbarnea, saying, Go up and take possession of the land which I have given you: then rebelled ye against the order of the Lord your God, and ye believed not in him, and ye hearkened not to his voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.24'>Rebellious have ye been against the Lord, from the day that I have known you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.25'>And I threw myself down before the Lord those forty days and forty nights, which I threw myself down; because the Lord had said that he would destroy you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.26'>And I prayed unto the Lord, and said, O Lord Eternal, destroy not thy people and thy heritage, which thou hast redeemed through thy greatness, which thou hast brought forth out of Egypt with a mighty hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.27'>Think of thy servants, of Abraham, of Isaac, and of Jacob; turn not unto the stubbornness of this people, nor to its wickedness, nor to its sin:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.28'>Lest the inhabitants of the land whence thou hast brought us out say, Out of want of ability in the Lord to bring them into the land which he had promised them, and out of his hatred to them, hath he brought them out to slay them in the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.9.29'>Whereas they are thy people and thy heritage, whom thou hast brought out by thy mighty power and by thy outstretched arm.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.10'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.1'>At that time the Lord said unto me, Hew for thyself two tables of stone like unto the first, and come up unto me into the mount; and make thyself an ark of wood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.2'>And I will write on the tables the words that were on the first tables which thou hast broken; and thou shalt put them in the ark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.3'>And I made an ark of shittimwood, and hewed two tables of stone like unto the first; and I went up into the mount, with the two tables in my hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.4'>And he wrote on the tables, like the first writing, the ten commandments, which the Lord had spoken unto you on the mount out of the midst of the fire on the day of the assembly; and the Lord gave them unto me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.5'>And I turned myself and came down from the mount, and I put the tables in the ark which I had made; and they have remained there, as the Lord hath commanded me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.6'>And the children of Israel took their journey from the wells of the children of Yaakan to Mosserah: there Aaron died, and he was buried there; and Elazar his son became priest in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.7'>From there they journeyed unto Gudgodah; and from Gudgodah to Yotbatha, a land of brooks of waters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.8'>At that time did the Lord separate the tribe of Levi, to bear the ark of the covenant of the Lord, to stand before the Lord to minister unto him, and to bless in his name, unto this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.9'>Therefore was not assigned unto Levi any portion or inheritance with his brethren: the Lord is his inheritance, as the Lord thy God hath spoken to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.10'>And I stayed on the mount, like the first days, forty days and forty nights; and the Lord hearkened unto me also at that time, the Lord would not destroy thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.11'>And the Lord said unto me, Arise, go on the journey before the people, that they may go in and take possession of the land, which I have sworn unto their fathers to give unto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.12'>And now, Israel, what doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to fear the Lord thy God, to walk in all his ways, and to love him, and to serve the Lord thy God with all thy heart and with all thy soul,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.13'>To keep the commandments of the Lord, and his statutes, which I command thee this day, for thy own good?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.14'>Behold, to the Lord thy God belong the heavens and the heavens of heavens, and the earth with all that is thereon;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.15'>Yet only in thy fathers had the Lord delight, to love them; he chose, therefore, their seed after them, namely you, from all the nations, as it is this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.16'>Remove therefore the obduracy of your heart, and be no more stiffnecked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.17'>For the Lord your God is the God of gods, and the Lord of lords, the great, the mighty, and the terrible God, who hath no regard to persons, and taketh no bribe;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.18'>Who executeth justice for the fatherless and the widow, and loveth the stranger, to give him food and raiment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.19'>Love ye then the stranger; for you have been strangers in the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.20'>The Lord thy God shalt thou fear: him shalt thou serve, and to him shalt thou cleave, and by his name shalt thou swear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.21'>He is thy praise, and he is thy God, who hath done for thee these great and fearful things, which thy own eyes have seen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.10.22'>With seventy persons did thy fathers go down into Egypt; and now the Lord thy God hath made thee like the stars of heaven in multitude.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.11'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.1'>Thou shalt therefore love the Lord thy God, and keep his charge, and his statutes, and his ordinances, and his commandments, all the days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.2'>And ye shall know this day, that I speak not with your children who have not known, and who have not seen the chastisement of the Lord your God, his greatness, his strong hand, and his outstretched arm;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.3'>And his signs, and his acts, which he displayed in the midst of Egypt, unto Pharaoh the king of Egypt, and unto all his land;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.4'>And what he did unto the army of Egypt, unto its horses, and to its chariots; over whom he caused the water of the Red Sea to flow, as they pursued after you, and whom the Lord destroyed unto this day;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.5'>And what he did unto you in the wilderness, until ye came unto this place;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.6'>And what he did unto Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab, the son of Reuben; how the earth opened her mouth, and swallowed them up, and their households, and their tents, and all the living substance that followed them, in the midst of all Israel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.7'>But it is your own eyes which have seen all the great acts of the Lord which he hath done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.8'>Ye shall therefore keep all the commandment which I command you this day, that ye may be strong, and go in and take possession of the land, whither ye go over to possess it;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.9'>And in order that ye may live many days in the land, which the Lord hath sworn unto your fathers to give unto them and to their seed, a land flowing with milk and honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.10'>For the land, whither thou goest in to possess it, is not like the land of Egypt, from where ye came out, where thou sowest thy seed, and waterest it with thy foot, as a garden of herbs;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.11'>But the land, whither ye go over to possess it, is a land of mountains and valleys, from the rain of heaven doth it drink water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.12'>A land which the Lord thy God careth for; always are the eyes of the Lord thy God upon it, from the beginning of the year even unto the end of the year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.13'>And it shall come to pass, if ye will hearken diligently unto my commandments which I command you this day, to love the Lord your God, and to serve him with all your heart and with all your soul,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.14'>That I will send rain for your land in its due season, the first rain and the latter rain, that thou mayest gather in thy corn, and thy wine, and thy oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.15'>And I will give grass in thy field for thy cattle; and thou shalt eat and be satisfied,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.16'>Take heed to yourselves, that your heart be not deceived, and ye turn aside, and serve other gods, and worship them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.17'>For then the Lords wrath will be kindled against you, and he will shut up the heavens that there be no rain, and the land will not yield her products; and ye shall perish quickly from off the good land which the Lord giveth unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.18'>Therefore shall ye lay up these my words in your heart and in your soul; and ye shall bind them for a sign upon your hand, and they shall be as frontlets between your eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.19'>And ye shall teach them to your children, to speak of them when thou sittest in thy house, and when thou walkest by the way, and when thou liest down, and when thou risest up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.20'>And thou shalt write them upon the doorposts of thy house, and upon thy gates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.21'>In order that your days may be multiplied, and the days of your children, in the land which the Lord swore unto your fathers to give unto them, as the days of the heavens over the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.22'>For if ye will diligently keep all this commandment which I command you, in order to do it, to love the Lord your God, to walk in all his ways, and to cleave unto him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.23'>Then will the Lord drive out all these nations from before you, and ye shall supplant nations greater and mightier than yourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.24'>Every place whereon the sole of your foot may tread shall be yours: from the wilderness and the Lebanon, from the river, the river Euphrates, even unto the Western Sea shall be your boundary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.25'>There shall no man be able to stand up before you; the dread of you and the fear of you will the Lord your God lay upon all the land which ye may tread upon, as he hath spoken unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.26'>Behold, I lay before you this day a blessing and a curse:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.27'>The blessing, if ye will hearken unto the commandments of the Lord your God, which I command you this day;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.28'>And the curse, if ye will not hearken unto the commandments of the Lord your God, and ye turn aside out of the way which I command you this day, to go after other gods, which ye know not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.29'>And it shall come to pass, when the Lord thy God shall have brought thee in unto the land whither thou goest to possess it, that thou shalt put the blessing upon mount Gerizzim, and the curse upon mount Ebal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.30'>Behold, they are on the other side of the Jordan, far away in the direction of the going down of the sun, in the land of the Canaanites, who dwell in the plain, opposite Gilgal, near the grove of Moreh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.31'>For ye are about to pass over the Jordan to go in to take possession of the land which the Lord your God giveth you; and ye will possess it, and dwell therein.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.11.32'>And ye shall then observe to do all the statutes and ordinances which I set before you this day.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.12'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.1'>These are the statutes and ordinances, which ye shall observe to do, in the land which the Lord, the God of thy fathers, giveth unto thee to possess it, and all the days that ye live upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.2'>Ye shall utterly destroy all the places whereon the nations which ye are about to drive out served their gods, upon the high mountains, and upon the hills, and under every green tree;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.3'>And ye shall overthrow their altars, and break their statues, and their groves shall ye burn with fire; and the graven images of their gods shall ye hew down; and ye shall destroy their name out of the same place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.4'>Ye shall not do so unto the Lord your God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.5'>But unto the place which the Lord your God may choose out of all your tribes to put his name there, even unto his habitation shall ye repair, and thither shalt thou come;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.6'>And ye shall bring thither your burntofferings, and your sacrifices, and your tithes, and the heaveoffering of your hand, and your vows, and your freewillofferings, and the firstborn of your herds and of your flocks;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.7'>And ye shall eat there before the Lord your God, and ye shall rejoice with all the acquisition of your hand, ye and your households, wherewith the Lord thy God may have blessed thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.8'>Ye shall not do after all the manner that we do here this day, every one whatsoever is right in his own eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.9'>For ye are not as yet come to the rest and to the inheritance, which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.10'>But ye will go over the Jordan, and dwell in the land which the Lord your God causeth you to inherit, and he will give you rest from all your enemies round about, so that ye may dwell in safety.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.11'>And then shall it be, that the place which the Lord your God will choose to cause his name to dwell there,even thither shall ye bring all that I command you: your burntofferings, and your sacrifices, your tithes, and the heaveoffering of your hand, and all your choice vows which ye may vow unto the Lord;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.12'>And ye shall rejoice before the Lord your God, ye, and your sons, and your daughters, and your menservants, and your maidservants, and the Levite who is within your gates; because he hath not any portion nor inheritance with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.13'>Take heed to thyself that thou offer not thy burntofferings in every place which thou mayest see;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.14'>But in the place which the Lord will choose in one of thy tribes, there shalt thou offer thy burntofferings, and there shalt thou do all that I command thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.15'>Notwithstanding, according to all the longing of thy soul, mayest thou kill and eat flesh, according to the blessing of the Lord thy God which he hath given thee, in all thy gates: the unclean and the clean may eat thereof, as of the roebuck, and as of the hart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.16'>Only the blood shall ye not eat: upon the earth shall ye pour it out as water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.17'>Thou mayest not eat within thy gates the tithe of thy corn, or of thy wine, or of thy oil, nor the firstborn of thy herds or of thy flocks, nor any of thy vows which thou mayest vow, nor thy freewillofferings, and the heaveoffering of thy hand;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.18'>But before the Lord thy God must thou eat them in the place which the Lord thy God may choose, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy manservant, and thy maidservant, and the Levite who is within thy gates; and thou shalt rejoice before the Lord thy God with all the acquisition of thy hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.19'>Take heed to thyself that thou forsake not the Levite as long as thou livest upon thy land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.20'>When the Lord thy God will enlarge thy border, as he hath spoken unto thee, and thou dost say, I wish to eat flesh, because thy soul longeth to eat flesh: then mayest thou, according to all the longing of thy soul, eat flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.21'>If the place which the Lord thy God may choose to put his name there be too far for thee: then mayest thou kill of thy herds and of thy flocks, which the Lord hath given thee, as I have commanded thee; and thou shalt eat in thy gates according to all the longing of thy soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.22'>But as the roebuck and the hart are eaten, so shalt thou eat the same: the unclean and the clean may eat thereof together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.23'>Only be firm so as not to eat the blood; for the blood is the life; and thou shalt not eat the life with the flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.24'>Thou shalt not eat it: upon the earth shalt thou pour it out like water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.25'>Thou shalt not eat it; in order that it may go well with thee, and with thy children after thee, when thou wilt do what is right in the eyes of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.26'>Nevertheless thy holy things which thou mayest have, and thy vows, shalt thou take, and go unto the place which the Lord may choose:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.27'>And thou shalt offer thy burntofferings, the flesh and the blood, upon the altar of the Lord thy God; and the blood of thy sacrifices shall be poured out upon the altar of the Lord thy God, and the flesh shalt thou eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.28'>Observe and hear all these words which I command thee; in order that it may go well with thee, and with thy children after thee for ever, when thou wilt do what is good and right in the eyes of the Lord thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.29'>When the Lord thy God will cut off the nations, whither thou goest to drive them out from before thee, and thou succeedest them, and dwellest in their land:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.30'>Then take heed to thyself that thou be not snared by following them, after they have been destroyed from before thee; and that thou inquire not after their gods, saying, How did these nations serve their gods? even so will I do likewise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.31'>Thou shalt not do so unto the Lord thy God; for every abomination to the Lord, which he hateth, have they done unto their gods; for even their sons and their daughters have they burnt in the fire to their gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.12.32'>
          <note>(13:1)</note> What thing soever I command you, even that shall ye observe to do: thou shalt not add thereto, and thou shalt not diminish therefrom.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.13'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.1'>
          <note>(13:2)</note> If there arise in the midst of thee a prophet, or a dreamer of dreams, and he giveth thee a sign or a token,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.2'>
          <note>(13:3)</note> And the sign or the token come to pass, whereof he spoke unto thee, saying, Let us go after other gods, which thou dost not know, and let us serve them:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.3'>
          <note>(13:4)</note> Then shalt thou not hearken unto the words of that prophet, or unto that dreamer of dreams; for the Lord your God proveth you, to know whether ye indeed love the Lord your God with all your heart and with all your soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.4'>
          <note>(13:5)</note> After the Lord your God shall ye walk, and him shall ye fear, and his commandments shall ye keep, and his voice shall ye obey, and him shall ye serve, and unto him shall ye cleave.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.5'>
          <note>(13:6)</note> And that prophet, or that dreamer of dreams, shall be put to death; because he hath spoken revolt against the Lord your God, who hath brought you out of the land of Egypt, and who hath redeemed you out of the house of bondmen, to mislead thee front the way which the Lord thy God commanded thee to walk therein; and thou shalt put the evil away from the midst of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.6'>
          <note>(13:7)</note> If thy brother, the son of thy mother, or thy son, or thy daughter, or the wife of thy bosom, or thy friend, who is dear to thee as thy own soul, should entice thee, in secret, saying, Let us go and serve other gods, which thou dost not know, either thou, or thy fathers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.7'>
          <note>(13:8)</note> Some of the gods of the nations which are round about you, that are nigh unto thee, or that are far off from thee, from one end of the earth even unto the other end of the earth:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.8'>
          <note>(13:9)</note> Then shalt thou not consent unto him, nor shalt thou hearken unto him; nor shall thy eye look with pity on him, nor shalt thou spare, nor shalt thou conceal it for him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.9'>
          <note>(13:10)</note> But thou shalt surely kill him; thy hand shall be the first upon him to put him to death, and the hand of all the people afterward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.10'>
          <note>(13:11)</note> And thou shalt stone him with stones, that he die; because he sought to mislead thee from the Lord thy God, who hath brought thee out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondmen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.11'>
          <note>(13:12)</note> And all Israel shall hear it, and they shall be afraid, and they shall not do any more such a wicked deed as this is in the midst of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.12'>
          <note>(13:13)</note> If thou shouldst hear concerning one of thy cities, which the Lord thy God hath given thee to dwell there, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.13'>
          <note>(13:14)</note> There have gone forth men, children of worthlessness, from the midst of thee, and have misled the inhabitants of their city, saying, Let us go and serve other gods, which ye have not known:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.14'>
          <note>(13:15)</note> Then shalt thou inquire, and make search, and ask diligently; and, behold, if it be true, the thing is certain, such abomination hath been wrought in the midst of thee:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.15'>
          <note>(13:16)</note> Then shalt thou smite the inhabitants of that city with the edge of the sword, devoting it utterly, and all that is therein, and the cattle thereof, to the edge of the sword.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.16'>
          <note>(13:17)</note> And all its spoil shalt thou gather into the midst of the marketplace thereof, and thou shalt burn with fire the city, and all its spoil entirely, unto the Lord thy God; and it shall be a ruinous heap for ever: it shall not be built again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.17'>
          <note>(13:18)</note> And there shall not cleave to thy hand aught of the devoted things; in order that the Lord may turn from the fierceness of his anger, and grant thee mercy, and have mercy upon thee, and multiply thee, as he hath sworn unto thy fathers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.13.18'>
          <note>(13:19)</note> When thou wilt hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God, to keep all his commandments which I command thee this day, to do what is right in the eyes of the Lord thy God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.14'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.1'>Ye are the children of the Lord your God: ye shall not cut yourselves, nor make any baldness between your eyes for the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.2'>For a holy people art thou unto the Lord thy God, and the Lord hath made choice of thee to be unto himself a peculiar nation above all the nations that are upon the face of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.3'>Thou shalt not eat any abominable thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.4'>These are the beasts which ye may eat: The ox, the sheep, and the goat,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.5'>The hart, and the roebuck, and the fallowdeer, and the chamois, and the gazelle, and the wild ox, and the antelope.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.6'>And every beast that hath parted hoofs, and whose feet are cleft into two claws, and cheweth the cud among the beaststhat alone may ye eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.7'>Nevertheless these shall ye not eat of those that chew the cud, and of those that possess the divided cloven hoof: The camel, and the hare, and the coney: for they chew the cud, but divide not the hoof; unclean are they unto you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.8'>And the swine, because it divideth the hoof, yet cheweth not the cud, it is unclean unto you; of their flesh shall ye not eat, and their dead carcass shall ye not touch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.9'>This may ye eat of all that is in the waters: all that hath fins and scales may ye eat;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.10'>And whatsoever hath not fins and scales shall ye not eat; it is unclean unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.11'>Every clean bird may ye eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.12'>But these are they which ye shall not eat of them: The eagle, and the ossifrage, and the osprey,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.13'>And the glede, and the kite, and the vulture after his kind,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.14'>And every raven after his kind,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.15'>And the ostrich, and the nighthawk, and the cuckoo, and the hawk after his kind,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.16'>The little owl, and the great owl and the swan,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.17'>And the pelican, and the giereagle, and the cormorant,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.18'>And the stork, and the heron after his kind, and the lapwing, and the bat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.19'>And every winged insect is unclean unto you: it shall not be eaten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.20'>All clean fowls may ye eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.21'>Ye shall not eat any thing that dieth of itself: unto the stranger that is in thy gates canst thou give it, that he may eat it; or thou mayest sell it unto an alien; for thou art a holy people unto the Lord thy God; thou shalt not seethe a kid in its mothers milk.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.22'>Thou shalt truly tithe all the produce of thy seed, which the field bringeth forth year by year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.23'>And thou shalt eat before the Lord thy God, in the place which he will choose to cause his name to dwell there, the tithe of thy corn, of thy wine, and of thy oil, and the firstborn of thy herds and of thy flocks; in order that thou may learn to fear the Lord thy God all the days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.24'>And if the way be too long for thee, so that thou art not able to carry it; because the place is too far from thee, which the Lord thy God will choose to set his name there, because the Lord thy God will bless thee:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.25'>Then shalt thou turn it into money, and bind up the money in thy hand, and thou shalt go unto the place which the Lord thy God will choose;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.26'>And thou shalt lay out that money for whatsoever thy soul longeth after, for oxen, or for sheep, or for wine, or for strong drink, or for whatsoever thy soul asketh of thee; and thou shalt eat it there before the Lord thy God, and thou shalt rejoice, thou, and thy household.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.27'>And the Levite, who is within thy gates, him shalt thou not forsake; for he hath no portion nor inheritance with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.28'>At the end of three years shalt thou bring forth all the tithe of thy produce in the same year, and thou shalt lay it down within thy gates:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.14.29'>And then shall come the Levite, because he hath no portion nor inheritance with thee, with the stranger, and the fatherless, and the widow, that are within thy gates, and they shall eat and be satisfied; in order that the Lord thy God may bless thee in all the work of thy hand which thou doest.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.15'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.1'>At the end of every seven years shalt thou make a release.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.2'>And this is the manner of the release: Every creditor shall release the loan which he hath lent to his neighbor; he shall not exact it of his neighbor, or of his brother; because the release year in honor of the Lord hath been proclaimed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.3'>Of a foreigner thou mayest exact payment; but that which is thine with thy brother shall thy hand release.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.4'>Although indeed there should be no needy man among thee; for the Lord will greatly bless thee in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance to possess it:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.5'>Yet only if thou wilt carefully hearken unto the voice of the Lord thy God, to observe to do all this commandment which I command thee this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.6'>For the Lord thy God blesseth thee, as he hath spoken unto thee; and thou shalt lend unto many nations, but thou shalt not borrow; and thou shalt rule over many nations, but over thee shall they not rule.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.7'>If there be among thee a needy man, any one of thy brethren within any of thy gates in thy land which the Lord thy God giveth thee: thou shalt not harden thy heart, nor shut thy hand from thy needy brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.8'>But thou shalt open wide thy hand unto him, and thou shalt surely lend him sufficient for his need, which his want requireth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.9'>Beware that there be not a wicked thought in thy heart, saying, The seventh year, the year of release, is at hand; and thy eye be thus evil against thy needy brother, so that thou wouldst give him nought; and if he cry concerning thee unto the Lord, it will be sin in thee:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.10'>Thou shalt surely give him, and thy heart shall not be grieved when thou givest unto him; for because of this thing the Lord thy God will bless thee in all thy work, and in all the acquisition of thy hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.11'>For the needy will not cease out of the land; therefore do I command thee, saying, Thou shalt open wide thy hand unto thy brother, to thy poor, and to thy needy, in thy land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.12'>If thy brother, the Hebrew, or a Hebrew woman, be sold unto thee, he shall serve thee six years; and in the seventh year shalt thou let him go free from thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.13'>And when thou lettest him go out free from thee, thou shalt not let him go away empty:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.14'>Thou shalt furnish him liberally out of thy flocks, and out of thy threshingfloor, and out of thy winepress; wherewith the Lord thy God hath blessed thee, that shalt thou give unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.15'>And thou shalt remember that thou hast been a bondman in the land of Egypt, and that the Lord thy God hath redeemed thee; therefore do I command thee this thing today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.16'>And it shall be, if he say unto thee, I will not go away from thee; because he loveth thee and thy house, because he is well with thee:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.17'>Then shalt thou take an awl, and thrust it through his ear unto the door, and he shall be unto thee a servant for ever; and also unto thy maidservant shalt thou do likewise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.18'>It shall not seem hard unto thee, when thou sendest him away free from thee, that for double the wages of a hired laborer hath he served thee six years; and the Lord thy God will bless thee in all that thou doest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.19'>All the firstborn males that come of thy herds and of thy flocks shalt thou sanctify unto the Lord thy God: thou shalt do no work with the firstborn of thy bullock, and not shear the firstborn of thy sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.20'>Before the Lord thy God shalt thou eat it year by year, in the place which the Lord will choose, thou with thy household.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.21'>And if there be any blemish thereon, if it be lame, or blind, or have any other ill blemish, thou shalt not sacrifice it unto the Lord thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.22'>Within thy gates shalt thou eat it, the unclean and the clean together, as the roebuck, and as the hart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.15.23'>Only the blood thereof shalt thou not eat: upon the ground shalt thou pour it out as water.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.16'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.1'>Observe the month of Abib, and prepare the passoversacrifice unto the Lord thy God; for in the month of Abib did the Lord thy God bring thee forth out of Egypt by night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.2'>And thou shalt sacrifice the passoveroffering unto the Lord thy God of sheep and oxen, in the place which the Lord will choose to let his name dwell there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.3'>Thou shalt not eat therewith any leavened bread: seven days shalt thou eat therewith unleavened bread, the bread of affliction; for in haste didst thou go forth out of the land of Egypt; in order that thou mayest remember the day of thy going forth out of the land of Egypt all the days of thy life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.4'>And there shall not be seen with thee any leaven in all thy borders seven days: neither shall there any of the flesh, which thou sacrificedst in the evening, on the first day, remain all night until the morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.5'>Thou mayest not slay the passover within any of thy gates, which the Lord thy God giveth thee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.6'>But at the place which the Lord thy God will choose to let his name dwell in, there shalt thou slay the passover at evening, at the going down of the sun, at the season that thou camest forth out of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.7'>And thou shalt roast and eat it in the place which the Lord thy God will choose; and thou shalt turn in the morning, and go unto thy tents.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.8'>Six days shalt thou eat unleavened bread; and on the seventh day shall be a solemn assembly to the Lord thy God: thou shalt do no work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.9'>Seven weeks shalt thou number unto thyself: from the time thou beginnest to put the sickle to the corn, shalt thou begin to number seven weeks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.10'>And thou shalt keep the feast of weeks unto the Lord thy God with a tribute of a freewilloffering of thy hand, which thou shalt give: according as the Lord thy God shall have blessed thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.11'>And thou shalt rejoice before the Lord thy God, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy manservant, and thy maidservant, and the Levite that is within thy gates, and the stranger, and the fatherless, and the widow, that are in the midst of thee, in the place which the Lord thy God will choose to let his name dwell there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.12'>And thou shalt remember that thou hast been a bondman in Egypt; and thou shalt observe and do these statutes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.13'>The feast of tabernacles shalt thou hold for thyself seven days, when thou hast gathered in the produce of thy threshingfloor and of thy winepress:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.14'>And thou shalt rejoice on thy feast, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy manservant, and thy maidservant, and the Levite, and the stranger, and the fatherless, and the widow, that are within thy gates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.15'>Seven days shalt thou keep a solemn feast unto the Lord thy God in the place which the Lord will choose; because the Lord thy God will bless thee in all thy product, and in all the work of thy hands, and thou shalt only rejoice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.16'>Three times in the year shall every one of thy males appear before the Lord thy God in the place which he will choose: on the feast of unleavened bread, and on the feast of weeks, and on the feast of tabernacles; and no one shall appear before the Lord empty;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.17'>Every man according to what his hand can give, according to the blessing of the Lord thy God which he hath given thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.18'>Judges and officers shalt thou appoint unto thyself in all thy gates, which the Lord thy God giveth thee, throughout thy tribes: and they shall judge the people with a just judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.19'>Thou shalt not wrest judgment; thou shalt not respect persons, and thou shalt not take a bribe; for the bribe blindeth the eyes of the wise, and perverteth the words of the righteous.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.20'>Justice, only justice shalt thou pursue; in order that thou mayest live, and retain possession of the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.21'>Thou shalt not plant unto thyself a grove, any tree, near the altar of the Lord thy God, which thou shalt make unto thyself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.16.22'>Neither shalt thou set thee up any statue, which the Lord thy God hateth.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.17'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.1'>Thou shalt not sacrifice unto the Lord thy God any bullock, or lamb, whereon there is a blemish, any thing evil; for it is an abomination unto the Lord thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.2'>If there be found in the midst of thee, within any one of thy gates, which the Lord thy God giveth thee. a man or a woman, that doth the wickedness in the eyes of the Lord thy God, to transgress his covenant,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.3'>And he hath gone and served other gods, and worshipped them, either the sun, or the moon, or any of the host of heaven, which I have prohibited;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.4'>And it be told thee, and thou hearest of it: then shalt thou inquire diligently; and, behold, if it be true, the thing is certain, such abomination hath been wrought in Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.5'>Then shalt thou bring forth that man or that woman, who have committed this wicked thing, unto thy gates, the man or the woman, and thou shalt stone them with stones till they die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.6'>Upon the evidence of two witnesses, or of three witnesses, shall he that is worthy of death be put to death; he shall not be put to death upon the evidence of one witness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.7'>The hand of the witnesses shall be first upon him to put him to death, and the hand of all the people at the last; and thou shalt put the evil away from the midst of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.8'>If a matter be unknown to thee for decision, between blood and blood, between plea and plea, and between bodily injury and injury, or matters of controversy within thy gates: then shalt thou arise, and get thee up unto the place which the Lord thy God will choose;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.9'>And thou shalt come unto the priests, the Levites, and unto the judge that may be in those days, and thou shalt inquire, and they shall inform thee of the sentence of the case;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.10'>And thou shalt do according to the sentence, which they may tell thee from that place which the Lord will choose, and thou shalt observe to do according to all that they may instruct thee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.11'>In accordance with the instruction which they may instruct thee, and according to the decision which they may say unto thee, shalt thou do: thou shalt not depart from the sentence which they may tell thee, to the right, or to the left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.12'>And the man that will act presumptuously, so as not to hearken unto the priest that standeth to minister there before the Lord thy God, or unto the judge, even that man shall die; and thou shalt put away the evil from Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.13'>And all the people shall hear, and be afraid, and not act presumptuously any more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.14'>When thou art come unto the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, and thou hast taken possession of it, and dwellest therein, and thou sayest, I wish to set a king over me, like all the nations that are round about me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.15'>Then mayest thou indeed set a king over thee, the one whom the Lord thy God will choose; but from the midst of thy brethren shalt thou set a king over thee; thou mayest not set over thee a stranger, who is not thy brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.16'>Only he shall not acquire for himself many horses; so that he may not cause the people to return to Egypt, in order to acquire many horses; whereas the Lord hath said unto you, Ye shall henceforth not return on that way any more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.17'>Neither shall he take to himself many wives, that his heart may not turn away; nor shall he acquire for himself too much silver and gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.18'>And it shall be, when he sitteth upon the throne of his kingdom, that he shall write for himself a copy of this law in a book out of that which is before the priests, the Levites;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.19'>And it shall be with him, and he shall read therein all the days of his life: in order that he may learn to fear the Lord his God, to keep all the words of this law and these statutes, to do them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.17.20'>So that his heart be not lifted up above his brethren, and so that he turn not aside from the commandment, to the right, or to the left: in order that he may live many days in his kingdom, he, and his children, in the midst of Israel.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.18'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.1'>The priests, the Levites, and all the tribe of Levi, shall have no portion nor inheritance with Israel: the fireofferings of the Lord, and his inheritance shall they consume.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.2'>But any inheritance shall he not have among his brethren: the Lord is his inheritance, as he hath spoken unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.3'>And this shall be the priests due from the people, from them that slay an animal, whether it be ox or lamb: then shall each one give unto the priest the shoulder, and the two cheeks, and the maw.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.4'>The firstfruit of thy corn, of thy wine, and of thy oil, and the first shearing of thy sheep, shalt thou give him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.5'>For him the Lord thy God hath chosen out of all thy tribes, to stand to minister in the name of the Lord, he and his sons all the days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.6'>And if the Levite come from any one of thy gates out of all Israel, where he sojourneth, and come with all the longing of his soul unto the place which the Lord will choose:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.7'>Then can he minister in the name of the Lord his God, like all his brethren the Levites, who stand there before the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.8'>They shall have like portions to eat, besides that which cometh of the sale of his patrimony.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.9'>When thou comest into the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, thou shalt not learn to do after the abominations of those nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.10'>There shall not be found among thee any one who causeth his son or his daughter to pass through the fire, one who useth divination, one who is an observer of times, or an enchanter, or a conjurer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.11'>Or a charmer, or a consulter with familiar spirits, or a wizard, or who inquireth of the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.12'>For an abomination unto the Lord are all that do these things; and on account of these abominations the Lord thy God doth drive them out from before thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.13'>Perfect shalt thou be with the Lord thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.14'>For these nations, which thou art about to dispossess, hearken unto observers of times, and unto diviners; but as for thee, the Lord thy God hath not assigned the like unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.15'>A prophet from the midst of thee, of thy brethren, like unto me, will the Lord thy God raise up unto thee; unto him shall ye hearken:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.16'>According to all that thou didst desire of the Lord thy God at Horeb on the day of the assembly, saying, I wish no more to hear the voice of the Lord my God, and this great fire I wish not to see again, that I die not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.17'>And the Lord said unto me, They have done well in what they have spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.18'>A prophet will I raise up unto them from among their brethren, like unto thee; and I will put my words in his mouth; and he shall speak unto them all that I may command him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.19'>And it shall come to pass, that if there be a man who will not hearken unto my words which he shall speak in my name, I myself will require it of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.20'>But the prophet, who may presume to speak a word in my name, which I have not commanded him to speak, or who may speak in the name of other Gods even that prophet shall die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.21'>And if thou shouldst say in thy heart, How shall we know the word which the Lord hath not spoken?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.18.22'>That which the prophet speaketh in the name of the Lord, and the thing do not happen and come not to pass this is the word which the Lord hath not spoken; in presumption hath the prophet spoken it; thou shalt not be afraid of him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.19'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.1'>When the Lord thy God shall have cut off the nations, whose land the Lord thy God giveth thee, and thou hast driven them out, and dwellest in their cities, and in their houses:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.2'>Then shalt thou set apart three cities for thyself, in the midst of thy land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.3'>Thou shalt put in order for thyself the way to them, and divide into three parts the territory of thy land, which the Lord thy God will give thee to inherit, and it shall serve, that every manslayer may flee thither.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.4'>And this is the case of the manslayer, who shall flee thither, that he may live: Whoso smiteth his neighbor without knowledge, when he hath not been an enemy to him in time past;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.5'>And he that goeth into the forest with his neighbor to hew wood, and his hand fetcheth a stroke with the axe to cut down the tree, and the iron slippeth from the helve, and striketh his neighbor, that he die: this one shall flee unto one of these cities, and live;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.6'>That the avenger of the blood pursue not the manslayer, while his heart is hot, and overtake him, because the way is long, and smite him dead; whereas he deserveth not a judgment of death, inasmuch as he was not an enemy to him in time past.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.7'>Therefore do I command thee, saying, Three cities shalt thou set apart for thyself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.8'>And if the Lord thy God enlarge thy boundary, as he hath sworn unto thy fathers, and give thee all the land which he hath spoken to give unto thy fathers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.9'>Because thou dost keep all this commandment to do it, which I command thee this day, to love the Lord thy God, and to walk in his ways all the days: then shalt thou add for thyself three cities more, unto these three;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.10'>That innocent blood be not shed in the midst of thy land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance, and bloodguiltiness be brought upon thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.11'>But if any man be an enemy to his neighbor, and he lie in wait for him, and rise up against him, and smite him mortally so that he die, and he flee unto one of these cities:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.12'>Then shall the elders of his city send and fetch him thence, and they shall deliver him into the hand of the avenger of the blood, that he may die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.13'>Thy eye shall not look with pity on him; but thou shalt put away the shedding of innocent blood from Israel, that it may go well with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.14'>Thou shalt not remove the landmark of thy neighbor, which they of old time have set, in thy inheritance which thou shalt inherit, in the land that the Lord thy God giveth thee to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.15'>There shall not rise up one single witness against a man for any iniquity, or for any sin, in any sin that he sinneth: upon the evidence of two witnesses, or upon the evidence of three witnesses, must a case be established.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.16'>If a witness of violence rise up against any man to testify against him for any wrong:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.17'>Then shall both the men, who have the controversy, stand before the Lord, before the priests and the judges, who shall be in those days;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.18'>And the judges shall inquire diligently; and, behold, if the witness be a false witness, he hath testified a falsehood against his brother:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.19'>Then shall ye do unto him, as he had purposed to do unto his brother; and thou shalt put away the evil from the midst of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.20'>And those who remain shall hear, and be afraid, and shall henceforth commit no more any such evil thing in the midst of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.19.21'>And thy eye shall have no pity; but life shall go for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.20'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.1'>When thou goest out to battle against thy enemies, and thou seest horse, and chariot, people more in number than thou: be not afraid of them; for the Lord thy God is with thee, who brought thee up out of the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.2'>And it shall be, when ye come nigh unto the battle, that the priest shall approach and speak unto the people;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.3'>And he shall say unto them, Hear, O Israel, ye come nigh this day unto the battle against your enemies: let not your hearts faint, fear not, and be not downcast, and do not tremble because of them:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.4'>For the Lord your God it is who goeth with you, to fight for you against your enemies, to help you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.5'>And the officers shall speak unto the people, saying, What man is there who hath built a new house, and hath not dedicated it? let him go and return unto his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man dedicate it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.6'>And what man is there who hath planted a vineyard, and hath not redeemed it? let him go and return unto his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man redeem it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.7'>And what man is there that hath betrothed a wife, and hath not taken her? let him go and return unto his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man take her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.8'>And the officers shall speak yet farther unto the people, and they shall say, What man is there that is fearful and fainthearted? let him go and return unto his house, that the heart of his brethren become not as faint as his heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.9'>And it shall be, when the officers have made an end of speaking unto the people, that they shall appoint captains of the armies at the head of the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.10'>When thou comest nigh unto a city to make war against it, then summon it with words of peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.11'>And it shall be, if it make thee an answer of peace, and open its gates unto thee: then shall it be, that all the people that are found therein shall be tributaries unto thee, and they shall serve thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.12'>But if it will not make peace with thee, and wageth war against thee; then shalt thou besiege it;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.13'>And when the Lord thy God hath delivered it into thy hands, thou shalt smite every male thereof with the edge of the sword;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.14'>But the women, and the little ones, and the cattle, and all that may be in the city, all the spoil thereof, shalt thou take as booty unto thyself; and thou shalt enjoy the spoil of thy enemies, which the Lord thy God hath given thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.15'>Thus shalt thou do unto all the cities which are very far off from thee, which are not of the cities of these nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.16'>But of the cities of these people, which the Lord thy God doth give thee for an inheritance, shalt thou not let live a single soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.17'>But thou shalt utterly devote them; namely, the Hittites, and the Emorites, the Canaanites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites; as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.18'>In order that they may not teach you to do in accordance with all their abominations, which they have done unto their gods; and ye would thus sin against the Lord your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.19'>When thou besiegest a city a long time, to make war against it to capture it, thou shalt not destroy the trees thereof by forcing an axe against them; for of them thou mayest eat, and thou shalt not cut them down, for man liveth of the trees of the field, to employ them in thy siege;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.20.20'>Only those trees of which thou knowest that they are not fruittrees, thou mayest destroy and cut down; and thus thou canst build bulwarks against the city that wageth war with thee, until it be subdued.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.21'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.1'>If there be found a slain person in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee to possess it, lying in the field, and it be not known who hath slain him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.2'>Then shall thy elders and thy judges go forth, and they shall measure unto the cities which are round about the one that is slain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.3'>And it shall be, that the city which is the nearest unto the slain person, even the elders of that city shall take a heifer, which hath not been wrought with, which hath not drawn in a yoke;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.4'>And the elders of that city shall bring down the heifer unto a rough valley, which is neither tilled nor sown, and they shall break there the neck of the heifer in the valley;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.5'>And the priests the sons of Levi shall come near; for them the Lord thy God hath chosen to minister unto him, and to bless in the name of the Lord; and after their decision shall be done at every controversy and every injury;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.6'>And all the elders of that city who are nearest unto the slain person shall wash their hands over the heifer, the neck of which is broken in the valley.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.7'>And they shall commence and say, Our hands have not shed this blood, and our eyes have not seen it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.8'>Grant pardon unto thy people Israel, whom thou hast redeemed, O Lord, and lay not innocent blood in the midst of thy people Israel: and the blood shall be forgiven unto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.9'>And thou shalt put away the guilt of the innocent blood from the midst of thee, when thou wilt do what is right in the eyes of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.10'>When thou goest forth to war against thy enemies, and the Lord thy God delivereth them into thy hands, and thou takest captives of them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.11'>And thou seest among the captives a woman of handsome form, and hast a desire unto her, that thou wouldst take her to thee for wife:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.12'>Then shalt thou bring her home to thy house; and she shall shave her head, and let grow her nails;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.13'>And she shall put off the raiment of her captivity from her, and she shall remain in thy house, and weep for her father and her mother a full month; and after that thou mayest go in unto her, and be her husband, that she may become thy wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.14'>And it shall be, if thou have no delight in her, then shalt thou let her go whither she will; but thou shalt nowise sell her for money; thou shalt not make a servant of her, because thou hast humbled her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.15'>If a man have two wives, one beloved, and the other hated, and they bear him children, both the beloved and the hated; so that the firstborn son be hers that is hated:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.16'>Then shall it be, when he divideth as inheritance among his sons what he hath, that he shall not institute the son of the beloved as the firstborn before the son of the hated, the firstborn;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.17'>But the firstborn, the son of the hated woman, shall he acknowledge, to give him a double portion of all that is found in his possession; for he is the beginning of his strength; to him belongeth the right of the first birth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.18'>If a man have a stubborn and rebellious son, who hearkeneth not to the voice of his father, or the voice of his mother, and they chastise him, and he will not hearken unto them:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.19'>Then shall his father and his mother lay hold on him, and bring him out unto the elders of his city, and unto the gate of his place;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.20'>And they shall say unto the elders of his city, This our son is stubborn and rebellious, he will not hearken to our voice; he is a glutton, and a drunkard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.21'>And all the men of his city shall stone him with stones, that he die; and thou shalt put away the evil from the midst of thee; and all Israel shall hear, and be afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.22'>And if a man have committed a sin for which there is a punishment of death, and he be to be put to death, and thou hang him on a tree:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.21.23'>Then shall his body not remain all night on the tree, but thou shalt surely bury him on that day; for he that is hanged is a dishonor of God;and thou shalt not defile thy land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.22'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.1'>Thou shalt not see thy brothers ox or his lamb go astray, and withdraw thyself from them: thou shalt surely bring them back again unto thy brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.2'>But if thy brother be not nigh unto thee, or thou know him not: then shalt thou take it unto thy own house, and it shall remain with thee until thy brother inquire after it, and then shalt thou restore it to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.3'>In like manner shalt thou do with his ass; and in like manner shalt thou do with his raiment; and in like manner shalt thou do with every lost thing of thy brothers, which may have been lost to him, and which thou hast found; thou art not at liberty to withdraw thyself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.4'>Thou shalt not see thy brothers ass or his ox fallen down by the way, and withdraw thyself from them: thou shalt surely help him to lift them up again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.5'>A woman shall not have upon her the apparel of a man, and a man shall not put on a womans garment; for an abomination unto the Lord thy God are all who do this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.6'>If a birds nest chance to be before thee in the way, on any tree, or on the ground, with young ones, or with eggs, and the mother be sitting upon the young, or upon the eggs: thou shalt not take the mother with the young;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.7'>But thou shalt surely let the mother go, and the young thou mayest take to thyself; in order that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayest live many days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.8'>When thou buildest a new house, thou shalt make a battlement for thy roof; that thou bring not blood upon thy house, if any one were to fall from there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.9'>Thou shalt not sow thy vineyard with divers seeds; that the ripe fruit of thy seed which thou hast sown, and the fruit of the vineyard, be not defiled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.10'>Thou shalt not plough with an ox and an ass together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.11'>Thou shalt not wear a garment of divers sorts, of woolen and linen together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.12'>Thou shalt make thyself fringes upon the four corners of thy vesture, wherewith thou coverest thyself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.13'>If any man take a wife, and go in unto her, and hate her,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.14'>And he lay an accusation against her, and spread abroad an evil name upon her, and say, This woman I took for wife, and when I came near to her, I found no tokens of virginity in her:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.15'>Then shall the father of the damsel, and her mother, take and bring forth the tokens of the damsels virginity unto the elders of the city, to the gate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.16'>And the father of the damsel shall say unto the elders, My daughter I gave unto this man for wife; but he hath conceived hatred toward her;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.17'>And, lo, he hath laid an accusation against her, saying, I have found no tokens of virginity in thy daughter; and yet these are the tokens of my daughters virginity; and they shall spread the cloth before the elders of the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.18'>And the elders of that city shall take that man and chastise him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.19'>And they shall amerce him in a hundred shekels of silver, and give them unto the father of the damsel; because he hath spread abroad an evil name upon a virgin of Israel; and she shall remain his wife; he shall not be at liberty to put her away all his days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.20'>But if this thing was true, there have not been found tokens of virginity in the damsel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.21'>Then shall they lead out the damsel to the door of her fathers house, and the men of her city shall stone her with stones that she die; because she hath wrought a disgraceful deed in Israel, to commit incest in her fathers house; and thou shalt put away the evil from the midst of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.22'>If a man be found lying with a woman married to a husband: then shall both of them die, the man that lieth with the woman, and the woman; and thou shalt put away the evil from Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.23'>If a damsel that is a virgin be betrothed unto a man, and a man find her in the city, and lie with her:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.24'>Then shall ye lead them both out unto the gate of that city, and ye shall stone them with stones that they die; the damsel, because she cried not for aid in the city; and the man, because he hath done violence to his neighbors wife; and thou shalt put away the evil from the midst of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.25'>But if in the field the man should find the betrothed damsel, and the man take hold of her by force, and lie with her: then shall the man that lay with her die alone;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.26'>But unto the damsel shalt thou not do any thing; there is in the damsel no sin worthy of death; for as when a man riseth against his neighbor, and striketh him dead. even so is this matter;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.27'>For in the field did he find her; had the betrothed damsel even cried, there would have been none to aid her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.28'>If a man find a damsel that is a virgin, who is not betrothed, and lay fast hold on her, and lie with her, and they be found:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.29'>Then shall the man who lieth with her give unto the father of the damsel fifty shekels of silver; and she shall become his wife, because he hath done violence to her, he shall not be at liberty to put her away all his days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.22.30'>
          <note>(23:1)</note> A man shall not take his lathers wife, and he shall not uncover his fathers skirt.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.23'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.1'>
          <note>(23:2)</note> He that is wounded in the testicles, or hath his privy member cut, shall not enter into the congregation of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.2'>
          <note>(23:3)</note> One born from prohibited connections shall not enter into the congregation of the Lord; even the tenth generation of him shall not enter into the congregation of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.3'>
          <note>(23:4)</note> An Ammonite and a Moabite shall not enter into the congregation of the Lord; even the tenth generation of him shall not enter into the congregation of the Lord, for ever;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.4'>
          <note>(23:5)</note> For the reason, that they met you not with bread and with water on the way, when ye came forth out of Egypt; and because he hired against thee Bilam the son of Beor of Pethor in Mesopotamia, to curse thee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.5'>
          <note>(23:6)</note> But the Lord thy God would not hearken unto Bilam; and the Lord thy God changed unto thee the curse into a blessing, because the Lord thy God loved thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.6'>
          <note>(23:7)</note> Thou shalt not seek their peace and their welfare all thy days, for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.7'>
          <note>(23:8)</note> Thou shalt not abhor an Edomite; for he is thy brother; thou shalt not abhor an Egyptian; because thou wast a stranger in his land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.8'>
          <note>(23:9)</note> The children that are born unto them in the third generation, may enter of them into the congregation of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.9'>
          <note>(23:10)</note> When thou goest forth into camp against thy enemies, then keep thyself from every evil thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.10'>
          <note>(23:11)</note> If there be among thee any man, that is not clean by reason of an occurrence by night; then shall he go abroad to without the camp, he shall not come within the camp;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.11'>
          <note>(23:12)</note> But it shall be, that toward evening he shall bathe himself in water; and when the sun goeth down, he may come into the midst of the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.12'>
          <note>(23:13)</note> And a place shalt thou have without the camp, whither thou shalt go forth abroad:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.13'>
          <note>(23:14)</note> And a spade shalt thou have with thy weapons: and it shall be, when thou sittest abroad, that thou shalt dig therewith, and shalt afterward cover that which cometh from thee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.14'>
          <note>(23:15)</note> For the Lord thy God walketh in the midst of thy camp, to deliver thee and to give up thy enemies before thee; therefore shall thy camp be holy; that he see no unseemly thing in thee, and turn away from thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.15'>
          <note>(23:16)</note> Thou shalt not deliver unto his master the servant who may escape unto thee from his master;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.16'>
          <note>(23:17)</note> With thee shall he dwell, in the midst of thee, in the place which he may choose in any one of thy gates, where it seemeth best to him: thou shalt not oppress him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.17'>
          <note>(23:18)</note> There shall not be a prostitute of the daughters of Israel, and there shall not be a sodomite of the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.18'>
          <note>(23:19)</note> Thou shalt not bring the hire of a harlot, or the price of a dog, into the house of the Lord thy God for any vow; for both of these are equally an abomination unto the Lord thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.19'>
          <note>(23:20)</note> Thou shalt not take interest from thy brother, interest of money, interest of victuals, interest of any thing that is lent upon interest:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.20'>
          <note>(23:21)</note> From an alien thou mayest take interest; but from thy brother thou shalt not take interest; in order that the Lord thy God may bless thee in all the acquisition of thy hand, in the land whither thou goest to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.21'>
          <note>(23:22)</note> When thou makest a vow unto the Lord thy God, thou shalt not delay to pay it; for the Lord thy God will surely require it of thee; and it would be sin in thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.22'>
          <note>(23:23)</note> But if thou forbear to vow, it shall be no sin in thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.23'>
          <note>(23:24)</note> What is gone out of thy lips shalt thou keep and perform, as thou hast vowed unto the Lord thy God voluntarily, as thou hast spoken with thy mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.24'>
          <note>(23:25)</note> When thou comest into thy neighbors vineyard, thou mayest eat grapes at thy own pleasure, till thou have enough; but into thy vessel shalt thou not put any.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.23.25'>
          <note>(23:26)</note> When thou comest into the standing corn of thy neighbor, thou mayest pluck ears with thy hand; but a sickle shall thou not move over thy neighbors standing corn.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.24'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.1'>When a man hath taken a wife, and married her, and it come to pass, that if she find no favor in his eyes, because he hath found some scandalous thing in her, he may write her a bill of divorcement, and give it in her hand, and send her away out of his house;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.2'>And she shall depart out of his house; and if she go and become another mans wife;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.3'>And the latter husband hate her, and write her a bill of divorcement, and give it in her hand, and send her away out of his house; or if the latter husband, who took her as his wife, should die:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.4'>Then shall her former husband, who had sent her away, not be at liberty to take her again to be his wife, after she hath been defiled; for it is abomination before the Lord; and thou shalt not bring sin upon the land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.5'>When a man hath taken a new wife, he shall not go out to war, neither shall he be charged with any public business: he shall be free for his house one year, and shall cheer up his wife whom he hath taken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.6'>No man shall take to pledge the nether or the upper millstone; for he taketh a mans life to pledge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.7'>If a man be found stealing any one of his brethren of the children of Israel, and he treateth him as a slave, and selleth him: then shall that thief die; and thou shalt put the evil away from the midst of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.8'>Take heed of the plague of leprosy, to observe diligently, and to do according to all that the priests, the Levites, may instruct you; as I have commanded them, so shall ye observe to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.9'>Remember what the Lord thy God did unto Miriam on the journey, at your coming forth out of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.10'>When thou dost lend thy brother any thing as a loan, thou shalt not go into his house to take his pledge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.11'>In the street shalt thou stand, and the man to whom thou dost lend shall bring out unto thee the pledge into the street.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.12'>And if he be a poor man, thou shalt not lie down with his pledge:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.13'>Thou shalt punctually deliver him the pledge again when the sun goeth down, that he may lie under his own cover, and bless thee; and unto thee shall it be as righteousness before the Lord thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.14'>Thou shalt not withhold the wages of a hired man, of the poor and needy, whether he be of thy brethren, or of the strangers that are in thy land within thy gates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.15'>On the same day shalt thou give him his wages, that the sun may not go down upon it; for he is poor, and his soul longeth for it; so that he may not cry against thee unto the Lord, and it be sin in thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.16'>Fathers shall not be put to death for the children, neither shall children be put to death for the fathers: for his own sin shall every man be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.17'>Thou shalt not pervert the cause of the stranger, or of the fatherless; and thou shalt not take in pledge the raiment of a widow;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.18'>But thou shalt remember that thou waste a bondman in Egypt, and that the Lord thy God redeemed thee thence; therefore do I command thee to do this thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.19'>When thou cuttest down thy harvest in thy field, and forgettest a sheaf in the field, thou shalt not go back to fetch it; for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the widow shall it be; in order that the Lord thy God may bless thee in all the work of thy hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.20'>When thou beatest thy olivetree, thou shalt not go over the boughs again; for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the widow shall it be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.21'>When thou gatherest the grapes of thy vineyard, thou shalt not glean the small fruit afterward; for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the widow shall it be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.24.22'>And thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in the land of Egypt; therefore do I command thee to do this thing:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.25'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.1'>If there be a controversy between men, and they come nigh unto a court of justice, and they judge them; and they justify the righteous, and condemn the wicked:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.2'>Then shall it be, if the guilty man deserve to be beaten, that the judge shall cause him to lie down, and to be beaten before his face, according to the degree of his fault, by a certain number.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.3'>Forty stripes may he give him, not more; so that he shall not exceed to have him beaten above these with too many stripes, and thy brother be thus rendered vile before thy eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.4'>Thou shalt not muzzle the ox when he thresheth out the corn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.5'>If brothers dwell together, and one of them die, and have no child: then shall the wife of the dead not be married abroad, unto a stranger; her husbands brother shall go in unto her, and take her to himself for wife, and perform the duty of a husbands brother unto her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.6'>And it shall be, that the firstborn whom she may bear shall succeed in the name of his brother who is dead; so that his name be not blotted out of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.7'>And if the man have no desire to take his sisterinlaw: then shall his sisterinlaw go up to the gate unto the elders, and say, My husbands brother refuseth to raise up unto his brother a name in Israel, he will not perform on me the duty of a husbands brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.8'>Then shall the elders of his city call him, and speak unto him; and if he persist, and say, I have no desire to take her:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.9'>Then shall his sisterinlaw come nigh unto him in the presence of the elders, and pull his shoe from off his foot, and spit out before him, and shall commence and say, Thus shall be done unto that man that will not build up his brothers house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.10'>And his name shall be called in Israel, The house of the barefooted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.11'>When men strive together one with the other, and the wife of the one draweth near to deliver her husband out of the hand of him that smiteth him, and putteth forth her hand, and taketh him by the secrets:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.12'>Then shalt thou cut off her hand, thy eye shall not have pity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.13'>Thou shalt not have in thy bag divers weights, a great and a small.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.14'>Thou shalt not have in thy house divers measures, a great and a small.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.15'>A perfect and just weight shalt thou have, a perfect and just measure shalt thou have; in order that thy days may be prolonged in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.16'>For an abomination of the Lord thy God is every one that doth such things, every one that acteth unrighteously.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.17'>Remember what Amalek did unto thee, by the way, at your coming forth out of Egypt;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.18'>How he met thee by the way, and smote the hindmost of thee, all that were feeble behind thee, when thou was faint and weary; and he feared not God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.25.19'>And it shall come to pass, when the Lord thy God giveth thee rest from all thy enemies round about, in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance to possess it, that thou shalt blot out the remembrance of Amalek from under the heavens: thou shalt not forget.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.26'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.1'>And it shall come to pass, when thou art come in unto the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance, and thou hast taken possession of it, and dwellest therein:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.2'>That thou shalt take of the first of all the fruit of the soil, which thou shalt bring in from thy land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, and shalt put it in a basket; and thou shalt go unto the place which the Lord thy God will choose to let his name dwell there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.3'>And thou shalt come unto the priest that may be in those days, and thou shalt say unto him, I give thanks this day unto the Lord thy God, that I am come into the land which the Lord swore unto our fathers to give to us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.4'>And the priest shall take the basket out of thy hand, and set it down before the altar of the Lord thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.5'>And thou shalt commence and say before the Lord thy God, A Syrian, wandering about, was my father, and he went down into Egypt, and sojourned there with a family few in number, and he became there a nation, great, mighty, and numerous.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.6'>And the Egyptians treated us ill, and afflicted us, and laid upon us hard labor;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.7'>And then we cried unto the Eternal, the God of our fathers; and the Lord heard our voice, and looked on our affliction, and our trouble, and our oppression;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.8'>And the Lord brought us forth out of Egypt with a mighty hand, and with an outstretched arm, and with great terror, and with signs, and with wonders;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.9'>And he brought us unto this place, and gave unto us this land, a land flowing with milk and honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.10'>And now, behold, I have brought the first of the fruits of the soil, which thou hast given me, O Lord; and thou shalt set it down before the Lord thy God, and prostrate thyself before the Lord thy God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.11'>And thou shalt rejoice with every good thing which the Lord thy God hath given unto thee, and unto thy house, thou, with the Levite, and the stranger that is in the midst of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.12'>When thou hast made an end of giving away all the tithe of thy produce in the third year, the year of the tithing, and hast given it unto the Levite, to the stranger, to the fatherless, and to the widow, and they have eaten it within thy gates, and are satisfied:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.13'>Then shalt thou say before the Lord thy God, I have removed away the hallowed things out of the house, and I have also given them unto the Levite, and unto the stranger, to the fatherless, and to the widow, according to all thy commandment which thou hast commanded me; I have not deviated from thy commandments, and I have not forgotten;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.14'>I have not eaten thereof in my mourning, neither have I removed away aught thereof in an unclean state, nor have I given aught thereof for the dead: I have hearkened to the voice of the Lord my God, I have done all, just as thou hast commanded me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.15'>Look down from the habitation of thy holiness, from the heavens, and bless thy people Israel, and the soil which thou hast given unto us, as thou hast sworn unto our fathers, a land flowing with milk and honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.16'>This day the Lord thy God commandeth thee to do these statutes and ordinances; and thou shalt keep and do them with all thy heart, and with all thy soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.17'>Thou hast this day acknowledged the Lord, that he is thy God, and that thou wilt walk in his ways, and keep his statutes, and his commandments, and his ordinances, and hearken unto his voice;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.18'>And the Lord hath acknowledged thee this day, that thou art unto him a peculiar people, as he hath spoken unto thee, and that thou shouldst keep all his commandments;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.26.19'>So that he may set thee highest above all nations that he hath made, in praise, and in name, and in honor; and that thou mayest be a holy people unto the Lord thy God, as he hath spoken.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.27'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.1'>And Moses with the elders of Israel commanded the people, saying, Keep the whole commandment which I command you this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.2'>And it shall be on the day when ye pass over the Jordan unto the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, that thou shalt set up for thyself great stones, and cover them with plaster;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.3'>And thou shalt write upon them all the words of this law, so soon as thou art passed over; in order that thou mayest go in unto the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, a land flowing with milk and honey; as the Lord, the God of thy fathers, hath spoken unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.4'>And it shall be so soon as ye are gone over the Jordan, that ye shall set up these stones, which I command you this day, on mount Ebal; and thou shalt cover them with plaster.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.5'>And thou shalt build there an altar unto the Lord thy God, an altar of stones: thou shalt not lift up any iron tool upon them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.6'>Of whole stones shalt thou build the altar of the Lord thy God; and thou shalt offer thereupon burntofferings unto the Lord thy God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.7'>And thou shalt slay peaceofferings, and eat them there; and thou shalt rejoice before the Lord thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.8'>And thou shalt write upon the statues all the words of this law, very plainly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.9'>And Moses with the priests, the Levites, spoke unto all Israel, saying, Be attentive, and hearken, O Israel! this day art thou become a people unto the Lord thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.10'>Thou shalt therefore hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God, and do his commandments and his statutes, which I command thee this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.11'>And Moses commanded the people on the same day, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.12'>These shall stand upon mount Gerizzim to bless the people, when ye are come over the Jordan: Simeon, and Levi, and Judah, and Issachar, and Joseph, and Benjamin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.13'>And these shall stand for the sake of the curse upon mount Ebal: Reuben, Gad, and Asher, and Zebulun, Dan, and Naphtali.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.14'>And the Levites shall commence, and say unto all the men of Israel with a loud voice,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.15'>Cursed be the man who maketh a graven or molten image, the abomination of the Lord, the work of the hands of the craftsman, and putteth it in a secret place; and all the people shall answer, and say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.16'>Cursed be he that holdeth in light esteem his father or his mother; and all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.17'>Cursed be he that removeth the landmark of his neighbor; and all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.18'>Cursed be he that causeth the blind to wander out of the way; and all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.19'>Cursed be he that perverteth the cause of the stranger, of the fatherless, and of the widow; and all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.20'>Cursed be he that lieth with his fathers wife; because he uncovereth his fathers skirt; and all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.21'>Cursed be he that lieth with any manner of beast; and all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.22'>Cursed be he that lieth with his sister, the daughter of his father, or the daughter of his mother; and all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.23'>Cursed be he that lieth with his motherinlaw; and all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.24'>Cursed be he that smiteth his neighbor secretly; and all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.25'>Cursed be he that taketh a bribe to slay a person, an innocent blood; and all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.27.26'>Cursed be he that executeth not the words of this law to do them; and all the people shall say, Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.28'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.1'>And it shall come to pass, if thou wilt hearken diligently unto the voice of the Lord thy God, to observe to do all his commandments which I command thee this day, that the Lord thy God will set thee highest above all nations of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.2'>And all these blessings shall come upon thee, and overtake thee; because thou wilt hearken unto the voice of the Lord thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.3'>Blessed shalt thou be in the city, and blessed shalt thou be in the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.4'>Blessed shall be the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy ground, and the fruit of thy cattle, the increase of thy cattle, and the young of thy flocks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.5'>Blessed shall be thy basket and thy kneadingthrough.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.6'>Blessed shalt thou be at thy coming in, and blessed shalt thou be at thy going out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.7'>The Lord will cause thy enemies that rise up against thee to be smitten before thy face: on one way shall they come out against thee, and on seven ways shall they flee before thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.8'>The Lord will command upon thee the blessing in thy storehouse, and in all the acquisitions of thy hand; and he trill bless thee in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.9'>The Lord will raise thee up unto himself as a holy people, as he hath sworn unto thee; if thou wilt keep the commandments of the Lord thy God, and walk in his ways.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.10'>And all the nations of the earth shall see, that thou art called by the name of the Lord; and they shall be afraid of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.11'>And the Lord will make thee preeminent for good, in the fruit of thy body, and in the fruit of thy cattle, and in the fruit of thy ground, in the land which the Lord swore unto thy fathers to give unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.12'>The Lord will open unto thee his good treasure, the heaven, to give the rain of thy land in its season, and to bless all the work of thy hand; and thou shalt lend unto many nations, but thou shalt not borrow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.13'>And the Lord will constitute thee the head, and not the tail; and thou shalt only be uppermost, and thou shalt not be beneath; if thou wilt hearken unto the commandments of the Lord thy God, which I command thee this day to observe and to do;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.14'>And thou wilt not go aside from all the words which I command thee this day, to the right, or to the left, to go after strange gods, to serve them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.15'>But it shall come to pass, if thou wilt not hearken unto the voice of the Lord thy God, to observe to do all his commandments and his statutes which I command thee this day: that all these curses shall come upon thee, and overtake thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.16'>Cursed shalt thou be in the city, and cursed shalt thou be in the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.17'>Cursed shall be thy basket and thy kneadingtrough.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.18'>Cursed shall be the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy land, the increase of thy cattle, and the young of the flocks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.19'>Cursed shalt thou be at thy coming in, and cursed shalt thou be at thy going out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.20'>The Lord will send out against thee misfortune, confusion, and failure, in all the occupation of thy hand which thou mayest engage in; until thou be destroyed, and until thou perish quickly; because of the wickedness of thy doings, that thou hast forsaken me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.21'>The Lord will cause the pestilence to cleave unto thee, until it have consumed thee from off the land, whither thou goest to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.22'>The Lord will smite thee with consumption, and with fever, and with inflammation, and with extreme burning, and with drought, and with blasting, and with mildew; and they shall pursue thee until thou be lost.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.23'>And thy heavens that are over thy head shall be copper, and the earth that is under thee shall be iron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.24'>The Lord will give as the rain of thy land powder and dust: from heaven shall it come down upon thee, until thou be destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.25'>The Lord will cause thee to be smitten before thy enemies: on one way shalt thou go out against them, and on seven ways shalt thou flee before them; and thou shalt become a horror unto all the kingdoms of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.26'>And thy carcass shall become food unto all the fowls of the heavens, and unto the beasts of the earth, but with no one to scare them away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.27'>The Lord will smite thee with the inflammatory disease of Egypt, and with the hemorrhoids, and with the scab, and with the itch, whereof thou shalt not be able to be healed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.28'>The Lord will sinite thee with madness, and with blindness, and with confusion of heart;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.29'>And thou shalt grope about at noonday, as the blind gropeth about in the darkness, and thou shalt not prosper in thy ways; and thou shalt be only oppressed and robbed all the days, but with no one to help.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.30'>A wife wilt thou betroth, and another man shall lie with her; a house wilt thou build, and thou shalt not dwell therein; a vineyard wilt thou plant, and thou shalt not redeem it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.31'>Thy ox shall be slain before thy eyes, and thou shalt not eat thereof; thy ass shall be violently taken away from before thy face, and shall not be brought back to thee; thy sheep shall be given unto thy enemies, without any one to help thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.32'>Thy sons and thy daughters shall be given unto another people, and thy eyes shall look on, and fail with longing for them all the day long; but without any power in thy hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.33'>The fruit of thy soil, and all thy exertion, shall a nation which thou knowest not eat up; and thou shalt only be oppressed and crushed all the days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.34'>And thou shalt become mad from the sight of thy eyes which thou wilt see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.35'>The Lord will smite thee with a sore inflammation upon the knees, and upon the legs, of which thou shalt not be able to be healed, from the sole of thy foot unto the top of thy head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.36'>The Lord will drive thee, and thy king whom thou wilt set over thee, unto a nation which neither thou nor thy fathers have known; and thou wilt serve there strange gods, of wood and stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.37'>And thou shalt become an astonishment, a proverb, and a byword, among all the nations whither the Lord will lead thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.38'>Much seed wilt thou carry out into the field, yet but little shalt thou gather in; for the locust shall consume it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.39'>Vineyards wilt thou plant and dress; but wine shalt thou not drink nor lay up; for the worms shall eat them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.40'>Olivetrees wilt thou have throughout all thy borders; but with the oil shalt thou not anoint thyself; for thy olive shall cast the fruit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.41'>Sons and daughters wilt thou beget; but they shall not remain thine: for they shall go into captivity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.42'>All thy trees and the fruit of thy land shall the cricket strip bare.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.43'>The stranger that is in the midst of thee shall get up above thee higher and higher; but thou shalt come down lower and lower;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.44'>He shall lend to thee, and thou shalt not lend to him; he shall become the head, and thou shalt become the tail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.45'>And there shall come upon thee all these curses, and they shall pursue thee, and overtake thee, till thou be destroyed; because thou didst not hearken unto the voice of the Lord thy God, to keep his commandments and his statutes which he hath commanded thee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.46'>And they shall remain on thee for a sign and for a token, and on thy seed, for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.47'>For the reason that thou didst not serve the Lord thy God with joyfulness, and with gladness of heart, while there was an abundance of all things;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.48'>Therefore shalt thou serve thy enemies whom the Lord will send out against thee, in hunger, and in thirst, and in nakedness, and in want of every thing; and they will put a yoke of iron upon thy neck, until they have destroyed thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.49'>The Lord will bring up against thee a nation from afar, from the end of the earth, as the eagle rusheth down; a nation whose tongue thou wilt not understand;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.50'>A nation of a fierce countenance, that will not have respect for the old, nor show favor to the young;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.51'>And it will eat the fruit of thy cattle, and the fruit of thy soil, until thou be destroyed; so that it will not leave unto thee corn, wine, or oil, the increase of thy cattle, or the young of thy flocks, until it have ruined thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.52'>And it will besiege thee in all thy gates, until thy high and strong walls come down, wherein thou trustest, throughout all thy land; and it will besiege thee in all thy gates throughout all thy land, which the Lord thy God hath given thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.53'>And thou shalt eat the fruit of thy own body, the flesh of thy sons and of thy daughters, whom the Lord thy God hath given thee, in the siege, and in the straitness, wherewith thy enemy will distress thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.54'>The man that is the most tender among thee, and who is very delicate,his eye shall look enviously toward his brother, and toward the wife of his bosom, and toward the remnant of his children whom he may spare;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.55'>So as not to give to any of them of the flesh of his children which he may eat; because there is nothing left unto him, in the siege, and in the straitness, wherewith thy enemy will distress thee in all thy gates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.56'>The woman, the most tender among thee, and the most delicate, who hath never adventured to set the sole of her foot upon the ground for delicateness and tenderness,her eye shall look enviously toward the husband of her bosom, and toward her son, and toward her daughter,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.57'>And toward her young one that is come from between her feet, and toward her children which she hath born; for she shall eat them for want of every thing secretly, in the siege and in the straitness, wherewith thy enemy will distress thee in thy gates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.58'>If thou wilt not observe to do all the words of this law which are written in this book; to fear this glorious and fearful name, the Lord thy God:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.59'>Then will the Lord render peculiar thy plagues, and the plagues of thy seed, plagues great, and of long continuance, and sicknesses sore, and of long continuance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.60'>And he will bring back upon thee all the diseases of Egypt, of which thou wast afraid; and they shall cleave unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.61'>Also every sickness, and every plague which is not written in the book of this law, will the Lord bring upon thee, until thou be destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.62'>And ye shall be left but few in number, instead of that ye once were as the stars of heaven for multitude; because thou didst not hearken unto the voice of the Lord thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.63'>And it shall come to pass, that, as the Lord rejoiced over you to do you good, and to multiply you, so will the Lord rejoice over you to bring you to nought, and to destroy you; and ye shall be plucked from off the land whither thou goest to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.64'>And the Lord will scatter thee among all the nations, from one end of the earth even unto the other end of the earth; and there wilt thou serve strange gods, which neither thou nor thy fathers have known, even wood and stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.65'>And among these nations shalt thou find no ease, and there shall not be any rest for the sole of thy foot: and the Lord will give thee there a trembling heart, and a failing of eyes, and a faintness of soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.66'>And thy life shall hang in doubt before thee; and thou shalt be in dread day and night, and thou shalt have no confidence of thy life;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.67'>In the morning thou wilt say, Who would but grant that it were only evening! and at evening thou wilt say, Who would but grant that it were only morning! from the dread of thy heart which thou wilt experience, and from the sight of thy eyes which thou wilt see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.28.68'>And the Lord will bring thee back to Egypt in ships, by the way whereof I have spoken unto thee, Thou shalt no more see it again: and there will ye offer yourselves for sale unto your enemies for bondmen and bondwomen, without any one to buy you.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.29'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.1'>
          <note>(28:69)</note> These are the words of the covenant, which the Lord commanded Moses to make with the children of Israel in the land of Moab, besides the covenant which he had made with them in Horeb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.2'>
          <note>(29:1)</note> And Moses called unto all Israel, and said unto them, Ye yourselves have seen all that the Lord hath done before your eyes in the land of Egypt unto Pharaoh, and unto all his servants, and unto all his land;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.3'>
          <note>(29:2)</note> The great proofs which thy eyes have seen, those great signs, and miracles:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.4'>
          <note>(29:3)</note> Yet the Lord gave you not a heart to perceive, and eyes to see, and ears to hear, until this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.5'>
          <note>(29:4)</note> And I have led you forty years in the wilderness; your clothes did not fall worn out from off you, and thy shoe did not fall worn out from off thy foot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.6'>
          <note>(29:5)</note> Bread have ye not eaten, and wine or strong drink have ye not drunk; in order that ye might understand that I am the Lord your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.7'>
          <note>(29:6)</note> And when ye came unto this place, Sichon the king of Cheshbon, and Og the king of Bashan went out against us unto battle, and we smote them:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.8'>
          <note>(29:7)</note> And we took their land, and gave it for an inheritance unto the Reubenites, and to the Gadites, and to the half tribe of the Menassites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.9'>
          <note>(29:8)</note> Keep ye therefore the words of this covenant, and do them, that ye may prosper in all that ye do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.10'>
          <note>(29:9)</note> Ye are standing this day, all of you, before the Lord your God; your heads of your tribes, your elders, and your officers, all the men of Israel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.11'>
          <note>(29:10)</note> Your little ones, your wives, and thy stranger that is in the midst of thy camp, from the hewer of thy wood unto the drawer of thy water:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.12'>
          <note>(29:11)</note> That thou shouldst enter into the covenant of the Lord thy God, and into his oath of denunciation, which the Lord thy God maketh with thee this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.13'>
          <note>(29:12)</note> In order to raise thee up today unto himself for a people, and that he may be unto thee a God, as he hath spoken unto thee, and as he hath sworn unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.14'>
          <note>(29:13)</note> And not with you alone do I make this covenant and this oath;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.15'>
          <note>(29:14)</note> But with him that is standing here with us this day before the Lord our God, and with him that is not here with us this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.16'>
          <note>(29:15)</note> (For ye know how we dwelt in the land of Egypt; and how we passed through the nations through which ye have passed;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.17'>
          <note>(29:16)</note> And ye saw their abominations, and their idols, of wood and stone, silver and gold, which they had with them:)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.18'>
          <note>(29:17)</note> So that there may not be among you a man, or a woman, or a family, or a tribe, whose heart turneth away this day from the Lord our God, to go to serve the gods of these nations; that there may not be among you a root that beareth abundantly poison and wormwood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.19'>
          <note>(29:18)</note> And it might come to pass, when he heareth the words of this denunciation, that he would bless himself in his heart, saying, There will be peace unto me, though I walk in the stubbornness of my heart; in order that the indulgence of the passions may appease the thirst for them:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.20'>
          <note>(29:19)</note> The Lord will not pardon him; but then the anger of the Lord and his jealousy will smoke against that man, and there shall rest upon him all the curse that is written in this book; and the Lord will blot out his name from under the heavens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.21'>
          <note>(29:20)</note> And the Lord will single him out unto evil out of all the tribes of Israel, according to all the denunciations of the covenant which is written in this book of the law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.22'>
          <note>(29:21)</note> And the latest generation, your children that will rise up after you, and the stranger that will come from a far land, will say, when they see the plagues of that land, and its sufferings with which the Lord hath smitten it;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.23'>
          <note>(29:22)</note>That the whole soil thereof is brimstone, and salt, and a burning waste, which is not sown, and beareth not, and in which no kind of grass springeth up, like the overthrow of Sodom, and Gomorrah, Admah, and Zeboyim, which the Lord overthrew in his anger, and in his wrath:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.24'>
          <note>(29:23)</note> Even all the nations will say, Wherefore hath the Lord done thus unto this land? whence the heat of this great anger?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.25'>
          <note>(29:24)</note> Then shall men say, Because they had forsaken the covenant of the Lord, the God of their fathers, which he made with them when he brought them forth out of the land of Egypt;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.26'>
          <note>(29:25)</note> And they went and served other gods, and bowed down to them, gods which they knew not, and which he had not assigned unto them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.27'>
          <note>(29:26)</note> And the anger of the Lord was kindled against this land, to bring upon it the entire curse that is written in this book;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.28'>
          <note>(29:27)</note> And the Lord plucked them out of their land in anger, and in wrath, and in great indignation, and he cast them into another land, as it is this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.29.29'>
          <note>(29:28)</note> The secret things belong unto the Lord our God; but those things which are publicly known belong unto us and to our children for ever, to do all the words of this law.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.30'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.1'>And it shall come to pass, when all these things are come upon thee, the blessing and the curse, which I have set before thee, and thou reflectest on them in thy heart among all the nations, whither the Lord thy God hath driven thee,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.2'>So that thou returnest unto the Lord thy God, and hearkenest unto his voice according to all that I command this day, thou and thy children, with all thy heart, and with all thy soul:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.3'>That then the Lord thy God will restore thy captivity, and have mercy upon thee; and he will again gather thee from all the nations, whither the Lord thy God hath scattered thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.4'>If thy outcasts be at the outmost parts of heaven, from there will the Lord thy God gather thee, and from there will he fetch thee:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.5'>And the Lord thy God will bring thee into the land which thy fathers possessed, and thou shalt possess it; and he will do thee good, and multiply thee above thy fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.6'>And the Lord thy God will circumcise thy heart, and the heart of thy seed, to love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, in order that thou mayest live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.7'>And the Lord thy God will put all these denunciations upon thy enemies, and on those that hate thee, who have persecuted thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.8'>And thou wilt return and hearken unto the voice of the Lord, and thou wilt do all his commandments which I command thee this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.9'>And the Lord thy God will make thee preeminent in every work of thy hand, in the fruit of thy body, and in the fruit of thy cattle, and in the fruit of thy land, for good; for the Lord will again rejoice over thee for good, as he rejoiced over thy fathers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.10'>If thou wilt hearken unto the voice of the Lord thy God, to keep his commandments and his statutes which are written in this book of the law; if thou wilt return unto the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.11'>For this commandment which I command thee this day, is not hidden from thee, nor is it far off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.12'>It is not in heaven; that thou shouldst say, Who will go up for us to heaven, and fetch it down unto us, and cause us to hear it, that we may do it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.13'>Neither is it beyond the sea; that thou shouldst say, Who will go over the sea for us, and fetch it unto us, and cause us to hear it, that we may do it!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.14'>But the word is very nigh unto thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that thou mayest do it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.15'>See, I have set before thee this day life and the good, death and the evil;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.16'>In that I command thee this day to love the Lord thy God, to walk in his ways, and to keep his commandments and his statutes and his ordinances; that thou mayest live and multiply; and that the Lord thy God may bless thee in the land whither thou goest to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.17'>But if thy heart turn away, so that thou wilt not hearken, and thou sufferest thyself to be drawn away, and thou bowest down to other gods, and servest them:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.18'>I announce unto you this day, that ye shall surely perish; ye shall not remain many days upon the land, whither thou passest over the Jordan to go thither to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.19'>I call heaven and earth as witnesses against you this day, that I have set before you life and death, the blessing and the curse; therefore choose thou life, in order that thou mayest live, both thou and thy seed;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.30.20'>To love the Lord thy God, to hearken to his voice, and to cleave unto him; for he is thy life, and the length of thy days; that thou mayest dwell in the land which the Lord swore unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give unto them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.31'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.1'>And Moses went and spoke these words unto all Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.2'>And he said unto them, I am a hundred and twenty years old this day; I am not able any more to go out and come in; for the Lord hath said unto me, Thou shalt not go over this Jordan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.3'>The Lord thy God it is who goeth over before thee; he will destroy these nations from before thee, and thou shalt dispossess them: Joshua it is who goeth over before thee, as the Lord hath spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.4'>And the Lord will do unto them as he hath done to Sichon and to Og, the kings of the Emorites, and unto their land, whom he hath destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.5'>And the Lord will give them up before you; and ye shall do unto them according unto the whole of the commandment which I have commanded you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.6'>Be strong and of a good courage, be not afraid and be not dismayed on account of them; for the Lord thy God it is that goeth with thee; he will not let thee fail, nor forsake thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.7'>And Moses called unto Joshua, and said unto him before the eyes of all Israel, Be strong and of a good courage; for thou must go with this people unto the land which the Lord hath sworn unto their fathers to give unto them; and thou shalt divide it for them as a possession.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.8'>And the Lord it is that goeth before thee; he will be with thee, he will not let thee fail, nor will he forsake thee: fear not, nor be thou discouraged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.9'>And Moses wrote down this law, and delivered it unto the priests the sons of Levi, who bore the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and unto all the elders of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.10'>And Moses commanded them, saying, At the end of every seven years, at the fixed time of the year of release, on the feast of tabernacles,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.11'>When all Israel come to appear before the Lord thy God in the place which he will choose, shalt thou read this law in the presence of all Israel in their hearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.12'>Assemble the people together, the men, and the women, and the children, and thy stranger that is within thy gates; in order that they may hear, and in order that they may learn how they are to fear the Lord your God, and observe to do all the words of this law;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.13'>And that their children, who have not yet any knowledge, may hear, and learn to fear the Lord your God, all the days which ye live in the land whither ye go over the Jordan to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.14'>And the Lord said unto Moses, Behold, thy days approach that thou must die; call Joshua, and place yourselves in the tabernacle of the congregation, that I may give him a charge: and Moses and Joshua went, and placed themselves in the tabernacle of the congregation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.15'>And the Lord appeared in the tabernacle in a pillar of cloud; and the pillar of cloud stood at the door of the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.16'>And the Lord said unto Moses, Behold, thou shalt sleep with thy fathers: and then will this people rise up, and go astray after the gods of the strangers of the land, whither they go to be in the midst of them, and they will forsake me, and break my covenant which I have made with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.17'>And my anger shall be kindled against them on that day, and I will forsake them, and I will hide my face from them, and they shall be given to be devoured, and many evils and troubles shall overtake them; and they will say on that day, Is it not, because my God is not in the midst of me, that these evils have overtaken me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.18'>But I will assuredly hide my face on that day on account of all the evils which they have wrought, because they have turned unto other gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.19'>Now therefore write ye for yourselves this song, and teach it the children of Israel, put it in their mouth; in order that this song may become for me a witness against the children of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.20'>For when I shall have brought them into the land which I have sworn unto their fathers, that floweth with milk and honey; and they shall have eaten and filled themselves, and grown fat: then will they turn unto other gods, and serve them, and provoke me, and break my covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.21'>And it shall come to pass, when many evils and troubles have befallen them, that this song shall testify against them as a witness; for it shall not be forgotten out of the mouth of their seed; for I know their inclination which they have shown, even this day, before I have brought them into the land which I have sworn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.22'>And Moses wrote down this song on the same day, and taught it the children of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.23'>And he gave a charge unto Joshua the son of Nun, and said, Be strong and of a good courage; for thou shalt bring the children of Israel into the land which I have sworn unto them; and I will be with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.24'>And it came to pass, when Moses had made an end of writing the words of this law in a book, until they were finished,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.25'>That Moses commanded the Levites, the bearers of the ark of the covenant of the Lord, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.26'>Take this book of the law, and put it at the side of the ark of the covenant of the Lord your God, that it may remain there against thee for a witness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.27'>For I know thy rebellion, and thy stiff neck: behold, while I am yet alive with you this day, have ye been rebellious against the Lord, and how much more after my death?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.28'>Assemble unto me all the elders of your tribes, and your officers; and I will speak in their ears these words, and I will call as witnesses against them the heavens and the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.29'>For I know that after my death ye will to a surety become corrupt, and turn aside from the way which I have commanded you; and that the evil will befall you in the latter days, when ye do the evil in the eyes of the Lord, to incense him through the work of your hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.31.30'>And Moses spoke in the ears of all the congregation of Israel the words of this song, until they were ended.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.32'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.1'>Give ear, O ye heavens, and I will speak; and let the earth hear the words of my mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.2'>My doctrine shall drop as the rain, my speech shall distil as the dew, as heavy rains upon the grass, and as showers upon herbs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.3'>When I call on the name of the Lord, ascribe ye greatness unto our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.4'>He is the Rock, his work is perfect; for all his ways are just: the God of truth and without iniquity, just and upright is he.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.5'>The corruption is not his, it is the defect of his children, of the perverse and crooked generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.6'>Will ye thus requite the Lord, O people, worthless and unwise? is he not thy father who hath bought thee? is it not he who hath made thee, and established thee?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.7'>Remember the days of old, consider the years of former generations; ask thy father, and he will tell thee; thy elders, and they will say it unto thee:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.8'>When the Most High divided to the nations their inheritance, when he separated the sons of man: he set the bounds of the tribes according to the number of the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.9'>For the portion of the Lord is his people; Jacob is the lot of his inheritance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.10'>He found him in a desert land, and in the waste of the howling of the wilderness; he encircled him, he watched him, he guarded him as the apple of his eye.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.11'>As an eagle stirreth up his nest, fluttereth over his young, spreadeth abroad his wings, seizeth them, beareth them aloft on his pinions:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.12'>So did the Lord alone lead him, and there was not with him a stranger god.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.13'>He caused him to stride on the high places of the earth, and he ate the products of the fields; and he made him to suck honey out of the rock, and oil out of the flinty stone;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.14'>Cream of cows, and milk of sheep, with fat of lambs, and rams of the breed of Bashan, and goats, with the fat of the kidneys of wheat; and of the blood of the grape thou drunkest unmixed wine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.15'>Thus did Yeshurun grow fat, and he kicked; thou art grown fat, thick, fleshy;and then he forsook the God who made him, and lightly esteemed the Rock of his salvation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.16'>They incensed him with strange gods, with abominations they provoked him to anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.17'>They sacrificed unto evil spirits, things that are not god, gods that they know not, new ones lately come up, which your fathers dreaded not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.18'>Of the Rock that begat thee thou wast unmindful, and forgottest the God that had brought thee forth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.19'>And the Lord saw this, and he was angry; because of the provoking of his sons and of his daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.20'>And he said, I will hide my face from them, I will see what their end will be; for a perverse generation are they, children in whom there is no faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.21'>They have moved me to wrath with things that are not god; they have provoked me to anger with their vanities; and I too will move them to jealousy with those which are not a people; I will provoke them to anger with a worthless nation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.22'>For a fire is kindled in my anger, and it burneth unto the lowest deep; and it consumeth the earth with her products, and it setteth on fire the foundations of the mountains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.23'>I will heap upon them miseries; all my arrows will I spend upon them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.24'>They shall be wasted with hunger, and devoured with burning heat, and with bitter deadly disease; also the tooth of beasts will I let loose against them, with the poison of serpents that crawl in the dust.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.25'>Without shall the sword destroy, and terror within the chambers, both the young man and the virgin, the suckling with the man of gray hairs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.26'>I said, I would drive them into one corner, I would cause their remembrance to cease from among men:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.27'>Were it not that I feared the wrath of the enemy, lest their oppressors should mistake the truth, lest they should say, Our hand is high, and the Lord hath not wrought all this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.28'>For a nation void of counsel are they, and there is no understanding in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.29'>If they were but wise, they would understand this, they would consider their latter end!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.30'>How should one chase a thousand, and two put ten thousand to flight, unless their Rock had sold them, and the Lord had delivered them up?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.31'>For not as our Rock is their rock, even our enemies themselves being judges.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.32'>For from the vine of Sodom is their vine, and from the fields of Gomorrah; their grapes are grapes of gall, they bear bitter clusters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.33'>The poison of serpents is their wine, and the deadly venom of asps.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.34'>Behold! this is laid up in store with me, it is sealed up among my treasures!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.35'>Mine are vengeance and recompense, at the time that their foot shall slip; for nigh draweth the day of their calamity, and the future speedeth along for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.36'>For the Lord will espouse the cause of his people, and bethink himself concerning his servants: when he seeth that their power is gone, and the guarded and fortified axe no more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.37'>Then will he say, Where are their gods, the rock in whom they trusted,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.38'>They that ate the fat of their sacrifices, and drank the wine of their drinkofferings? let them arise and help you, let them be a protection over you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.39'>See now that I, even I, am he, ard there is no god with me: I alone kill, and I make alive; I wound, and I heal; and no one can deliver out of my hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.40'>For I lift up my hand to heaven, and say, I live for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.41'>When I whet my glittering sword, and my hand taketh hold on judgment: I will render vengeance unto my enemies, and those that hate me will I requite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.42'>I will make my arrows drunken with blood, and my sword shall devour flesh; from the blood of the slain and of the captives, from the crushed head of the enemy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.43'>Speak aloud, O ye nations, the praises of his people; for he will avenge the blood of his servants, and vengeance will he render to his adversaries, and forgive his land, and people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.44'>And Moses came and spoke all the words of this song in the ears of the people, he, and Hoshea the son of Nun.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.45'>And when Moses had made an end of speaking all these words to all Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.46'>He said unto them, Set your hearts unto all the words which I testify against you this day, so that ye may command them your children, to observe to do all the words of this law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.47'>For it is not a vain word for you; on the contrary, it is your life; and through this word shall ye live many days in the land, whither ye go over the Jordan to possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.48'>And the Lord spoke unto Moses on that selfsame day, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.49'>Get thee up into this mountain of Abarim, unto mount Nebo, which is in the land of Moab, that is in front of Jericho; and behold the land of Canaan, which I give unto the children of Israel for a possession;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.50'>And die on the mount whither thou goest up, and be gathered unto thy people; as Aaron thy brother died on mount Hor, and was gathered unto his people;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.51'>Because ye trespassed against me in the midst of the children of Israel at the waters of contention at Kadesh, in the wilderness of Zin; because ye sanctified me not in the midst of the children of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.32.52'>For from afar shalt thou see the land; but thither shalt thou not go unto the land which I give the children of Israel.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.33'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.1'>And this is the blessing, wherewith Moses, the man of God, blessed the children of Israel before his death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.2'>And he said, The Lord came from Sinai, and rose up from Seir unto them: he shone forth from mount Paran, and he came from among myriads of saints; from his right hand he gave a fiery law unto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.3'>Yea, thou also lovedst the tribes; all their saints were in thy hand; and they, prostrate before thy feet, received thy words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.4'>"The law which Moses commanded us, is the inheritance of the congregation of Jacob."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.5'>Thus became he king in Yeshurun, when the heads of the people were assembled, as one the tribes of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.6'>May Reuben live, and not die; and may not his men be few.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.7'>And this is the blessing of Judah, and he said, Hear, Lord, the voice of Judah, and bring him unto his people: let the power of his hands contend for him; and be thou a help to him from his adversaries.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.8'>And of Levi he said, Thy Thummim and thy Urim are with thy holy man, whom thou didst prove at Massah, and with whom thou didst strive at the waters of Meribah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.9'>Who said of his father and of his mother, I have not seen him; and who did not acknowledge his brothers, nor regarded his own children; for they observe thy word, and thy covenant they keep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.10'>They shall teach thy ordinances unto Jacob, and thy law unto Israel: they shall put incense before thee, and whole burntsacrifice upon thy altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.11'>Bless, O Lord, his substance, and receive favorably the work of his hands: crush the loins of those that rise up against him, and those that hate him, that they cannot rise again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.12'>And of Benjamin he said, The beloved of the Lord is he, he shall dwell in safety by him: he will shield him all the day long, and between his shoulders will he dwell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.13'>And of Joseph he said, Blessed of the Lord be his land, through the precious gift of heaven, through the dew, and through the deep that coucheth beneath,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.14'>And through the precious fruits brought forth by the sun, and through the precious things put forth by the moon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.15'>And through the best things of the ancient mountains, and through the precious things of the everlasting hills,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.16'>And through the precious things of the earth and its fulness, and through the goodwill of him that dwelt in the thornbush: may this blessing come upon the head of Joseph, and upon the crown of the head of him that was separated from his brothers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.17'>His firstborn steer is adorned with glory, and his horns are like the horns of reem; with them shall he push nations together to the ends of the earth: and they are the myriads of Ephraim, and they are the thousands of Menasseh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.18'>And of Zebulun he said, Rejoice, Zebulun, in thy going out; and, Issachar, in thy tents.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.19'>They will call the tribes unto the mountain; there will they offer sacrifices of righteousness; for they will suck the abundance of the seas, and the treasures hid in the sand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.20'>And of Gad he said, Blessed be he that enlargeth Gad: like a lioness lieth he down, and teareth off the arm with the crown of the head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.21'>And he provided the first part for himself, because there is the field of the lawgiver, of the hidden; and he went forth at the head of the people: he executed the justice of the Lord, and his judgments with Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.22'>And of Dan he said, Dan is a lions whelp, that leapeth forth from Bashan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.23'>And of Naphtali he said, O Naphtali, satisfied with favor, and full of the blessing of the Lord, take thou possession of the west and the south.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.24'>And of Asher he said, More than all the children be Asher blessed: he shall be the most favored of his brethren, and bathe his foot in oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.25'>Iron and copper shall be thy bolts; and as thy younger days so shall thy old age be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.26'>There is none like unto the God of Yeshurun, who rideth to help thee upon the heavens, and in his excellency upon the skies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.27'>Thy refuge is the eternal God, and here beneath, the everlasting arms; and he thrust out the enemy from before thee; and he said, Destroy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.28'>And then dwelt Israel in safety, alone, the fountain of Jacob; in a land of corn and wine; also its heavens shall drop down dew.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.33.29'>Happy art thou, O Israel! who is like unto thee, O people, saved by the Lord, the Shield of thy help, and who is the Sword of thy excellency! and thy enemies shall fawn upon thee; and thou shalt tread upon their highplaces.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Deut.34'>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.1'>And Moses went up from the plains of Moab unto the mount of Nebo, to the top of Pisgah, that is before Jericho; and the Lord showed him all the land from Gilad unto Dan,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.2'>And all Naphtali, and the land of Ephraim, and Menasseh, and all the land of Judah, unto the western sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.3'>And the south, and the plain, the valley of Jericho, the city of palmtrees, unto Zoar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.4'>And the Lord said unto him, This is the land which I swore unto Abraham, unto Isaac, and unto Jacob, saying, Unto thy seed will I give it: I have let thee see it with thy eyes, but thither shalt thou not go over.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.5'>And Moses the servant of the Lord died there in the land of Moab, according to the order of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.6'>And he buried him in the valley in the land of Moab, opposite Bethpeor; but no man knoweth of his sepulchre unto this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.7'>And Moses was a hundred and twenty years old when he died; his eye was not dimmed, and his natural force had not abated.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.8'>And the children of Israel wept for Moses in the plains of Moab thirty days; and then were ended the days of weeping and mourning for Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.9'>And Joshua the son of Nun was full of the spirit of wisdom; for Moses had laid his hands upon him; and the children of Israel hearkened unto him, and did, as the Lord had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.10'>And there arose not a prophet since then in Israel like unto Moses, whom the Lord knew face to face,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.11'>In respect to all the signs and the wonders, which the Lord had sent him to do in the land of Egypt to Pharaoh, and to all his servants, and to all his land,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Deut.34.12'>And in respect to all that mighty hand, and in all the great terrific deeds which Moses displayed before the eyes of all Israel.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>