<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='Roth' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='Roth'>
        <title>Rotherham Version</title>
        <contributor>CrossWire Bible Society</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-22</date>
        <description>The Emphasized Bible by J. B. Rotherham</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>Roth</identifier>
        <source>http://www.crosswire.org/sword/servlet/SwordMod.Verify?modName=Rotherham&amp;pkgType=win</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the  world</coverage>
        <rights>originally published by Samuel Bagster and Sons in 1902</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='1John'>
      <chapter osisID='1John.1'>
        <title>There hath befallen them the thing</title>
        <verse osisID='1John.1.1'>That which was from the beginning, which we have heard, which we have seen with our eyes, which we for ourselves gazed upon, and our hands did handle, concerning the Word of Life,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.1.2'>And, the Life, was made manifest, and we have seen, and are bearing witness, and announcing unto you, the Age-abiding Life, which, indeed, was with the Father, and was made manifest unto us;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.1.3'>That which we have seen and heard, are we announcing, even unto you, in order that, ye too, may have fellowship with us, and, our own fellowship also, may be with the Father, and with his Son Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.1.4'>And, these things, are we writing, in order that, our joy, may be made full.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.1.5'>And this is the message which we have heard from him, and are reporting unto you,that, God, is, light, and in him is, no darkness at all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.1.6'>If we sayWe have, fellowship, with him! and, in darkness, are walking, we are dealing falsely, and not doing the truth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.1.7'>Whereas, if, in the light, we are walking, as, he, is in the light, we have, fellowship one with another, and, the blood of Jesus his Son, is cleansing us from all sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.1.8'>If we saySin, have we none! we are deceiving, ourselves, and, the truth, is not in us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.1.9'>If we are confessing our sins, faithful, is he and, righteousthat he should forgive us our sins, and cleanse us from all unrighteousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.1.10'>If we sayWe have not sinned! false, are we making, him, and, his word, is not in us.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1John.2'>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.1'>My dear children! these things, am I writing unto you, in order that ye may not be committing sin. And, if anyone should commit sin, an Advocate, have we, with the Father, Jesus Christ, the Righteous;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.2'>And, he, is, a propitiation, concerning our sins,and, not concerning our own only, but, also concerning those of the whole world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.3'>And, hereby, perceive we, that we understand him,if, his commandments, we are keeping.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.4'>He that saithI understand him! And, his commandments, is not keeping, is false, and, in him, the truth is not!</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.5'>But whosoever may be keeping his word, of a truth, in this man, the love of God hath been made perfect. Hereby, perceive we, that, in him, we are.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.6'>He that saith, that, in him, he abideth, ought, just as He walked, himself also, to be walking.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.7'>Beloved! no new commandment, am I writing unto you; but an old commandment, which ye have been holding from the beginning: The old commandment is the word which ye have heard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.8'>Again, a new commandment, am I writing unto you,which thing is true, in him and in you, because, the darkness, is passing away, and, the real light, already is shining.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.9'>He that saith he is, in the light, and hateth, his brother, is, in the darkness, until even now!</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.10'>He that loveth his brother, is abiding, in the light, and, cause of stumbling, in him, is there none.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.11'>Whereas, he that hateth his brother, in the darkness, dwelleth, and in the darkness, walketh; and knoweth not whither he is drifting, because the, darkness, hath blinded his eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.12'>I write unto you, dear children, because your sins have been forgiven you, for the sake of his name:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.13'>I write unto you, fathers, because ye understand him who was from the beginning: I write unto you, young men, because ye have overcome the wicked one. I have written unto you, little children, because ye understand the Father:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.14'>I have written unto you, fathers, because ye understand him who was from the beginning: I have written you, young men, because ye are, strong, and the word of God, within you, abideth, and ye have overcome the wicked one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.15'>Be not loving the world, nor yet the things that are in the world: if anyone be loving the world, the love of the Father is not in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.16'>Because, all that is in the worldthe coveting of the flesh, the coveting of the eyes, and the vain grandeur of lifeis not of the Father, but is, of the world;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.17'>And, the world, passeth away, and the coveting  thereof , but, he that doeth the will of God, endureth unto times age-abiding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.18'>Little children! it is, the last hour; and, just as ye have heard that, an antichrist, is coming, even now, antichrists have become, many, whence we perceive that it is, the last hour:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.19'>From among us, they went out, but they were not of us; for, if, of us, they had been, they would in that case have abode with us; but</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.20'>And, ye, have, an anointing, from the Holy One,Ye all, know:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.21'>I have not written unto you because ye know not the truth, but because ye know it, and because, no falsehood, is, of the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.22'>Who, is the False One;save he that denieth that, Jesus, is the Christ? The same, is the Antichrist,he that denieth the Father and the Son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.23'>Whosoever denieth the Son, neither hath he, the Father: He that confesseth the Son, hath, the Father also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.24'>As for you, what ye have heard from the beginning, in you, let it abide. If, in you, shall abide, that which, from the beginning, ye have heard, ye also, in the Son, and  in  the Father, shall abide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.25'>And, this, is the promise, which he hath promised unto us,The age-abiding life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.26'>These things, have I written unto you, concerning them who would lead you astray.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.27'>And, as for you, the anointing which ye have received from him, abideth in you, and ye have, no need, that anyone be teaching you; but, as, his anointing, is teaching you, and is, true, and is no falsehood, even just as it hath taught you, abide ye in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.28'>And, now, dear children, abide ye in him, in order that, if he be made manifest, we may have boldness, and not be shamed away from him by his presence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.2.29'>If ye know that he is, righteous, ye perceive thatwhosoever doeth righteousness, of him, hath been born.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1John.3'>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.1'>Behold, what manner of love, the Father hath bestowed upon usthat, children of God, we should be called,and such we are! Therefore, the world understandeth us not, because it understood not him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.2'>Beloved! now, are we, children of God; and, not yet, hath it been made manifest, what we shall be,We know that, if it should be made manifest, like unto him, shall we be, because we shall see him, just as he is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.3'>And, whosoever hath this hope on him, is purifying himself, just as, He, is pure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.4'>Whosoever is committing sin, lawlessness also, is committing, and, sin, is, lawlessness;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.5'>And ye know, that, He, was made manifestin order that, our sins, he should take away, and, sin, in him, is there none.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.6'>Whosoever, in him, doth abide, is not sinning: whosoever is sinning, hath not seen him, and doth not understand him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.7'>Dear children! Let, no one, lead you astray! He that is doing righteousness, is, righteous, just as, He, is righteous:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.8'>He that is committing sin, is, of the adversary, because, from the beginning, the adversary is sinning. To this end, was the Son of God made manifest, in order that he might undo the works of the adversary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.9'>Whosoever hath been born of God, is not committing, sin, because, a seed of him, within him, abideth; and he cannot be committing sin, because, of God, hath he been born.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.10'>Herein, are, manifest, the children of God, and the children of the adversary: Whoever is not doing righteousness, is not of God, nor yet he that is not loving his brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.11'>Because, this, is the message which ye have heard from the beginningthat we should be loving one another,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.12'>Not just as, Cain, was, of the wicked one, and slew his brother! And, for what cause, slew he him? Because, his works, were, wicked, whereas, those of his brother, were, righteous.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.13'>Be not marveling, brethren, if, the world, is hating you:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.14'>We, know, that we have passed over out of death into life, because we love the brethren: he that loveth not, abideth in death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.15'>Whosoever is hating his brother, is, a murderer; and ye know that, no murderer, hath life age-during, within him abiding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.16'>Hereby, have we come to understand love: in that, He, for us, his life laid down; and, we, ought, for the brethren, our lives to lay down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.17'>But, whoso hath this worlds goods, and beholdeth his brother having, need, and shutteth up his tender affections from him, how, is, the love of God, abiding in him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.18'>Dear children! Let us not be loving in word, nor yet with the tongue, but in deed and truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.19'>Hereby, shall we get to know, that, of the truth, we are, and, before him, shall persuade our heart;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.20'>Because, if our own heart condemn us, greater, is God, than our heart, and perceiveth all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.21'>Beloved! if our heart be not condemning us, boldness, have we, towards God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.22'>And, whatsoever we are asking, we are receiving from him, because, his commandments, are we keeping, and, the things that are pleasing before him, are we doing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.23'>And, this, is his commandment,that we should believe in the name of his Son Jesus Christ, and be loving one anotherjust as he gave a commandment unto us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.3.24'>And, he that keepeth his commandments, in him, abideth, and, he, in him. And, hereby, perceive we, that he abideth in us, by reason of the Spirit which, unto us, he hath given.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1John.4'>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.1'>Beloved! not in every spirit, believe ye, but test the spirits, whether they are, of God; because, many false prophets, have gone out into the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.2'>Hereby, do ye perceive the Spirit of God:every spirit that confesseth Jesus Christ as having come, in flesh, is, of God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.3'>And, every spirit that doth not confess Jesus, of God, is not. And, this, is the</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.4'>Ye, are, of God, dear children, and have overcome them; because, greater, is he that is in you, than he that is in the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.5'>They, are, of the world: For this cause, of the world, they speak, and the world, unto them, doth hearken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.6'>We, are, of God: he that is getting to understand God, hearkeneth unto us,whoso is not of God, hearkeneth not unto us: from this, perceive wethe spirit of truth, and the spirit of error.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.7'>Beloved! let us be loving one another; because, love, is, of God, and, whosoever loveth, of God, hath been born, and is getting to understand God:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.8'>He that doth not love, doth not understand God, because, God, is, love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.9'>Herein, hath the love of God in us, been made manifest, that, his only-begotten Son, God sent into the world, in order that we might live through him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.10'>Herein, is love: not that, we, have loved God, but that, he, loved us, and sent forth his Son, as a propitiation concerning our sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.11'>Beloved! If, in this way, God, loved us, we also, ought to love, one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.12'>Upon God, hath no one, at any time, gazed: If we love one another, God, in us, abideth, and, his love, hath been perfected within us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.13'>Hereby, perceive wethat, in him, are we abiding, and, he, in us,in that, of his Spirit, hath he given unto us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.14'>And, we, for ourselves have gazed, and are bearing witnessthat, the Father, sent forth the Son, as Saviour of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.15'>Whosoever shall confess, that, Jesus  Christ  is the Son of God, God, in him, abideth, and, he, in God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.16'>And, we, have come to understand and to trust the love which, God, hath, in us. God, is, love; and, he that abideth in love, in God, abideth, and, God, in him  abideth .</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.17'>Herein, hath love with us, been made perfect,in order that, boldness, we might have in the day of judging,in that, just as, He, is, we also, are, in this world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.18'>Fear, existeth not, in love, but, perfect love, casteth fear, outside; because, fear, hath correction: he that feareth, hath not been made perfect, in love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.19'>We, love, because, he, first loved us:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.20'>If one should say, I love God, and should be hating, his brother, false, is he; for, he that doth not love his brother, whom he hath seen, God, whom he hath not seen, he cannot love!</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.4.21'>And, this commandment, have we from him,that, he who loveth God, love, his brother also.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1John.5'>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.1'>Whosoever believeth that, Jesus, is the Christ, of God, hath been born: and, whosoever loveth him that begat, loveth him that hath been begotten of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.2'>Hereby, perceive we, that we love the children of God, as soon as, God, we love, and, his commandments, we are doing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.3'>For, this is the love of Godthat, his commandments, we be keeping, and, his commandments, are not burdensome;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.4'>Because, whatsoever hath been born of God, overcometh the world; and, this, is the victory that hath overcome the worldour faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.5'> And  who is he that overcometh the world, save he that believeth that, Jesus, is the Son of God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.6'>This, is he that came through means of water and blood, Jesus Christ: not, by the water, only, but, by the water and by the blood,and, the Spirit, it is, that is bearing witness, because, the Spirit, is the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.7'>Because, three, are they who are bearing witness</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.8'>The Spirit, and the Water, and the Blood; and, the three, are,   , unto one thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.9'>If, the witness of men, we receive, the witness of God, is, greater. Because, this, is the witness of Godin that he hath borne witness concerning his Son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.10'>He that believeth on the Son of God, hath the witness, within himself: He that doth not believe God, false, hath made him,because he hath not believed on the witness which, God, hath witnessed, concerning his Son</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.11'>And, this, is the witness:that, life age-abiding, hath God given unto us, and, this life, is, in his Son:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.12'>He that hath the Son, hath, the life,he that hath not the Son of God, hath not, the life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.13'>These things, have I written unto youin order that ye may know that ye have, Life Age-abidingunto you who believe on the name of the Son of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.14'>And, this, is the boldness which we have towards him: that, if, anything, we ask, according to his will, He doth hearken unto us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.15'>And, if we know that he doth hearken unto us, whatsoever we ask, we know that we have the things asked, which we have asked of him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.16'>If one should see his brother committing a sin, not unto death, he shall ask, and He will grant unto him life,for them who are sinning, not unto death. There, is, a sin, unto death: not concerning that, am I saying, that he should make request.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.17'>All unrighteousness, is, sin, and there, is, a sin, not unto death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.18'>We know that, whosoever hath been born of God, is not committing sin,Nay, he that hath been born of God, He keepeth him, and, the wicked one, doth not touch him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.19'>We know that, of God, are we; and, the whole world, in the wicked one, is lying.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.20'>We know, moreover, that, the Son of God, hath come, and hath given us insight, so that we are getting to understand, him that is Real,and we are in him that is Real, in his Son Jesus Christ. This, is the Real God, and life age-abiding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1John.5.21'>Dear children! Guard yourselves from idols.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>