<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='Roth' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='Roth'>
        <title>Rotherham Version</title>
        <contributor>CrossWire Bible Society</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-22</date>
        <description>The Emphasized Bible by J. B. Rotherham</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>Roth</identifier>
        <source>http://www.crosswire.org/sword/servlet/SwordMod.Verify?modName=Rotherham&amp;pkgType=win</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the  world</coverage>
        <rights>originally published by Samuel Bagster and Sons in 1902</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='1Pet'>
      <chapter osisID='1Pet.1'>
        <title>To him, therefore, who knoweth how to be doing, a right thing, and is not doing it, it is, sin, unto him.</title>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.1'>Peter, an apostle of Jesus Christ, unto the chosen pilgrims of the dispersion, throughout Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia and Bithynia,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.2'>fehlt</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.3'>Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, Who, according to his great mercy, hath regenerated us unto a living hope, through the resurrection of Jesus Christ from among the dead,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.4'>Unto an inheritance, incorruptible and undefiled and unfading, reserved in the heavens for you</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.5'>who, in Gods power, are being guarded through faith unto salvationready to be revealed in the last ripe time:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.6'>Wherein ye exult, though, for a little, just now, if needful, put to grief in manifold temptations,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.7'>In order that the proving of your faithmuch more precious than of gold that perisheth even though, by means of fire, it is provedmay be found unto praise and glory and honour in the revealing of Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.8'>Whom, not having seen, ye love, on whom, though at present not looking, but believing, ye exult with joy unspeakable and filled with glory,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.9'>Being about to bear away the end of your faitha salvation of souls:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.10'>Concerning which salvation, prophetswho concerning the favour for you, did prophesysought out and searched out,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.11'>Searching into what particular, or what manner, of season the Spirit of Christ which was in them was pointing to, when witnessing beforehand as toThe sufferings, for Christ, and the glories, after these,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.12'>Unto whom it was revealedthat, Not unto themselves, but unto us, they were ministering them, which things have, now, been announced unto you through them who have told you the good tidings with Holy Spirit sent forth from heaven: into which things messengers are coveting to obtain a nearer view.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.13'>Wherefore, girding up the loins of your mind, keeping sober, perseveringly direct your hope unto the favour, being borne along to you, in the revealing of Jesus Christ:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.14'>As obedient persons, not configuring yourselves unto your former covetings in your ignorance:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.15'>But, according as he that hath called you is holy, do, ye yourselves, also become, holy in all manner of behaviour,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.16'>Inasmuch as it is writtenHoly shall ye be, because, I, am holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.17'>And, if, as Father, ye are invoking him who, without respect of persons, judgeth according to each mans work, with reverence, for the time of your sojourning, behave ye;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.18'>Knowing that, Not with corruptible things, with silver or gold, have ye been redeemed from your unmeaning behaviour paternally handed down,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.19'>But with precious blood, as of a lamb, unblemished and unspotted, of an Anointed One,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.20'>Foreknown, indeed, before the foundation of the world, but made manifest at a last stage of the times, for the sake of you</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.21'>who, through him, are faithful towards God,Who raised him from among the dead, and glory to him gave, So that your faith and hope are directed towards God:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.22'>Having purified, your souls, by the obedience of the truth, unto unfeigned brotherly affection, from the heart, love, one another, earnestly;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.23'>Having been regeneratedNot out of corruptible seed, but incorruptiblethrough means of the word of a Living and Abiding God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.24'>Inasmuch asAll flesh, is as grass, and, all the glory thereof, as the flower of grass,The grass hath withered, and the flower hath fallen out,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.1.25'>But the declaration of the Lord age-abidingly remaineth; And, this, is a declaration which in the joyful message hath been announced unto you.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Pet.2'>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.1'>Putting away, therefore, all vice and all deceit and hypocrisy and envyings and all detractions,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.2'>As new-born babes, for the pure milk that is for the mind, eagerly crave, that, thereby, ye may grow unto salvation:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.3'>If ye have tasted for yourselves that, gracious, is the Lord,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.4'>Unto whom coming near, as unto a living stoneby men, indeed, rejected, but, with God, chosen, held in honour,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.5'>Yourselves also, as living stones, are being built up a spiritual house, for a holy priesthood, to offer spiritual sacrifices, well-pleasing unto God through Jesus Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.6'>Inasmuch as it is contained in scriptureLo! I lay in Zion an outmost corner stone, chosen, held in honour, and, he that resteth faith thereupon, shall not be put to shame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.7'>Unto you, then, is the honour  who believe; but, unto such as disbelieve, The stone which the builders rejected,The same, hath become head of the corner,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.8'>And a stone to strike against, and a rock to stumble over: Who stumble because, unto the word, they do not yield,unto which also they have been appointed;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.9'>But, ye, are a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people for a peculiar treasure, that, the excellences, ye may tell forth, of him who, out of darkness, hath called you into his marvellous light:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.10'>Who, at one time, were a No-people, but, now, are a people of God,who had not been enjoying mercy, but, now, have received mercy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.11'>Beloved! I exhort you, as sojourners and pilgrims, to abstain from fleshly covetings, such as take the field against the soul;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.12'>Having, your behaviour among the nations, honourable,in order that, wherein they speak against you as evil-doers, they may, owing to the honourable works they are permitted to behold, glorify God in the day of visitation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.13'>Submit yourselves unto every human creation, for the Lords sake,whether unto a king, as one that protecteth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.14'>Or unto governors, as, through him, sentfor vengeance on evil-doers, but praise to such as do good;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.15'>Because, so, is the will of God,by doing good, to be putting to silence, the ignorance of heedless men:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.16'>As free, yet, not as a cloak of vice, holding your freedom, but, as Gods servants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.17'>Unto all men, give honour, unto the brotherhood, shew love, unto God, give reverence, the king, hold in honour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.18'>Ye domestics, submitting yourselves, in all reverence, unto your masters,not only unto the good and considerate, but also unto the perverse;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.19'>For, this, is thankworthy,If, for the sake of conscience towards God, one beareth griefs, suffering wrongfully,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.20'>For what sort of honour is itif, committing sin, and being buffeted, ye endure it? But, if, doing good, and suffering, ye endure it, this, is thankworthy with God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.21'>For, hereunto, have ye been called; because, Christ also, suffered in your behalf, unto you, leaving behind a pattern, that ye might follow in his steps:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.22'>Who did not, a sin, commit, neither was deceit found in his mouth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.23'>Who, being reviled, was not reviling again, suffering, he was not threatening, but was making surrender unto him that judgeth righteously,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.24'>Who, our sins, himself, bare up, in his body, unto the tree, in order that we, from our sins getting away, in righteousness, might live,by whose stripes, ye have been healed;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.2.25'>For ye were as sheep going astray, but have now turned back unto the shepherd and overseer of your souls.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Pet.3'>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.1'>In like manner, ye wives,submitting yourselves unto your own husbands; in order that, if any are not yielding unto the word, through their wives behaviour, they may, without the word, be won,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.2'>Having been permitted to behold your reverently chaste behaviour,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.3'>Whose adorning, let it benot the outward, of plaiting the hair and wearing golden ornaments, or putting on of apparel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.4'>But the hidden character, of the heart,in the incorruptible   of the quiet, and meek, spirit, which is, in presence of God, of great price.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.5'>For, so, at one time, the holy women also, who directed their hope towards God, used to adorn themselves, being in submission unto their own husbands:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.6'>As, Sarah, was obedient unto Abraham, calling him, lord,whose children ye have becomeso long as ye are doing good, and not bringing yourselves into fear of any single cause of alarm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.7'>Ye husbands, in like manner, dwelling with them according to knowledge,as unto a weaker vessel, unto the female</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.8'>And, finally, all, being of one mind, having fellowfeeling, attached to the brethren, of tender affection, of lowly mind:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.9'>Not returning evil for evil, nor reviling for reviling, but, on the contrary, bestowing a blessing,because, hereunto, have ye been called, in order that, a blessing, ye might inherit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.10'>For, he that desireth to love, life, and to see good days, Let him cause his tongue to cease from mischief, and lips, that they speak not deceit;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.11'>Let him turn away from mischief, and do good, Let him seek peace, and pursue it;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.12'>Because, the eyes of the Lord, are towards the righteous, and his ears, unto their supplication,Whereas, the face of the Lord, is against them that are doing mischievous things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.13'>Who, then, is he that shall harm you, if, for that which is good, ye become zealous?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.14'>Nevertheless, even if ye should suffer for righteousness sake, happy   ! Their fear, however, do not fear, neither be troubled;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.15'>But, the Lord Christ, hallow ye in your hearts, ready always for a defence, unto every one that is asking you a reason concerning, the hope within you,nevertheless, with meekness and reverence:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.16'>Having, a good conscience, in order that, wherein they speak against you, they may be put to shame who cast wanton insult on, your good behaviour in Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.17'>For it is, better, as well-doers, if it should please the pleasure of God, to be suffering, than, as evil-doers:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.18'>Because, Christ also, once for all, concerning sins, died,Just in behalf of unjust,in order that he might introduce us unto God; being put to death, indeed, in flesh, but made alive in spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.19'>In which, even unto the spirits in prison, he went and proclaimed,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.20'>fehlt</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.21'>Which   in manner corresponding, doth, now, save, you alsoeven immersion,not a putting away of the filth of the flesh, but the request unto God, for a good conscience, through the resurrection of Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.3.22'>Who is on the right hand of God, having gone into heaven, messengers and authorities and powers, having been made subject unto him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Pet.4'>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.1'>Christ, then, having suffered in flesh, do, ye also, with the same purpose, arm yourselves,because, he that hath suffered in flesh, hath done with sins,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.2'>To the end that, no longer, in mens covetings, but in Gods will, ye may live, the still remaining time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.3'>For, sufficient, is the bygone timeto have wrought out, the will of the nations, having gone on in wanton ways, covetings, wine-drinkings, revellings, drinking-bouts, and impious idolatries:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.4'>Wherein they are taken by surprise that ye run not with them into the same overflow of riotous excess,uttering defamation:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.5'>Who shall render an account unto him who is holding in readiness to judge living and dead;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.6'>For, unto this end, even unto the dead, was the glad-message delivered,in order that they might be judged, indeed, according to men in flesh, but might live according to God in spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.7'>But, the end of all things, hath drawn near:be of sound mind, therefore, and be sober for prayers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.8'>Before all things, keeping, fervent, your love, among yourselves, because, love, covereth a multitude of sins;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.9'>Showing hospitality one to another without murmuring,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.10'>Each one, according as he hath received a gift of favour, unto one another, ministering the same, as careful stewards of the manifold favour of God:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.11'>If any one speaketh, as oracles of God, if any one ministereth, as of strength which, God, supplieth,that, in all things, God may be glorified through Jesus Christ,unto whom are the glory and the dominion, unto the ages of ages. Amen!</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.12'>Beloved! be not held in surprise by the burning among you, which, for putting you to the proof, is befalling you, as though a, surprising, thing were happening unto you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.13'>But, in so far as ye are taking fellowship in the Christs sufferings, rejoice! in order that, in the revealing of his glory also, ye may rejoice with exultation:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.14'>If ye are being reproached in the name of Christ, happy   of God, unto you is bringing rest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.15'>For let, none of you, be suffering as a murderer, or a thief, or an evil-doer, or as one prying into other mens affairs;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.16'>But, if as a Christian, let him not be ashamed, but be glorifying God in this name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.17'>For it is the ripe time for the judgment to begin with the house of God; but, if first with us, what shall be the end of them who yield not unto the glad-message of God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.18'>And, if, the righteous man, is, with difficulty, saved, where then shall, the ungodly and sinful man, appear?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.4.19'>So then, let, them who are even suffering, according to the will of God, unto a faithful Creator, be committing their souls, in well-doing.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Pet.5'>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.1'>Elders, therefore, among you, I exhort  who am their co-elder and a witness of the sufferings of the Christ, who also, in the glory about to be revealed, have, a share;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.2'>Shepherd the beloved flock of God, which is among you,not by compulsion, but by choice, nor yet for base gain, but of a ready mind,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.3'>Nor yet as lording it over the allotted portions, but becoming, ensamples, to the beloved flock;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.4'>And, when the Chief Shepherd is manifested, ye shall bear away, the unfading crown of glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.5'>In like manner, ye younger mensubmit yourselves unto elders;All, however, one towards another, gird on humility; because, God, against the haughty, arrayeth himself, whereas, unto the lowly, he giveth favour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.6'>Be made lowly, therefore, under the strong hand of God, that he may lift, you, up in due time,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.7'>All your anxiety, casting upon him, because he careth for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.8'>Be sober! be watchful! Your slanderous adversary, as a roaring lion, is walking aboutseeking to devour:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.9'>Whom resist, steadfast in your faith, knowing that, the same sufferings, in your brotherhood that is in the world, are being accomplished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.10'>Howbeit, the God of all favourwho hath called you unto his age-abiding glory in Christwhen, for a little, ye have suffered, Himself, will adjust, confirm, strengthen:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.11'>Unto him, be the dominion, unto the ages. Amen!</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.12'>By Silvanus, the faithful brother, as I account him, have I briefly written, unto you, exhorting and adding testimonythat, this, is the true favour of Godwithin which, stand ye fast!</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.13'>She who, in Babylon, is co-elect, and Mark my son, salute you:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Pet.5.14'>Salute ye one another with a kiss of love. Peace unto you all who are in Christ.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>