<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='Roth' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='Roth'>
        <title>Rotherham Version</title>
        <contributor>CrossWire Bible Society</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-22</date>
        <description>The Emphasized Bible by J. B. Rotherham</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>Roth</identifier>
        <source>http://www.crosswire.org/sword/servlet/SwordMod.Verify?modName=Rotherham&amp;pkgType=win</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the  world</coverage>
        <rights>originally published by Samuel Bagster and Sons in 1902</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='2Pet'>
      <chapter osisID='2Pet.1'>
        <title>So then, let, them who are even suffering, according to the will of God, unto a faithful Creator, be committing their souls, in well-doing.</title>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.1'>Simon Peter, servant and apostle of Jesus Christ, unto them who have obtained, equally precious, faith, with us, in the righteousness of our God, and Saviour Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.2'>Favour unto you, and peace, be multiplied, in the personal knowledge of God and of Jesus our Lord;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.3'>As, all things, suited for life and godliness his divine power, unto us, hath given, through the personal knowledge of him that hath called us through glory and excellence,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.4'>Through which, his precious, and very great, promises, have, unto us, been given, in order that, through these, ye might become sharers in a divine natureescaping the corruption that is in the world by coveting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.5'>And, for this very reason alsoadding, on your part, all diligence, supply, in your faith, excellence, and, in your excellence, knowledge,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.6'>And, in your knowledge, self-control, and, in your self-control, endurance, and, in your endurance, godliness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.7'>And, in your godliness, brotherly affection, and, in your brotherly affection, love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.8'>These things, unto you, belonging and abounding, neither idle nor unfruitful, constitute you, regarding the personal knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.9'>For, he to whom these things are not present, is, blind, seeing only what is near, having come, to forget, his purification from his old sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.10'>Wherefore, all the more, brethren, give diligence to be making, firm, your calling and election; for, these things, doing, in nowise shall ye stumble at any time,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.11'>For, thus, shall richly be further supplied unto youthe entrance into the age-abiding kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.12'>Wherefore, I shall be certain to be, always, putting you in remembrance concerning these things,although, indeed, ye know them, and have become confirmed in the present truth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.13'>Right, nevertheless, I account itas long as I am in this tent, to be stirring you up by putting you in remembrance,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.14'>Knowing that, speedy, is the putting off of my tenteven as, our Lord Jesus Christ also, made clear to me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.15'>Yea, I will give diligence also, that, at every time, ye may be able, after my own departure, to be keeping up the remembrance of, these very things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.16'>For, not as having followed, cleverly devised stories, made we known unto you the power and presence of our Lord Jesus Christ, but as having been made, spectators, of his majesty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.17'>For, when he received from God the Father honour and glory, a voice, being borne to him such as this, by the magnificent gloryMy Son, the beloved, is, this, in whom, I, delight,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.18'>Even this voice, we, heard, when, out of heaven, it was borne, we being, with him, in the holy mount.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.19'>And we have, more firm, the prophetic word;whereunto ye are doing, well, to take heed,as unto a lamp shining in a dusky place,until, day, shall dawn, and, a day-star, shall arise in your hearts:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.20'>Of this, first, taking notethat, no prophecy of scripture, becometh, self-solving;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.1.21'>For not, by will of man, was prophecy brought in, at any time, but, as, by Holy Spirit, they were borne along, spake, men, from God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Pet.2'>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.1'>But there arose false-prophets also among the people, as, among you also, there shall be, false-teachers,men who will stealthily bring in destructive parties, even the Master that bought them, denying, bringing upon themselves speedy destruction;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.2'>And, many, will follow out their wanton ways,by reason of whom, the way of truth, will be defamed,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.3'>And, in greed, with forged words, will they, of you, make merchandise: for whom, the sentence from of old, is not idle, and, their destruction, doth not slumber.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.4'>Forif, God, spared not, messengers, when they sinned, but, to pits of gloom, consigning them, in the lowest hades, delivered them up to be kept, unto judgment,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.5'>And, an ancient world, spared not, but, with seven others, preserved, Noah, a proclaimer, of righteousness, a flood, upon a world of ungodly persons, letting loose,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.6'>And, the cities of Sodom and Gomorrah, reducing to ashes, he condemned, an example of such as should be ungodly, having set forth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.7'>And, righteous Lot, when getting worn out by the behaviour of them who were impious in wantonness, he rescued</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.8'>For, in seeing and hearing, since he dwelt right among them, as a righteous man, he used to torment his soul, day by day, with their lawless deeds</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.9'>fehlt</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.10'>Most of all, however, them who go their way, after the flesh, with a coveting of defilement, and who despise, lordship,daring! willful! before dignitaries, they tremble not, defaming,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.11'>where, messengers, though, greater in might and power, are not bringing against them  before the Lord  a defamatory accusation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.12'>These, however, as unreasoning creatures that have been bred as being, by nature, for capture and destruction, in the things they are ignorant of, uttering defamation, in their spoiling, shall also be made a spoil,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.13'>Doing wrong themselves, for a reward of wrong, accounting, a delight, their day-time delicacy, spots and blemishes, indulging in delicacies with their stratagems, as they carouse together with you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.14'>Having, eyes, full of an adulteress, and that cannot rest from sin, enticing unstable souls, having, a heart trained in greed,children of a curse,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.15'>Forsaking a straight path, they have gone astray, following out the way of Balaam   of Beor, who loved, a reward of wrong,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.16'>But had, a reproof, of his own transgression, a dumb beast of burden, in mans voice, finding utterance, forbade the prophets madness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.17'>These, are fountains without water, and mists, by a tempest, driven along,for whom, the gloom of darkness, hath been reserved;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.18'>For, great swelling words of vanity, uttering, they entice with carnal covetingsin wanton waysthem who are, well-nigh, escaping from the men who, in error, have their behaviour;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.19'>Promising, freedom to them, they themselves, being all the while, slaves of corruption,for, by whom one hath been defeated, by the same, hath he become enslaved,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.20'>For, if, having escaped from the defilements of the world by a personal knowledge of the Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, but, by the same having again become entangled, they are defeated, the, last, state hath become, for them, worse than, the first;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.21'>For, better, had it been for themnot to have obtained a personal knowledge of the way of righteousness, than, having obtained such knowledge, to turn back out of the holy commandment delivered unto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.2.22'>There hath befallen them the thing</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Pet.3'>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.1'>This, already, beloved, is the second letter I am writing unto you; and, in these letters, I am stirring upby way of calling to remembranceyour uncorrupted mind,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.2'>To remember the fore-spoken declarations made by the holy prophets, and the commandment of the Lord and Saviour, by your apostles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.3'>Of this, first, taking notethat there will come, in the last of the days, with scoffing, scoffers, after their own covetings, going on,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.4'>and sayingWhere is the promise of his presence? For, since the fathers fell asleep, all things, thus remain, from the beginning of creation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.5'>For this they, willfully, forgetthat there were, heavens, from of old, and, an earth, on account of water and by means of water, compacted, by Gods word,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.6'>By which means, the world that then was, with water being flooded, perished;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.7'>While, the heavens and the earth that now are, by the same word, have been stored with fire, being kept unto the day of judgment and destruction of the ungodly men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.8'>But, this one thing, forget not, beloved,that, one day, with the Lord, is as a thousand years, and, a thousand years, as one day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.9'>The Lord is, not slack, concerning his promise, as some count, slackness; but is long-suffering with regard to you, not being minded that any should perish, but that, all, unto repentance, should come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.10'>Howbeit the day of the Lord will be here, as a thief,in which, the heavens, with a rushing noise, will pass away, while, elements, becoming intensely hot, will be dissolved, and, earth, and the works therein, will be discovered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.11'>Seeing that all these things are thus to be dissolved, what manner of persons, ought  ye  all the while to be, in holy ways of behaviour and acts of godliness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.12'>Expecting and hastening the presence of the day of God, by reason of which, heavens, being on fire, will be dissolved, and, elements, becoming intensely hot, are to be melted;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.13'>But, new heavens, and a new earth, according to his promise, are we expecting, wherein, righteousness, is to dwell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.14'>Wherefore, beloved, these things, expectinggive diligence, unspotted and unblemished, by him, to be found, in peace;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.15'>And account, our Lords long suffering,   salvation:even as, our beloved brother Paul also, according to the wisdom given unto him, hath written unto you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.16'>As also, in all letters, speaking in them concerning these things,in which   are some things, hard to be understood, which, the uninstructed and unstable, wrest,as also the other scriptures,unto their own destruction.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.17'>Ye, therefore, beloved, taking note beforehand, be on your guard, lest, with the error of the impious being led away, ye fall from your own steadfastness;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Pet.3.18'>But be growing in the favour and knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ:unto whom be the glory, both now and unto a day that abideth.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>