<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='Roth' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='Roth'>
        <title>Rotherham Version</title>
        <contributor>CrossWire Bible Society</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-22</date>
        <description>The Emphasized Bible by J. B. Rotherham</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>Roth</identifier>
        <source>http://www.crosswire.org/sword/servlet/SwordMod.Verify?modName=Rotherham&amp;pkgType=win</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the  world</coverage>
        <rights>originally published by Samuel Bagster and Sons in 1902</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='2Sam'>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.1'>
        <title>and to them who were in Hebron,and to all the places where David had been to and fro, he and his men.</title>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.1'>And so it was, after the death of Saul, when David had returned from the smiting of the Amalekites, and David had abode in Ziklag two days,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.2'>yea so it was, on the third day, that lo! a man came out of the camp, from Saul, with his clothes rent, and earth upon his head,and so it was, when he came in unto David, that he fell to the earth, and did homage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.3'>And David said unto him, From whence comest thou? And he said unto him, Out of the camp of Israel, am I escaped.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.4'>And David said unto himHow turned out the matter? tell me, I pray thee. And he saidThe people have fled from the battle, yea moreover, many, of the people have fallen, and died, Yea moreover, Saul, and Jonathan his son, are dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.5'>Then said David unto the young man who was telling him,How knowest thou that Saul and Jonathan his son are dead?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.6'>And the young man who was telling him said, It, so happened, that I was on Mount Gilboa, when lo! Saul, leaning upon his spear, and lo! the chariots and horsemen, hotly pursued him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.7'>so he turned behind him, and saw me,and cried out unto me, and I said, Behold me!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.8'>And he said unto me, Who art thou? And I said unto him, An Amalekite, am I.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.9'>And he said unto me, I pray thee, take thy stand by me, and put me to death, for the cramp hath seized me,even for as long as my life shall be in me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.10'>So I took my stand by him, and put him to death, for I perceived that he could not survive his fall,so I took the crown that was on his head, and the bracelet that was on his arm, and have brought them in unto my lord, here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.11'>Then David took hold of his clothes, and rent them,yea moreover,   all the men who were with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.12'>And they lamented aloud, and wept, and fasted until the evening,for Saul, and for Jonathan his son, and for the people of Yahweh, and for the house of Israel, because they had fallen by the sword.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.13'>And David said unto the young man who was telling him, Whence art thou? And he said, Son of a sojourneran Amalekite, am I.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.14'>And David said unto him,How wast thou not afraid to thrust forth thy hand, to destroy the Anointed of Yahweh?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.15'>So David called one of the young men, and said,Go nearfall upon him. And he smote him, that he died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.16'>And David said unto him, Thy blood, be upon thine own head,for, thine own mouth, hath testified against thee, saying, I myself, put to death the Anointed of Yahweh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.17'>Then chanted David this dirge,over Saul and over Jonathan his son;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.18'>and he thought to teach the sons of Judah   the Bow,lo! it is written in the Book of the Upright:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.19'>The beauty of Israel! on thy high plumesslain! How have fallenthe mighty!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.20'>Do not tell it in Gath, Do not publish it in the streets of Ashkelon,lest the daughters of the Philistines rejoice, lest the daughters of the Uncircumcised triumph.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.21'>Ye mountains in Gilboa! Be there neither dew nor rain upon you, nor fields of offerings,for, there, were cast away, the shields of the mighty, The shield of Saul, unanointed with oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.22'>From the blood of the slain, from the fat of the mighty, the bow of Jonathan neer drew back,and, the sword of Saul, neer returned, empty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.23'>Saul and Jonathan, delightfully loving in their lives, even, in their death, were not divided,Beyond eagles, were they swift, beyond lions, were they strong!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.24'>Ye daughters of Israel! For Saul, weep ye,who clothed you in crimson,   with lovely things, who hung ornaments of gold on your apparel!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.25'>How have fallen the mighty, in the midst of the battle! Jonathan, on thy high places, slain!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.26'>I am distressed for thee, my brother, Jonathan! Delightful to me, exceedingly,Wonderful, was thy love to me, passing the love of women.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.1.27'>How have fallen the mighty, and perished the weapons of war!</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.2'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.1'>And it came to pass, after this, that David enquired of Yahweh, sayingShall I go up into one of the cities of Judah? And Yahweh said unto him, Go up. And David saidWhither shall I go up? And he saidUnto Hebron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.2'>So David went up thither, and his two wives also,Ahinoam, the Jezreelitess, and Abigail, wife of Nabal the Carmelite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.3'>His men also who were with him, did David bring up, every man with his household,and they dwelt in the cities of Hebron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.4'>Then came the men of Judah, and anointed David there, to be king over the house of Judah. And they told David, saying, Men of Jabesh-gilead, were they who buried Saul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.5'>So David sent messengers unto the men of Jabesh-gilead,and said unto themBlessed, be ye of Yahweh, that ye did this lovingkindness unto your lord, unto Saul, and buried him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.6'>Now, therefore, Yahweh requite you with lovingkindness and truth,moreover also, I, will requite you, for this noble deed, in that ye did this thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.7'>Now, therefore, let your hands be made firm, and become ye sons of valour, for your lord Saul is dead,and, me, moreover have the house of Judah anointed, to be king over them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.8'>But, Abner son of Ner, prince of the host that pertained unto Saul, took Ish-bosheth, son of Saul, and brought him over to Mahanaim;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.9'>and made him king for Gilead, and for the Ashurites, and for Jezreel,and over Ephraim, and over Benjamin, and over, all Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.10'>Forty years old, was Ish-bosheth son of Saul, when he began to reign over Israel, and, two years, reigned he,but, the house of Judah, followed David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.11'>And it came to pass, that, the number of the days that David was king in Hebron, over the house of Judah, was seven years and six months.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.12'>And Abner son of Ner, and the servants of Ish-bosheth, son of Saul, came out from Mahanaim to Gibeon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.13'>And, Joab son of Zeruiah, and the servants of David, went out from Hebron and met, by the pool of Gibeon, together, and they sat down, these, by the pool, on the one side, and, those, by the pool, on the other side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.14'>Then said Abner unto Joab, Let the young men arise, I pray thee, and make sport before us. And Joab saidLet them arise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.15'>Then there arose, and went over by number,twelve of Benjamin, pertaining to Ish-bosheth, son of Saul, and twelve, of the servants of David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.16'>And they caught every one his fellow by the head, with his sword in his fellows side, so they fell, together,and that place was called Helkath-hazzadim, which is in Gideon. \fs15</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.17'>So the battle became exceeding obstinate, on that day,and Abner and the men of Israel were defeated before the servants of David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.18'>Now there were there, three sons of Zeruiah, Joab, and Abishai, and Asahel,and, Asahel, was light of foot as a wild gazelle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.19'>And Asahel pursued Abner,and turned not, in going, to the right hand or to the left, from pursuing Abner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.20'>Then Abner looked behind him, and saidArt thou Asahel? And he saidI am.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.21'>Then Abner said to himTurn thee aside, to thy right hand, or to thy left, and lay thee hold on one of the young men, and take thee his armour. But Asahel would not turn aside from pursuing him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.22'>And Abner said, yet again, unto Asahel, Turn thee aside from pursuing me,wherefore should I smite thee to the earth? how then should I lift up my face unto Joab, thy brother?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.23'>Howbeit he refused to turn aside, wherefore Abner smote him with the hinder end of the spear, in the belly, that the spear came out behind him, and he fell there, and died on the spot,and so it was, that, as many as came up to the place where Asahel fell and died, stood still.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.24'>Then Joab and Abishai pursued Abner,but, the sun, had gone in by the time, they, had come as far as the hill of Ammah, that overlooketh Giah, by way of the wilderness of Gibeon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.25'>And, when the sons of Benjamin had gathered themselves together after Abner, and become one band,and had taken their stand on the top of a certain hill,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.26'>then Abner cried aloud unto Joab, and saidTo the uttermost, must the sword devour? Dost thou not well know that, bitter, shall it be, in the latter end? How long, then, wilt thou not bid the people turn back from pursuing their own brethren?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.27'>Then said JoabAs God liveth, surely, if thou hadst not spoken, then in the morning, the people would of themselves have gone up, every man from pursuing his brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.28'>So Joab blew with the horn, and all the people stood still, and they neither pursued Israel further,nor fought any more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.29'>And, Abner and his men, journeyed through the waste plain all that night,and crossed the Jordan, and went through all the Bithron, and entered Mahanaim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.30'>And, Joab, returned from pursuing Abner, and, when he had gathered together all the people, there were missing of the servants of Davidnineteen men, and Asahel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.31'>but, the servants of David, had smitten of Benjamin, of the men of Abner,   three hundred and sixty men, had died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.2.32'>And they carried Asahel, and buried him in the grave of his father, which was in Bethlehem,and Joab and his men journeyed all the night, and had daylight in Hebron.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.3'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.1'>And the war between the house of Saul and the house of David was prolonged,and, David, waxed stronger and stronger, and, the house of Saul, became weaker and weaker.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.2'>And there were born unto David, sons, in Hebron,and it came to press thatHis firstborn was Amnon, by Ahinoam, the Jezreelitess;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.3'>And his second Chileab, by Abigail, wife of Nabal the Carmelite, And the third Absolom, son of Maachah, daughter of Talmai, king of Geshur;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.4'>And the fourth Adonijah, son of Higgith,And the fifth Shephatiah, son of Abital;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.5'>And the sixth Ithream, by Eglah wife of David. These, were born unto David, in Hebron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.6'>And it came to pass, while the war continued between the house of Saul and the house of David, that, Abner, shewed himself courageous for the house of Saul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.7'>Now, Saul, had a concubine, whose name, was Rizpah daughter of Aiah,and   said unto Abner, Why, wentest thou in, unto my fathers concubine?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.8'>And it provoked Abner greatly, on account of the words of Ish-bosheth, and he saidAm I, the head of the dogs, that pertain unto Judah? To-day, would I deal in lovingkindness with the house of Saul thy father, towards his brethren, and towards his friends, and have not delivered thee into the hand of David,and yet thou hast charged upon me the transgression of the woman, today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.9'>So, may God do unto Abner, and, so, may he add to him,if, as Yahweh hath sworn unto David, even so, I deal not with him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.10'>by turning over the kingdom from the house of Saul,and establishing the throne of David, over Israel and over Judah, from Dan, even unto Beer-sheba.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.11'>And he could no further answer Abner, a word,because he feared him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.12'>So Abner sent messengers unto David, on the spot, sayingWhose, is the land? Saying   Solemnise thy covenant with me; and lo! my hand, shall be with thee, to bring round unto thee, all Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.13'>And he saidGood! I, will solemnise with thee a covenant,but, one thing, must I ask of thee, sayingThou shalt not see my face, except thou have brought in Michal, Sauls daughter, when thou comest to see my face.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.14'>And David sent messengers unto Ish-bosheth son of Saul, saying,Give up my wife, Michal, whom I espoused to myself, for a hundred foreskins of Philistines.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.15'>So Ish-bosheth sent and took her from her husband,from Paltiel, son of Laish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.16'>And her husband went along with her, weeping as he went behind her, as far as Behurim,when Abner said unto himGo, return. And he returned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.17'>Then had Abner, speech, with the elders of Israel, saying,In times past, ye were seeking David, to be king over you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.18'>Now, therefore, act,for Yahweh, spake unto David, saying, By the hand of David my servant, will I save my people Israel, out of the hand of the Philistines, and out of the hand of all their enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.19'>And Abner also spake in the ears of Benjamin, and Abner also went to speak in the ears of David, in Hebron, all that was pleasing in the eyes of Israel, and in the eyes of all the house of Benjamin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.20'>So, when Abner came in unto David, in Hebron, and, with him, twenty men, David made, for Abner, and for the men who were with him, a banquet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.21'>Then said Abner unto DavidI will verily arise and go, and gather together unto my lord the king, all Israelthat they may solemnise with thee a covenant, so shalt thou reign over all that thy soul desireth. And David let Abner go, and he departed in peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.22'>And lo! the servants of David, and Joab, came in from a raid, and, great spoil, brought they in with them; but, Abner, was not with David in Hebron, for he had let him go, and he had departed in peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.23'>When, Joab, and all the host that was with him, had come in, then told they Joab, saying, Abner son of Ner hath been in unto the king, and he hath let him go, and he hath departed in peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.24'>Then Joab came in unto the king, and saidWhat hast thou done? Lo! Abner came in unto thee. Wherefore is it that thou didst let him go, so that he is clean departed?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.25'>Thou knowest Abner son of Ner, that, to deceive thee, he came,and to take knowledge of thy going out, and thy coming in, and to take knowledge of all that thou art doing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.26'>And, when Joab had come out from David, he sent messengers after Abner, and brought him back from the well of Sirah,but, David, knew it not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.27'>So Abner returned to Hebron, and Joab took him aside into the midst of the gate, to speak with him quietly,and then smote him there, in the belly, that he died, for the blood of Asahel the brother of Joab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.28'>And, when David heard of it, after that, he saidGuiltless, am I and my kingdom before Yahweh, unto times age-abiding,of the blood of Abner son of Ner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.29'>Let it be hurled upon the head of Joab, and against all his fathers house,and let there not fail from the house of Joabone that hath an issue, or a leper, or one that leaneth on a crutch, or that falleth by the sword, or that lacketh bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.30'>Thus, Joab and Abishai his brother, slew Abner,because he had caused the death of Asahel their brother, in Gibeon, in the battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.31'>And David said unto Joab, and unto all the people who were with him,Rend your clothes, and gird you with sackcloth, and lament aloud before Abner. And, King David himself, was following the bier.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.32'>And they buried Abner in Hebron,and the king lifted up his voice and wept, at the grave of Abner, and all the people wept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.33'>And the king addressed his dirge unto Abner, and said,As a base man dieth, should Abner have died?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.34'>Thy hands, were not bound, And, thy feet, near to fetters, were not brought, As one falleth before assassins, so didst thou fall! And again all the people wept over him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.35'>And, when all the people came near to get David to eat bread, while yet it was day, David sware, sayingSo, let God do to me, and, so, let him add, if, before the sun go in, I taste bread, or anything else.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.36'>And, all the people, took note of it, and it was noble in their eyes,as, all that the king did, was, in the eyes of all the people, noble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.37'>So then all the people, and all Israel, took note, that day, that it was not of the king, to cause the death of Abner son of Ner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.38'>And the king said unto his servants,Will ye not take note that, a prince and a great man, hath fallen this day, in Israel?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.3.39'>And, I myself, this day, am weak, though anointed king, but, these men, the sons of Zeruiah, are more severe than I: Yahweh repay, the doer of wickedness, according to his wickedness.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.4'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.4.1'>Now, when Ish-bosheth son of Saul heard that Abner had died in Hebron, his hands became feeble,and, all Israel, were dismayed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.4.2'>And two men, captains of bands, pertained to Ish-bosheth son of Saulthe name of the one, was Baanah, and, the name of the other, Rechabsons of Rimmon the Beerothite, of the sons of Benjamin,for, even Beeroth, used to be reckoned unto Benjamin;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.4.3'>and the Beerothites fled to Gittaim,and have been sojourners there, until this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.4.4'>And, Jonathan, son of Saul, had a son, lame of his feet,five years old, was he, when tidings came in of Saul and Jonathan from Jezreel, so his nurse took him up, and fled, and it came to pass, when she started up to flee, that he fell and was lamed, and, his name, was, Mephibosheth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.4.5'>So then the sons of Rimmon the Beerothite, Rechab and Baanah, took their journey and came in, about the heat of the day, unto the house of Ish-bosheth,when, he, was lying on his noonday couch;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.4.6'>and, thither, entered they as fro as the middle of the house, to fetch wheat, and they smote him in the belly,and, Rechab and Baanah his brother, escaped.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.4.7'>Thus they entered the house when, he, was lying on his bed, in his sleeping-chamber, and smote him, and slew him, and beheaded him,and took his head, and journeyed by way of the waste plain all the night;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.4.8'>and brought in the head of Ish-bosheth unto David, at Hebron, and said unto the king, Lo! the head of Ish-bosheth son of Saul, thine enemy, who sought thy life: so hath Yahweh given to my lord the king, avengement this day, on Saul and on his seed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.4.9'>Then David responded to Rechab and Baanah his brother, sons of Rimmon the Beerothite, and said unto them,By the life of Yahweh, who hath redeemed my soul out of all distress,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.4.10'>when he that brought tidings to me, saying, Lo! Saul is dead, though, he, was as one that bringeth good tidings, in his own eyes, yet I seized him, and slew him in Ziklag,which was how I gave him reward for his tidings:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.4.11'>how much more, when, lawless men, have slain a righteous person, in his own house, upon his bed? Now, therefore, must I not require his blood at your hands, and so consume you, out of the earth?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.4.12'>David therefore commanded the young men, and they slew them, and cut off their hands, and their feet, and hanged them up over the pool, in Hebron,but, the head of Ish-bosheth, took they, and buried in the grave of Abner, in Hebron.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.5'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.1'>Then came all the tribes of Israel unto David, in Hebron,and spake, sayingBehold us! thy bone and thy flesh, we are.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.2'>Also, in time past, when Saul was king over us, thou, wast he that led out and brought in, Israel,and Yahweh said to theeThou, shalt be shepherd unto my people, Israel, and, thou, shalt become leader over Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.3'>So all the elders of Israel came unto the king, in Hebron, and King David solemnised to them a covenant in Hebron, before Yahweh, and they anointed David to be king over Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.4'>Thirty years old, was David when he began to reign,forty years, he reigned:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.5'>in Hebron, reigned he over Judah, seven years, and six months,and, in Jerusalem, reigned he thirty and three years, over all Israel and Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.6'>Then went the king and his men, to Jerusalem, against the Jebusites, inhabiting the land,and they spake to David, sayingThou canst not come in hither, unless thou take away the blind and lameThinking, David will not come in hither.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.7'>So then David captured the citadel of Zion,the same, is the city of David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.8'>And David said, on that dayWhosoever is smiting the Jebusites, then let him reach as far as the aqueduct. But, as for the lame and the blind, they were the hated of Davids soul,for which cause, they kept on saying, Blind and lame! he will not enter the place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.9'>So then David dwelt in the citadel, and called it, The City of David,and David built round about, from Millo and inwards.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.10'>And David went on and on waxing great,Yahweh, God of hosts, being with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.11'>Then Hiram, king of Tyre, sent messengers unto David, with cedar-wood, and carpenters, and masons, and they built a house for David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.12'>So David perceived that Yahweh had established him to be king over Israel,and that he had exalted his kingdom, for the sake of his people Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.13'>And David took him yet more concubines and wives, out of Jerusalem, after he had come from Hebron, and there were, yet further, born unto David, sons and daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.14'>Now, these, are the names of the sons who were born unto him in Jerusalem,Shammua and Shobab, and Nathan, and Solomon;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.15'>and Ibhar and Elishua and Nepheg and Yaphia;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.16'>and Elishama and Eliada, and Eliphalet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.17'>And, when the Philistine heard that they had anointed David to be king over Israel, then came up all the Philistines to seek to secure David, and David heard of it, and went down into the citadel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.18'>Now, the Philistines, had come,and had spread themselves out in the vale of Rephaim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.19'>So then David enquired of Yahweh, saying,Shall I go up against the Philistines? Wilt thou deliver them into my hand? And Yahweh said unto DavidGo up; for I, will surely deliver, the Philistines into thy hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.20'>And David entered Baal-perazim, and David smote them there, and saidYahweh hath broken forth upon mine enemies, before me, like a breaking forth of waters. For this cause, called he the name of that place, Baal-perazim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.21'>And they left their images there,and David and his men took them away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.22'>And, yet again, did the Philistines come up, and they spread themselves out in the vale of Rephaim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.23'>So David enquired of Yahweh, and he saidThou shalt not go up,Get round behind them, and come in upon them, over against the mulberry-trees.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.24'>And it shall be, when thou shalt hear a sound of marching in the tops of the mulberry-trees, then, shalt thou act with decision,for, then, will Yahweh have gone forth before thee, to smite the host of the Philistines.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.5.25'>And David did so, as Yahweh had commanded him,and smote the Philistines, from Gibeon until thou enterest Gezer.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.6'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.1'>And David, once more, gathered together all the choice young men in Israel, thirty thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.2'>Then David, and all the people that were with him, arose and went beyond Baale Judah,to bring up from thence, the ark of God, the name whereof is called by the name of Yahweh of hosts, who inhabiteth the cherubim thereupon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.3'>So they carried the ark of God in a new waggon, and brought it out of the house of Abinadab, who was in Gibeah,and, Uzza and Ahio, sons of Abinadab, were driving the new waggon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.4'>So they brought it out of the house of Abinadab, which was in Gibeah, with the ark of God,and, Ahio, was going before the ark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.5'>And, David and all the house of Israel, were dancing for joy before Yahweh, with all boldness and with songs,and with lyres, and with harps, and with timbrels, and with sistrums, and with cymbals.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.6'>And, when they came as far as the threshing-floor of Nachon, Uzzah thrust forth his hand unto the ark of God, and took hold of it, for the oxen were restive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.7'>Then was kindled the anger of Yahweh, against Uzzah, and God smote him there, for the error,so that he died there, by the ark of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.8'>And it was a sadness unto David, for that Yahweh had broken in with a breach against Uzzah,therefore called he that place, Perez-uzzah   until this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.9'>And David was afraid of Yahweh, on that day,and said, How can the ark of Yahweh come unto me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.10'>So David would not remove unto him the ark of Yahweh, unto the city of David,but David took it aside to the house of Obed-edom, the Gittite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.11'>And the ark of Yahweh abode in the house of Obed-edom the Gittite, three months,and Yahweh blessed Obed -edom, and all his household.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.12'>And it was told King David, saying, Yahweh hath blessed the household of Obed-edom, and all that he hath, because of the ark of God. David therefore went and brought up the ark of God, out of the house of Obed-edom, unto the city of David, with rejoicing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.13'>And so it was that, when they who bare the ark of Yahweh had stepped forward six paces, he sacrificed an ox and a heifer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.14'>And, David, was dancing with all boldness before Yahweh,David, being girt with an ephod of linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.15'>So, David and all the house of Israel, were bringing up the ark of Yahweh,with triumphant shoutings, and with the sound of a horn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.16'>Now it so came about that, when the ark of Yahweh entered the city of David, Michal Sauls daughter, looked out through the window, and saw King David, leaping and dancing before Yahweh, and she despised him, in her heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.17'>So they brought in the ark of Yahweh, and set it in its place, in the midst of the tent which David had stretched out for it,and David caused to go up ascending-sacrifices before Yahweh, and peace-offerings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.18'>And, when David had finished offering up the ascending-sacrifice and the peace-offerings, he blessed the people in the name of Yahweh of hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.19'>And he apportioned to all the people, to all the multitude of Israel, both to men and to womento every one, a loaf of bread, and a sweet drink, and a raisin-cake,and all the people went their way, every one unto his own house;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.20'>and David returned, to bless his household. Then came forth Michal Sauls daughter to meet David, and saidHow honoured, to-day, was the king of Israel in disrobing himself to-day, in the sight of the handmaids of his servants, as one of the low people, might disrobe himself?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.21'>And David said unto Michal, Before Yahweh, I will dance,blessed, be Yahweh, who made choice of me above thy father, and above all his house, putting me in charge as leader over the people of Yahweh, over Israel,therefore will I dance before Yahweh;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.22'>and will make myself, yet more, lightly esteemed that this, and become lowly in mine own eyes,nevertheless, with the handmaids of whom thou hast spoken, with them, shall I be honoured.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.6.23'>Therefore, Michal Sauls daughter, had no child,unto the day of her death.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.7'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.1'>And it came to pass, when the king had taken up his abode in his house,and Yahweh had given him rest round about, from all his enemies,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.2'>that the king said unto Nathan the prophet, See, I pray theeI, have my abode in a house, of cedar, but, the ark of God, abideth in, the midst, of curtains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.3'>And Nathan said unto the king, All that is in thy heart, godo,for Yahweh is with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.4'>But so it was, in that night, that the word of Yahweh came unto Nathan, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.5'>Go and say unto my servantunto David: Thus, saith Yahweh,Shalt, thou, build me a house, for me to dwell in;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.6'>seeing that I have not dwelt in a house, since the day that I brought up the sons of Israel out of Egypt, even unto this day,but have been wandering in a tent as my habitation?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.7'>Wheresoever I have wandered with any of the sons of Israel, spake I ever, a word, with any one of the tribes of Israel, whom I charged to shepherd my people Israel, saying,Wherefore have ye not built me a house, of cedar?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.8'>Now, therefore, thus, shalt thou say unto my servant, unto David: Thus, saith Yahweh of hosts, I myself, took thee away from the pasture, from after the flock,to become leader over my people, over Israel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.9'>and was with thee, whithersoever thou didst go, and have cut off all thine enemies, from before thee,and will make thee a name, like the name of the great ones who are in the earth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.10'>and will appoint a place for my people, for Israel, and will plant them, and they shall inhabit their place, and be unsettled no more,neither shall the sons of perversity again humiliate them, as at first;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.11'>even from the day when I put judges in charge over my people Israel, thus will I give thee rest from all thine enemies. And Yahweh must tell thee that, a house, will Yahweh make for thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.12'>And it shall be that, when thy days shall be fulfilled, and thou shalt sleep with thy fathers, then will I raise up thy seed after thee, which proceedeth from thine own body,and I will establish his kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.13'>He, shall build a house for my name,and I will establish his kingly throne unto times age-abiding:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.14'>I, will become his father, And, he, shall become my son: If he commit iniquity, then will I correct him, with the rod of men, and with the stripes of the sons of men;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.15'>But, my lovingkindness, shall not depart from him,as I caused it to depart from Saul, whom I caused to depart from before thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.16'>So shall thy house and thy kingdom be made steadfast unto times age-abiding, before thee,thy throne, shall be established unto times age-abiding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.17'>According to all these words, and according to all this vision, so, spake Nathan unto David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.18'>Then entered King David, and tarried before Yahweh,and saidWho am, I, My Lord, Yahweh, and what is my house, that thou hast brought me, hitherto;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.19'>and hast yet further made this seem little in thine eyes, My Lord, Yahweh, in that thou hast spoken, even of the house, of thy servant, for a great while to come? This, then is the law of manhood, O My Lord, Yahweh!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.20'>What more, then, can David yet further speak unto thee,seeing that, thou thyself knowest thy servant, O My Lord Yahweh?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.21'>For the sake of thine own word, and according to thine own heart, hast thou done all this great thing,making it known unto thy servant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.22'>For this cause, hast thou magnified thyself, O Yahweh Elohim,for there is none like unto, thee, yea there is no God besides thee, according to all that we have heard with our ears.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.23'>Who, then, is like thy people, like Israel, a nation alone in the earth? whom God went to redeem for himself as a people, so to make himself a name, and to do for you the great deed, fearful things also for thy land, to make way for thy people, whom thou hadst redeemed for thyself, out of Egypt,   nations and their gods;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.24'>and hast established for thyself thy people Israelfor thyself as a people, unto times age-abiding,thou thyself, also, O Yahweh, becoming their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.25'>Now, therefore, O Yahweh Elohim, the word which thou hast spoken concerning thy servant, and concerning his house, confirm thou, unto times age-abiding,and do, as thou hast spoken:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.26'>that thy name may be age-abidingly magnified, saying, Yahweh of hosts, is God over Israel, and so, the house of thy servant David, be established before thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.27'>For, thou, O Yahweh of hosts, God of Israel, hast unveiled the ear of thy servant, sayingA house, will I build for thee. For this cause, hath thy servant found in his heart, to pray unto thee, this prayer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.28'>Now, therefore, O My Lord, Yahweh, thou, art God, and, thy words, shall prove true,therefore hast thou spoken unto thy servant this goodness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.7.29'>Now, therefore, be pleased to bless the house of thy servant, that it may continue age-abidingly before thee,for, thou, O My Lord, Yahweh, hast spoken, therefore, with thine own blessing, shall the house of thy servant be age-abidingly blessed.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.8'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.1'>And it came to pass, after this, that David smote the Philistines, and subdued them,and David took the bridle of the metropolis, out of the hand of the Philistines.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.2'>And he smote Moab, and measured them with the line casting, them down to the ground, and be measured with two lines to put to death, and with one full line to keep alive,so the Moabites became Davids, as servants, bringing gifts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.3'>And David smote Hadadezer son of Rehob, king of Zobah,when he went to lay his hand on the River Euphrates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.4'>And David captured from him, a thousand and seven hundred horsemen, and twenty thousand footmen,and David destroyed all the chariots, but reserved of them, a hundred chariots.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.5'>And, when the Syrians of Damascus came to help Hadadezer, king of Zobah, David smote of the Syrians, twenty-two thousand men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.6'>Then David put garrisons in Syria of Damascus, and the Syrians became Davids, as servants bringing gifts,and so Yahweh gave victory unto David, whithersoever he went.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.7'>And David took the shields of gold which had come to the servants of Hadadezer,and brought them to Jerusalem;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.8'>also, from Betah and from Berothai, cities of Hadadezer, did King David take bronze, exceeding much.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.9'>And, when Tou king of Hamath heard that David had smitten all the forces of Hadadezer,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.10'>then Tou sent Hadoram his son unto King David, to ask after his welfare, and to bless him, because he had fought against Hadadezer and had smitten him, for Hadadezer had had wars with Tou,and, in his hand, were vessels of silver, and vessels of gold, and vessels of bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.11'>Them also, did King David hallow unto Yahweh,with the silver and the gold which he had hallowed from all the nations which he had subdued:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.12'>from Syria, and from Moab, and from the sons of Ammon, and from the Philistines, and from Amalek,and from the spoil of Hadadezer son of Rehob, king of Zobah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.13'>And David made a name, when he returned from his smiting of the Syrians in the valley of salt,eighteen thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.14'>And he put, in Edom, garrisons, throughout all Edom, put be garrisons, and so it was that all Edom became servants unto David,and Yahweh gave victory unto David, whithersoever he went.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.15'>And David reigned over all Israel,and so it was that David used to execute justice and righteousness for all his people;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.16'>and, Joab, son of Zeruiah, was over the army,and, Jehoshaphat, son of Ahilud, was remembrancer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.17'>And, Zadok, son of Ahitub, and Abimelech, son of Abiathar, were priests,and, Seraiah, was scribe;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.8.18'>and, Benaiah, son of Jehoiadah, was over the Cherethites and the Pelethites,and, the sons of David, became, chief rulers.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.9'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.9.1'>And David said, Is there yet one left unto the house of Saul,that I may show him lovingkindness, for the sake of, Jonathan?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.9.2'>Now, unto the house of Saul, belonged a servant, whose name, was Ziba, and, when they had called him unto David, the king said unto himArt, thou, Ziba? And he saidThy servant!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.9.3'>Then said the kingIs there never a man remaining unto the house of Saul, that I may show him the lovingkindness of God? And Ziba said unto the king, There remaineth a son unto Jonathan, lame in his feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.9.4'>And the king said to him, Where is he? And Ziba said unto the king, Lo! he, is in the house of Machir son of Ammiel, in Lo-debar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.9.5'>Then sent King David,and fetched him out of the house of Machir son of Ammiel, from Lo-debar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.9.6'>Now, when Mephibosheth, son of Jonathan, son of Saul, came in unto David, he fell on his face and did homage. And David said, Mephibosheth? And he said, Lo! thy servant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.9.7'>And David said to himDo not fear, for I will, indeed shew, thee lovingkindness, for the sake of Jonathan thy father, and will restore unto thee all the land of Saul thy father,but, thou thyself, shall eat bread at my table, continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.9.8'>And he did homage, and saidWhat is thy servant,that thou hast turned towards such a dead dog as I?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.9.9'>Then the king called for Ziba, Sauls servant, and said unto him,All that pertained unto Saul and unto all his house, have I given unto the son of thy lord:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.9.10'>therefore shalt thou till for him the ground, thou, and thy sons, and thy servants, and shalt bring in, so that thy lords son may have bread to eat, but, Mephibosheth, thy lords son, shall continually eat bread at my table. Now, Ziba, had fifteen sons, and twenty servants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.9.11'>Then said Ziba unto the king, According to all that my lord the king shall command his servant, so, will thy servant do,but, Mephibosheth, is to eat at the table of David, as one of the sons of the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.9.12'>Now, Mephibosheth, had a little son, whose name, was Micha. And, all that dwelt in the house of Ziba, were servants unto Mephibosheth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.9.13'>So, Mephibosheth, dwelt in Jerusalem, for, at the table of the king, continually, had he to eat,he being lame, in both his feet.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.10'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.1'>And it came to pass, after this, that the king of the sons of Ammon died,and that Hanun his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.2'>Then said DavidI will shew lovingkindness unto Hanun son of Nahash, as his father shewed, unto me, lovingkindness. So David sent to comfort him, by the hand of his servants, as to his father,and the servants of David came into the land of the sons of Ammon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.3'>Then said the rulers of the sons of Ammon unto Hanun their lordIs David honouring thy father, in thine eyes, that he hath sent unto thee comforters? Is it not, for the sake of exploring the city, and spying it out, and overthrowing it, that David hath sent his servants unto thee?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.4'>Wherefore Hanun took Davids servants, and shaved off half their beards, and cut off their upper garments in the middle, as far as their buttocks,and let them go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.5'>And, when they told David, he sent to meet them, because the men were greatly ashamed,and the king saidTarry at Jericho, until your beards be grown, then shall ye return.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.6'>And, when the sons of Ammon saw that they had made themselves odious with David, the sons of Ammon sent and hired the Syrians of Beth-rehob, and the Syrians of Zobatwenty thousand footmen, and of king Maacaha thousand men, and men of Tobtwelve thousand men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.7'>And, when David heard of it, he sent Joab and all the army of heroes,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.8'>And the sons of Ammon came out, and set in array for battle, at the entrance of the gate,whereas, the Syrians of Zoba, and of Rehob, and the men of Tob and of Maacah, were by themselves, in the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.9'>And, when Joab saw that the front of the battle was towards him, before and behind, he chose out of all the chosen men of Israel, and set them in array against the Syrians;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.10'>while, the rest of the people, he delivered into the hand of Abishai his brother,and set   in array against the sons of Ammon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.11'>And he saidIf the Syrians be too strong for me, then shalt thou become my deliverance,but, if, the sons of Ammon, be too strong for thee, then will I come with deliverance to thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.12'>Be strong, and let us put forth our strength, for the sake of our people, and for the sake of the cities of our God,and, Yahweh, do what is good in his own eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.13'>And Joab drew nigh, and the people that were with him, to fight against the Syrians,and they fled before him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.14'>And, when, the sons of Ammon, saw that the Syrians had fled, then fled they before Abishai, and entered the city,so Joab returned from the sons of Ammon, and entered Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.15'>And, when the Syrians saw that they were defeated before Israel, they gathered themselves together;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.16'>and Hadadezer sent and brought out the Syrians that were beyond the River, and they entered Helam,Shobach the prince of the host of Hadadezer being before them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.17'>And, when it was told David, he gathered together all Israel, and passed over the Jordan, and entered Helam,and the Syrians set themselves in array to meet David, and fought with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.18'>Then fled the Syrians before Israel, and David slew of the Syrians seven hundred chariots, and forty thousand horsemen,Shobach also, prince of their host, smote he, that he died, there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.10.19'>And, when all the kings who were servants to Hadadezer saw that they were defeated before Israel, they made peace with Israel, and served them,and the Syrians feared to give help any more unto the sons of Ammon.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.11'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.1'>And it came to pass, at the return of the year, at the time of the going forth of kings, that David sent Joab, and his servants with him, and all Israel, and they destroyed the sons of Ammon, and laid siege to Rabbah,but, David, was remaining in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.2'>And it came to pass that, at eventide, David arose from his couch, and walked to and fro on the roof of the kings house, when, from the roof, he saw a woman bathing herself,the woman being exceeding beautiful to look upon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.3'>And David sent and enquired after the woman,and one saidIs not, this, Bath-sheba, daughter of Eliam, wife of Uriah the Hittite?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.4'>And David sent messengers, and fetched her, and she came in unto him, and he lay with her, she having purified herself from her uncleanness,and she returned unto her own house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.5'>And the woman, having conceived, sent and told David, and said, I am with child.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.6'>Then sent David unto Joab, Send unto me Uriah the Hittite. So Joab sent Uriah unto David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.7'>And, when Uriah had come in unto him, David askedhow Joab prospered, and how the people prospered, and how the war prospered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.8'>Then said David unto Uriah, Go down unto thy house, and bathe thy feet. And, when Uriah went out of the house of the king, there followed him, a present from the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.9'>But Uriah slept at the entrance of the kings house, with all the servants of his lord,and went not down unto his own house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.10'>And it was told David, saying, Uriah went not down, unto his own house. So David said unto UriahWas it not, from a journey, thou didst come? why, then, hast thou not been down unto thine own house?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.11'>And Uriah said unto DavidThe ark, and Israel and Judah, are dwelling in huts and, my lord Joab, and the servants of my lord, on the face of the field, are encamped, Was, I, then, to enter my own house, to eat and to drink and to lie with my wife? By thy life, yea by the life of thy soul, I could not do this thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.12'>Then said David unto UriahAbide here to-day also, and, to-morrow, will I let thee go. So Uriah abode in Jerusalem that day, and the morrow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.13'>And David called him, and he did eat before him, and drank, and he made him drunk,and he went forth in the evening to lie down on his bed, with the servants of his lord, but, unto his own house, went he not down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.14'>And so it was, in the morning, that David wrote a letter unto Joab,and sent it by the hand of Uriah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.15'>and he wrote in the letter, saying,Set ye Uriah in the forefront of the hottest battle, and retire ye from him, that he be smitten and die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.16'>So it came to pass, when Joab was laying siege to the city, that he put Uriah in the place where he knew that the men of valour, were.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.17'>And forth sallied the men of the city, and fought with Joab, and there fell some of the people, of the servants of David,then died also, Uriah the Hittite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.18'>So Joab sent and told David all the news of the battle;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.19'>and he charged the messenger saying,When thou hast ended all the news of the battle, in speaking unto the king,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.20'>then shall it be, if the kings anger arise, and he say unto thee, Why came ye near unto the city, to fight? Knew ye not, that they would shoot from off the wall?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.21'>Who smote Abimelech son of Jerubbaal? Did not, a woman, cast on him an upper millstone from off the wall, that he died, in Thebez? Wherefore came ye near unto the wall? Then shalt thou sayMoreover, thy servant, Uriah the Hittite, died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.22'>And the messenger went his way,and came in, and told David, all that Joab had sent him   .</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.23'>And the messenger said unto David, The men were too strong for us, and sallied forth against us, in the field,so we were drawn against them as far as the opening of the gate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.24'>Then did the archers shoot upon thy servants, from off the wall, and there died some of the servants of the king,moreover also, thy servant, Uriah the Hittite, died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.25'>Then said David unto the messengerThus, shalt thou say unto Joab,Let not this thing be grievous in thine eyes, for, now this one, and then that one, doth the sword devour,make hot thy battle against the city, and overthrow it; Thus embolden thou him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.26'>And, when Uriahs wife heard that Uriah her husband was dead, she made loud lamentation over her lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.11.27'>And, when the time of mourning had passed, David sent and received her into his house, and she became his wife, and bare him a son. But the thing which David had done was wicked in the eyes of Yahweh.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.12'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.1'>So then Yahweh sent Nathan the prophet unto David,who therefore came unto him and said to himTwo men, there were in a certain city, the one, rich, and, the other, poor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.2'>The, rich, man had flocks and herds exceeding many;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.3'>whereas the, poor, man had, nothing,save one little lamb, which he had made his own, and sustained, and it had grown up with him and with his children, all together,of his own morsel, used it to eat, and, out of his own cup, used it to drink, and, in his own bosom, used it to lie, and it was to him, as a daughter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.4'>Now there came a traveller to the rich man, but he thought it a pity to take of his own flock, or his own herd, to make ready for the wayfarer who had come to him,so he took the lamb of his poor neighbour, and made ready for the man who had come to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.5'>Then was kindled the anger of David against the man, fiercely,and he said unto Nathan, By the life of Yahweh, doomed to death, is the man that hath done this;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.6'>and, the lamb, shall he pay back sevenfold,because he did this thing, and, for that he had no pity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.7'>Then said Nathan unto David: Thou, art the man! Thus, saith Yahweh, God of IsraelI, anointed thee to be king over Israel, and, I, delivered thee out of the hand of Saul;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.8'>and gave unto thee the household of thy lord, and the wives of thy lord, into thy bosom, and gave unto thee the house of Israel and Judah. And, if this had been too little, I could have further given thee more and more of such things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.9'>Wherefore, hast thou despised the word of Yahweh, by doing that which is wicked in mine eyes? Uriah the Hittite, hast thou smitten with the sword, and, his wife, hast thou taken to thyself to wife, yea, him, hast thou slain with the sword of the sons of Ammon!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.10'>Now, therefore, the sword shall not depart from thy house, unto age-abiding times,because thou hast despised me, and taken the wife of Uriah the Hittite to be thy wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.11'>Thus, saith Yahweh,Behold me! raising up over thee calamity out of thine own household, and I will take thy wives, before thine eyes, and give unto thy neighbour, and he will lie with thy wives, in the eyes of this sun.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.12'>For, thou, didst it, in secret,but, I, will do this thing, before all Israel, and before the sun.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.13'>And David said unto Nathan, I have sinned against Yahweh. Then said Nathan unto David,Yahweh also, hath put away thy sin, thou shalt not die!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.14'>Nevertheless, because thou hast greatly blasphemed Yahweh, by this thing, the very son that is born to thee, shall, die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.15'>And Nathan departed unto his own house,and Yahweh struck the child that the wife of Uriah had borne unto David, and it fell sick.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.16'>David therefore earnestly sought God in behalf of the boy,and David kept a fast, and used to go in and pass the night, and lie upon the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.17'>And the elders of his house stood up over him, to raise him from the ground,but he would not, neither would he eat food with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.18'>And it came to pass, on the seventh day, that the child died,but the servants of David feared to tell him that the child was dead, for said theyLo! while the child was living, we spake unto him, and he hearkened not unto our voice, how then can we say unto him, The child is dead, and so he do   harm?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.19'>But, when David saw that his servants were whispering among themselves, then understood David that the child was dead,and David said unto his servantsIs the child, dead? And they answeredDead!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.20'>Then David arose from the ground, and bathed and anointed, and changed his apparel, and, entering into the house of Yahweh, bowed himself down,then came he into his own house, and asked, and they set before him food, and he did eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.21'>Then said his servants unto him, What is this thing that thou hast done? For the childs sake, while living, thou didst fast and weep, but, as soon as the child was dead, thou didst arise and eat food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.22'>And he said,While yet the child lived, I fasted, and wept,for I saidWho knoweth whether Yahweh may not grant me favour, and the child live?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.23'>But, now, that he is dead, wherefore should I go on fasting? can I bring him back again? I am going unto him, but, he, will not come back unto me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.24'>And David consoled Bath-sheba his wife, and went in unto her, and lay with her,and she bare a son, and called his name, Solomon, and Yahweh loved him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.25'>And he sent by the hand of Nathan the prophet, and called his name Jedidiah, for Yahwehs sake. \fs15</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.26'>And Joab fought against Rabbah, of the sons of Ammon,and captured the royal city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.27'>Then Joab sent messengers unto David,and saidI have fought against Rabbah, I have also captured the city of the waters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.28'>Now, therefore, gather thou together the rest of the people, and encamp against the city, and capture it,lest, I, capture the city, and it be called by my name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.29'>So David gathered together all the people, and went to Rabbah,and fought against it, and captured it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.30'>Then took he the crown of Milcom from off his head, the weight thereof, being a talent of gold, with the precious stones, and it remained on the head of David,the spoil of the city also, brought he forth in great abundance;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.12.31'>the people also that were therein, brought he forth, and put them to the saw, and to threshing sledges of iron, and to axes of iron, and made them pass through the brickkiln, and thus used he to do unto all the cities of the sons of Ammon. And David and all the people returned unto Jerusalem.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.13'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.1'>And it came to pass, after this, that, Absolom, son of David, having a beautiful sister, whose name, was Tamar, Amnon son of David loved her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.2'>And it so troubled Amnon, that he made himself ill on account of Tamar his sister, for, a virgin, was she, and it was monstrous in Amnons own eyes, to do, anything, unto her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.3'>But, Amnon, had a friend, whose name, was Jonadab, son of Shimeah, Davids brother,and, Jonadab, was a very cunning man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.4'>So he said to him,Why art thou looking so wretcheda kings son toomorning by morning? Wilt thou not tell me? And Amnon said to him, With Tamar, my brother Absoloms sister, am I in love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.5'>And Jonadab said unto him: Take to thy bed, and feign thyself ill,and, when thy father cometh in to see thee, then shalt thou say unto himI pray thee, let Tamar my sister come, that she may give me food, and let her prepare, before mine eyes, some delicacy, to the end that I may see   , and so eat at her hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.6'>So Amnon took to his bed, and feigned himself ill,and, when the king came in to see him, Amnon said unto the kingI pray thee, let Tamar my sister come, and make ready before mine eyes a couple of cakes, that I may eat at her hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.7'>So David sent unto Tamar, in the housesaying,Come, I pray thee, to the house of Amnon thy brother, and prepare him enticing food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.8'>And Tamar went to the house of Amnon her brother, he having taken to his bed,and took dough and kneaded it, and folded it before his eyes, and baked the cakes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.9'>Then took she the pan and put them out before him, but he refused to eat. And Amnon saidHave forth every one from me. And they went out every one from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.10'>Then said Amnon unto TamarBring the food into the chamber, that I may eat out of thine own hand. So Tamar took the cakes which she had made, and brought them in to Amnon her brother, in the chamber.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.11'>And, when she brought them unto him to eat, he took hold of her, and said to her, Come lie with me, my sister!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.12'>But she said to himNay! my brother, do not force me, for it should not be done so in Israel,do not commit this vileness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.13'>And, I,whither could I take my reproach? Thou, too, wouldest be as one of the vile fellows, in Israel. Now, therefore, speak, I pray thee, unto the king, for he would not withhold me from thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.14'>But he would not hearken unto her voice,and, being stronger than she, forced her, and lay with her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.15'>Then did Amnon hate her with a very great hatred, for, greater, was the hatred wherewith he hated her, than the love wherewith he had loved her,so Amnon said to herRisebegone!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.16'>But she said to himNo occasion for this greater wrong, after what thou hast done with me, to put me away! Nevertheless he would not hearken unto her;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.17'>but called his young man who waited on him, and saidI pray you, put forth this woman from me, outside,and bolt the door after her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.18'>Now she had upon her a long tunic, for, so, used kings daughters to apparel themselves, when they were virgins, in robes. And his attendant took her forth, outside, and bolted the door, after her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.19'>And Tamar put ashes upon her head, and, the long tunic that was upon her, she rent,and put her hand upon her head, and went her way, crying out as she went.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.20'>And Absolom her brother said unto herHath, Amnon thy brother, been with thee? Now, therefore, my sister, hold thy peacethy brother, he is, do not lay to thy heart, this thing. But Tamar remained, and was desolate in the house of Absolom her brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.21'>And, King David, heard all these things,and it angered him greatly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.22'>And Absolom spake not with Amnon, either bad or good,though Absolom hated Amnon, because he had forced Tamar his sister.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.23'>And it came to pass, after two years of days, that Absolom had, sheepshearers in Baal-hazor, which is beside Ephron,and Absolom invited all the kings sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.24'>Absolom came also unto the king, and said, See, I pray thee, thy servant hath, sheepshearers,I pray thee, let the king and his servants go with thy servant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.25'>And the king said unto AbsolomNay! my son, do not, I pray thee, let us all go, lest we be burdensome upon thee. And, though he urged him, he would not go, but blessed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.26'>Then said Absolom, If not, then, I pray thee, let Amnon my brother go with us. And the king said unto him, Wherefore should he go with thee?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.27'>And Absolom urged him,so he let Amnon and all the kings sons go with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.28'>Now Absolom had commanded his young men, sayingMark, I pray you, when the heart of Amnon is merry with wine, and I say unto youSmite ye Amnon, then shall ye put him to death, do not fear,have not, I myself, commanded you? Be bold, and show yourselves to be sons of valour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.29'>So Absoloms young men did to Amnon as Absolom had commanded. Then arose all the kings sons, and rode awayeach man on his mule, and fled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.30'>And it came to pass, while, they, were yet on the road, that, the report, reached David, saying,Absolom hath smitten all the kings sons, and there is not left of them, one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.31'>And the king arose, and rent his garments, and lay on the ground,and all his servants who stood by rent their garments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.32'>Then responded Jonadab son of Shimeah Davids brother, and saidLet not my lord say that they have put, all the young menthe kings sons, to death; for, Amnon alone, is dead; for, by the bidding of Absolom, was it appointed, from the day that he forced Tamar his sister.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.33'>Now, therefore, let not my lord the king lay to his heart such a thingto say, All the kings sons, are dead,but, Amnon alone, is dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.34'>Now Absolom had fled. And the young man that was watching lifted up his eyes and looked, and lo! much people, coming on the road behind him, on the mountain-side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.35'>So Jonadab said unto the king, Lo! the kings sons, are come,according to the word of thy servant, so hath it come to pass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.36'>And so it was, as he made an end of speaking, that lo! the kings sons, came, and lifted up their voice and wept,the king also, and all his servants, wept with an exceeding great weeping.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.37'>But, Absolom, had fled, and had taken his journey unto Talmai son of Ammihud, king of Geshur. And David the king mourned for his son continually,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.38'>But, Absolom, had fled, and had taken his journey to Geshur,and it came to pass that he was there three years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.13.39'>And the spirit of the king pined to go forth unto Absolom,for he had consoled himself over Amnon, in that he was dead.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.14'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.1'>And Joab, son of Zeruiah, perceived that the heart of the king was towards Absolom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.2'>So Joab sent to Tekoa, and fetched from thence, a wise woman,and said unto herI pray thee, feign thyself a mourner, and put on, I pray thee, mourning apparel, and do not anoint thyself with oil, but be as a woman that hath, these many days, been mourning for the dead;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.3'>so shalt thou come in unto the king, and speak unto him, after this manner. And Joab put the words in her mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.4'>And, when the woman of Tekoa came in unto the king, she fell on her face to the ground, and did homage,and saidSave, O king!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.5'>And the king said to herWhat aileth thee? And she saidOf a truth, a widow woman, am I, for my husband is dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.6'>Now, thy maidservant, had two sons, and they two strove together in the field, with none to tear them apart,so the one smote the other, and slew him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.7'>Lo! therefore, all the family hath risen up against thy maidservant, and have said: Give up him that hath smitten his brother, that we may put him to death, for the life of his brother, whom he hath slain, that we may destroy, the heir also. So will they quench my ember that is left, and make my husband without name or remainder, on the face of the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.8'>And the king said unto the womanGo to thy house, and, I, will give command concerning thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.9'>Then said the woman of Tekoa unto the king, Upon me, my lord, O king, be the iniquity, and upon the house of my father, but, the king and his throne, be guiltless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.10'>And the king said,He that speaketh unto thee, bring him in unto me, and he shall, no more, annoy thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.11'>Then said she: Let the king, I pray thee, remember Yahweh thy God; so that the blood-redeemer may not make utter ruin, and that they destroy not my son. And he saidBy the life of Yahweh, not one hair of thy son shall fall to the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.12'>Then said the woman, Pray let thy maidservant speak unto my lord the king, a word. And he saidSpeak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.13'>And the woman said, Wherefore, then, hast thou devised the like of this, for the people of God; and yet the king, in speaking this word, is verily guilty, unless the king, bring back his fugitive?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.14'>For, when we, die, we become as water poured on the ground, which cannot be gathered up again,therefore doth God not take away the life, but deviseth plans so as not to thrust out from him, a fugitive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.15'>Now, therefore,   that I have come to speak unto the king my lord this word, because the people kept putting me in fear,so thy maidservant saidDo let me, I pray you, speak unto the king! peradventure the king will fulfil the request of his handmaid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.16'>For the king can hearken, to rescue his handmaid out of the power of the man who would seek to destroy both me and my son together, out of the inheritance of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.17'>So thy maidservant said, Pray let the word of my lord the king be comforting,for, as the messenger of God, so is my lord the king, in hearing the good and the bad, Yahweh thy God, then, be with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.18'>Then responded the king, and said unto the woman, Nay, now! do not hide from me, the thing which I am about to ask thee. And the woman said, Pray let my lord the king speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.19'>Then said the king, Is, the hand of Joab, with thee, in all this? And the woman answered and saidBy the life of thy soul, my lord, O king, there is no way to the right or to the left, of anything that my lord the king hath spoken, for, thy servant Joab himself, charged me, and, himself, put, in the mouth of thy maidservant, all these words:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.20'>for the purpose of turning round the face of the matter, hath thy servant Joab done this thing,my lord being wise, as with the wisdom of a messenger of God, in knowing all that is</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.21'>Then said the king unto Joab, See, I pray thee, I a have done this thing,go thenbring back the young man, Absolom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.22'>So Joab fell with his face to the earth, and did homage, and blessed the king,and Joab saidTo-day, doth thy servant know, that I have found favour in thine eyes, my lord O king, in that the king hath fulfilled the request of thy servant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.23'>And Joab arose, and went to Geshur,and brought Absolom to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.24'>And the king saidLet him go round to his own house, and, my face, let him not see. So Absolom went round, unto his own house, and, the face of the king, saw he not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.25'>Now, like unto Absolom, was there no man handsome in all Israel, to be greatly praised,from the sole of his foot, even unto the crown of his head, there was not, in him, a blemish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.26'>And when he polled his headand it was at every years end that he used to poll it, because it was heavy upon him, therefore he used to poll ithe would weigh the hair of his head, two hundred shekels, by the royal standard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.27'>And there were born to Absolom three sons, and one daughter, whose name, was Tamar,she, was a woman beautiful to look upon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.28'>So Absolom dwelt in Jerusalem two years of days,and, the face of the king, had he not seen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.29'>Then sent Absolom unto Joab, to send him unto the king, but he would not come to him,so he sent yet a second time, but he would not come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.30'>Then said he unto his servantsSee, the allotted portion of Joab, adjoineth me, and, he, hath barley there, go, and set it on fire. So the servants of Absolom set the portion on fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.31'>Then rose Joab, and went unto Absolom, in his house,and said unto him, Wherefore, have thy servants set the portion that pertaineth to me, on fire?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.32'>And Absolom said unto JoabLo! I sent unto thee, sayingCome hither, that I may send thee unto the king, sayingWherefore, am I come from Geshur? I, might as well have yet been there. Now, therefore, let me see the face of the king, and, if there is in me iniquity, then let him put me to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.14.33'>So Joab came unto the king, and told him, and the king called for Absolom, and he came in unto the king, and bowed himself down with his face to the ground, before the king,and the king kissed Absolom.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.15'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.1'>And it came to pass, after this, that Absolom prepared him chariots and horses,and fifty men, to run before him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.2'>And Absolom used to rise up early, and take his stand beside the way of the gate,and so it waswhen any man who had a controversy would come unto the king for judgment, then Absalom called unto him, and said: Of what city, art, thou? And he said, Of one of the tribes of Israel, is thy servant. And Absolom said unto him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.3'>See! thy cause, is good and right,but, to hear it, thou hast no one, from the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.4'>And Absalom said, Oh would that I were appointed to judge in the land! that, unto me, might come every man having a complaint or a defence, then would I see him righted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.5'>Moreover, so it used to be, that, when any man came near to do him homage, he would put forth his hand, and lay hold of him, and kiss him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.6'>And Absolom did, after this manner, to all Israel who came for judgment, unto the king,so Absolom stole away the heart of the men of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.7'>And it came to pass, at the end of forty years, that Absolom said unto the kingLet me go, I pray thee, that I may pay my vow which I have vowed unto Yahweh, in Hebron;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.8'>for thy servant vowed, a vow, while I abode in Geshur in Syria, saying,If Yahweh, will but bring me back, unto Jerusalem, then will I serve Yahweh,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.9'>And the king said unto himGo and prosper! So he arose and went to Hebron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.10'>And Absolom sent spies throughout all the tribes of Israel, saying,When ye hear the sound of the horn, then shall ye say, Absolom hath become king in Hebron!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.11'>And, with Absolom, went two hundred men, out of Jerusalem, who, having been bidden, were going in their simplicity,neither knew they anything.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.12'>And Absalom sent and called Ahithophel the Gilonite, Davids counsellor, out of his city, out of Gilo, when he was offering sacrifices,and so it was that the conspiracy was strong, and, the people, went on multiplying with Absolom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.13'>Then came one bearing tidings unto David, saying,It hath come about, that the heart of the men of Israel goeth after Absolom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.14'>Then said David, to all his servants who were with him in JerusalemArise and let us flee, or we shall have no way of escape from the face of Absolom,make speed to depart, lest he make speed, and so overtake us, and bring down misfortune upon us, and smite the city with the edge of the sword.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.15'>And the kings servants said unto the king,According to all that my lord the king shall choose, here are thy servants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.16'>So the king went forth, with all his household attending him,but the king left ten women who were concubines, to keep the house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.17'>Thus then the king went forth, with all the people attending him,and they came to a stand at a place that was far off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.18'>And, all his servants, were passing on beside him, and all the Cherethites, and all the Pelethites, and, all the Gittitessix hundred men, who had accompanied him from Gath,were passing on before the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.19'>Then said the king, unto Ittai the Gittite, Wherefore shouldest, thou also, go with us? return and abide with the king, for, a stranger, art thou, moreover also, an exile, art thou from thine own country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.20'>Only yesterday, camest thou, and, today, shall I let thee wander with us, on our journey, seeing that, I, am going, whithersoever I may? Return and take back thy brethren with thee, and may Yahweh deal with thee in lovingkindness and faithfulness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.21'>But Ittai answered the king, and said,By the life of Yahweh, and by the life of my lord the king, surely, in whatsoever place, my lord the king, may be, whether for death or for life, there will, thy servant, be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.22'>Then said David unto IttaiGo, and pass on. So Ittai the Gittite passed on, with all his men, and all the little ones that were with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.23'>And, fall the land, was weeping, with a loud voice, and, all the people, were passing on,the king also, was passing on, through the torrent-bed of Kidron, and all the people were passing on over the face of the way leading to the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.24'>And lo! Zadok also, and all the Levites with him, were bearing the ark of the covenant of God, and they set down the ark of God, and Abiathar went up, until all the people had made an end of passing over out of the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.25'>Then said the king unto Zadok, Take back the ark of God into the city,if I find favour in the eyes of Yahweh, then will he bring me back, and let me see both him and his habitation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.26'>but, if thus, he say, I have no delight in thee, here I am, let him do unto me as may be good in his eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.27'>And the king said, unto Zadok the priest, Art thou not, a seer? return into the city, in peace,and Ahimaaz thine own son, and Jonathan son of Abiatharyour two sons, with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.28'>See! I, am tarrying in the waste plains of the wildernessuntil there come word from you, to tell me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.29'>So Zadok and Abiathar took back the ark of God to Jerusalem,and abode there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.30'>Now, David, was going up by the ascent of Olivet, weeping as he went up, with his head covered, himself, passing on barefoot,and all the people who were with him, covered every man his head, and went up, weeping as they went.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.31'>And, unto David, it was told, saying, Ahithophel, is among the conspirators with Absolom. And David said, Turn to foolishness, I pray thee, the counsel of Ahithophel, O Yahweh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.32'>And it came to pass, when David reached the summit, where he bowed himself down unto God, that lo! there met him, Hushai the Archite, his tunic rent, and earth upon his head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.33'>And David said unto him,If thou pass over with me, then shalt thou become unto me, a burden;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.34'>but, if, to the city, thou return, then canst thou say unto AbsolomThy servant, I, O king, will be, as, the servant of thy father, I was formerly, so will I, now, be thy servant: thus shalt thou frustrate for me the counsel of Ahithophel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.35'>And hast thou not, with thee, there Zadok and Abiathar the priests? so then it shall be, that, what thing soever thou shalt hear out of the house of the king, thou shalt tell to Zadok and to Abiathar, the priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.36'>Lo! they have there with them, their two sons, Ahimaaz for Zadok, and Jonathan for Abiathar,so shall ye send, by their hand, unto me, everything which ye shall hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.15.37'>So Hushai, Davids friend, went into the city,when, Absolom, was about to enter Jerusalem.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.16'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.1'>Now, David, had passed on but a little from the summit, when lo! Ziba, servant of Mephibosheth, met him,with a couple of asses saddled, and, upon them, two hundred cakes of bread, and one hundred cakes of raisins, and one hundred summer fruits, and a skin of wine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.2'>And the king said unto Ziba, What meanest thou, by these? And Ziba saidThe asses, are for the kings household, to ride on, and, the bread and the summer fruits, are for the young men to eat, and, the wine, is for drink to such as are faint in the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.3'>Then said the king, And where is thy lords son? And Ziba said unto the kingLo! abiding in Jerusalem, for he said, To-day, will the house of Israel, restore unto me, the kingdom of my father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.4'>Then said the king unto Ziba, Lo! thine, is all that pertained to Mephibosheth. And Ziba saidI have done homage, that I might find favour in thine eyes, my lord O king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.5'>And, when King David had come as far as Bahurim, lo! from thence a man coming out, of the family of the house of Saul, whose name, was Shimei son of Gera, coming out and cursing as he came.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.6'>And he pelted, with stones, David and all the servants of King David,all the people, and all the mighty men, being on his right hand and on his left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.7'>And, thus, said Shimei, when he cursed,Out! Out! thou man of bloodshed, and man of the Abandoned One!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.8'>Yahweh, hath brought back upon thee, all the shed-blood of the house of Saul, in whose stead thou hast reigned, and Yahweh hath delivered the kingdom into the hand of Absolom thy son,and, here thou art, in thy ruin, for that, a man of bloodshed, thou art.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.9'>Then said Abishai, son of Zeruiah, unto the kingWherefore should this dead dog curse my lord the king? I pray thee, let me cross over and take off his head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.10'>But the king said, What have I in common with you, ye sons of Zeruiah? thus, he curseth, because, Yahweh, hath said unto himCurse David. Who then can say, Why hast thou done thus?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.11'>Then said David unto Abishai, and unto all his servants, Lo! my own son who sprang from my body, is seeking my life,then how much more, now, a Benjamite? Let him alone, and let him curse, for, Yahweh, hath permitted him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.12'>It may be, that Yahweh will behold with his eye,and that Yahweh will return me good, for his cursing this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.13'>And, when David and his men went along in the way, Shimei, was going along on the side of the hill over against him, cursing as he went, pelting him with stones, and throwing dust.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.14'>And the king and all the people that were with him arrived, weary,and they refreshed themselves there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.15'>And, Absolom and all the men of Israel, entered Jerusalem,and Ahithophel with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.16'>And it came to pass, when Hushai the Archite, the friend of David, came in unto Absolom, that Hushai said unto Absolom: Long live the king! Long live the king!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.17'>Then said Absolom unto Hushai, Is, this, thy lovingkindness unto thy friend? Wherefore wentest thou not with thy friend?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.18'>And Hushai said unto Absolom, Nay! but, whom Yahweh, and all this people, and the men of Israel have chosen, his, will I be, and, with him, will I dwell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.19'>And, again, whom, should, I serve? Should it not be in presence of his son? as I served in presence of thy father, so, will I continue thy presence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.20'>Then said Absolom unto Ahithophel,Give ye your counsel, what we shall do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.21'>And Ahithophel said unto Absolom, Go in unto thy fathers concubines, whom he hath left to keep the house,so shall all Israel hear that thou hast made thyself odious unto thy father, and the hands of all that are with thee, shall be strengthened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.22'>And they stretched out for Absolom a tent, upon the house-top,and Absolom went in unto his fathers concubines, in the sight of all Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.16.23'>Now, the counsel of Ahithophel which he counselled in those days, was as if a man had enquired at the oracle of God,so, was all the counsel of Ahithophel, both to David, and also to Absolom.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.17'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.1'>Then said Ahithophel unto Absolom: I pray thee, let me choose for myself, twelve thousand men, and arise, and pursue David to-night;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.2'>and let me come upon him, when, he, is weary, and weak-handed, so shall I strike him with terror, and all the people who are with him shall flee,then will I smite the king alone:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.3'>that I may bring back all the people unto thee,when all return  the man whom thou art seeking, all the people, will be at peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.4'>And the saying was right in the eyes of Absolom, and in the eyes of all the elders of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.5'>Then said Absolom, I pray you, call ye Hushai the Archite also,and let us hear what is in, his, mouth, also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.6'>And, when Hushai came in unto Absolom, Absolom spake unto him, sayingAfter this manner, hath Ahithophel spoken, shall we do what he saith? if not, thou, speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.7'>Then said Hushai unto Absolom,Not good, is the counsel that Ahithophel hath givenat this time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.8'>And Hushai saidThou, knowest thy father and his menthat, men of might, they are, and, embittered in soul, they are, like a bear bereaved of her young, in the field,thy father also, is a man of war, and will not lodge with the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.9'>Lo! by this time, hath, he, hidden himself in some pit, or other place,and it shall be, as soon as he falleth upon them at the first, that he that hearkeneth for tidings will hear   , and will sayThere is a defeat among the people that are following Absolom:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.10'>then will, even the son of valour himself, whose heart is as the heart of a lion, utterly melt,for all Israel do know that, a man of might, is thy father, and that, sons of valour, are they who are with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.11'>Therefore I counselthat there be a general gathering together unto thee of all Israel, from Dan even unto Beer-sheba, as the sand that is by the sea for multitude,and that, thine own presence, be going on in their midst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.12'>So shall we come upon him in some place where he hath been found, yea, we, shall be upon him, as when the dew falleth upon the ground,and there shall not be left of him, or of the men that are with him, so much as one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.13'>But, if, into a city, he withdraw, then will all Israel bring up unto that city, ropes,and we will drag it down unto the ravine, until there be not found in that place, so much as a small stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.14'>Then said Absolom and all the men of Israel, Better, is the counsel of Hushai the Archite, than the counsel of Ahithophel. Yahweh, indeed, had given charge to frustrate the wise counsel of Ahithophel, to the intent that Yahweh might bring upon Absolom, ruin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.15'>So Hushai said unto Zadok and unto Abiathar the priests, Thus and thus, did Ahithophel counsel Absolom and the elders of Israel,and, thus and thus, have, I, counselled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.16'>Now, therefore, send quickly, and tell David, saying,Do not lodge to-night in the waste plains of the wilderness, thou must, even pass over, lest the king be swallowed up, and all the people who are with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.17'>Now, Jonathan and Ahimaaz, were staying by En-rogel, and a maidservant was to go and tell them, and, they, were to go and tell King David,for they might not be seen to eater the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.18'>And, though a young man did see them, and told Absolom, yet they both departed quickly, and entered the house of a man in Bahurim, and, he, had a well in his court, into which they went down;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.19'>and the woman took and spread the cover over the face of the well, and spread thereon her pounded corn,so nothing was known.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.20'>Then came the servants of Absolom unto the woman in the house, and saidWhere are Ahimaaz and Jonathan? And the woman said to themThey have passed over the stream of water. And, when they had searched and not found, they returned to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.21'>And it came to pass, after those had gone, that these came up out of the well, and went, and told King David,and said unto David,Arise ye and pass quickly over the water, for, thus and thus, hath Ahithophel counselled against you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.22'>So David arose, and all the people who were with him, and passed over the Jordan, by the morning light, so much as one, was not lacking, who had not passed over the Jordan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.23'>Now, when, Ahithophel, saw that his counsel was not followed, he saddled his ass, and arose and went unto his own house, unto his own city, and gave charge unto his household, and hanged himself, and died, and was buried in the grave of his father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.24'>When, David, had come to Mahanaim, Absolom, had passed over the Jordan, he and all the men of Israel with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.25'>Now Absolom had appointed, Amasa, instead of Joab, over the army,Amasa, being the son of a man whose name was Ithra the Ishmaelite, who went in unto Abigail, daughter of Nahash, sister of Zeruiah, mother of Joab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.26'>And Israel and Absolom encamped in the land of Gilead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.27'>And it came to pass, when David entered Mahanaim, that Shobi son of Nahash of Rabbah of the sons of Ammon and Machir son of Ammiel of Lo-debar, and Barzillai the Gileadite, of Rogelim,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.28'>brought, sleeping rugs, and basins, and earthen vessels, and wheat and barley, and meal and roasted corn,and beans and lentils, and parched pulse;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.17.29'>and honey and cream, and sheep, and cheese of kine, for David, and for the people that were with him, to eat,for they said, The people, are hungry and weary and thirsty, in the wilderness.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.18'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.1'>Then David mustered the people that were with him,and set over them, captains of thousands, and captains of hundreds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.2'>And David sent forth the peoplea third part, under the hand of Joab, and, a third part, under the hand of Abishai son of Zeruiah, brother of Joab, and, a third part, under the hand of Ittai the Gittite. Then said the king, unto the people, I myself, will, surely go forth, with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.3'>But the people saidThou must not go forth, for, if we, flee, they will not regard us, neither, if half of us die, will they regard us, for, thou, compared with us,   ten thousand,now, therefore, it will be better that thou come to us out of the city, with succour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.4'>And the king said unto them, Whatever is best in your eyes, I will do. And the king stood beside the gate, while, all the people, came out by hundreds and by thousands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.5'>And the king charged Joab and Abishai and Ittai, saying, Deal gently, for my sake, with the young man, even Absolom. And, all the people, heard when the king charged all the captains, for the sake of Absolom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.6'>So the people went forth into the field against Israel,and the battle took place in the forest of Ephraim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.7'>Then were the people of Israel defeated there, before he servants of David,and the slaughter there was great, on that daytwenty thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.8'>And the battle there was spread out over the face of all the land,and the forest devoured more of the people than the sword devoured on that day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.9'>Now, when Absolom met the servants of David, Absolom, was riding upon a mule, and the mule came under the thick branches of a large oak, and his head caught hold of the oak, and he was suspended between heaven and earth, the mule that was under him passing on.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.10'>And a certain man saw it, and told Joab,and saidLo! I saw Absolom suspended in an oak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.11'>Then said Joab to the man that was telling him, Lo! since thou sawest him, why didst thou not smite him there, to the ground? then should I have been bound to give thee ten pieces of silver, and a girdle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.12'>And the man said unto Joab, Though I were weighing upon my palm a thousand pieces of silver, yet would I not put forth my hand against the son of the king,for, in our hearing, the king Charged thee and Abishai and Ittai, saying, Watch any man who   the young man Absolom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.13'>Otherwise, had I dealt with my life falsely (and nothing can be hid from the king), then, thou thyself, wouldst have stood aloof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.14'>And Joab said, Not thus, may I tarry before thee. And he took three darts in his hand, and thrust them into the heart of Absolom, while he was yet alive in the midst of the oak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.15'>Then came round ten young men who bare Joabs armour,and smote Absolom, and slew him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.16'>Then Joab blew with a horn, and the people returned from pursuing Israel,for Joab had restrained the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.17'>And they took Absolom, and cast him, in the forest, into a large pit, and raised up over him a very great heap of stones,and, all Israel, fled, every man to his home.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.18'>But, Absolom, had taken, and raised up for himself, in his lifetime, the pillar that is in the kings vale, for he said, I have no son, to keep in remembrance my name, so he called the pillar after his own name, and it is called Absoloms monument unto this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.19'>Then, Ahimaaz, son of Zadok, said, Let me run, I pray thee, and carry tidings unto the king,how that Yahweh hath vindicated him, at the hand of his enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.20'>And Joab said to himNot a man to bear tidings, art thou this day, but thou shalt bear tidings another day,but, this day, shalt thou not bear tidings, for this cause, that, the kings son, is dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.21'>Then said Joab to a Cushite, Go tell the king, what thou hast seen. And the Cushite bowed himself down to Joab, and ran.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.22'>Then, yet again, said Ahimaaz son of Zadok unto Joab. But, be what may, do, I pray thee, let, me also, run, after the Cushite. And Joab saidWherefore is it that, thou, wouldst run, my son, when, thou, hast no tidings of, any profit?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.23'>But, be what may, I will run. So he said to himRun. Then ran Ahimaaz by the way of the plain, and got beyond the Cushite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.24'>Now, David, was sitting between the two gates,and the watchman went on to the top of the gate-house, upon the wall, and lifted up his eyes, and looked, and lo! a man, running alone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.25'>So the watchman called out, and told the king. And the king said, If he is alone, there are tidings in his mouth. And he came on nearer and nearer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.26'>Then saw the watchman another man, running, so he called out unto the porter, Lo! a man, running alone. And the king said. This one also, beareth tidings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.27'>Then said the watchman, It seemeth, to me, that, the running of the foremost, is like the running of Ahimaaz son of Zadok. And the king said, A good man, is he, and, with good tidings, he cometh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.28'>Then called out Ahimaaz, and said unto the king, Peace! And he bowed himself down to the king, with his face to the earth,and saidBlessed, be Yahweh thy God, who hath surrendered the men who were lifting up their hand, against my lord the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.29'>And the king said, Is it, well, with the young manAbsolom? Then said AhimaazI saw a great crowd, when Joab sent the kings servant and   .</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.30'>And the king said, Aside! stand, here. So he turned aside, and stood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.31'>Then lo! the Cushite, coming in,and the Cushite saidTidings, getteth my lord the king, how that Yahweh hath vindicated thee to-day, at the hand of all them who had risen up against thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.32'>And the king said unto the CushiteIs it, well, with the young manAbsolom? Then said the CushiteBe, like the young man, the enemies of my lord the king, and all who have risen up against thee, for harm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.18.33'>Then was the king deeply moved, and went up to the chamber over the gate, and wept,and, thus, he said as he wentO my son Absolom, my sonmy sonAbsolom! could, I, but have died in thy stead, O Absolom, my sonmy son!</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.19'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.1'>And it was told Joab,Lo! the king, is weeping and mourning over Absolom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.2'>So the victory, on that day, was turned into mourning, with all the people,for the people heard, on that day, saying, The king is distressed for his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.3'>And the people stole away, on that day, to go into the city,as people steal away who are put to shame, when they flee in battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.4'>But, the king, muffled his face, and the king made outcry, with a loud voice,O my son Absolom, O Absolom, my son, my son!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.5'>Then came Joab unto the king, in the house, and saidThou hast, to-day, covered with shame the faces of all thy servants, who have rescued thy life to-day, and the lives of thy sons and thy daughters, and the lives of thy wives, and the lives of thy concubines;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.6'>by loving them who hated thee, and hating them who loved thee,for thou hast declared, to-day, that, nothing to thee, are princes or servants, for I perceive, to-day, that, if, Absolom, had lived, and, all we, to-day had died, that, then, it had been right in thine eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.7'>Now, therefore, risego forth, and speak unto the heart of thy servants,for, by Yahweh, have I sworn, that, if thou do not go forth, not a man shall tarry with thee to-night, and this will be to thee, a greater misfortune, than all the misfortune that hath come upon thee from thy youth until now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.8'>So the king arose, and took his seat in the gate,and, to all the people, was it told, sayingLo! the king, is sitting in the gate. Then came all the people before the king, but, Israel, had fled every man to his home.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.9'>And it came to pass that all the people were reproaching one another, throughout all the tribes of Israel, saying,the king, delivered us out of the hand of our enemies, and, he, rescued us out of the hand of the Philistines, but, now, he hath fled out of the land, away from Absolom;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.10'>and, Absolom, whom we anointed over us, hath died in the battle. Now, therefore, why are, ye, silent as to bringing back the king?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.11'>And, King David, sent unto Zadok and unto Abiathar the priests, saying, Speak ye unto the elders of Judah, saying, Wherefore should ye be behindhand, in bringing back the king unto his home,seeing that, the speech of all Israel, hath come unto the king, regarding his home?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.12'>Mine own brethren, are ye, my bone and my flesh, are ye,wherefore then should ye be behindhand in bringing back the king?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.13'>And, unto Amasa, shall ye say, Art not, thou, my bone and my flesh? So, let God do to me, and, so, let him add, if thou become not, prince of the army, before me continually, instead of Joab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.14'>Thus bowed he the heart of all the men of Judah, as one man,and they sent unto the king, Return, thou, and all thy servants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.15'>Then the king returned, and came as far as the Jordan,and, Judah, came to Gilgal, to go and meet the king, to escort the king over the Jordan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.16'>Then hastened Shimei, son of Gera, the Benjamite, who was of Bahurim,and came down, with the men of Judah, to meet King David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.17'>And, a thousand men, were with him, out of Benjamin, Ziba also, servant of the house of Saul, and his fifteen sons and twenty servants, with him,and they went through the Jordan, before the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.18'>But the ferry-boat kept crossing, to bring over the household of the king, and to do what was good in his eyes. And, Shimei, son of Gera, fell down before the king, when he had passed over the Jordan;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.19'>and he said unto the kingLet not my lord impute to me iniquity, neither do thou remember the perverseness of thy servant, on the day that thou wentest out, my lord O king, from Jerusalem, that the king should lay it upon his heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.20'>For thy servant doth know, that, I, sinned, lo! therefore, I have arrived to-day, as the first of all the house of Joseph, to come down to meet my lord the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.21'>Then responded Abishai, son of Zeruiah, and said, For this, shall not Shimei be put to death, for that he cursed the Anointed of Yahweh?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.22'>But David said, What have I in common with you, ye sons of Zeruiah, for ye would become to me, to-day, a very traitor! Shall there, to-day, be put to death a man in Israel? for do I not know, that, to-day, I, am king over Israel?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.23'>Then said the king unto ShimeiThou shalt not die. And the king sware to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.24'>And, Mephibosheth, son of Saul, came down to meet the king,he had neither dressed his feet, nor trimmed his beard, nor, his clothes, had he washed, from the day the king departed, until the day that he entered in peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.25'>And it came to pass, when he entered Jerusalem to meet the king, that the king said unto him, Wherefore wentest thou not with me, Mephibosheth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.26'>And he said, My lord, O king, my servant, betrayed me, for thy servant saidI will even saddle me mine ass, that I may ride thereon, and go with the king, for, lame, is thy servant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.27'>And he hath slandered thy servant, unto my lord the king,but, my lord the king, is as a messenger of God, do therefore what is good in thine own eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.28'>For, when all the house of my father were nothing better than dead men, unto my lord the king, then didst thou set thy servant among them that used to eat at thy table,what then have I further, by way of right, or to cry out any further unto the king?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.29'>Then the king said unto him, Wherefore shouldst thou speak any further of thine affairs? I have saidThou and Ziba, shall share the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.30'>And Mephibosheth said unto the king, Even the whole, let him take,now that my lord the king hath entered, in peace, into his own house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.31'>And, Barzillai the Gileadite, came down from Rogelim,and passed, with the king, over the Jordan, to escort him over the Jordan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.32'>Now, Barzillai, was very aged, eighty years old,and, he himself, had sustained the king, throughout his sojourn in Mahanaim, for he was, an exceeding great man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.33'>So then the king said unto Barzillai,Thou, come over with me, and I will sustain thee with me, in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.34'>But Barzillai said unto the king,Like unto what, are the days of the years of my life, that I should come up with the king, to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.35'>Eighty years old, am I to-daycould I discern between good and bad? or could thy servant taste what I might eat, and what I might drink? or could I hearken any more to the voice of singing men and singing women? Wherefore, then, should thy servant yet be a burden unto my lord the king?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.36'>Just a little way, will thy servant pass over the Jordan with the king,but wherefore should the king recompense me with this reward?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.37'>Let thy servant, I pray thee, turn back again, that I may die in mine own city, by the grave of my father, and my mother. But here is thy servant Chimhamlet him pass over with my lord the king, and do unto him that which may be good in thine eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.38'>Then said the king, With me, shall Chimham pass over, and, I, will do unto him that which shall be good in thine eyes,and, whatsoever thou shalt choose to lay upon me, I will do for thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.39'>And, when all the people had passed over the Jordan, then, the king, passed over, and the king kissed Barzillai, and blessed him, and he returned unto his own place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.40'>And the king passed over to Gilgal, and, Chimham, passed over with him,and, all the people of Judah, escorted the king, yea moreover, half the people of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.41'>Then lo! all the men of Israel, were coming unto the king,and they said unto the kingWhy did our brethren the men of Judah steal thee away, and escort the king and his household over the Jordan, and all the men of David with him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.42'>And all the men of Judah made answer unto the men of IsraelBecause the king is, near of kin, unto us, wherefore, then, is it, that ye are angry over this matter? Have we, eaten, at the kings cost? or hath he, bestowed any gifts, on us?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.19.43'>And the men of Israel answered the men of Judah, and saidTen parts, have we in the king, therefore, even in David, have we more right than ye. Why, then, made ye light of us, so that our word was not heard first as to bringing back our king? And, the words of the men of Judah, were fiercer than, the words of the men of Israel.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.20'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.1'>Now, in that place, there happened to be an abandoned man, whose name, was Sheba son of Bichri, a man of Benjamin,so he blew a horn, and saidWe have no share in David, Nor inheritance have we in the son of Jesse, Every man to his home, O Israel!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.2'>Then went up all the men of Israel from following David, to follow Sheba son of Bichri,but, the men of Judah, clave unto their king, from the Jordan, even as far as Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.3'>And David entered into his own house, in Jerusalem, and the king took the ten women, the concubines whom he had left to keep the house, and put them in ward, and sustained them, but, unto them, went he not in,so they were shut up until the day of their death, in lifelong widowhood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.4'>Then said the king unto Amasa, Assemble me the men of Judah, within three days,and, thou, here, take thy stand!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.5'>So Amasa went, to assemble Judah,but he tarried beyond the fixed time, which he had appointed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.6'>Then said David unto Abishai, Now, shall Sheba son of Bichri, do us more harm than Absolom,thou, take the servants of thy lord, and pursue him, lest he have got him into fortified cities, and so have escaped our eye.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.7'>Then went out after himthe men of Joab, and the Cherethites and the Pelethites, and all the mighty men,and they went out from Jerusalem, to pursue Sheba son of Bichri.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.8'>When, they, were by the great stone which is in Gibeon, Amasa, had arrived before them. Now, Joab, was girded about with his war-coat as his upper garment, and, over it, a girdle with a sword, fastened upon his loins, in the sheath thereof, and, it, came out and fell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.9'>Then said Joab unto Amasa, Art thou, well, my brother? And Joab took Amasa by the beard with his right hand, to kiss him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.10'>Amasa not heeding the sword that was in the hand of Joab, he smote him therewith in the belly, and shed out his bowels to the ground, and   him not again, and he died. So, Joab and Abishai his brother, pursued Sheba son of Bichri.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.11'>Now, a man, stood over him, of the young men of Joab,and saidWhosoever is well pleased with Joab, and whosoever pertaineth to David, let him follow Joab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.12'>But, Amasa, was wallowing in blood, in the midst of the highway,and, when the man saw that all the people stood still, he moved Amasa, out of the highway into the field, and cast over him a garment, as soon as he saw that every man that came up to him stood still.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.13'>When he had removed him out of the highway, every man passed on, after Joab, to pursue Sheba son of Bichri.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.14'>And he passed on throughout all the tribes of Israel, unto Abel and unto Beth-maachah, and all the Berites,and they were called together, and came in, yea and followed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.15'>So they came, and laid siege against him, in Abel, Beth-maachah, and they cast up a mound against the city, so that it stood within a rampart, and, all the people who were with Joab, were battering the wall to throw it down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.16'>Then cried a wise woman out of the city,Hear ye! hear ye! I pray you, say unto Joab, Come near hither, and let me speak unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.17'>So he came near unto her, and the woman said,Art thou Joab? And he said,I am. And she said unto him,Hear thou the words of thy handmaid. And he said, I do hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.18'>Then spake she, saying,They, used to speak, in former times, saying, Enquire, in Abel! And, so, they ended it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.19'>I, am of the peaceable among the faithful in Israel,thou, art seeking to put to death a city, and a mother in Israel, wherefore wouldst thou swallow up the inheritance of Yahweh?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.20'>Then answered Joab and said,Far be it! far be it from me! I will neither swallow up nor lay waste.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.21'>Not so, is the matter! but, a man of the hill country of Ephraim, Sheba son of Bichri, his name, hath lifted up his hand against the king, even against David, give up him alone, and I will depart from the city. And the woman said unto Joab, Lo! his head, shall be cast unto thee, through the wall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.22'>So the woman came unto all the people in her wisdom, and they cut off the head of Sheba son of Bichri, and cast it out unto Joab. And he blew with a horn, and they dispersed themselves from the city, every man to his home; but, Joab, returned to Jerusalem unto the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.23'>And, Joab, was   unto all the army of Israel,And, Benaiah, son of Jehoiada, was over the Cherethites and over the Pelethites,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.24'>And, Adoniram, was over the tribute,And, Jehoshaphat, son of Ahilud, was the remembrancer;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.25'>And, Sheva, was scribe,And, Zadok and Abiathar, were priests;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.20.26'>Moreover also, Ira the Jairite, was chief ruler unto David.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.21'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.1'>And there came to be a famine, in the days of David, for three years, year after year, so then David sought the face of Yahweh,and Yahweh saidIt respecteth Saul and his house, as to bloodshed, in that he put to death the Gibeonites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.2'>The king therefore called the Gibeonites, and said unto them (now, the Gibeonites, were, not of the sons of Israel, but of the remnant of the Amorites, with whom, the sons of Israel, had entered into an oath, and Saul had sought to smite them, in his jealousy for the sons of Israel and Judah)</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.3'>wherefore David said unto the GibeonitesWhat shall I do for you, and wherewith shall I make propitiation, so that ye may bless the inheritance of Yahweh?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.4'>And the Gibeonites said unto himIt is not a matter with us of silver or gold, with Saul or with his house, neither would we have a man put to death in Israel. And he said,What do ye say I should do for you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.5'>Then said they unto the king, The man who consumed us, and who thought to have destroyed us from taking a place within any of the bounds of Israel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.6'>let there be delivered up to usseven men of his sons, and we will crucify them unto Yahweh in Gibeah of Saul, the chosen of Yahweh. And the king said, I, will deliver them up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.7'>But the king had pity upon Mephibosheth, son of Jonathan, Sauls son,because of the oath of Yahweh that was between them, between David and Jonathan, Sauls son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.8'>So the king took the two sons of Rizpah daughter of Aiah, whom she had borne to Saul, even Armoni and Mephibosheth,and the five sons of Michal daughter of Saul, whom she had borne to Adriel son of Barzillai, the Meholathite;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.9'>and delivered them up into the hand of the Gibeonites, and they crucified them in the mountain, before Yahweh, so they seven fell together,they being put to death in the first days of harvest, in the beginning of the barley harvest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.10'>Then Rizpah daughter of Aiah, took sackcloth, and spread it out for herself, on the rock, from the beginning of harvest, until water poured out upon them from the heavens,and suffered neither the birds of the heavens to rest on them by day, nor the wild beasts of the field,   by night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.11'>And it was told David,what Rizpah daughter of Aiah, Sauls concubine, had done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.12'>So David went and fetched the bones of Saul, and the bones of Jonathan his son, from the owners of Jabesh-gilead,who stole them from the broadway of Beth-shan, where the Philistines had hanged them, on the day when the Philistines had smitten Saul in Gilboa;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.13'>and he brought up from thence the bones of Saul, and the bones of Jonathan his son,and they gathered together the bones of them who had been crucified;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.14'>so they buried the bones of Saul and Jonathan his son in the land of Benjamin, in Zelah, in the grave of Kish his father, thus did they all that the king commanded,and God suffered himself to be entreated for the land, after this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.15'>And the Philistines had yet again a war with Israel,so David went down, and his servants with him, and fought the Philistines, and David became faint.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.16'>So, Ishbi-benob, who was of the descendants of the giant, the weight of whose spear-head, was three hundred shekels of bronze, he also being newly armed, thought to smite David;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.17'>but Abishai son of Zeruiah, came to his help, and smote the Philistine, and slew him. Then, sware the men of David unto him, sayingThou must not go forth any more with us, to battle, that thou quench not the lamp of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.18'>And it came to pass, after this, that there was yet again a battle in Gob, with the Philistines,then, Sibbekai the Hushathite smote Saph, who was of the descendants of the giant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.19'>And there was yet again a battle in Gob with the Philistines,when Elhanan son of Jaare-oregim of Bethlehem, smote Goliath the Gittite, the shaft of whose spear was like a weavers beam.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.20'>And there was yet again a battle in Gath; when there was a man of stature, with six fingers on each hand, and six toes on each foot, twenty-four in number; he also, having been born to the giant;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.21'>but, when he reproached Israel, Jonathan son of Shimeah Davids brother, smote, him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.21.22'>These four, had been born to the giant in Gath,but they fell by the hand of David, and by the hand of his servants.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.22'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.1'>And David spake unto Yahweh, the words of this song, in the day when Yahweh had rescued him, out of the hand of all his enemies, and out of the hand of Saul;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.2'>and he said,Yahweh, was my mountain crag and my stronghold, and my deliverermine;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.3'>My God, was my rock, I sought refuge in him,My shield, and my horn of salvation, my high tower, and my refuge, My Saviour! from violence, thou didst save me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.4'>As one worthy to be praised, called I on Yahweh,And, from my foes, was I saved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.5'>When the breakers of death had encompassed me,the torrents of perdition, made me afraid,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.6'>the meshes of hades, had surrounded me,the snares of death had confronted me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.7'>In my distress, called I on Yahweh, Yea, unto my God, did I call,and he hearkened, out of his temple, unto my voice, and, my cry for help, was in his ears!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.8'>Then did the earth shake and quake, the foundations of the heavens, were deeply moved,yea they did shake, because he was angry,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.9'>There went up a smoke in his nostrils, and, a fire out of his mouth, devoured,live coals, were kindled from it:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.10'>Then he stretched out the heavens, and came down,and, thick gloom, was under his feet;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.11'>Then he rode on a cherub, and flew,and was seen on the wings of the wind;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.12'>And made of the darkness around him, pavilions,gathering of waters, clouds of vapours.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.13'>Out of the brightness before him, were kindled live coals of fire;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.14'>Thunder from the heavens, did Yahweh give forth,yea, the Highest, uttered his voice;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.15'>And he sent forth arrows, and scattered them,lightning, and confused them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.16'>Then appeared the channels of the sea, were uncovered the foundations of the world,at the rebuke of Yahweh, the blast of the breath of his nostrils;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.17'>He sent from on high, he took me,he drew me out of many waters;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.18'>He rescued me from my foe, in his might,from them who hated me, because they were too strong for me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.19'>They confronted me, in the day of my necessity,then became Yahweh my stay:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.20'>And brought out, into a large place, even me,he delivered me, because he delighted in me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.21'>Yahweh rewarded me, according to my righteousnessaccording to the cleanness of my hands, he repaid me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.22'>For I had kept the ways of Yahweh,and not broken away from my God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.23'>For, all his regulations, were before me,and, as for his statutes, I turned not from them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.24'>So became I blameless towards him,and kept myself from mine iniquity:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.25'>Yahweh therefore repaid me, according to my righteousness,according to my pureness before his eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.26'>With the loving, thou didst show thyself loving,with the blameless hero, thou didst show thyself blameless;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.27'>With the pure, thou didst show thyself pure,but, with the perverse, thou didst shew thyself ready to contend:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.28'>And, a patient people, thou didst save,but, thine eyes, were on the loftythou layedst them low;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.29'>For, thou, wast my lamp, O Yahweh,and, Yahweh, enlightened my darkness;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.30'>For, by thee, I ran through a troop,by my God, I leapt over a wall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.31'>As for God, blameless is his way,the speech of Yahweh, hath been proved, a shield, he is to all who seek refuge in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.32'>For who is a GOD, save Yahweh? and who a Rock, save our God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.33'>GOD, is my fortress of strength,and shewed to the blameless his way;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.34'>Planting my feet like the hinds,yea, on my high places, he caused me to stand;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.35'>Teaching my hands, to war,so that a bow of bronze was bent by mine arms;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.36'>Thus didst thou grant me, as a shield, thy salvation,and, thy condescension, made me great.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.37'>Thou didst widen my stepping-places, under me,so that mine ankles faltered not:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.38'>I pursued my foes, and destroyed them,and returned not, till they were consumed;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.39'>So I consumed them, and crushed them, and they rose not again,thus fell they under my feet:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.40'>Thus didst thou gird me with strength, for the battle,thou subduedst mine assailants under me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.41'>And, as for my foes, thou didst give me their neck,yea, them who hated me, that I might destroy them:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.42'>They cried out, but there was none to save,unto Yahweh, but he answered them not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.43'>Then did I beat them in pieces, like the dust of the earth,like the clay of the lanes, did I crush them, stamp them down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.44'>Thus didst thou rescue me from the contentions of my people, didst keep me to be the head of nations:a people whom I had not known, served me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.45'>The sons of the foreigner, came cringing unto me,at the hearing of the ear, they submitted to me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.46'>The sons of the foreigner, were disheartened, and came quaking, out of their fortresses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.47'>Yahweh liveth, and blessed be my rock,and exalted be the God (of the rock) of my salvation:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.48'>The GOD who hath avenged me, and brought down peoples under me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.49'>And brought me forth from among my foes,yea, from mine assailants, hast thou set me on high, from the man of violence, hast thou delivered me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.50'>For this cause, will I praise thee, O Yahweh, among the nations,and, to thy name, will I touch the strings:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.22.51'>Who hath made great the victories of his King,and shown lovingkindness to his Anointed One, to David and to his Seed, unto times age-abiding.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.23'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.1'>Now, these, are the last words of David,The oracle of David, son of Jesse, Yea the oracle of The man raised up on high, The Anointed of the God of Jacob, the Delight of the Songs of Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.2'>The Spirit of Yahweh, spake in me,And, his word, was on my tongue;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.3'>Said the God of Israel, Unto me, spake the Rock of Israel:One Ruling over Men, A Righteous One, ruling in the reverence of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.4'>Is even as the light of the morning when ariseth the sun,A morning, without clouds,   from rain, the fresh shoots out of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.5'>When, not so, was my house with GOD, Then, a covenant age-abiding, he appointed me, Ordered in all things and guarded, Now that it is all my salvation and all my desire, Will he not make it shoot forth?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.6'>But, as for the abandoned, like thorns to be tossed away are they all,For, not with the hand, can they be taken;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.7'>But, the man that would touch them, Must fence himself with iron, and the shaft of a spear,Then, with fire, shall they be, consumed, on the spot!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.8'>These, are the names of the mighty men, who belonged to David,The president a Tachmonite head of the charioteers, the same, was Adino the Eznite, for eight hundred, slain at one time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.9'>And, after him, Eleazar son of Dodo, son of Ahohi,in the hero-class of mighty men, with David, when they reproached the Philistines, they were gathered together there to battle, but the men of Israel had gone up;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.10'>he, however, arose and smote among the Philistines until his hand was weary, and his hand clave unto his sword, so Yahweh wrought a great victory on that day,the people, coming back after him, only to strip the slain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.11'>And, after him, Shammah son of Agee, the Hararite,and, when the Philistines were gathered together into a troop, there being at hand an allotment of field-land full of lentils, but, the people, having fled from the face of the Philistines,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.12'>then took he his stand in the midst of the allotment, and defended it, and smote the Philistines,and Yahweh wrought a great victory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.13'>And three of the thirty chiefs descended, and came in, towards harvest, unto David, unto the cave of Adullam,although, a troop of Philistines, were encamped in the vale of Rephaim;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.14'>and, David, then was in a stronghold,and, a garrison of Philistines, was then in Bethlehem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.15'>And David longed, and said,Who will give me to drink water out of the well of Bethlehem, that is within the gate?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.16'>And the three mighty men brake through the camp of Philistines, and drew water out of the well of Bethlehem, that was within the gate, and bare it, and brought it in unto David,yet would he not drink, but poured it out unto Yahweh,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.17'>and saidBe it far from me, O Yahweh, that I should do this! is it not the blood of the men who went with their lives   ? So he would not drink it. These things, did the three mighty men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.18'>And. Abishai brother of Joab son of Zeruiah, he, was chief of three, in that he brandished his spear against three hundred whom he slew; and, he, had a name among three.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.19'>Was he not most honourable, of the three, and so became their captain? Nevertheless, unto the three, he attained not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.20'>Benaiah also, son of Jehoiadah, son of an active man, hero of many a deed, a man of Kabzeel, he, smote the two sons of Ariel of Moab, he, also went down and smote a lion in the midst of a pit, on a day of snow;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.21'>he, also smote an Egyptian, who was of valiant bearing, and, in the hand of the Egyptian, was a spear, but he went down unto him with a staff,and wrested the spear out of the hand of the Egyptian, and slew him with his own spear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.22'>These things, did Benaiah son of Jehoiada, and, he, had a name among three mighty men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.23'>He was the most honourable, of thirty, although, unto the three, he attained no,so David added him to his council.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.24'>Asahel, brother of Joab, was among the thirty,Elhanan, son of Dodo, of Bethlehem;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.25'>Shammah, the Harodite; Elika, the Harodite;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.26'>Helez, the Paltite, Ira, son of Ikkesh, the Tekoite;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.27'>Abiezer, the Anathothite, Mebunnai, the Hushathite;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.28'>Zalmon, the Ahohite, Maharai, the Netophathite;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.29'>Heleb, son of Baanah, the Netophathite,Ittai, son of Ribai, of Gibeah, of the sons of Benjamin;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.30'>Benaiah, a Pirathonite, Hiddai, of the torrents of Gaash;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.31'>Abi-albon, the Arbathite, Azmaveth, the Barhumite;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.32'>Eliahba, the Shaalbonite, (Of) the sons of Jashen, Jonathan;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.33'>Shammah, the Hararite, Ahiam, son of Sharar, the Ararite;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.34'>Eliphelet, son of Ahasbai, son of the Maacathite. Eliam, son of Ahithophel, the Gilonite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.35'>Hezro, the Carmelite, Paarai, the Arbite;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.36'>Igal, son of Nathan, of Zobah, Bani, the Gadite;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.37'>Zelek, the Ammonite,Naharai, the Beerothite, armour bearers to Joab son of Zeruiah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.38'>Ira, the Ithrite, Gareb, the Ithrite;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.23.39'>Uriah, the Hittite, In all, thirty and seven.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Sam.24'>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.1'>And again was the anger of Yahweh kindled against Israel,so that he suffered David to be moved against them, saying, Go, count Israel and Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.2'>The king, therefore, said unto Joab, captain of the force, who was with himGo to and fro, I pray thee, throughout all the tribes of Israel, from Dan even unto Beer -sheba, and number ye the people,so shall I know the sum of the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.3'>Then said Joab unto the kingYea, Yahweh thy God add unto the people, how many soever they be, a hundredfold, and   the eyes of my lord the king, to see it,but, my lord the king, wherefore doth he find pleasure in this thing?</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.4'>Notwithstanding, the word of the king prevailed against Joab, and over the captains of the force,so Joab went forth, with the captains of the force, before the king, to number the peopleIsrael.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.5'>And they passed over the Jordan,and encamped in Aroer, on the right side of the city, that is in the midst of the ravine of Gad, even towards Jazer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.6'>Thus came they to Gilead, and unto the land of Tahtim-hodshi,and came to Dan-jaan, and round about Zidon;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.7'>and entered the fortress of Tyre, and all the cities of the Hivites, and of the Canaanites,and they went out to the South of Judah, even to Beer-sheba.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.8'>So, when they had gone to and fro throughout all the land, they came, at the end of nine months and twenty days, unto Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.9'>And Joab delivered up the sum of the number of the people, unto the king,and there were found to be, in Israel, eight hundred thousand men of valour, drawing the sword,and, the men of Judah, five hundred thousand men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.10'>And the heart of David smote him, after he had reckoned up the people,and David said unto YahwehI have sinned greatly, in what I have done, Now, therefore, O Yahweh, take away, I beseech thee, the iniquity of thy servant, for I have done very foolishly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.11'>And, when David arose in the morning, the word of Yahweh, had come unto Gad the prophet, the seer of David, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.12'>Go and speak unto DavidThus, saith Yahweh, Three things, do I offer thee,choose thee one of them, that I may do it unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.13'>So Gad came in unto David, and told him,and said to him: Shall there come unto thee seven years of famine in thy land? Or, for three months, wilt thou flee before thine enemies while, they, pursue thee? Or shall there be, for three days, pestilence in thy land? Now, consider and see, what, answer, I shall return to him that sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.14'>And David said unto GadI am in a great strait,let us fall, I pray thee, into the hand of Yahweh, for, manifold, are, his compassions, but, into the hand of man, let me not fall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.15'>So Yahweh sent forth a pestilence throughout Israel, from the morning even unto the time appointed,and there died of the people, from Dan even unto Beer-sheba, seventy thousand men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.16'>But, when the messenger stretched out his hand towards Jerusalem, to destroy it, then relented Yahweh as to the evil, and he said to the messenger who was destroying the peopleEnough! now, stay thy hand. And, the messenger of Yahweh, was by the threshing-floor of Araunah the Jebusite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.17'>Then said David unto Yahweh, when he saw the messenger who was smiting the people, yea he saidLo! I, have sinned, and, I, have done perversely, but what have, these sheep, done? Let thy hand, I pray thee, be against me, and against the house of my father!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.18'>And Gad came unto David, on that day,and said unto himGo up, rear thou unto Yahweh an altar, in the threshing-floor of Araunah the Jebusite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.19'>So David went up, according to the word of Gad, as Yahweh had commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.20'>And Araunah looked out, and saw the king, and his servants, passing over unto himso Araunah went forth, and did homage unto the king, with his face to the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.21'>Then said Araunah, Wherefore, hath my lord the king come unto his servant? And David saidTo buy of thee the threshing-floor, to build an altar unto Yahweh, that the plague may be stayed from off the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.22'>Then said Araunah unto David, Let my lord the king accept it and cause to ascend what is good in his own eyes,see! the oxen for the ascending-sacrifice, and the threshing-sledges and ox-yokes for wood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.23'>The whole, did Araunah give, as a king to a king. And Araunah said unto the king, Yahweh thy God, accept thee!</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.24'>But the king said unto AraunahNay! but I will, buy, it of thee, for a price, and will not cause to ascend unto Yahweh my God, offerings that have cost me nothing. So David bought the threshing-floor, and the oxen, for fifty shekels of silver;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Sam.24.25'>and David built there an altar unto Yahweh, and caused to go up ascending-sacrifices and peace-offerings,then was Yahweh entreated for the land, and the plague was stayed from Israel.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>