<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='Roth' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='Roth'>
        <title>Rotherham Version</title>
        <contributor>CrossWire Bible Society</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-22</date>
        <description>The Emphasized Bible by J. B. Rotherham</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>Roth</identifier>
        <source>http://www.crosswire.org/sword/servlet/SwordMod.Verify?modName=Rotherham&amp;pkgType=win</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the  world</coverage>
        <rights>originally published by Samuel Bagster and Sons in 1902</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Mic'>
      <chapter osisID='Mic.1'>
        <title>And God saw their doings, that they turned from their wicked way,and God was grieved over the calamity which he had spoken of executing upon them, and executed it not.</title>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.1'>The word of Yahweh which came unto Micah the Morashtite, in the days of Jotham, Ahaz, Hezekiah, kings of Judah,of which he had vision concerning Samaria, and Jerusalem:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.2'>Hear ye peoples, all of you, Hearken, O earth and the fulness thereof,and let My Lord Yahweh be among you for a witness, My Lord out of his holy temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.3'>For lo! Yahweh, coming forth out of his place,that he may descend, and march along upon the high places of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.4'>Then shall the mountains be melted beneath him, and, the valleys, be cleft,as wax before the fire, as waters poured out in a steep place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.5'>For the transgression of Jacob, is all this, and for the sin of the house of Israel,Whose is the transgression of Jacob? Is it not Samarias? And whose is the sin of Judah? Is it not Jerusalem?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.6'>Therefore will I make of Samaria a heap in a field, the plantings in a vineyard,and I will pour down, into the valley, her stones, and, her foundations, will I lay bare;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.7'>And, all her images, shall be beaten in pieces, and, all her rewards for unchastity, shall be burned in the fire, and, all her idols, will I make a desolation,for, out of the reward of unchastity, she gathered</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.8'>For this cause, will I lament and howl, I will go stript and bare,I will make a lamentation, like the wild dogs, and a mourning, like ostriches.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.9'>For dangerous are her wounds,for she hath come as far as Judah, she hath reached as far as the gate of my people, as far as Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.10'>In Gath, do not tell, in Accho, do not weep,in Beth-laphrah, roll yourselves in dust.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.11'>Pass thou over (for you), thou inhabitress of Shaphir, of disgraceful disclosure,the inhabitress of Zaanan, hath not gone forth, at the lamentation of Beth-ezel, shall he take from you his station,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.12'>Though the inhabitress of Maroth waited for blessing,yet there came down calamity from Yahweh, to the gate of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.13'>Bind the chariot to the steed, O inhabitress of Lachish,the beginning of sin, was she to the daughter of Zion, for, in thee, have been found the transgressions of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.14'>Therefore, shalt thou give a dismission, against Moresheth-gath,The houses of Achzib, served for a deception to the kings of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.15'>The time shall yet be when, the heir, I will bring unto thee, O inhabitress of Mareshah,as far as Adullam, shall enter the glory of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.1.16'>Make thee bald, and cut off thy hair, for the children of thy pleasures,enlarge thy baldness, like a vulture, for they are exiled from thee.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mic.2'>
        <verse osisID='Mic.2.1'>Alas for them who devise iniquity and work wickedness upon their beds,in the light of the morning, they will execute it, for it is in the power of their hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.2.2'>Thus do they covet fields and seize them, and houses and take them away,and so they oppress the master and his household, the man and his inheritance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.2.3'>Therefore,Thus, saith Yahweh, Behold me! devising, against this family, a calamity,from which ye shall not remove your neck, neither shall ye walk loftily, for, a time of calamity, shall it be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.2.4'>In that day, shall one take up against you a by-word, and lament a lamentable lamentation, sayingwe are made, utterly desolate, the portion of my people, he passeth to others,How doth he set me aside! To an apostate, our fields, doth he apportion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.2.5'>Therefore, shalt thou have none to throw a measuring-line by lot,in the convocation of Yahweh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.2.6'>Do not sputterSo they sputter! They must not sputter as to these things, Must he not put away reproaches?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.2.7'>O thou who art said to be the house of Jacob, Is the spirit of Yahweh, impatient? Or are, these, his doings? Are not, his words, pleasant to him who is upright in his walk?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.2.8'>But, against my people, as an enemy, he setteth himself, from off the robe, they tear away, the cloak,from such as are passing by with confidence, as men averse from war.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.2.9'>The wives of my people, ye do even drive out, each from the house of her darlings,from over her children, ye do take away mine ornament, as long as life shall last.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.2.10'>Arise ye and depart, for, this, is not the place of rest,Because it is defiled, it shall make desolate with a desolation that is ruthless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.2.11'>If there be a man, who goeth after wind, and, falsehood, hath woven,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.2.12'>I will, surely assemble, O Jacob, all of thee, I will, surely gather, the remnant of Israel, at once, will I make them like sheep in distress,Like a flock in the midst of its pasture, shall they hum with men,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.2.13'>One making a breach, hath gone up, before them, they have broken in, and passed through, and, by the gate, have departed,and their king, hath passed through, before them, with, Yahweh, at their head!</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mic.3'>
        <verse osisID='Mic.3.1'>Then said I, Hear, I pray you, ye heads of Jacob, and ye judges of the house of Israel,Is it not yours to know justice?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.3.2'>Ye haters of right, and lovers of wrong,tearing away their skin from off them, and their flesh from off their bones;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.3.3'>Who indeed have eaten the flesh of my people, and, their skin from off them, have stript, and, their bones, have they broken in pieces,and will spread them out, as flesh with a fork, and as flesh, in the midst of a pot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.3.4'>Then, shall they make outcry unto Yahweh, but he will not answer them,that he may hide his face from them, at that time, even as they have made wicked their doings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.3.5'>Thus, saith Yahweh, concerning the prophets who are leading astray my people,who bite with their teeth, and then cryProsper! and whoso holdeth not to their mouth, they hallow against him a war!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.3.6'>Therefore, shall it be night to you, for lack of vision, and darkness to you, for lack of divination,and the sun, shall go in, over the prophets, and the day, shall be overcast because of them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.3.7'>And the men of vision, shall turn pale, and the diviners, shall blush, and shall put a covering upon their lip, all of them,because there is no answer of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.3.8'>But, in very deed, I, am full of vigour, with the spirit of Yahweh, and of justice and of valour,to declare to Jacob, his transgression, and to Israel, his sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.3.9'>Hear this, I pray you, ye heads of the house of Jacob, and ye judges of the house of Israel,who abhor justice, and, all right, do pervert:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.3.10'>Building Zion, with deeds of blood,and Jerusalem, with perversity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.3.11'>Her heads, for a bribe, pronounce sentence, and, her priests, for a price, give direction, and, her prophets, for silver, divine,yet, on Yahweh, they lean, saying, Is not, Yahweh, in our midst? there shall not come upon us, calamity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.3.12'>Wherefore, for your sake, Zion, as a field, shall be ploughed, and, Jerusalem, unto heaps of ruins, shall be turned,and, the mountain of the house, shall</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mic.4'>
        <verse osisID='Mic.4.1'>But it shall come to pass, in the afterpart of the days, that the mountain of the house of Yahweh shall be, set up, as the head of the mountains, and, exalted, shall it be, above the hills,and peoples, shall stream thereunto;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.4.2'>Yea many nations, shall go, and saycome ye, and let us ascend unto the mountain of Yahweh, and unto the house of the God of Jacob, that he may teach us of his ways, and we may walk in his paths,for, out of Zion, shall go forth a law, and, the word of Yahweh, out of Jerusalem;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.4.3'>And he will judge between many peoples, and be umpire to strong nations far and wide,and they will beat their swords into ploughshares, and their spears into pruning-hooks, Nationagainst nationshall not lift up sword, neither shall they learnany moreto make war.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.4.4'>And they shall dwellevery manunder his own vine and under his own fig-tree, with none to make them afraid,for, the mouth of Yahweh of hosts, hath spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.4.5'>For, all the peoples, walk, every man in the name of his god,we, therefore, will walk in the name of Yahweh our God, to times age-abiding and beyond.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.4.6'>In that day, Declareth Yahweh, will I take up her teat is lame, and, her that hath been an outcast, will I carry,even whomsoever I have afflicted;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.4.7'>And will make of her that was lame a residue, and of her that was removed far away a strong nation,and Yahweh, shall be king, over them, in Mount Zion, from henceforth, even unto times age-abiding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.4.8'>Thou, therefore, O Migdal-eder, mound of the daughter of Zion, as far as thee, shall it come,so shall arrive the chief dominion, the kingdom of the daughter of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.4.9'>Meanwhile, wherefore shouldst thou cry out aloud? King, is there none within thee? or hath, thy counselor, perished? for labour, hath seized thee, as a woman in child-birth:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.4.10'>Be in labour, and bear, O daughter of Zion, as a woman in child-birth,for, meanwhile, shalt thou go forth out of the city, and dwell in the field, and shalt come as far as Babylon, there, shalt thou be delivered, there, will Yahweh, redeem thee, out of the grasp of thine enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.4.11'>Meanwhile, therefore, shall be gathered against thee many nations,who are sayingLet her be defiled, and let our eyes gaze upon Zion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.4.12'>But, they, know not the purposes of Yahweh, neither have they discerned his counsel,for he hath gathered them, as sheaves, to a threshing-floor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.4.13'>Arise and thresh, O daughter of Zion, for, thy horn, will I make to be iron, and, thy hoofs, will I make to he bronze, so shalt thou beat in pieces many peoples,and shalt devote to Yahweh their unrighteous gain, and their substance, to the Lord of all the earth.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mic.5'>
        <verse osisID='Mic.5.1'>Meanwhile, shalt thou gather together in troops, thou daughter of a troop, siege, hath he laid against us,with a sceptre, will they smite on the cheek, the judge of Israel!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.5.2'>Thou, therefore, Bethlehem Ephrathah, though, little, to be among the thousands of Judah, out of thee, shall Mine come forth, to be ruler in Israel,whose comings forth, have been from of old, from the days of age-past time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.5.3'>Therefore, will he give them up, until the time when, one who is to bring forth, hath brought forth,and, the remainder of his brethren, return unto the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.5.4'>Then shall he stand, and tend his flock in the strength of Yahweh, In the excellency of the name of Yahweh his God, have they endured,For, now, shall he be great unto the ends of the earth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.5.5'>So shall this one be Prosperity. As for Assyriawhen he shall enter our land, and when he shall tread down in our palaces, then will we raise up against him, seven shepherds, and eight princes of mankind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.5.6'>Then shall they shepherd the land of Assyria with the sword, and the land of Nimrod in the entrances thereof,So shall he deliver from Assyria, when he shall enter our land, and when he shall tread down within our bounds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.5.7'>And, the remnant of Jacob, shall be, in the midst of many peoples, as dew from Yahweh, as myriad drops on plants,which tarrieth not for man, nor waiteth for the sons of Adam.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.5.8'>And, the remnant of Jacob, shall be among the nations, in the midst of many peoples, as a lion among the beasts of the jungle, as a young lion among flocks of sheep,who, if he passeth by, both treadeth downand teareth in pieces, and none can deliver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.5.9'>Let thy hand be uplifted against thine adversaries,and, all thine enemies, shall be cut off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.5.10'>And it shall come to pass, in that day, Declareth Yahweh, That I will cut off thy horses out of thy midst,and will destroy thy chariots;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.5.11'>And will cut off the cities of thy land,and will pull down all thy fortresses;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.5.12'>And will cut off incantations, out of thy hand,and, users of hidden arts, shalt thou not have;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.5.13'>And I will cut off thine images and thy pillars out of thy midst,and thou shalt not bow thyself down, any more, to the work of thine own hands;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.5.14'>And I will uproot thy Sacred Stems out of thy midst,and will destroy thy cities:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.5.15'>Then will I execute, with anger and with indignation, vengeance upon the nations,of which they have not heard.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mic.6'>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.1'>Hear, I pray you, what, Yahweh, is saying,arise thou, maintain thy controversy before the mountains, and let the hills hear thy voice:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.2'>Hear, ye mountains, the controversy of Yahweh, and ye lasting rocks, the foundations of the earth,for, a controversy, hath Yahweh, with his people, and, with Israel, will he dispute.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.3'>O my people! what have I done to thee? and wherein have I wearied thee? Testify thou against me!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.4'>For I brought thee up out of the land of Egypt, and, out of the house of slaves, I ransomed thee,and I sent before thee, Moses, Aaron and Miriam.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.5'>O my people! remember, I pray you, what Balak king of Moab, counseled, and what Balaam son of Beer, answered him,from the Acacias as far as Gilgal, that ye may know the righteousness of Yahweh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.6'>Wherewith, shall I come before Yahweh? bow myself to God on high? Shall I come before him with ascending-sacrifice? with calves of a year old?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.7'>Will Yahweh, be pleased, with thousands of rams? with myriads of torrents of oil? Shall I give my firstborn for my transgression? the fruit of my body for the sin of my soul?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.8'>He hath told thee, O son of earth, what is good,what then is, Yahweh, seeking of thee, but, to do justice, to delight in lovingkindness, and humbly to walk with thy God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.9'>The voice of Yahweh, to the city, crieth out, With safety for him who regardeth his name,Hear ye the rod, and who hath appointed it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.10'>Even yet, are there, in the house of the lawless one, the treasures of lawlessness,and the scant measureaccurst?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.11'>Shall I be pure with lawless balances? or with bag of deceitful weights?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.12'>For, her rich men, are full of violence, and, her inhabitants, have spoken falsehood,and, their tongue, is deceitful in their mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.13'>Moreover also, I, have made thee sick with smiting thee,laying thee waste because of thy sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.14'>Thou, shalt eatand not be satisfied, but be shrunk with hunger within thee,Though thou remove, yet shalt thou not set in safety, and, what thou dost set in safety, to the sword, will I deliver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.15'>Thou, shalt sow, but shalt not reap,thou, shalt tread the olive, but shalt not anoint thee with oil, also the grape, but shalt not drink the wine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.6.16'>For strictly observed are the statutes of Omri, and every doing of the house of Ahab, and ye have walked in their counsels,to the end I may give thee up to desolation, and her inhabitants to hissing, that, the reproach of peoples, ye may bear.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mic.7'>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.1'>Alas for me! for I am become as gatherings of summer fruit, as gleaning-grapes in harvest, there is no cluster to eat, the first ripe fruit, my soul, craved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.2'>Perished is the man of lovingkindness out of the earth, and, upright among men, is there none,they all, for bloodshed, lie in wait. Every manfor his brother, do they hunt as for one devoted to destruction.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.3'>Of wickedness with both hands to make sure, the ruler, doth make demandand the judgefor a recompense,and, as for the great man, he, is putting into words the desire of his soul, So have they woven the net!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.4'>The best of them, is as a sharp briar, and, the most upright, worse than a thorn hedge, The day of thy watchmenof thy visitation, hath come, Now, shall be their confusion!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.5'>Do not trust in a friend, do not put confidence in an associate,from her that lieth in thy bosom, keep thou the doors of thy mouth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.6'>For, the son, treateth as foolish, the father, and, the daughter, riseth up against, her mother, the daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law,The foes of a man, are the men of his own house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.7'>But, I, for Yahweh, will watch, I will wait for the God of my salvation,My God, will hear me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.8'>Do not rejoice, O mine enemy, against me, Though I fall, I shall rise again! Though I sit in darkness, Yahweh, is a light to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.9'>The indignation of Yahweh, will I bear, for I have sinned against him,until he take up my controversy, then will he do me justice, he will bring me forth to the light, I shall behold his righteousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.10'>So shall she who had been mine enemy fear, and shame, shall cover her, who used to say unto meWhere is Yahweh thy God? Mine own eyes, shall look upon her, Now, shall she become one to he trodden down, like the mire of the lanes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.11'>On the day for building thy walls,on that day, far away shall be thy boundary:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.12'>The very day, that, against thee, shall one come from Assyria, and   the cities of Egypt; yea from Egypt, even unto the River, and from sea to sea, and from mountain to mountain:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.13'>Though the land become a desolation, because of them that dwell therein,by reason of the fruit of their doings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.14'>Shepherd thou thy people with thy rod, the flock of thine inheritance, Dwell thou alone, a jungle in the midst of a fruitful field,Let them feed in Bashan and in Gilead, as in the days of age-past times.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.15'>As in the days of thy coming forth out of the land of Egypt, will I shew him wonders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.16'>Nations, shall see, that they may turn pale at all their valour,they shall lay hand on mouth, their ears, shall be silent:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.17'>They shall lick the dust like the serpent, Like the crawlers of the earth, shall they come quaking out of their fastnesses,Towards Yahweh our God, shall they pay adoration, and shall fear because of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.18'>Who is a GOD like unto thee, taking away the iniquityand passing over the transgressionof the remnant of his inheritance? He hath not held fast, perpetually, his anger, for, one who delighteth in lovingkindness, is he!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.19'>He will again have compassion upon us, he will subdue our iniquities,Thou wilt castinto the depths of the seaall their sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mic.7.20'>Thou wilt grantthe faithfulness to Jacob, the lovingkindness to Abraham,which thou didst swear to our fathers, from the days of ancient time.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>