<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='Roth' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='Roth'>
        <title>Rotherham Version</title>
        <contributor>CrossWire Bible Society</contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-22</date>
        <description>The Emphasized Bible by J. B. Rotherham</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>Roth</identifier>
        <source>http://www.crosswire.org/sword/servlet/SwordMod.Verify?modName=Rotherham&amp;pkgType=win</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the  world</coverage>
        <rights>originally published by Samuel Bagster and Sons in 1902</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Rev'>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.1'>
        <title>I hope, however, straightway, to see thee, and, mouth to mouth, will we talk. Peace be unto thee. The friends salute thee. Salute the friends by name.</title>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.1'>The Revelation of Jesus Christ, which God gave to him, to point out unto his servants the things which must needs come to pass with speed,and he shewed them by signs, sending through his messenger, unto his servant John;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.2'>who bare witness as to the word of God, and the witness of Jesus Christ,whatsoever things he saw.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.3'>Happy! he that readeth, and they who hear, the words of the prophecy, and keep the things, therein, written; for, the season, is, near.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.4'>John, unto the Seven Assemblies which are in Asia, Favour to you, and peace, fromHim who Is, and who Was, and who is Coming, and fromThe Seven Spirits which are before his throne,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.5'>and fromJesus Christ,The Faithful Witness, The Firstborn of the Dead, and The Ruler of the Kings of the Earth. Unto him that loveth us, and loosed us out of our sins with his blood,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.6'>and he hath made us   a kingdompriests unto his God and Father, Unto him, be the glory, and the dominion, unto the ages. Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.7'>Lo! he cometh with the clouds, and every eye shall see him, such also as pierced him; and all the tribes of the land shall smite themselves for him. Yea! Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.8'>I, am, the A, and, the Z, saith the Lord,the, God who Is, and who Was, and who is Coming, The Almighty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.9'>I, John, your brother, and partaker with you in the tribulation and kingdom and endurance in Jesus, came to be in the isle that is called Patmos, because of the word of God, and the witness of Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.10'>I came to be, in Spirit, in the Lords Day, and heard, behind me, a loud voice, as of a trumpet,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.11'>sayingWhat thou seest, write in a scroll, and send unto the Seven Assemblies,unto Ephesus, and unto Smyrna, and unto Pergamum,and unto Thyatira, and unto Sardis, and unto Philadelphia,and unto Laodicea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.12'>And I turned round, to see the Voice which was speaking with me, and, having turned, I saw Seven Lamps of gold;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.13'>and, in the midst of the lamps, One like unto a Son of Man:clothed with a robe, reaching to the feet, and girt about at the breasts with a girdle of gold,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.14'>And his head and hair, white, like white woollike snow, and, his eyes, like a flame of fire,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.15'>And, his feet, like unto glowing copper, as if in a furnace refined, and, his voice, like a sound of many waters,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.16'>And, having in his right hand, seven stars, and, out of his mouth, a sharp, two-edged sword, going forth; and, his whole appearance, as when, the sun, shineth in its strength.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.17'>And, when I saw him, I fell at his feet as dead, and he laid his right hand upon me, sayingDo not fear! I, am the First, and the Last,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.18'>and the Living One,and I became dead;and lo! living, am I, unto the ages of ages, and have the keys of death and of hades.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.19'>Write, thereforewhat things thou hast seen and what they are; and what things are about to come to pass, after these things:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.1.20'>The sacred secret of the seven stars, which thou sawest upon my right hand, and the seven lamps of gold:The seven stars, are, messengers of the seven assemblies, and, the seven lamps, are, seven assemblies</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.2'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.1'>Unto the messenger of the assembly, in Ephesus, write:These things, saith he that holdeth the seven stars in his right hand, he that walketh in the midst of the seven lamps of gold:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.2'>I know thy works, and thy toil, and endurance, and that thou canst not bear bad men, and thou hast tried them who were affirming themselves to be apostles, and they were not, and hast found them false;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.3'>And thou hast, endurance, and hast borne for the sake of my name, and hast not grown weary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.4'>Nevertheless, I have against thee, that, thy first love, thou hast left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.5'>Remember, therefore, whence thou hast fallen, and repent, and do, thy first works; otherwise, I come unto thee, and will remove thy lamp out of its place, except thou repent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.6'>But, this, thou hast, that thou hatest the works of the Nicolaitanes, which, I also, hate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.7'>He that hath an ear, let him hear what, the Spirit, is saying unto the assemblies. Unto him that overcomethI will give, unto him, to eat of the tree of life, which is in the paradise of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.8'>And, unto the messenger of the assembly, in Smyrna, write:These things, saith the first and the last, who became dead, and lived:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.9'>I know thy tribulation, and destitution, nevertheless, thou art, rich, and the profane speech from among them who affirm that they themselves are, Jews, and they are not, but a synagogue of Satan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.10'>Do not fear the things which thou art about to suffer. Lo! the adversary is about to cast some of you into prison, that ye may be tried, and may have tribulation ten days. Become thou faithful until death, and I will give thee the crown of life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.11'>He that hath an ear, let him hear what, the Spirit, is saying unto the assemblies. He that overcometh, shall in nowise be injured by reason of the second death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.12'>And, unto the messenger of the assembly, in Pergamum, write:These things, saith he that hath the sharp, two-edged sword:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.13'>I know where thou dwellest, where, the throne of Satan, is; and thou art holding fast my name, and didst not deny my faith, even in the days of Antipas, my witness, my faithful one, who was killed near you, where, Satan, dwelleth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.14'>Nevertheless, I have against thee, a few things,that thou hast there, such as hold fast the teaching of Balaam,who went on to teach Balak to throw a cause of stumbling before the sons of Israel, to eat idol-sacrifices and to commit lewdness:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.15'>thus, even, thou, hast such as hold fast the teaching of the Nicolaitanes, in like manner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.16'>Repent, therefore, otherwise, I come unto thee speedily,and will fight against them, with the sword of my mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.17'>He that hath an ear, let him hear what, the Spirit, is saying unto the assemblies. Unto him that overcometh, I will give, unto him, of the hidden manna, and I will give unto him a white stone, and, upon the stone, a new name written, which, no one, knoweth, save he that receiveth it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.18'>And, unto the messenger of the assembly, in Thyatira, write:These things, saith the Son of God, who hath his eyes like a flame of fire, and his feet like unto glowing copper:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.19'>I know thy works, and thy love, and faith, and ministry, and endurance,and that, thy last works, are more than the first.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.20'>Nevertheless, I have against thee, that thou sufferest the woman Jezebel, she who calleth herself a prophetess, and is teaching and leading astray my own servants to commit lewdness and to eat idol-sacrifices;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.21'>and I gave her time, that she might repent, and she willeth not to repent out of her lewdness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.22'>Lo! I cast her into a bed, and them who are committing adultery with her, into great tribulation,except they repent out of her works;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.23'>and, her children, will I slay with death;and all the assemblies shall get to know, that, I, am he that searcheth reins and hearts, and will give unto you, each one, according to your works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.24'>But, unto you, I say,the rest who are in Thyatira, as many as have not this teaching, such as have not come to know the deep things of Satan, as they say, I do not cast upon you any other burden;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.25'>nevertheless, what ye have, hold fast, till I shall have come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.26'>And, he that overcometh, and keepeth throughout my works, I will, give unto him, authority over the nations;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.27'>and he shall shepherd them with a sceptre of iron,as, vessels of earthenware, are dashed in pieces:as, I also, have received from my Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.28'>And I will give unto him the morning star.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.2.29'>He that hath an ear, let him hear what, the Spirit, is saying unto the assemblies.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.3'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.1'>And, unto the messenger of the assembly, in Sardis, write:These things, saith he that hath the seven Spirits of God, and the seven stars: I know thy works,that, a name, thou hast, that thou art living, and art, dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.2'>Become thou watchful, and strengthen the things that remain, that were about to die; for I have not found thy works fulfilled before my God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.3'>Remember, therefore, how thou hast received, and didst hear, and keep it and repent. If then thou shall not watch, I will have come as a thief, and in nowise shalt thou get to know, during what sort of hour, I will have come upon thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.4'>Nevertheless, thou hast a few names, in Sardis, which have not defiled their garments; and they shall walk with me in white, because they are, worthy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.5'>He that overcometh, shall, thus, array himself in white garments, and in nowise will I blot out his name, from the book of life; and I will confess his name before my Father, and before his messengers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.6'>He that hath an ear, let him hear what, the Spirit, is saying unto the assemblies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.7'>And, unto the messenger of the assembly, in Philadelphia, write:These things, saith he that is holy, he that is true, he that hath the key of David, he that openeth and no one shall shut, and shutteth and no one openeth:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.8'>I know thy works,lo! I have set before thee an open door, as to which, no one, can shut it,that thou hast, a little strength, and hast kept my word, and hast not denied my name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.9'>Lo! I give them of the synagogue of Satan, who are affirming themselves to be, Jews, and are not,but say what is false,lo! I will cause them, that they shall have come, and shall bow down before thy feet, and shall get to know that, I, loved thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.10'>Because thou didst keep my word of endurance, I also, will keep thee out of the hour of trial, which is about to come upon the whole habitable world, to try them that dwell upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.11'>I come quickly: hold fast that which thou hast, that, no one, take thy crown.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.12'>He that overcometh, I will make, him, a pillar in the sanctuary of my God, and, outside, shall he in nowise go forth any more; and I will write upon him the name of my God, and the name of the city of my God, the new Jerusalem, which cometh down out of heaven from my God, and   my new name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.13'>He that hath an ear, let him hear what, the Spirit, is saying unto the assemblies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.14'>And, unto the messenger of the assembly, in Laodicea, write:These things, saith the Amen, the faithful and true witness the beginning of the creation of God:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.15'>I know thy works;that neither, cold, art thou, nor hot: I would that, cold, thou hadst been, or hot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.16'>Thus, because, lukewarm, thou art, and neither hot nor cold, I am about to vomit thee out of my mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.17'>Because thou sayest, Rich, am I, and have become enriched, and, of nothing, have I need, and knowest not that, thou, art the wretched one, and pitiable, and destitute, and blind, and naked,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.18'>I counsel thee to buy of me, gold refined by fire, that thou mayest become rich,and white raiment, that thou mayest array thyself, and, the shame of thy nakedness, may not be made manifest,and eye-salve, to anoint thine eyes, that thou mayest see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.19'>I, as many as I tenderly love, I convict and put under discipline: be zealous, therefore, and repent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.20'>Lo! I am standing at the door, and knocking; if anyone shall hearken unto my voice, and open the door, I will come in unto him, and will sup with him, and, he, with, me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.21'>He that overcometh, I will give, unto him, to take his seat with me in my throne, as, I also, overcame, and took my seat with my Father in his throne.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.3.22'>He that hath an ear, let him hear what, the Spirit, is saying unto the assemblies.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.4'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.4.1'>After these things, I saw, and lo! a door set open in heaven; and, the first voice which I heard as of a trumpet, speaking with me, sayingCome up hither! and I will point out to thee the things which must needs come to pass. After these things,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.4.2'>straightway, I came to be in Spirit, and lo! a throne, stood in heaven, and, upon the throne,   one sitting;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.4.3'>and, he that was sitting,   a rainbow round about the throne, like in appearance unto an emerald,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.4.4'>And, round about the throne, were four and twenty thrones; and, upon the thrones, four and twenty elders sitting, clothed in white garments, and, upon their heads,   crowns of gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.4.5'>And, out of the throne, are coming forth lightnings, and voices, and thunderings; and   seven torches of fire, burning before the throne, which are the seven Spirits of God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.4.6'>and, before the throne,   four living creatures full of eyes, before and behind;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.4.7'>and, the first living creature,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.4.8'>and, the four living creatures, each one of them, have severally six wings, round about and within, full of eyes; and they, cease, not, day and night, sayingHoly! holy! holy! Lord, God, the Almighty,Who was, and Who is, and Who is coming.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.4.9'>And, whensoever the living creatures shall give glory, and honour, and thanksgiving, unto him that sitteth upon the throne, unto him that liveth unto the ages of ages,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.4.10'>the four and twenty elders will fall down before him that sitteth upon the throne, and do homage unto him that liveth unto the ages of ages,and will cast their crowns before the throne, saying</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.4.11'>Worthy, art thou, O Lord, and our God, to receive the glory, and the honour, and the power: because thou didst create all things, and, by reason of thy will, they were, and were created.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.5'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.5.1'>And I saw, upon the right hand of him that was sitting upon the throne, a scroll; written within, and on the back, sealed up with seven seals.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.5.2'>And I saw a mighty messenger, proclaiming with a loud voiceWho is worthy to open the scroll, and to unloose the seals thereof?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.5.3'>And, no one, was able, in heaven, or on earth, or under the earth, to open the scroll, or, to look thereon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.5.4'>And, I, began to weep much, because, no one, worthy, was found, to open the scroll, or, to look thereon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.5.5'>And, one of the elders, saith unto meDo not weep! Lo! the lion that is of the tribe of Judah, the root of David, hath overcome, to open the scroll and the seven seals thereof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.5.6'>And I saw, in the midst of the throne and of the four living creatures, and in the midst of the elders, a Lamb, standing, showing that it had been slain,having seven horns, and seven eyes, which are the  seven  Spirits of God sent forth into all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.5.7'>And he came, and at once took   out of the right hand of him that was sitting upon the throne.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.5.8'>And, when he took the scroll, the four living creatures, and the four-and-twenty elders, fell down before the Lamb, having, each one, a harp, and bowls of gold full of incense,which are the prayers of the saints;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.5.9'>and they sing a new song, sayingWorthy, art thou, to take the scroll and to open the seals thereof; because thou wast slain, and didst redeem unto God by thy blood   out of every tribe, and tongue, and people, and nation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.5.10'>And didst make them, unto our God, a kingdom and priests,and they reign on the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.5.11'>And I saw, and heard a voice of many messengers, round about the throne and the living creatures and the elders,and the number of them was myriads of myriads and thousands of thousands</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.5.12'>saying with a loud voiceWorthy, is the Lamb that hath been slain, to receive the power, and riches, and wisdom, and might, and honour, and glory, and blessing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.5.13'>And, every created thing which was in heaven, and upon the earth, and under the earth, and upon the sea, and, all the things in them, heard I, sayingUnto him that sitteth upon the throne, and unto the Lamb, be the blessing, and the honour, and the glory, and the dominion, unto the ages of ages!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.5.14'>And the four living creatures continued sayingAmen! And, the elders, fell down and did homage.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.6'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.1'>And I saw, when the Lamb opened one of the seven seals, and I heard one of the four living creatures saying, as with a voice of thunderGo!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.2'>And I saw, and lo! a white horse,and he that was sitting thereon holding a bow; and there was given unto him a crown, and he went forth conquering, and that he might conquer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.3'>And, when he opened the second seal, I heard the second living creature, sayingGo!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.4'>And there went forth another, a red horse,and, unto him that was sitting thereon, it was given,  unto him , to take away peace from the earth, and that, one another, they should slay; and there was given unto him a great sword.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.5'>And, when he opened the third seal, I heard the third living creature, sayingGo! And I saw, and lo! a black horse, and he that was sitting thereon holding a pair of balances in his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.6'>And I heard as a voice in the midst of the four living creatures, sayingA quart of wheat for, a denary, and three quarts of barley, for a denary,and, the oil and the wine, do not wrong.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.7'>And, when he opened the fourth seal, I heard the voice of the fourth living creature, sayingGo!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.8'>And I saw, and lo! a livid horse,and he that was sitting thereupon had for a name, Death, and, Hades, was following with him; and there was given unto them authority over the fourth of the earth, to slay with sword, and with famine, and with death, and by the wild beasts of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.9'>And, when he opened the fifth seal, I saw, beneath the altar, the souls of them who had been slain because of the word of God and because of the witness which they held.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.10'>And they cried out with a loud voice, sayingHow long, O Sovereign, the Holy and True, dost thou not vindicate and avenge our blood from them that dwell upon the earth?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.11'>And there was given to them, each one, a white robe, and it was bidden them, that they should rest yet a little whileuntil the number should be made full of their fellow-servants also, and their brethren, who were about to be slain as even, they.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.12'>And I saw, when he opened the sixth seal, that a, great earthquake, took place; and, the sun, became black as sackcloth of hair, and, the full moon, became as blood,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.13'>and, the stars of heaven, fell to the earth, as, a fig-tree, sheddeth her winter figs, when, by a great wind, it is shaken,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.14'>and, the heaven, was withdrawn, as a scroll rolling itself up, and, every mountain and island, out of their places, were shaken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.15'>And, the kings of the earth, and the great men, and the rulers of thousands, and the rich, and the mighty, and every bondman and freeman, hid themselves within the caves and within the rocks of the mountains;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.16'>and they say, unto the mountains and unto the rocksFall upon us, and hide us from the face of him that sitteth upon the throne, and from the anger of the Lamb;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.6.17'>Because the great day of their anger is come, and who is able to stand?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.7'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.1'>After this, I saw four messengers, standing at the four corners of the earth, holding fast the four winds of the earth, that no wind might blow upon the land, or upon the sea, or upon any tree.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.2'>And I saw another messenger, ascending from the rising of the sun, holding the seal of the Living God; and he cried out with a loud voice unto the four messengers unto whom it had been given to injure the land and the sea,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.3'>sayingDo not injure the land, or the sea, or the trees, until we have sealed the servants of our God upon their foreheads.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.4'>And I heard the number of the sealed,a hundred and forty-four thousand,sealed out of every tribe of the sons of Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.5'>Of the tribe of Judah, twelve thousand sealed, of the tribe of Reuben, twelve thousand, of the tribe of Gad, twelve thousand,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.6'>Of the tribe of Asher, twelve thousand, of the tribe of Naphtali, twelve thousand, of the tribe of Manasseh, twelve thousand,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.7'>Of the tribe of Simeon, twelve thousand, of the tribe of Levi, twelve thousand, of the tribe of Issachar, twelve thousand,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.8'>Of the tribe of Zebulun, twelve thousand, of the tribe of Joseph, twelve thousand, of the tribe of Benjamin, twelve thousand, sealed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.9'>After these things, I saw, and 1o! a great multitude,which, to number it! no one was able,of every nation, and   tribes, and peoples, and tongues; standing before the throne, and before the Lamb; arrayed in white robes, and palm-branches in their hands;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.10'>and they cry out with a loud voice, sayingSalvation unto our God who sitteth upon the throne, and unto the Lamb!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.11'>And, all the messengers, were standing round about the throne and the elders and the four living creatures; and they fell down before the throne upon their faces, and rendered homage unto God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.12'>sayingAmen! The blessing, and the glory, and the wisdom, and the thanksgiving, and the honour, and the power, and the might,be unto our God, unto the ages of ages.  Amen !</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.13'>And one of the elders began, saying unto meThese who are arrayed in white robes, who are they? and whence came they?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.14'>And I at once said to himMy lord! thou, knowest! And he said unto meThese, are they who come out of the great tribulation, and they washed their robes, and made them white in the blood of the Lamb;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.15'>For this cause, are they before the throne of God, and are rendering divine service unto him, day and night, in his sanctuary; and he that sitteth upon the throne shall spread his tent over them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.16'>They shall hunger no more, neither thirst any more, neither in any wise shall the sun fall upon them, nor any burning heat;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.7.17'>Because, the Lamb that is in the midst of the throne, shall shepherd them, and shall lead them unto lifes fountains of waters; and God shall wipe away every tear out of their eyes.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.8'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.8.1'>And, as soon as he opened the seventh seal, there came to be silence in heaven, as it were half an hour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.8.2'>And I saw the seven messengers which, before God, do stand; and there were given unto them seven trumpets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.8.3'>And, another messenger, came, and took his stand at the altar, having a censer of gold: and there was given unto him much incense, that he might give   unto the prayers of all the saints, upon the altar of gold that is before the throne.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.8.4'>And the smoke of the incense went up, with the prayers of the saints, out of the hand of the messenger before God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.8.5'>And the messenger at once took the censer, and filled it from the fire of the altar, and cast unto the earth; and there came to be thunderings, and voices, and lightnings, and an earthquake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.8.6'>And, the seven messengers who had the seven trumpets, prepared themselves, that they might sound.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.8.7'>And, the first, sounded; and there came to be hail and fire mingled with blood, and it was cast unto the earth; and, the third of the earth, was burned up, and, the third of the trees, was burned up, and, all green herbage, was burned up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.8.8'>And, the second messenger, sounded; and, as it were a great mountain burning with fire, was cast into the sea; and the third of the sea became blood,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.8.9'>and the third of the creatures which were in the sea, which had life, died, the third of the ships, was destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.8.10'>And, the third messenger, sounded; and there fell, out of heaven, a great star, burning as a torch, and it fell upon the third of the rivers, and upon the fountains of waters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.8.11'>And, the name of the star, is called Wormwood; and the third of the waters became wormwood, and many of the men died of the waters, because they were made bitter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.8.12'>And, the fourth messenger, sounded; and the third of the sun was smitten, and the third of the moon, and the third of the stars,in order that the third of them might be darkened, and the day might not shine for the third of it, and the night, in like manner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.8.13'>And I saw, and I heard one eagle, flying in mid-heaven, saying with a loud voiceWoe! woe! woe! unto them that are dwelling upon the earth, by reason of the remaining voices of the trumpet, of the three messengers who are about to sound.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.9'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.1'>And, the fifth messenger, sounded; and I saw a star, out of heaven, fallen unto the earth, and there was given unto him the key of the shaft of the abyss.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.2'>And he opened the shaft of the abyss; and there came up a smoke out of the shaft, as the smoke of a great furnace, and the sun and the air were darkened, by reason of the smoke of the shaft.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.3'>And, out of the smoke, came forth, locusts, upon the earth; and there was given unto them licence, as the scorpions of the earth have licence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.4'>And it was bidden them that they should not injure the herbage of the earth, nor any green thing, nor any tree,but only the men who have not the seal of God upon their foreheads.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.5'>And it was given unto them, that they should not slay them, but that they should be tormented five months; and, the torture of them, was as of a scorpions torture, whensoever it smiteth a man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.6'>And, in those days, shall men seek death, and in nowise shall find it, and shall covet to die, and death fleeth from them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.7'>And, the likenesses of the locusts, were like unto horses prepared for battle; and, upon their heads, as it were crowns, like unto gold, and, their faces, were as the faces of men,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.8'>and, they had hair, as the hair of women, and, their teeth, were, as of lions,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.9'>and they had breastplates as breastplates of iron, and, the sound of their wings, was as the sound of chariots of many horses, running into battle;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.10'>and they have tails like unto scorpions, and stings, and, in their tails, is their licence to injure men five months.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.11'>They have over them, as king, the messenger of the abyss, whose name, in Hebrew, is Abaddon  "=Destroyer" , and, in the Greek, he hath for name, Destroyer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.12'>The first, Woe, hath passed away, lo! there come, yet, two, Woes, after these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.13'>And, the sixth messenger, sounded; and I heard one voice, from among the horns of the altar of gold which is before God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.14'>saying unto the sixth messenger, who was holding the trumpetLoose the four messengers, who are bound at the great river Euphrates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.15'>And the four messengers were loosed, who had been prepared for the hour, and day, and month, and year, that they should slay the third of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.16'>And, the number of the armies of the horsemen, was twice ten thousand times ten thousandI heard the number of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.17'>And, thus, saw I the horses in the vision,and them who were sitting upon them, having breastplates as of fire and hyacinth and brimstone;and, the heads of the horses, were as heads of lions, and, out of their mouths, come forth fire and smoke and brimstone:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.18'>by these three plagues, were slain, the third part of mankind, by reason of the fire and the smoke and the brimstone, that proceedeth out of their mouths;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.19'>for, the licence of the horses, is, in their mouth, and in their tails, for, their tails, are like unto serpents, having heads, and, with them, they injure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.20'>And, the rest of mankind who were not slain by these plagues, repented not of the works of their hands,that they should not do homage unto the demons, nor unto the idols of gold and of silver and of copper and of stone and of wood, which can neither see nor hear nor walk;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.9.21'>Neither repented they of their murders, or of their sorceries, or of their lewdnesses, or of their thefts.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.10'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.10.1'>And I saw another, a mighty messenger, descending out of heaven,arrayed with a cloud, and, the rainbow, was upon his head, and, his face, was as the sun, and, his feet, were as pillars of fire,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.10.2'>and   holding in his hand a little scroll, opened; and he set his right foot upon the sea, and his left upon the land,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.10.3'>and cried out with a loud voice, just as a lion, roareth. And, when he cried out, the seven thunders uttered their own voices.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.10.4'>And, when the seven thunders had spoken, I was about to write, and I heard a voice out of heaven, sayingSeal up the things which the seven thunders have uttered, and do not write, them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.10.5'>And, the messenger, whom I saw standing upon the sea and upon the land, lifted up his right hand unto heaven,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.10.6'>and sware, by him that liveth unto the ages of ages, who created heaven, and the things that are therein, and the earth, and the things that are therein,  and the sea, and the things that are therein,  Delay, no longer, shall there be;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.10.7'>but, in the days of the sounding of the seventh messenger, as soon as he is about to blow his trumpet, then shall have been completed the sacred secret of God as he told the good-news unto his own servants the prophets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.10.8'>And, the voice which I had heard out of heaven,   talking with me; and sayingGo take the opened scroll, that is in the hand of the messenger who is standing upon the sea and upon the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.10.9'>And I went away unto the messenger, asking him to give me the little scroll; and he saith unto meTake it, and eat it up; and it shall embitter thy belly, but, in thy mouth, shall be sweet as honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.10.10'>And I took the little scroll out of the hand of the messenger, and did eat it up; and it was, in my mouth, as honey, sweet, and, when I had eaten it, embittered was my belly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.10.11'>And they say unto meIt behoveth thee again to prophesy against peoples and nations and tongues, and many kings.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.11'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.1'>And there was given unto me a reed, like unto a staff, sayingRise, and measure the Sanctuary of God, and the altar, and them who are doing homage therein;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.2'>and, the court that is outside the Sanctuary, cast thou outside, and do not measure, it, because it hath been given unto the nations, and, the holy city, shall they tread under foot, forty and two months.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.3'>And I will give unto my two witnesses, that they shall prophesy, a thousand two hundred and sixty days, arrayed in sackcloth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.4'>These, are the two olive-trees, and the two lamps, which, before the Lord of the earth, do stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.5'>And, if any one, upon them, chooseth to inflict injury, fire, cometh forth out of their mouth, and devoureth their enemies; and, if anyone shall choose, upon them, to inflict injury, thus, must he be slain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.6'>These, have authority to shut heaven, in order that, no rain, be moistening in the days of their prophesying; and, authority, have they, over the waters, to be turning them into blood, and to smite the land, with any manner of plague, as often as they will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.7'>And, as soon as they have completed their witnessing, the wild-beast that is to come up out of the abyss, will make war with them, and overcome them, and slay them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.8'>And their dead bodies   upon the broadway of the great city, the which is called, spiritually, Sodom and Egypt, where, their Lord also was crucified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.9'>And   of the peoples, and tribes, and tongues, and nations, see, their dead bodies three days and a half, and, their dead bodies, do they not suffer to be put into a tomb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.10'>And, they who are dwelling upon the earth, rejoice over them, and make merry, and, gifts, will they send one to another,because, these two prophets, tormented them that were dwelling upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.11'>And, after  the  three days and a half, a spirit of life from God, entered within them, and they stood upon their feet; and, great fear, fell upon them who were beholding them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.12'>And they heard a loud voice out of heaven, saying unto themCome up hither! And they went up into heaven, in the cloud, and, their enemies, beheld them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.13'>And, in that hour, there came to be a great earthquake; and, the tenth of the city, fell, and there were slain, in the earthquake, names of menseven thousand. And, the rest, became, greatly afraid, and gave glory unto the God of heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.14'>The second Woe, hath passed away,lo! the third Woe, cometh speedily.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.15'>And, the seventh messenger, sounded; and there came to be loud voices in heaven, sayingThe kingdom of the world, hath become   of our Lord and of his Christ, and he shall reign unto the ages of ages.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.16'>And, the twenty-four elders who, before God, do sit upon their thrones, fell down upon their faces, and rendered homage unto God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.17'>sayingWe give thanks unto thee, O Lord God, the Almighty, Who is, and Who was; because thou hast taken thy great power, and hast become king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.18'>And, the nations, were angered; and thine anger, came, and the fit time of the dead, to be vindicated, and to give their reward unto thy servants the prophets, and unto the saints, and unto them who revere thy namethe small and the great, and to despoil them who were despoiling the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.11.19'>And the sanctuary of God which is in heaven, was opened, and the ark of his covenant in his sanctuary, appeared, and there came to be lightnings, and voices, and thunderings, and an earthquake, and great hail.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.12'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.1'>And, a great sign, appeared in heaven: a woman arrayed with the sun, and, the moon, beneath her feet, and, upon her head, a crown of twelve stars;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.2'>and she was with child, and crieth out, being in pangs and in anguish to bring forth?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.3'>And there appeared another sign in heaven; and lo! a great red dragon,having seven heads and ten horns, and, upon his heads, seven diadems;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.4'>and, his tail, draweth the third part of the stars of heaven, and did cast them to the earth. And, the dragon, stood before the woman who was about to bring forth, that, as soon as she should bring forth, he might devour, her child.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.5'>And she brought forth a son, a manchild, who was about to shepherd all the nations with a sceptre of iron; and her child was caught away unto God and unto his throne.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.6'>And, the woman, fled into the desert, where she hath a place prepared of God, that, there, they should nourish her a thousand, two hundred, and sixty days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.7'>And there came to be war in heaven: Michael and his messengers   to war with the dragon; and, the dragon, fought, and his messengers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.8'>and he prevailed not, neither was place found for them, any longer, in heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.9'>And the great dragon was cast out,the ancient serpent, he that is called Adversary and the Satan, that deceiveth the whole habitable world,he was cast to the earth, and his messengers, with him, were cast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.10'>And I heard a loud voice in heaven, sayingNow, hath come the salvation, and the power, and the kingdom of our God, and the authority of his Christ; because the accuser of our brethren hath been cast out, who was accusing them before our God day and night;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.11'>And, they, overcame him by reason of the blood of the Lamb, and by reason of their witnessing word, and they loved not their life, even unto death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.12'>For this cause, be joyful, O heavens, and ye who, therein, are tabernacling. Woe! unto the earth, and the sea, because the Adversary hath come down unto you, having great wrathknowing that, but a little season, he hath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.13'>And, when the dragon saw that he was cast to the earth, he pursued the woman who had brought forth the manchild.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.14'>And there were given unto the woman the two wings of the great eagle, that she might fly into the desert, into her place,where she is nourished, a season and seasons and half a season, from the face of the serpent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.15'>And the serpent cast out of his mouth, after the woman, water as a river, that he might cause her to be carried away by the stream.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.16'>And the earth helped the woman, and the earth opened her mouth, and swallowed up the river which the dragon cast out of his mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.12.17'>And the dragon was angered against the woman, and went away to make war with the rest of her seedwith them who were keeping the commandments of God, and holding the witness of Jesus;and he stood upon the sand of the sea.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.13'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.1'>And I saw, out of the sea, a wild-beast coming up; having ten horns, and seven heads, and, upon his horns, ten diadems, and, upon his head, names of blasphemy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.2'>And, the beast which I saw, was like unto a leopard; and, his feet, as of a bear, and, his mouth, as the mouth of a lion. And the dragon gave unto him his power, and his throne, and great authority.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.3'>And   one of his heads, showing that it had been slain unto death, and, the stroke of his death, was healed. And the whole earth marveled after the wild-beast,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.4'>and did homage unto the dragon, because he gave his authority unto the wild-beast; and they did homage unto the wild-beast, sayingWho is like unto the wild-beast? and Who can make war with him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.5'>And there was given unto him, a mouth speaking great things and blasphemies; and it was given unto him to act, forty and two months.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.6'>And he opened his mouth for blasphemy against God, to blaspheme his name, and his tent,them, who, in heaven were tabernacling.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.7'> And it was given unto him, to make war with the saints, and to overcome them;  and there was given him, authority against every tribe and people and tongue and nation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.8'>And all they who are dwelling upon the earth will do homage unto him,  whose name is not written in the scroll of life of the Lamb slain from the foundation of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.9'>If any-one hath an ear: let him hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.10'>If anyone</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.11'>And I saw another wild-beast, coming up out of the earth; and he had two horns, like unto a lamb, and began speaking as a dragon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.12'>And, all the authority of the first wild-beast, he useth before him; and causeth the earth, and them who, therein, are dwelling, that they shall do homage unto the first wild-beast, whose stroke of death, was healed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.13'>And he doeth great signs, so that, even fire, he causeth to be coming down unto the earth before men;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.14'>and he deceiveth them who are dwelling upon the earth, by reason of the signs which it was given him to do before the wild-beast,saying unto them who are dwelling upon the earth, that they should make an image unto the wild-beast who hath the stroke of the sword, and yet did live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.15'>And it was given unto it, to give spirit unto the image of the wild-beast, in order that the image of the wild-beast should both speak and should cause that, as many as should not do homage unto the image of the wild-beast, should be slain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.16'>And he causeth allthe small and the great, and the rich and the poor, and the free and the bond,that they should give unto them a mark, upon their right hand or upon their forehead;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.17'> and  that no one should be able to buy or to sell, save he that hath the mark, the name of the beast, or the number of his name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.13.18'>Here, is, wisdom: he that hath understanding, let him count the number of the beast, for it is, the number of a man; and, his number, is 666.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.14'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.1'>And I saw, and lo! the Lamb, standing upon the mount Zion,and, with him, a hundred and forty-four thousand, having his name and his Fathers name written upon their foreheads.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.2'>And I heard a sound out of heaven, as the sound of many waters, and as the sound of, loud thunders; and, the sound which I heard, was as of harp-singers harping with their harps,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.3'>And they sing as it were a new song before the throne, and before the four living creatures and the elders. And, no one, was able to learn the song, save the hundred and forty-four thousand, who had been redeemed from the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.4'>These, are they, who with women, were not defiled, for they are, virgin. These, are they who follow the Lamb whithersoever he is going. These, were redeemed from mankind, as a firstfruit unto God and the Lamb;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.5'>and, in their mouth, was found no falsehood,faultless, they are.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.6'>And I saw another messenger, flying in mid-heaven, having an age-abiding glad-message to announce unto them who are dwelling upon the earth, even unto every nation and tribe and tongue and people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.7'>saying with a loud voice,Fear God and give him glory, because the hour of his judging is come; and do homage unto him that made heaven and the earth and sea and fountains of waters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.8'>And, another, a second  messenger  followed, sayingFallen! fallen! is Babylon the great, who, of the wine of the wrath of her lewdness, hath caused all the nations to drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.9'>And, another, a third messenger, followed them, saying with a loud voiceIf anyone doeth homage unto the beast and his image, and receiveth a mark upon his forehead, or upon his hand,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.10'>he also, shall drink of the wine of the wrath of God, which is prepared, unmixed, in the cup of his anger;and he shall be tormented with fire and brimstone, before holy messengers and before the Lamb;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.11'>And, the smoke of their torment, unto ages of ages, ascendeth; And they have no rest day or night, who do homage unto the beast and his image, or if anyone receiveth the mark of his name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.12'>Here, is, the endurance of the saints,they who keep the commandments of God and the faith of Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.13'>And I heard a voice out of heaven, sayingWrite! Happy, the dead who, in the Lord, do die, from henceforth. Yea! (saith the Spirit) that they may rest from their toils, for, their works, do follow with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.14'>And I saw, and lo! a white cloud, and, upon the cloud, one sitting like unto a son of man, having, upon his head, a crown of gold, and, in his hand, a sharp sickle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.15'>And, another messenger, came forth out of the sanctuary, crying out with a loud voice, unto him that was sitting upon the cloudThrust in thy sickle, and reap; because the hour to reap is come, because the harvest of the earth is ripe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.16'>And he that was sitting upon the cloud, thrust in, his sickle upon the earth; and the earth was reaped.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.17'>And, another messenger, came forth out of the sanctuary that is in heaven,he also, having a sharp sickle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.18'>And, another messenger,  came forth  out of the altar, who hath authority over the fire,and called out with a loud voice, unto him who had the sharp sickle, sayingThrust in thy sharp sickle, and gather the clusters of the vine of the earth; because the grapes thereof are fully ripe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.19'>And the messenger, thrust in, his sickle into the earth, and gathered the vine of the earth, and cast   into the great wine-press of the wrath of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.14.20'>And the wine-press was trodden outside the city, and there came forth blood out of the wine-press, even unto the bits of the horses, at a distance of a thousand six hundred furlongs.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.15'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.15.1'>And I saw another sign in heaven, great and marvellous,seven messengers having seven plagues, the last, because, in them, was ended the wrath of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.15.2'>And I saw as a glassy sea mingled with fire, and them who escape victorious from the beast, and from his image, and from the number of his name, standing upon the glassy sea, having harps of God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.15.3'>and they sing the song of Moses the servant of God and the song of the Lamb, sayingGreat and marvelous, are thy works, Lord, God, the Almighty! Righteous and true, are thy ways, O King of the ages!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.15.4'>Who shall in anywise not be put in fear, O Lord, and glorify thy name,because, alone, full of lovingkindness; because, all the nations, will have come, and will do homage before thee, because, thy righteous deeds, were made manifest?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.15.5'>And, after these things, I saw, and the sanctuary of The Tent of Witness in heaven, was opened;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.15.6'>And the seven messengers who had the seven plagues, came forth, out of the sanctuary clothed with a   stone, pure, bright, and girt about the breasts with girdles of gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.15.7'>And, one of the four living creatures, gave, unto the seven messengers, seven golden bowls, full of the wrath of God who liveth unto the ages of ages.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.15.8'>And the sanctuary was filled with smoke by reason of the glory of God, and by reason of his power; and, no one, was able to enter into the sanctuary, until the seven plagues of the seven messengers should be ended.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.16'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.1'>And I heard aloud voice, out of the sanctuary, saying unto the seven messengersGo, and be pouring out the seven bowls of the wrath of God unto the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.2'>And the first departed, and poured out his bowl unto the earth; and there came to be a baneful and painful ulcer, upon the men who had the mark of the beast, and them who were doing homage unto his image.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.3'>And, the second, poured out his bowl into the sea; and it became blood, as of a dead man, and, every living soul, diedas regardeth the things in the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.4'>And, the third, poured out his bowl into the rivers, and the fountains of waters; and they became blood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.5'>And I heard the messenger of the waters, sayingRighteous, art thou Who art, and Who wast, Who art full of lovingkindness,in that, these things, thou hast adjudged;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.6'>Because, blood of saints and prophets, poured they out, and, blood, unto them, hast thou given to drink: Worthy, they are!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.7'>And I heard the altar, sayingYea! Lord, God, the Almighty: True and righteous, are thy judgments!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.8'>And, the fourth, poured out his bowl upon the sun; and it was given unto it, to scorch mankind with fire;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.9'>and mankind were scorched with a great scorching heat, and they blasphemed the name of God who had authority over these plagues, and repented not to give him glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.10'>And, the fifth, poured out his bowl upon the throne of the beast; and his kingdom became darkened, and they began to gnaw their tongues by reason of the pain,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.11'>and they blasphemed the God of heaven, by reason of their pain, and by reason of their ulcers, and repented not of their works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.12'>And, the sixth, poured out his bowl upon the great river:  the  Euphrates; and the water thereof, was dried up, that the way might be prepared, of the kings who were from the rising of the sun.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.13'>And I saw, out of the mouth of the dragon, and out of the mouth of the beast, and out of the mouth of the false-prophet, three impure spirits, as frogs;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.14'>for they are spirits of demons, doing signs, which are to go forth unto the kings of the whole habitable earth, to gather them together unto the battle of the great day of God the Almighty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.15'>Lo! I come as a thief! Happy, he that is watching, and keeping his garments, lest, naked, he be walking, and they see his shame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.16'>And he gathered them together unto the place that is called, in Hebrew, Har Magedon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.17'>And, the seventh, poured out his bowl upon the air.And there came forth a loud voice out of the sanctuary, from the throne, sayingAccomplished!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.18'>And there came to be lightnings, and voices, and thunders; and, a great earthquake, took place,such as had never taken place since men came to be on the earth,such a mighty earthquake, so great;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.19'>and the great city became   into three parts, and the cities of the nations fell; and, Babylon the Great, was brought into remembrance before God, to give unto her the cup of the wine of the wrath of his anger;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.20'>and, every island, fled, and, mountains, were not found.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.16.21'>And, great hail, as talents, cometh down out of heaven upon mankind; and men blasphemed God, by reason of the plague of hail,because the plague thereof was, exceeding great.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.17'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.1'>And one of the seven messengers who had the seven bowls came, and spake with me, sayingHither! I will point out to thee the judgment of the great harlot, who sitteth upon many waters,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.2'>with whom the kings of the earth committed lewdness,and they who were dwelling upon the earth were made drunk with the wine of her lewdness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.3'>And he carried me away into a desert, in spirit. And I saw a woman, sitting upon a scarlet wild-beast full of names of blasphemy, having seven heads and ten horns.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.4'>And, the woman, was arrayed with purple and scarlet, and decked with gold and precious stone and pearls,having a cup of gold in her hand, full of abominations and the impurities of her lewdness;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.5'>and, upon her forehead, a name written, a secret: Babylon the great, the Mother of the Harlots and of the Abominations of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.6'>And I saw the woman, drunk with the blood of the saints, and with the blood of the witnesses of Jesus. And I was astonished, when I beheld her, with great astonishment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.7'>And the messenger said unto meWherefore wast thou astonished? I, will tell thee the secret of the woman, and of the wild-beast that carrieth her, which hath the seven heads and the ten horns.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.8'>The wild-beast which thou sawest, was, and is not, and is about to come up out of the abyss, and into, destruction, goeth away. And they who are dwelling upon the earth whose name is not written upon the book of life from the foundation of the world, will be astonished, when they see the wild-beast, because it was, and is not, and shall be present.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.9'>Here, is the mind that hath wisdom. The seven heads, are, seven mountains, whereupon the woman sitteth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.10'>and they are, seven kings: the five, have fallen, the one, is, the other, hath not yet come; and, whensoever he shall come, a little while, must he remain,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.11'>and the wild-beast which was and is not. And he, is an eighth, and is, of the seven,and, into destruction, goeth away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.12'>And, the ten horns which thou sawest, are, ten kings,who, indeed, have not received, sovereignty, as yet, but, authority, as kings, for one hour, shall receive, with the wild-beast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.13'>These, have, one mind, and, their power and authority, unto the wild-beast, they give.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.14'>These, with the Lamb, will make war; and, the Lamb, will overcome them, because he is, Lord of lords, and King of kings,and, they who are with him, are called and chosen and faithful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.15'>And he saith unto meThe waters which thou sawest, where the harlot sitteth, are, peoples and multitudes, and nations and tongues.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.16'>And the ten horns which thou sawest, and the wild-beast, these, shall hate the harlot, and, desolate, shall make her, and naked, and, her flesh, shall they eat, and, herself, shall they burn up with fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.17'>For, God, hath put into their hearts, to do his mind, and to do one mind,and to give their sovereignty unto the wild-beast, until the words of God shall be completed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.17.18'>And, the woman whom thou sawest, is the great city, which hath sovereignty over the kings of the earth.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.18'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.1'>After these things, I saw another messenger, coming down out of heaven,having great authority; and, the earth, was illumined with his glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.2'>And he cried out, with a mighty voice, sayingFallen! fallen! is Babylon the Great, and hath become a habitation of demons, and a prison of every impure spirit, and a prison of every impure and hated bird;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.3'>Because, by reason  of the wine  of the wrath of her lewdness, have all the nations fallen, and, the kings of the earth, with her, did commit lewdness, and, the merchants of the earth, by reason of the power of her wantonness, waxed rich.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.4'>And I heard another voice out of heaven, sayingCome forth, my people, out of her,that ye may have no fellowship with her sins, and, of her plagues, that ye may not receive;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.5'>because her sins were joined together as far as heaven, and God hath remembered her unrighteous deeds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.6'>Render ye unto her, as, she also, rendered, and double  the  double, according to her works,in the cup wherein she mixed, mix, unto her, double,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.7'>As much as she glorified herself, and waxed wanton, so much give, unto her, torment and grief:because, in her heart, she saithI sit a Queen, and, widow, am I not, and, grief, in nowise shall I see!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.8'>Therefore, in one day, shall have come her plagues,death and grief and famine; and, with fire, shall she be burned up;because, mighty, is the  Lord  God who hath judged her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.9'>And they shall weep and wail over hershall the kings of the earth who, with her, committed lewdness and waxed wanton,as soon as they see the smoke of her burning,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.10'>afar off, standing, because of their fear of her torment, sayingAlas! alas! the great city! Babylon, the mighty city! That, in one hour, hath come thy judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.11'>And, the merchants of the earth, weep and grieve over her, because, their cargo, no one, buyeth any more:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.12'>cargo of gold, and silver, and precious stone, and pearls, and fine linen, and purple, and silk, and scarlet, and all thyine wood, and every article of ivory, and every article of wood most precious, and of copper, and of iron, and of marble,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.13'>and cinnamon, and spice, and incense, and unguent, and frankincense, and wine, and oil, and fine flour, and wheat, and cattle, and sheep, and   of horses, and of chariots, and of bodies, and lives of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.14'>And, the fruit of the coveting of thy soul, hath departed from thee, and, all things rich and bright, have perished from thee; and, no more, in anywise, for them, shall they seek.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.15'>The merchants of these things, who were enriched by her, afar off, shall stand, because of their fear of her torment, weeping, and grieving,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.16'>as they sayAlas! alas! the great city! She that was arrayed in fine linen, and purple, and scarlet, and decked with gold, and precious stone, and pearl,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.17'>That, in one hour, hath been laid waste, such great wealth as this! And, every pilot, and every passenger, and mariners, and as many as, by the sea, carry on traffic, afar off did stand,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.18'>and they cried out, seeing the smoke of her burning, sayingWhat city is like unto the great city?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.19'>And they cast dust upon their heads, and cried out, weeping and grieving, sayingAlas! alas! the great city! Whereby were made rich all that had ships in the sea, by reason of her costliness,that, in one hour, she hath been laid waste!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.20'>Be glad over her, thou heaven! And ye saints, and ye apostles, and ye prophets! For that God hath exacted your vindication from her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.21'>And one mighty messenger lifted a stone, as it were a great millstone, and cast it into the sea, sayingThus, with main force, shall be cast down, Babylon the great city,and in nowise be found any more;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.22'>And sound of harp-singers, and musicians, and flute-players, and trumpeters,in nowise be heard in thee any more; and any artisan  of any art ,in nowise be found in thee any more; and sound of millstone,in nowise be found in thee any more;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.23'>And light of lamp,in nowise shine in thee any more; and voice of bridegroom and bride,in nowise be heard in thee any more; because, thy merchants, were the great ones of the earth, because, with thy sorcery, were all the nations deceived:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.18.24'>And, in her, blood of prophets and saints, was found,and of all who had been slain upon the earth.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.19'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.1'>After these things, I heard as it were, a loud voice of a great multitude in heaven, sayingHallelujah! The salvation and the glory and the power of our God!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.2'>Because, true and righteous, are his judgments; because he hath judged the great harlot, who, indeed, corrupted the earth with her lewdness,and hath avenged the blood of his servants, at her hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.3'>And, a second time, have they saidHallelujah! And, her smoke, ascendeth unto ages of ages.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.4'>And the twenty-four elders and the four living creatures, fell down, and did homage unto God, who sitteth upon the throne, sayingAmen! Hallelujah!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.5'>And, a voice, from the throne, came forth, sayingBe giving praise unto our God, all ye his servants, ye that revere him, the small and the great.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.6'>And I heard as a voice of a great multitude, and as a voice of many waters, and as a voice of mighty thunderings, sayingHallelujah! Because the Lord,  our  God, the Almighty, hath become king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.7'>Let us rejoice and exult, and give glory unto him, because the marriage of the Lamb, is come, and, his wife, hath made herself ready;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.8'>and it hath been given unto her, that she should be arrayed in fine linen, bright, pure, for, the fine linen, is, the righteous acts of the saints.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.9'>And he saith unto meWrite! Happy, they who, unto the marriage supper of the Lamb, have been bidden! And he saith unto meThese words, are, true   of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.10'>And I fell down at his feet, to do him homage; and he saith unto meSee!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.11'>And I saw heaven, set open, and lo! a white horse, and, he that was sitting thereon,  called  Faithful, and True; and, in righteousness, doth he judge and make war;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.12'>and, his eyes, are a flame of fire, and, upon his head, are many diadems, having, a name, written, which, no one, knoweth, but himself,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.13'>and arrayed with a mantle sprinkled with blood, and his name hath been calledThe Word of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.14'>And, the armies which were in heaven, were following him, upon white horses, clothed with fine linen, white, pure;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.15'>and, out of his mouth, is going forth a sharp sword, that, therewith, he may smite the nations,and, he, shall shepherd them with a sceptre of iron, and, he, treadeth the wine-press of the wrath of the anger of God the Almighty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.16'>And he hath, upon his mantle and upon his thigh, a name, writtenKing of kings, and Lord of lords.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.17'>And I saw one messenger, standing in the sun, and he cried out with a loud voice, saying, unto all the birds that fly in mid-heaven,Hither! be gathered together unto the great supper of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.18'>that ye may eat the flesh of kings, and the flesh of captains, and the flesh of mighty men, and the flesh of horses, and of them who sit upon them, and the flesh of all, both free and bond, and small and great.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.19'>And I saw the wild-beast, and the kings of the earth, and their armies, gathered togetherto make war with him who was sitting upon the horse, and with his army.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.20'>And the wild-beast, was taken, and, with him, the false prophet who wrought the signs before him, whereby he deceived them who received the mark of the wild-beast and them who were doing homage unto his image,alive, were they two cast into the lake of fire that burneth with brimstone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.19.21'>And, the rest, were slain with the sword of him that was sitting upon the horse, which went forth out of his mouth, and, all the birds, were filled with their flesh.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.20'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.20.1'>And I saw a messenger, coming down out of heaven, having the key of the abyss, and a great chain upon his hand;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.20.2'>and he laid hold of the dragon, the ancient serpent, who is Adversary and the Accuser, and bound him for a thousand years,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.20.3'>and cast him into the abyss, and fastened and sealed   over him,that he might not deceive the nations any more, until the thousand years, should be ended: after these, must he be loosed for a short time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.20.4'>And I saw thrones, and they sat upon them, and sentence of judgment was given unto them; and   the souls of them who had been beheaded because of the witness of Jesus and because of the word of God, and such as had not done homage unto the wild-beast or unto his image, nor had received the mark upon their forehead or upon their hand; and they lived and reigned with the Christ, for a thousand years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.20.5'>The rest of the dead, lived not, until the thousand years, were ended. This, is the first resurrection.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.20.6'>Happy and holy, is he that hath part in the first resurrection: upon these, the second death, hath no authority; but they shall be priests of God and of the Christ, and shall reign with him for the thousand years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.20.7'>And, as soon as the thousand years, shall be ended, the Accuser shall be loosed out of his prison,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.20.8'>and will go forth to deceive the nations that are in the four corners of the earth, the Gog and Magog, to gather them together unto the battlethe number of whom, is as the sand of the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.20.9'>And they came up over the breadth of the land, and surrounded the camp of the saints, and the beloved city. And there came down fire out of heaven, and devoured them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.20.10'>and, the Adversary that had been deceiving them, was cast into the lake of fire and brimstone, where</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.20.11'>And I saw a great white throne, and him that was sitting thereon, from whose face fled the earth and heaven, and, place, was not found for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.20.12'>And I saw the dead, the great and the small, standing before the throne; and, books, were opened, and, another book, was opened, which is, the book, of life; and the dead, were judged, out of the things written in the books, according to their works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.20.13'>And the sea gave up the dead that were in it, and, death and hades, gave up the dead that were in them; and they were judged, each one, according to their works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.20.14'>And, death and hades, were cast into the lake of fire. This, is, the second deaththe lake of fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.20.15'>And, if anyone was not found, in the book of life, written, he was cast into the lake of fire.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.21'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.1'>And I saw a new heaven and a new earth; for, the first heaven and the first earth, have passed away, and, the sea, is no more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.2'>And, the holy city, new Jerusalem, saw I coming down out of heaven from God, prepared as a bride adorned for her husband.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.3'>And I heard a loud voice out of the throne, sayingLo! the tent of God, is with men, and he will tabernacle with them, and, they, shall be, his peoples, and, he, shall be, God with them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.4'>And he will wipe away every tear out of their eyes,and, death, shall be no more, and grief and outcry and pain shall be no more: the first things, have passed away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.5'>And he that was sitting upon the throne said Lo! I make all things, new. And he saithWrite! because, these words, are, faithful and true.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.6'>And he said unto meAccomplished! I, am the A, and the Z, the Beginning and the End: I, unto him that is thirsting, will give of the fountain of the water of life, freely:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.7'>He that overcometh, shall inherit these things,And I will be, to him, a God, and, he, shall be, to me, a son;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.8'>But, as for the timid, and disbelieving, and abominable, and murderers, and fornicators, and sorcerers, and idolaters, and all the false, their part, is in the lake that burneth with fire and brimstone,which is the second death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.9'>And there came one of the seven messengers which had the seven bowls, that were full of the seven last plagues, and spake with me, saying Hither! I will point out to thee the bride, the wife of the Lamb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.10'>And he carried me away, in spirit, unto a mountain great and high, and pointed out to me the holy city, Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.11'>having the glory of God,her lustre, like unto a stone most precious, as a jasper stone, shining as crystal;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.12'>having a wall great and high, having twelve gates, and, at the gates, twelve messengers, and names inscribed, which are   of the twelve tribes of the sons of Israel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.13'>on the east, three gates, and, on the north, three gates, and, on the south, three gates, and, on the west, three gates;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.14'>and, the wall of the city, having twelve foundations, and, upon them, twelve names of the twelve apostles of the Lamb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.15'>And, he that was talking with me, had, for a measure, a reed of gold, that he might measure the city, and the gates thereof, and the wall thereof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.16'>And, the city, four-square, lieth, and, the length thereof, is as great as the breadth. And he measured the city, with the reed,twelve thousand furlongs: the length, and the breadth, and the height thereof, are, equal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.17'>And he measured the wall thereof,a hundred and forty-four cubits: the measure of a man, which is   of a messenger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.18'>And, the structure of the wall thereof, was jasper, and, the city, was pure gold, like unto pure glass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.19'>The foundations of the wall of the city, with every precious stone were adorned: the first foundation, was jasper, the second, sapphire, the third, chalcedony, the fourth, emerald,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.20'>the fifth, sardonyx, the sixth, sardius, the seventh, chrysolite, the eighth, beryl, the ninth, topaz, the tenth, chrysoprase, the eleventh, hyacinth, the twelfth, amethyst;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.21'>and, the twelve gates, were twelve pearls,each one of the gates, severally, was of one pearl; and, the broadway of the city, was pure gold, as transparent glass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.22'>And, sanctuary, saw I none therein; for, the Lord, God, the Almighty, is the sanctuary thereof, and the Lamb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.23'>And, the city, hath no need of the sun, nor of the moon, that they should shine therein; for, the glory of God, illumined it, and, the lamp thereof, was the Lamb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.24'>And the nations, shall walk, through her light; and, the kings of the earth, do bring their glory into it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.25'>and, the gates thereof, shall in nowise be shut, by day,night, in fact, shall not be there,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.26'>and they shall bring the glory and the honour of the nations into it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.21.27'>And in nowise shall there enter into it, anything common, or he that doeth abomination and falsehood,but only they who are written in the Lambs book of life.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Rev.22'>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.1'>And he pointed out to me a river of water of life, bright as crystal, issuing forth out of the throne of God and of the Lamb,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.2'>in the midst of the broadway thereof. And, on this side of the river and on that, was a tree of life, bearing twelve crops of fruit, every several month, yielding its fruit; and, the leaves of the tree, were for the healing of the nations,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.3'>And, no curse, shall there be, any more; and, the throne of God and of the Lamb, shall be, therein,and his servants will render divine service unto him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.4'>and they shall see his face, and, his name,   upon their foreheads.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.5'>And, night, shall be, no more; and they have no need of the light of a lamp or the light of a sun, because, the Lord, God, will give them light,and they shall reign unto the ages of ages.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.6'>And he said unto me-These words, are faithful and true; and, the Lord, the God of the spirits of the prophets, hath sent his messenger, to point out, unto his servants, the things which must needs come to pass with speed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.7'>AndLo! I come speedily! Happy, is he that keepeth the words of the prophecy of this scroll.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.8'>And, I, John, am he that was hearing and seeing these things; and, when I had heard and seen, I fell down to do homage at the feet of the messenger who had been pointing out unto me these things,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.9'>and he saith unto meSee   not! A fellow-servant, am I, of thee, and of thy brethren the prophets, and of them who keep the words of this scroll: unto God, do homage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.10'>And he saith unto meDo not seal up the words of the prophecy of this scroll, for, the season, is, near:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.11'>He that is doing unjustly, let him do unjustly, still, and, he that is filthy, let him be made filthy, still; and, he that is righteous, let him do righteousness, still, and, he that is holy, let him be hallowed, still:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.12'>Lo! I come speedily, and my reward is with me, to render unto each one as, his, work is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.13'>I, am the A and the Z, the First and the Last, the Beginning and the End.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.14'>Happy, they who are washing their robes, that their right may be unto the tree of life and, by the gates, they may enter into the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.15'>Outside, are the dogs, and the sorcerers, and the unchaste, and the murderers, and the idolaters, and every one loving and doing falsehood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.16'>I, Jesus, have sent my messenger, to bear witness unto you of these things, for the assemblies. I, am the Root and the Offspring of David, the bright and the morning Star.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.17'>And, the Spirit and the Bride, sayCome! and, he that heareth, let him sayCome! and, he that is athirst, let him come,he that will, let him take of the water of life, freely.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.18'>I, bear witness, unto every one that heareth the words of the prophecy of this scroll:If anyone shall lay aught upon them, God, will lay upon him, the plagues which are written in this scroll;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.19'>And, if anyone shall take away from the words of this prophetic scroll, God, will take away his part,from the tree of life, and out of the holy city,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.20'>He that beareth witness of these things, saithYea! I come, speedily. Amen! come, Lord Jesus!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Rev.22.21'>The favour of the Lord Jesus  Christ  be with the saints.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>