<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='LXXE' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='LXXE'>
        <title>Brenton's English Septuagint</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>

Introduction
~~~~~~~~~~~~

  The Septuagint is the most ancient translation of the Old Testament into
  Greek. The translators were likely Jews of the dispersion, living in
  Alexandria, Egypt.

  The beginning of the Jewish presence in Egypt is difficult to date
  precisely. There may have been a Jewish colony there as early as the tenth
  century BC, when Shishak (Shashanq) invaded Palestine and took treasures
  from the temple and the king's palace (2 Chronicles 12.1-8). But certainly a
  number of Jews lived in Egypt after the murder of Gedaliah (~586 BC), when
  "the captains of the forces set out and went to Egypt; for they were afraid
  of the Chaldeans" (2 Kings 25-26). Jeremiah, Baruch, and the princesses also
  went into Egypt at that time, though Jeremiah prophecied that they would all
  "perish by the sword and by famine, until not one is left" (Jeremiah 43.6,
  44.27). One expects, on the basis of that prophecy, that this was not the
  beginning of a permanent settlement. A lasting Jewish presence in Egypt can,
  however, be definitely dated from the the time of the founding of the city
  of Alexandria in 332 BC, when Alexander the Great granted them citizenship.

  In time, the Jews in Alexandria lost familiarity with Hebrew, and spoke
  Greek instead. It was natural, then, that they would require a translation
  of the scriptures into Greek for public worship in the synagogues and for
  private study. An account of the translation of the Septuagint is told in
  The Letter of Aristeas, which claims that Demetrius Phalereus, who ran the
  royal library in Alexandria, urged the king (Philadelphus (285-247 BC)) to
  obtain a copy of the Jewish law for the library. Philadelphus sent a
  deputation to the high priest Eleazar in Jerusalem, and the result was that
  seventy-two elders arrived in Egypt with a copy of the Hebrew law written on
  rolls of skins in golden letters. They were given accommodations on the
  island of Pharos, and completed their translation in seventy-two days. The
  same basic account is given in Aristobulus, Philo, and Josephus.

  Even if the account given in the Letter of Aristeas is inaccurate, it seems
  clear that the Hebrew Old Testament was available in Greek in Alexandria
  before the birth of Christ. As Christianity began to spread, the Septuagint
  was used with persuasive effect by Christian apologists - so well, in fact,
  that in time the Jews of the dispersion replaced it with newer works. For
  instance, a proselyte to Judaism named Aquila completed a extremely literal
  translation of the Old Testament into Greek about the year 128. Other
  translations were made by Theodotion of Ephesus and a certain Symmachus,
  called an Ebionite, also in the second century.

  The most ancient manuscripts of the complete (or nearly complete) Septuagint
  are known as Vaticanus, Sinaiticus, and Alexandrinus. Vaticanus and
  Sinaiticus have been dated to the mid-fourth century, and Alexandrinus to
  the fifth. 

  Based on an earlier Hebrew original, the Septuagint departs from the
  Masoretic text* frequently. "The book of Jeremiah is noteworthy," for
  instance, "in that the present Hebrew text differs substantially from the
  Greek version (the Septuagint) in both content and order. Thus the
  Septuagint omits several passages (e.g., 33.14-26) and combines the oracles
  against foreign nations into a single section following 25.14, though in a
  different order. In addition, there are many smaller differences from verse
  to verse. Remarkably, among the portions of the text of Jeremiah in Hebrew
  that are found among the Dead Sea Scrolls are not only those that reflect
  the standard Hebrew text but also those that reflect the text tradition
  represented by the Septuagint. It is likely, then, that these two text
  traditions represent the contrasting editorial work on the book of Jeremiah
  that took place in Egypt (the Septuagint tradition) and in Palestine or
  Babylon (the traditional Hebrew text)." [Introduction to the book of
  Jeremiah, The New Oxford Annotated Bible, page 960.] Around the end of the
  first century, the Hebrew text was standardized to a form nearly identical
  with the modern Masoretic text. Variant readings, such as those represented
  in the Septuagint, were no longer transmitted in the Hebrew language. 

      * The Masoretic text is the source from which modern translations intoEnglish are made. While the oldest complete manuscripts of theSeptuagint date from the fourth century, the oldest complete HebrewOld Testament, the Leningrad Codex, was copied in ~ 1008 A.D. ModernEnglish translations of the Old Testament rely primarily on theLeningrad Codex as published in the Hebraica Stuttgartensia. Forexamples of Septuagint departures from the Masoretic text supported bythe Dead Sea Scrolls, see the appendix.

      * Another contrast between the Septuagint and the modern Hebrew OldTestament involves the canon of scripture. The Septuagint includesseveral books and sections of books absent from the modern Hebrewtext: 1 Esdras; Tobit; Judith; 1-3 Maccabees; the Wisdom of Solomon;the Wisdom of Sirach (Ecclesiasticus); Baruch; the Epistle ofJeremiah; The Song of the Three Children; Daniel and Susanna; Daniel,Bel and the Dragon; Additions to the Book of Esther; Psalm 151; andthe Prayer of Manasseh. The difference in content has been explainedin various ways. Perhaps the most straightforward account is that theJews of Alexandria had a relatively broad canon, which was generallyadopted by the Christians as they employed the Septuagint as their OldTestament. The Jews of Palestine, when they established their canonaround the turn of the first century at the council of Jamnia, mayhave been reiterating the position that had been more or less settledin Palestine for some time - though some books just made (Esther,Ecclesiastes, the Song of Solomon, and Ezekiel, for instance) ormissed (Sirach) the cut. The conflict with Christians may have servedas a catalyst to push the Jews of the dispersion into the Palestiniancamp. This article - concerned with the text of the books within theHebrew canon - will not address the controversy surrounding the OldTestament canon in any depth.

  From the time of Jerome (early fifth century), Old Testament translations to
  the vernacular in the West have used the Hebrew as the primary source - the
  Septuagint has been relegated to a secondary role. (Incidentally, some are
  under the mistaken impression - given by misleading language in the preface
  to the 1899 edition - that the Douay Old Testament was translated from a
  Latin text based on the Septuagint. Unfortunately, Jerome's Vulgate - apart
  from the Psalms and the books then available only in Greek - by and large
  follows the Hebrew text.) It is hoped that the reader will reconsider the
  wisdom of this course of action, given the clear preference the New
  Testament displays for Septuagint readings. Fortunately, a new English
  translation of the Septuagint is being prepared for publication in 2004.

  This article comprises two main sections. The first deals with the early
  Church’s use of the Septuagint - particularly their sense that the Hebrew
  text was unreliable. It begins with the discussion between Jerome and
  Augustine regarding the former’s decision to craft his Latin translation
  from the available Hebrew text, rather than from the Septuagint. It is from
  Jerome’s fateful choice that the West derives its tradition of favoring the
  Hebrew to the Greek. The second part of this article provides a detailed
  comparison of the New Testament quotations from the Old. These were made to
  assess the extent to which the New Testament authors depended on the
  Septuagint instead of the Hebrew text. Conclusions are given in the The
  Septuagint in the New Testament.

    </description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>LXXE</identifier>
        <source>

http://www.answersingenesis.org/OnlineBible/files/lxxe.exe

The Septuagint LXX in English
http://www.christianmedia.us/LXXE/

The English Translation of the Septuagint Bible Online
http://www.ecmarsh.com/lxx/    

    </source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>
    
      1851 Brenton's English Septuagint

The Bible text designated LXXE is from an English
translation of The Septuagint by Sir Lancelot 
Charles Lee Brenton, originally published in 1851. 
The electronic text is copyright 1988 by FABS 
International, Inc. Footnotes, additions, and 
corrections to the main text copyright 1999 by Larry 
Nelson, Box 2083, Rialto, CA  92376. All rights 
reserved. Used by permission.

  </rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='4Macc'>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.1'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.1'>As I am going to demonstrate a most philosophical proposition, namely, that religious reasoning is absolute master of the passions, I would willingly advise you to give the utmost heed to philosophy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.2'>For reason is necessary to every one as a step to science: and more especially does it embrace the praise of prudence, the highest virtue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.3'>If, then, reasoning appears to hold the mastery over the passions which stand in the way of temperance, such as gluttony and lust,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.4'>it surely also and manifestly has the rule over the affections which are contrary to justice, such as malice; and of those which are hindrances to manliness, as wrath, and pain, and fear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.5'>How, then, is it, perhaps some may say, that reasoning, if it rule the affections, is not also master of forgetfulness and ignorance? They attempt a ridiculous argument.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.6'>For reasoning does not rule over its own affections, but over such as are contrary to justice, and manliness and temperance, and prudence; and yet over these, so as to withstand, without destroying them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.7'>I might prove to you, from may other considerations, that religious reasoning is sole master of the passions;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.8'>but I shall prove it with the greatest force from the fortitude of Eleazar, and seven brethren, and their mother, who suffered death in defence of virtue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.9'>For all these, contemning pains even unto death, by this contempt, demonstrated that reasoning has command over the passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.10'>For their virtues, then, it is right that I should commend those men who died with their mother at this time in behalf of rectitude; and for their honours, I may count them happy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.11'>For they, winning admiration not only from men in general, but even from the persecutors, for their manliness and endurance, became the means of the destruction of the tyranny against their nation, having conquered the tyrant by their endurance, so that by them their country was purified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.12'>But we may now at once enter upon the question, having commenced, as is our wont, with laying down the doctrine, and so proceed to the account of these persons, giving glory to the all wise God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.13'>The question, therefore, is, whether reasoning be absolute master of the passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.14'>Let us determine, then, What is reasoning? and what passion? and how many forms of the passions? and whether reasoning bears sway over all of these?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.15'>Reasoning is, then, intellect accompanied by a life of rectitude, putting foremost the consideration of wisdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.16'>And wisdom is a knowledge of divine and human things, and of their causes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.17'>And this is contained in the education of the law; by means of which we learn divine things reverently, and human things profitably.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.18'>And the forms of wisdom are prudence, and justice, and manliness, and temperance.19 The leading one of these is prudence; by whose means, indeed, it is that reasoning bears rule over the passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.20'>Of the passions, pleasure and pain are the two most comprehensive; and they also by nature refer to the soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.21'>And there are many attendant affections surrounding pleasure and pain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.22'>Before pleasure is lust; and after pleasure, joy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.23'>And before pain is fear; and after pain is sorrow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.24'>Wrath is an affection, common to pleasure and to pain, if any one will pay attention when it comes upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.25'>And there exists in pleasure a malicious disposition, which is the most multiform of all the affections.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.26'>In the soul it is arrogance, and love of money, and vaingloriousness, and contention, and faithlessness, and the evil eye.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.27'>In the body it is greediness and gormandizing, and solitary gluttony.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.28'>As pleasure and pain are, therefore, two growth of the body and the soul, so there are many offshoots of these passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.29'>And reasoning, the universal husbandman, purging, and pruning these severally, and binding round, and watering, and transplanting, in every way improves the materials of the morals and affections.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.30'>For reasoning is the leader of the virtues, but it is the sole ruler of the passions. Observe then first, through the very things which stand in the way of temperance, that reasoning is absolute ruler of the passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.31'>Now temperance consists of a command over the lusts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.32'>But of the lusts, some belong to the soul, others to the body: and over each of these classes the reasoning appears to bear sway.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.33'>For whence is it, otherwise, that when urged on to forbidden meats, we reject the gratification which would ensue from them? Is it not because reasoning is able to command the appetites? I believe so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.34'>Hence it is, then, that when lusting after water-animals and birds, and fourfooted beasts, and all kinds of food which are forbidden us by the law, we withhold ourselves through the mastery of reasoning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.1.35'>For the affections of our appetites are resisted by the temperate understanding, and bent back again, and all the impulses of the body are reined in by reasoning.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.2'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.1'>And what wonder? if the lusts of the soul, after participation with what is beautiful, are frustrated,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.2'>on this ground, therefore, the temperate Joseph is praised in that by reasoning, he subdued, on reflection, the indulgence of sense.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.3'>For, although young, and ripe for sexual intercourse, he abrogated by reasoning the stimulus of his passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.4'>And it is not merely the stimulus of sensual indulgence, but that of every desire, that reasoning is able to master.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.5'>For instance, the law says, Thou shalt not covet thy neighbour's wife, nor anything that belongs to thy neighbour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.6'>Now, then, since it is the law which has forbidden us to desire, I shall much the more easily persuade you, that reasoning is able to govern our lusts, just as it does the affections which are impediments to justice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.7'>Since in what way is a solitary eater, and a glutton, and a drunkard reclaimed, unless it be clear that reasoning is lord of the passions?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.8'>A man, therefore, who regulates his course by the law, even if he be a lover of money, straightway puts force upon his own disposition; lending to the needy without interest, and cancelling the debt of the incoming sabbath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.9'>And should a man be parsimonious, he is ruled by the law acting through reasoning; so that he does not glean his harvest crops, nor vintage: and in reference to other points we may perceive that it is reasoning that conquers his passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.10'>For the law conquers even affection toward parents, not surrendering virtue on their account.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.11'>And it prevails over marriage love, condemning it when transgressing law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.12'>And it lords it over the love of parents toward their children, for they punish them for vice; and it domineers over the intimacy of friends, reproving them when wicked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.13'>And think it not a strange assertion that reasoning can in behalf of the law conquer even enmity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.14'>It alloweth not to cut down the cultivated herbage of an enemy, but preserveth it from the destroyers, and collecteth their fallen ruins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.15'>And reason appears to be master of the more violent passions, as love of empire and empty boasting, and slander.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.16'>For the temperate understanding repels all these malignant passions, as it does wrath: for it masters even this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.17'>Thus Moses, when angered against Dathan and Abiram, did nothing to them in wrath, but regulated his anger by reasoning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.18'>For the temperate mind is able, as I said, to be superior to the passions, and to transfer some, and destroy others.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.19'>For why, else, does our most wise father Jacob blame Simeon and Levi for having irrationally slain the whole race of the Shechemites, saying, Cursed be their anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.20'>For if reasoning did not possess the power of subduing angry affections, he would not have spoken thus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.21'>For at the time when God created man, He implanted within him his passions and moral nature.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.22'>And at that time He enthroned above all the holy leader mind, through the medium of the senses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.23'>And He gave a law to this mind, by living according to which it will maintain a temperate, and just, and good, and manly reign.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.2.24'>How, then, a man may say, if reasoning be master of the passions, has it no control over forgetfulness and ignorance?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.3'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.1'>The argument is exceedingly ridiculous: for reasoning does not appear to bear sway over its own affections, but over those of the body,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.2'>in such a way as that any one of you may not be able to root out desire, but reasoning will enable you to avoid being enslaved to it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.3'>One may not be able to root out anger from the soul, but it is possible to withstand anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.4'>Any one of you may not be able to eradicate malice, but reasoning has force to work with you to prevent you yielding to malice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.5'>For reasoning is not an eradicator, but an antagonist of the passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.6'>And this may be more clearly comprehended from the thirst of king David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.7'>For after David had been attacking the Philistines the whole day, he with the soldiers of his nation slew many of them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.8'>then when evening came, sweating and very weary, he came to the royal tent, about which the entire host of our ancestors was encamped.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.9'>Now all the rest of them were at supper;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.10'>but the king, being very much athirst, although he had numerous springs, could not by their means quench his thirst;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.11'>but a certain irrational longing for the water in the enemy's camp grew stronger and fiercer upon him, and consumed him with languish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.12'>Wherefore his body-guards being troubled at this longing of the king, two valiant young soldiers, reverencing the desire of the king, put on their panoplies, and taking a pitcher, got over the ramparts of the enemies:</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.13'>and unperceived by the guardians of the gate, they went throughout the whole camp of the enemy in quest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.14'>And having boldly discovered the fountain, they filled out of it the draught for the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.15'>But he, though parched with thirst, reasoned that a draught reputed of equal value to blood, would be terribly dangerous to his soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.16'>Wherefore, setting up reasoning in opposition to his desire, he poured out the draught to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.17'>For the temperate mind has power to conquer the pressure of the passions, and to quench the fires of excitement,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.18'>and to wrestle down the pains of the body, however excessive; and, through the excellency of reasoning, to abominate all the assaults of the passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.19'>But the occasion now invites us to give an illustration of temperate reasoning from history.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.20'>For at a time when our fathers were in possession of undisturbed peace through obedience to the law, and were prosperous, so that Seleucus Nicanor, the king of Asia, both assigned them money for divine service, and accepted their form of government,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.3.21'>then certain persons, bringing in new things contrary to the general unanimity, in various ways fell into calamities.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.4'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.1'>For a certain man named Simon, who was in opposition to Onias, who once held the high priesthood for life, and was an honourable and good man, after that by slandering him in every way, he could not injure him with the people, went away as an exile, with the intention of betraying his country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.2'>Whence coming to Apollonius, the military governor of Syria, and Phoenicia, and Cilicia, he said,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.3'>Having good will to the king's affairs, I am come to inform thee that infinite private wealth is laid up in the treasuries of Jerusalem which do not belong to the temple, but pertain to king Seleucus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.4'>Apollonius, acquainting himself with the particulars of this, praised Simon for his care of the king's interests, and going up to Seleucus informed him of the treasure;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.5'>and getting authority about it, and quickly advancing into our country with the accursed Simon and a very heavy force,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.6'>he said that he came with the commands of the king that he should take the private money of the treasure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.7'>And the nation, indignant at this proclamation, and replying to the effect that it was extremely unfair that those who had committed deposits to the sacred treasury should be deprived of them, resisted as well as they could.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.8'>But Appolonius went away with threats into the temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.9'>And the priests, with the women and children, having supplicated God to throw his shield over the holy, despised place,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.10'>and Appolonius going up with his armed force to the seizure of the treasure,--there appeared from heaven angels riding on horseback, all radiant in armour, filling them with much fear and trembling.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.11'>And Apollonius fell half dead upon the court which is open to all nations, and extended his hands to heaven, and implored the Hebrews, with tears, to pray for him, and propitiate the heavenly host.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.12'>For he said that he had sinned, so as to be consequently worthy of death; and that if he were saved, he would celebrate to all men the blessedness of the holy place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.13'>Onias the high priest, induced by these words, although for other reasons anxious that king Seleucus should not suppose that Apollonius was slain by human device and not by Divine punishment, prayed for him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.14'>and he being thus unexpectedly saved, departed to manifest to the king what had happened to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.15'>But on the death of Seleucus the king, his son Antiochus Epiphanes succeeds to the kingdom: a man of haughty pride and terrible.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.16'>Who having deposed Onias from the high priesthood, appointed his brother Jason to be high priest:</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.17'>who had made a covenant, if he would give him this authority, to pay yearly three thousand six hundred and sixty talents.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.18'>And he committed to him the high priesthood and rulership over the nation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.19'>And he both changed the manner of living of the people, and perverted their civil customs into all lawlessness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.20'>So that he not only erected a gymnasium on the very citadel of our country, but neglected the guardianship of the temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.21'>At which Divine vengeance being grieved, instigated Antiochus himself against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.22'>For being at war with Ptolemy in Egypt, he heard that on a report of his death being spread abroad, the inhabitants of Jerusalem had exceedingly rejoiced, and he quickly marched against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.23'>And having subdued them, he established a decree that if any of them lived according to the laws of his country he should die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.24'>And when he could by no means destroy by his decrees the obedience to the law of the nation, but saw all his threats and punishments without effect,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.25'>for even women, because they continued to circumcise their children, were flung down a precipice along with them, knowing beforehand of the punishment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.4.26'>When, therefore, his decrees were disregarded by the people, he himself compelled by means of tortures every one of this race, by tasting forbidden meats, to abjure the Jewish religion.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.5'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.1'>The tyrant Antiochus, therefore, sitting in public state with his assessors upon a certain lofty place, with his armed troops standing in a circle around him, commanded his spearbearers to seize every one of the Hebrews, and to compel them to taste swine's flesh, and things offered to idols.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.2'/>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.3'>And should any of them be unwilling to eat the accursed food, they were to be tortured on the wheel, and so killed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.4'>And when many had been seized, a foremost man of the assembly, a Hebrew, by name Eleazar, a priest by family, by profession a lawyer, and advanced in years, and for this reason known to many of the king's followers, was brought near to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.5'>And Antiochus seeing him, said,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.6'>I would counsel thee, old man, before thy tortures begin, to tasted the swine's flesh, and save your life; for I feel respect for your age and hoary head, which since you have had so long, you appear to me to be no philosopher in retaining the superstition of the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.7'>For wherefore, since nature has conferred upon you the most excellent flesh of this animal, do you loathe it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.8'>It seems senseless not to enjoy what is pleasant, yet not disgraceful; and from notions of sinfulness, to reject the boons of nature.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.9'>And you will be acting, I think, still more senselessly, if you follow vain conceits about the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.10'>And you will, moreover, be despising me to your own punishment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.11'>Will you not awake from your trifling philosophy? and give up the folly of your notions; and, regaining understanding worthy of your age, search into the truth of an expedient course?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.12'>and, reverencing my kindly admonition, have pity upon your own years?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.13'>For, bear in mind, that if there be any power which watches over this religion of yours, it will pardon you for all transgressions of the law which you commit through compulsion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.14'>While the tyrant incited him in this manner to the unlawful eating of flesh, Eleazar begged permission to speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.15'>And having received power to speak, he began thus to deliver himself:</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.16'>We, O Antiochus, who are persuaded that we live under a divine law, consider no compulsion to be so forcible as obedience to that law;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.17'>wherefore we consider that we ought not in any point to transgress the law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.18'>And indeed, were our law (as you suppose) not truly divine, and if we wrongly think it divine, we should have no right even in that case to destroy our sense of religion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.19'>think not eating the unclean, then, a trifling offense.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.20'>For transgression of the law, whether in small or great matters, is of equal moment;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.21'>for in either case the law is equally slighted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.22'>But thou deridest our philosophy, as though we lived irrationally in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.23'>Yet it instructs us in temperance, so that we are superior to all pleasures and lusts; and it exercises us in manliness, so that we cheerfully undergo every grievance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.24'>And it instructs us in justice, so that in all our dealoings we render what is due; and it teaches us piety, so that we worship the one only God becomingly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.25'>Wherefore it is that we eat not the unclean; for believing that the law was established by God, we are convinced that the Creator of the world, in giving his laws, sympathises with our nature.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.26'>Those things which are convenient to our souls, he has directed us to eat; but those which are repugnant to them, he has interdicted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.27'>But, tyrant-like, thou not only forcest us to break the law, but also to eat, that thou mayest ridicule us as we thus profanely eat:</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.28'>but thou shalt not have this cause of laughter against me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.29'>nor will I transgress the sacred oaths of my forefathers to keep the law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.30'>No, not if you pluck out my eyes, and consume my entrails.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.31'>I am not so old, and void of manliness, but that my rational powers are youthful in defence of my religion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.32'>Now then; prepare your wheels, and kindle a fiercer flame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.33'>I will not so compassionate my old age, as on my account to break the law of my country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.34'>I will not belie thee, O law, my instructor! or forsake thee, O beloved self-control!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.35'>I will not put thee to shame, O philosopher Reason; or deny thee, O honoured priesthood, and science of the law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.36'>Mouth! thou shalt not pollute my old age, nor the full stature of a perfect life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.37'>My fathers shall receive me pure, not having quailed before your compulsion, though unto death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.5.38'>For over the ungodly thou shalt tyrannize; but thou shalt not lord it over my thoughts about religion, either by thine arguments, or through deeds.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.6'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.1'>When Eleazar had in this manner answered the exhortations of the tyrant, the spearbearers came up, and rudely haled Eleazar to the instruments of torture.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.2'>And first, they stripped the old man, adorned as he was with the comeliness of piety.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.3'>Then tying back his arms and hands, they disdainfully used him with stripes;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.4'>a herald opposite crying out, Obey the commands of the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.5'>But Eleazar, the high-minded and truly noble, as one tortured in a dream, regarded it not all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.6'>But raising his eyes on high to heaven, the old man's flesh was stripped off by the scourges, and his blood streamed down, and his sides were pierced through.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.7'>And falling upon the ground, from his body having no power to support the pains, he yet kept his reasoning upright and unbending.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.8'>then one of the harsh spearbearers leaped upon his belly as he was falling, to force him upright.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.9'>But he endured the pains, and despised the cruelty, and persevered through the indignities;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.10'>and like a noble athlete, the old man, when struck, vanquished his torturers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.11'>His countenance sweating, and he panting for breath, he was admired by the very torturers for his courage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.12'>Wherefore, partly in pity for his old age,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.13'>partly from the sympathy of acquaintance, and partly in admiration of his endurance, some of the attendants of the king said, Why do you unreasonably destroy yourself, O Eleazar, with these miseries?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.15'>We will bring you some meat cooked by yourself, and do you save yourself by pretending that you have eaten swine's flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.16'>And Eleazar, as though the advice more painfully tortured him, cried out,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.17'>Let not us who are children of Abraham be so evil advised as by giving way to make use of an unbecoming pretence;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.18'>for it were irrational, if having lived up to old age in all truth, and having scrupulously guarded our character for it, we should now turn back,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.19'>and ourselves should become a pattern of impiety to the young, as being an example of pollution eating.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.20'>It would be disgraceful if we should live on some short time, and that scorned by all men for cowardice,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.21'>and be condemned by the tyrant for unmanliness, by not contending to the death for our divine law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.22'>Wherefore do you, O children of Abraham, die nobly for your religion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.23'>Ye spearbearers of the tyrant, why do ye linger?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.24'>Beholding him so high-minded against misery, and not changing at their pity, they led him to the fire:</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.25'>then with their wickedly-contrived instruments they burnt him on the fire, and poured stinking fluids down into his nostrils.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.26'>And he being at length burnt down to the bones, and about to expire, raised his eyes Godward, and said,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.27'>Thou knowest, O God, that when I might have been saved, I am slain for the sake of the law by tortures of fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.28'>Be merciful to thy people, and be satisfied with the punishment of me on their account.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.29'>Let my blood be a purification for them, and take my life in recompense for theirs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.30'>Thus speaking, the holy man departed, noble in his torments, and even to the agonies of death resisted in his reasoning for the sake of the law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.31'>Confessedly, therefore, religious reasoning is master of the passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.32'>For had the passions been superior to reasoning, I would have given them the witness of this mastery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.33'>But now, since reasoning conquered the passions, we befittingly awared it the authority of first place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.34'>And it is but fair that we should allow, that the power belongs to reasoning, since it masters external miseries.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.6.35'>Ridiculous would it be were it not so; and I prove that reasoning has not only mastered pains, but that it is also superior to the pleasures, and withstands them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.7'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.1'>The reasoning of our father Eleazar, like a first-rate pilot, steering the vessel of piety in the sea of passions,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.2'>and flouted by the threats of the tyrant, and overwhelmed with the breakers of torture,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.3'>in no way shifted the rudder of piety till it sailed into the harbour of victory over death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.4'>Not so has ever a city, when besieged, held out against many and various machines, as did that holy man, when his pious soul was tried with the fiery trial of tortures and rackings, move his besiegers through the religious reasoning that shielded him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.5'>For father Eleazar, projecting his disposition, broke the raging wabves of the passions as with a jutting promontory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.6'>O priest worthy of the priesthood! thou didst not pollute thy sacred teeth; nor make thine appetite, which had always embraced the clean and lawful, a partaker of profanity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.7'>O harmonizer with the law, and sage devoted to a divine life!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.8'>Of such a character ought those to be who perform the duties of the law at the risk of their own blood, and defend it with generous sweat by sufferings even unto death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.9'>Thou, father, hast gloriously established our right government by thy endurance; and making of much account our service past, prevented its destruction, and, by thy deeds, hast made credible the words of philosophy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.10'>O aged man of more power than tortures, elder more vigorous than fire, greatest king over the passions, Eleazar!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.11'>For as father Aaron, armed with a censer, hastening through the consuming fire, vanquished the flame-bearing angel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.12'>so, Eleazar, the descendant of Aaron, wasted away by the fire, did not give up his reasoning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.13'>And, what is most wonderful, though an old man, though the labours of his body were now spent, and his fibres were relaxed, and his sinews worn out, he recovered youth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.14'>By the spirit of reasoning, and the reasoning of Isaac, he rendered powerless the many-headed instrument.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.15'>O blessed old age, and reverend hoar head, and life obedient to the law, which the faithful seal of death perfected.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.16'>If, then, an old man, through religion, despised tortures even unto death, confessedly religious reasoning is ruler of the passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.17'>But perhaps some might say, It is not all who conquer passions, as all do not possess wise reasoning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.18'>But they who have meditated upon religion with their whole heart, these alone can master the passions of the flesh;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.19'>they who believe that to God they die not; for, as our forefathers, Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, they live to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.20'>This circumstance, then, is by no means an objection, that some who have weak reasoning, are governed by their passions:</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.21'>since what person, walking religiously by the whole rule of philosophy, and believing in God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.22'>and knowing that it is a blessed thing to endure all kinds of hardships for virture, would not, for the sake of religion, master his passion?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.23'>For the wise and brave man only is lord over his passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.24'>Whence it is, that even boys, imbued with the philosophy of religious reasoning, have conquered still more bitter tortures:</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.7.25'>for when the tyrant was manifestly vanquished in his first attempt, in being unable to force the old man to eat the unclean thing,-</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.8'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.1'>Then, indeed, vehemently swayed with passion, he commanded to bring others of the adult Hebrews, and if they would eat of the unclean thing, to let them go when they had eaten; but if they objected, to torment them more grievously.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.2'>The tyrant having given this charge, seven brethren were brought into his presence, along with their aged mother, handsome, and modest, and well-born, and altogether comely.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.3'>Whom, when the tyrant beheld, encircling their mother as in a dance, he was pleased at them; and being struck with their becoming and ingenuous mien, smiled upon them, and calling them near, said:</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.4'>O youths, with favourable feelings, I admire the beauty of each of you; and greatly honouring so numerous a band of brethren, I not only counsel you not to share the madness of the old man who has been tortured before,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.5'>but I do beg you to yield, and to enjoy my friendship; for I possess the power, not only of punishing those who disobey my commands, but of doing good to those who obey them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.6'>Put confidence in me, then, and you shall receive places of authority in my government, if you forsake your national ordinance,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.7'>and, conforming to the Greek mode of life, alter your rule, and revel in youth's delights.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.8'>For if you provoke me by your disobedience, you will compel me to destroy you, every one, with terrible punishments by tortures.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.9'>Have mercy, then, upon your own selves, whom I, although an enemy, compassionate for your age and comeliness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.10'>Will you not reason upon this--that if you disobey, there will be nothing left for you but to die in tortures?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.11'>Thus speaking, he ordered the instruments of torture to be brought forward, that very fear might prevail upon them to eat unclean meat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.12'>And when the spearman brought forward the wheels, and the racks, and the hooks, and catapeltae, and caldrons, pans, and finger-racks, and iron hands and wedges, and bellows, the tyrant continue:</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.13'>Fear, young men, and the righteousness which ye worship will be merciful to you if you err from compulsion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.14'>Now they having listened to these words of persuasion, and seeing the fearful instruments, not only were not afraid, but even answered the arguments of the tyrant, and through their good reasoning destroyed his power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.15'>Now let us consider the matter: had any of them been weak-spirited and cowardly among them, what reasonings would they have employed but these?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.16'>O wretched that we are, and exceeding senseless! when the king exhorts us, and calls us to his bounty, should we not obey him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.17'>Why do we cheer ourselves with vain counsels, and venture upon a disobedience bringing death?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.18'>Shall we not fear, O brethren, the instruments of torture and weigh the threatenings of torment and shun this vain-glory and destructive pride?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.19'>Let us have compassion upon our age and relent over the years of our mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.20'>And let us bear in mind that we shall be dying as rebels.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.21'>And Divine Justice will pardon us if we fear the king through necessity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.22'>Why withdraw ourselves from a most sweet life, and deprive ourselves of this pleasant world?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.23'>Let us not oppose necessity, nor seek vain-glory by our own excruciation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.24'>The law itself is not forward to put us to death, if we dread torture.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.25'>Whence has such angry zeal taken root in us, and such fatal obstinacy approved itself to us, when we might live unmolested by the king?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.26'>But nothing of this kind did the young men say or think when about to be tortured.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.8.27'>For they were well aware of the sufferings, and masters of the pains. So that as soon as the tyrant had ceased counselling them to eat the unclean, they altogether with one voice, as from the same heart said:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.9'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.1'>Why delayest thou, O tyrant? for we are readier to die than to transgress the injunctions of our fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.2'>And we should be disgracing our fathers if we did not obey the law, and take knowledge for our guide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.3'>O tyrant, counsellor of law-breaking, do not, hating us as thou dost, pity us more than we pity ourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.4'>For we account escape to be worse than death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.5'>And you think to scare us, by threatening us with death by tortures, as though thou hadst learned nothing by the death of Eleazar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.6'>But if aged men of the Hebrews have died in the cause of religion after enduring torture, more rightly should we younger men die, scorning your cruel tortures, which our aged instructor overcame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.7'>Make the attempt, then, O tyrant; and if thou puttest us to death for our religion, think not that thou harmest us by torturing us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.8'>For we through this ill-treatment and endurance shall bear off the rewards of virtue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.9'>But thou, for the wicked and despotic slaughter of us, shalt, from the Divine vengeance, endure eternal torture by fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.10'>When they had thus spoken, the tyrant was not only exasperated against them as being refractory, but enraged with them as being ungrateful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.11'>So that, at his bidding, the torturers brought forth the eldest of them, and tearing through his tunic, bound his hands and arms on each side with thongs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.12'>And when they had laboured hard without effect in scourging him, they hurled him upon the wheel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.13'>And the noble youth, extended upon this, became dislocated.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.14'>And with every member disjointed, he exclaimed in expostulation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.15'>O most accursed tyrant, and enemy of heavenly justice, and cruel-hearted, I am no murderer, nor sacrilegious man, whom thou thus ill-usest; but a defender of the Divine law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.16'>And when the spearmen said, Consent to eat, that you may be releasted from your tortures,--</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.17'>he answered, Not so powerful, O accursed ministers, is your wheel, as to stifle my reasoning; cut my limbs, and burn my flesh, and twist my joints.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.18'>For through all my torments I will convince you that the children of the Hebrews are alone unconquered in behalf of virtue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.19'>While he was saying this, they heaped up fuel, and setting fire to it, strained him upon the wheel still more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.20'>And the wheel was defiled all over with blood, and the hot ashes were quenched by the droppings of gore, and pieces of flesh were scattered about the axles of the machine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.21'>And although the framework of his bones was now destroyed the high-minded and Abrahamic youth did not groan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.22'>But, as though transformed by fire into immortality, he nobly endured the rackings, saying</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.23'>Imitate me, O brethren, nor ever desert your station, nor abjure my brotherhood in courage: fight the holy and honourable fight of religion;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.24'>by which means our just and paternal Providence, becoming merciful to the nation, will punish the pestilent tyrant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.25'>And saying this, the revered youth abruptly closed his life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.26'>And when all admired his courageous soul, the spearmen brought forward him who was second in point of age, and having put on iron hands, bound him with pointed hooks to the catapelt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.27'>And when, on enquiring whether he would eat before he was tortured, they heard his noble sentiment,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.28'>after they with the iron hands had violently dragged all the flesh from the neck to the chin, the panther-like beasts tore off the very skin of his head: but he, bearing with firmness this misery, said,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.29'>How sweet is every form of death for the religion of our fathers! and he said to the tyrant,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.30'>Thinkest thou not, most cruel of all tyrants, that thou art now tortured more than I, finding thine overweening conception of tyranny conquered by our patience in behalf of our religion?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.31'>For I lighten my suffering by the pleasures which are connected with virtue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.9.32'>But thou art tortured with threatenings for impiety; and thou shalt not escape, most corrupt tyrant, the vengeance of Divine wrath.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.10'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.1'>Now this one, having endured this praiseworthy death, the third was brought along, and exhorted by many to taste and save his life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.2'>But he cried out and said, Know ye not, that the father of those who are dead, begat me also; and that the same mother bare me; and that I was brought up in the same tenets?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.3'>I abjure not the noble relationship of my brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.4'>Now then, whatever instrument of vengeance ye have, apply it to my body, for ye are not able to touch, even if ye wish it, my soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.5'>But they, highly incensed at his boldness of speech, dislocated his hands and feet with racking engines, and wrenching them from their sockets, dismembered him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.6'>And they dragged round his fingers, and his arms, and his legs, and his ankles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.7'>And not being able by any means to strangle him, they tore off his skin, together with the extreme tips of his fingers, flayed him, and then haled him to the wheel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.8'>around which his vertebral joints were loosened, and he saw his own flesh torn to shreds, and streams of blood flowing from his entrails.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.9'>And when about to die, he said,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.10'>We, O accursed tyrant, suffer this for the sake of Divine education and virtue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.11'>But thou, for thine impiety and blood-shedding, shalt endure indissoluble torments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.12'>And thus having died worthily of his brethren, they dragged forward the fourth, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.13'>Do not thou share the madness of thy brethren: but give regard to the king, and save thyself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.14'>But he said to them, You have not a fire so scorching as to make me play the coward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.15'>By the blessed death of my brethren, and the eternal punishment of the tyrant, and the glorious life of the pious, I will not repudiate the noble brotherhood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.16'>Invent, O tyrant, tortures; that you may learn, even through them, that I am the brother of those tormented before.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.17'>When he had said this, the blood-thirsty, and murderous, and unhallowed Antiochus ordered his tongue to be cut out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.18'>But he said, Even if you take away the organ of speech, yet God hears the silent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.19'>Behold, my tongue is extended, cut it off; for not for that halt thou extirpate our reasoning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.20'>Gladly do we lose our limbs in behalf of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.10.21'>But God shall speedly find you, since you cut off the tongue, the instrument of divine melody.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.11'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.1'>And when he had died, disfigured in his torments, the fifth leaped forward, and said,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.2'>I intend not, O tyrant, to get excused from the torment which is in behalf of virtue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.3'>But I have come of mine own accord, that by the death of me, you may owe heavenly vengeance a punishment for more crimes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.4'>O thou hater of virtue and of men, what have we done that thou thus revellest in our blood?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.5'>Does it seem evil to thee that we worship the Founder of all things, and live according to his surpassing law?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.6'>But this is worthy of honours, not torments;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.7'>hadst thou been capable of the higher feelings of men, and possessed the hope of salvation from God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.8'>Behold now, being alien from God, thou makest war against those who are religious toward God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.9'>As he said this, the spearbearers bound him, and drew him to the catapelt:</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.10'>to which binding him at his knees, and fastening them with iron fetters, they bent down his loins upon the wedge of the wheel; and his body was then dismembered, scorpion-fashion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.11'>With his breath thus confined, and his body strangled, he said,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.12'>A great favour thou bestowest upon us, O tyrant, by enabling us to manifest our adherence to the law by means of nobler sufferings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.13'>He also being dead, the sixth, quite a youth, was brought out; and on the tyrant asking him whether he would eat and be delivered, he said,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.14'>I am indeed younger than my brothers, but in understanding I am am as old;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.15'>for having been born and reared unto the same end, we are bound to die also in behalf of the same cause.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.16'>So that if ye think proper to torment us for not eating the unclean;--torment!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.17'>As he said this, they brought him to the wheel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.18'>Extended upon which, with limbs racked and dislocated, he was gradually roasted from beneath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.19'>And having heated sharp spits, they approached them to his back; and having transfixed his sides, they burned away his entrails.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.20'>And he, while tormented, said, O period good and holy, in which, for the sake of religion, we brethren have been called to the contest of pain, and have not been conquered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.21'>For religious understanding, O tyrant, is unconquered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.22'>Armed with upright virtue, I also shall depart with my brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.23'>I, too, bearing with me a great avenger, O deviser of tortures, and enemy of the truly pious.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.24'>We six youths have destroyed thy tyranny.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.25'>For is not your inability to overrule our reasoning, and to compel us to eat the unclean, thy destruction?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.26'>Your fire is cold to us, your catapelts are painless, and your violence harmless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.11.27'>For the guards not of a tyrant but of a divine law are our defenders: through this we keep our reasoning unconquered.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.12'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.1'>When he, too, had undergone blessed martyrdom, and died in the caldron into which he had been thrown, the seventh, the youngest of all, came forward:</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.2'>whom the tyrant pitying, though he had been dreadfully reproached by his brethren,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.3'>seeing him already encompassed with chains, had him brought nearer, and endeavoured to counsel him, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.4'>Thou seest the end of the madness of thy brethren: for they have died to torture through disobedience; and you, if disobedient, having been miserably tormented, will yourself perish prematurely.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.5'>But if you obey, you shall be my friend, and have a charge over the affairs of the kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.6'>And having thus exhorted him, he sent for the mother of the boy; that, by condoling with her for the loss of so many sons, he might incline her, through the hope of safety, to render the survivor obedient.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.7'>And he, after his mother had urged him on in the Hebrew tongue, (as we shall soon relate) saith,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.8'>Release me that I may speak to the king and all his friends.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.9'>And they, rejoicing exceedingly at the promise of the youth, quickly let him go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.10'>And he, running up to the pans, said,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.11'>Impious tyrant, and most blasphemous man, wert thou not ashamed, having received prosperity and a kingdom from God, to slay His servants, and to rack the doers of godliness?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.12'>Wherefore the divine vengeance is reserving thee for eternal fire and torments, which shall cling to thee for all time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.13'>Wert thou not ashamed, man as thou art, yet most savage, to cut out the tongues of men of like feeling and origin, and having thus abused to torture them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.14'>But they, bravely dying, fulfilled their religion towards God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.15'>But thou shalt groan according to thy deserts for having slain without cause the champions of virtue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.16'>Wherefore, he continued, I myself, being about to die,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.17'>will not forsake my brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.18'>And I call upon the God of my fathers to be merciful to my race.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.19'>But thee, both living and dead, he will punish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.12.20'>Thus having prayed, he hurled himself into the pans; and so expired.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.13'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.1'>If then, the seven brethren despised troubles even unto death, it is confessed on all sides that righteous reasoning is absolute master over the passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.2'>For just as if, had they as slaves to the passions, eaten of the unholy, we should have said that they had been conquered by the;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.3'>now it is not so: but by means of the reasoning which is praised by God, they mastered their passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.4'>And it is impossible to overlook the leadership of reflection: for it gained the victory over both passions and troubles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.5'>How, then, can we avoid according to these men mastery of passion through right reasoning, since they drew not back from the pains of fire?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.6'>For just as by means of towers projecting in front of harbours men break the threatening waves, and thus assure a still course to vessels entering port,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.7'>so that seven-towered right-reasoning of the young men, securing the harbour of religion, conquered the intermperance of passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.8'>For having arranged a holy choir of piety, they encouraged one another, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.9'>Brothers, may we die brotherly for the law. Let us imitate the three young men in Assyria who despised the equally afflicting furnace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.10'>Let us not be cowards in the manifestation of piety.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.11'>And one said, Courage, brother; and another, Nobly endure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.12'>And another, Remember of what stock ye are; and by the hand of our father Isaac endured to be slain for the sake of piety.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.13'>And one and all, looking on each other serene and confident, said, Let us sacrifice with all our heart our souls to God who gave them, and employ our bodies for the keeping of the law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.14'>Let us not fear him who thinketh he killeth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.15'>for great is the trial of soul and danger of eternal torment laid up for those who transgress the commandment of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.16'>Let us arm ourselves, therefore, in the abnegation of the divine reasoning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.17'>If we suffer thus, Abraham, and Isaac, and Jacob will receive us, and all the fathers will commend us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.18'>And as each one of the brethren was haled away, the rest exclaimed, Disgrace us not, O brother, nor falsify those who died before you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.19'>Now you are not ignorant of the charm of brotherhood, which the Divine and all wise Providence hath imparted through fathers to children, and hath engendered through the mother's womb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.20'>In which these brothers having remained an equal time, and having been formed for the same period, and been increased by the same blood, and having been perfected through the same principle of life,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.21'>and having been brought forth at equal intervals, and having sucked milk from the same fountains, hence their brotherly souls are reared up lovingly together;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.22'>and increase the more powerfully by reason of this simultaneous rearing, and by daily intercourse, and by other education, and exercise in the law of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.23'>Brotherly love being thus sympathetically constituted, the seven brethren had a more sympathetic mutual harmony.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.24'>For being educated in the same law, and practising the same virtues, and reared up in a just course of life, they increased this harmony with each other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.25'>For a like ardour for what is right and honourable increased their fellow-feeling towards each other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.26'>For it acting along with religion, made their brotherly feeling more desirable to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.13.27'>And yet, although nature and intercourse and virtuous morals increased their brotherly love those who were left endured to behold their brethren, who were illused for their religion, tortured even unto death.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.14'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.1'>And more that this, they even urged them on to this ill-treatment; so that they not only despised pains themselves, but they even got the better of their affections of brotherly love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.2'>O reasonings more royal than a king, and freer than freemen!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.3'>Sacred and harmonius concert of the seven brethern as concerning piety!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.4'>None of the seven youths turned cowardly, or shrank back from death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.5'>But all of them, as though running the road to immortality, hastened on to death through tortures.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.6'>For just as hands and feet are moved sympathetically with the directions of the soul, so those holy youths agreed unto death for religion's sake, as through the immortal soul of religion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.7'>O holy seven of harmonious brethren! for as the seven days of creation, about religion,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.8'>so the youths, circling around the number seven, annulled the fear of torments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.9'>We now shudder at the recital of the affliction of those young men; but they not only beheld, and not only heard the immediate execution of the threat, but undergoing it, persevered; and that through the pains of fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.10'>And what could be more painful? for the power of fire, being sharp and quick, speedily dissolved their bodies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.11'>And think it not wonderful that reasoning bore rule over those men in their torments, when even a woman's mind despised more manifold pains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.12'>For the mother of those seven youths endured the rackings of each of her children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.13'>And consider how comprehensive is the love of offspring, which draws every one to sympathy of affection,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.14'>where irrational animals possess a similar sympathy and love for their offspring with men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.15'>The tame birds frequenting the roofs of our houses, defend their fledglings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.16'>Others build their nests, and hatch their young, in the tops of mountains and in the precipices of valleys, and the holes and tops of trees, and keep off the intruder.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.17'>And if not able to do this, they fly circling round them in agony of affection, calling out in their own note, and save their offspring in whatever manner they are able.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.18'>But why should we point attention to the sympathy toward children shewn by irrational animals?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.19'>The very bees, at the season of honey-making, attack all who approach; and pierce with their sting, as with a sword, those who draw near their hive, and repel them even unto death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.14.20'>But sympathy with her children did not turn aside the mother of the young men, who had a spirit kindred with that of Abraham.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.15'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.1'>O reasoning of the sons, lord over the passions, and religion more desirable to a mother than progeny!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.2'>The mother, when two things were set before here, religion and the safety of her seven sons for a time, on the conditional promise of a tyrant,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.3'>rather elected the religion which according to God preserves to eternal life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.4'>O in what way can I describe ethically the affections of parents toward their children, the resemblance of soul and of form engrafted into the small type of a child in a wonderful manner, especially through the greater sympathy of mothers with the feelings of those born of them!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.5'>for by how much mothers are by nature weak in disposition and prolific in offspring, by so much the fonder they are of children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.6'>And of all mothers the mother of the seven was the fondest of children, who in seven childbirths had deeply engendered love toward them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.7'>and through her many pains undergone in connection with each one, was compelled to feel sympathy with them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.8'>yet, through fear of God, who neglected the temporary salvation of her children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.9'>Not but that, on account of the excellent disposition to the law, her maternal affection toward them was increased.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.10'>For they were both just and temperate, and manly, and high-minded, and fond of their brethren, and so fond of their mother that even unto death they obeyed her by observing the law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.11'>And yet, though there were so many circumstances connected with love of children to draw on a mother to sympathy, in the case of none of them were the various tortures able to pervert her principle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.12'>But she inclined each one separately and all together to death for religion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.13'>O holy nature and parental feeling, and reward of bringing up children, and unconquerable maternal affection!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.14'>At the racking and roasting of each one of them, the observant mother was prevented by religion from changing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.15'>She beheld her children's flesh dissolving around the fire; and their extremities quivering on the ground, and the flesh of their heads dropped forwards down to their beards, like masks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.16'>O thou mother, who wast tried at this time with bitterer pangs than those of parturition!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.17'>O thou only woman who hast brought forth perfect holiness!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.18'>Thy first-born, expiring, turned thee not; nor the second, looking miserable in his torments; nor the third, breathing out his soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.19'>Nor when thou didst behold the eyes of each of them looking sternly upon their tortures, and their nostrils foreboding death, didst thou weep!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.20'>When thou didst see children's flesh heaped upon children's flesh that had been torn off, heads decapitated upon heads, dead falling upon the dead, and a choir of children turned through torture into a burying ground, thou lamentedst not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.21'>Not so do siren melodies, or songs of swans, attract the hearers to listening, O voices of children calling upon your mother in the midst of torments!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.22'>With what and what manner of torments was the mother herself tortured, as her sons were undergoing the wheel and the fires!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.23'>But religious reasoning, having strengthened her courage in the midst of sufferings, enabled her to forego, for the time, parental love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.24'>Although beholding the destruction of seven children, the noble mother, after one embrace, stripped off her feelings through faith in God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.25'>For just as in a council-room, beholding in her own soul vehement counsellors, nature and parentage and love of her children, and the racking of her children,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.26'>she holding two votes, one for the death, the other for the preservation of her children,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.27'>did not lean to that which would have saved her children for the safety of a brief space.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.28'>But this daughter of Abraham remembered his holy fortitude.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.29'>O holy mother of a nation avenger of the law, and defender of religion, and prime bearer in the battle of the affections!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.30'>O thou nobler in endurance than males, and more manly than men in patience!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.31'>For as the ark of Noah, bearing the world in the world-filling flood, bore up against the waves,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.15.32'>so thou, the guardian of the law, when surrounded on every side by the flood of passions, and straitened by violent storms which were the torments of they children, didst bear up nobly against the storms against religion.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.16'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.1'>If, then, even a woman, and that an aged one, and the mother of seven children, endured to see her children's torments even unto death, confessedly religious reasoning is master even of the passions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.2'>I have proved, then, that not only men have obtained the mastery of their passions, but also that a woman despised the greatest torments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.3'>And not so fierce were the lions round Daniel, nor the furnace of Misael burning with most vehement fires as that natural love of children burned within her, when she beheld her seven sons tortured.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.4'>But with the reasoning of religion the mother quenched passions so great and powerful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.5'>For we must consider also this: that, had the woman been faint hearted, as being their other, she would have lamented over them; and perhaps might have spoken thus:</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.6'>Ah! wretched I, and many times miserable; who having born seven sons, have become the mother of none.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.7'>O seven useless childbirths, and seven profitless periods of labour, and fruitless givings of suck, and miserable nursings at the breast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.8'>Vainly, for your sakes, O sons, have I endured many pangs, and the more difficult anxieties of rearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.9'>Alas, of my children, some of you unmarried, and some who have married to no profit, I shall not see your children, nor be felicitated as a grandmother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.10'>Ah, that I who had many and fair children, should be a lone widow full of sorrows!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.11'>Nor, should I die, shall I have a son to bury me. But with such a lament is this the holy and God-fearing mother bewailed none of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.12'>Nor did she divert any of them from death, nor grieve for them as for the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.13'>But as one possessed with an adamantine mind, and as one bringing forth again her full number of sons to immortality, she rather with supplication exhorted them to death in behalf of religion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.14'>O woman, soldier of God for religion, thou, aged and a female, hast conquered through endurance even a tyrant; and though but weak, hast been found more powerful in deeds and words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.15'>For when thou wast seized along with thy children, thou stoodest looking upon Eleazar in torments, and saidst to thy sons in the Hebrew tongue,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.16'>O sons, noble is the contest; to which you being called as a witness for the nation, strive zealously for the laws of your country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.17'>For it were disgraceful that this old man should endure pains for the sake of righteousness, and that you who are younger should be afraid of the tortures.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.18'>Remember that through God ye obtained existence, and have enjoyed it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.19'>And on this second account ye ought to bear every affliction because of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.20'>For whom also our father Abraham was forward to sacrifice Isaac our progenitor, and shuddered not at the sight of his own paternal hand descending down with the sword upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.21'>And the righteous Daniel was cast unto the lions; and Ananias, and Azarias, and Misael, were slung out into a furnace of fire; yet they endured through God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.22'>You, then, having the same faith towards God, be not troubled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.23'>For it is unreasonable that they who know religion should not stand up against troubles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.24'>With these arguments, the mother of seven, exhorting each of her sons, over-persuaded them from transgressing the commandment of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.16.25'>And they saw this, too, that they who die for God, live to God; as Abraham, and Isaac, and Jacob, and all the patriarchs.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.17'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.1'>And some of the spearbearers said, that when she herself was about to be seized for the purpose of being put to death, she threw herself upon the pile, rather than they should touch her person.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.2'>O thou mother, who together with seven children didst destroy the violence of the tyrant, and render void his wicked intentions, and exhibit the nobleness of faith!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.3'>For thou, as an house bravely built upon the pillar of thy children, didst bear without swaying, the shock of tortures.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.4'>Be of good cheer, therefore, O holy-minded mother! holding the firm substance of the hope of your steadfastness with God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.5'>Not so gracious does the moon appear with the stars in heaven, as thou art established honourable before God, and fixed in the firmament with thy sons who thou didst illuminate with religion to the stars.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.6'>For thy bearing of children was after the fashion of a child of Abraham.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.7'>And, were it lawful for us to paint as on a tablet the religion of thy story, the spectators would not shudder at beholding the mother of seven children enduring for the sake of religion various tortures even unto death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.8'>And it had been a worth thing to have inscribed upon the tomb itself these words as a memorial to those of the nation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.9'>Here an aged priest, and an aged woman, and seven sons, are buried through the violence of a tyrant, who wished to destroy the polity of the Hebrews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.10'>These also avenged their nation, looking unto God, and enduring torments unto death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.11'>For it was truly a divine contest which was carried through by them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.12'>For at that time virtue presided over the contest, approving the victory through endurance, namely, immortality, eternal life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.13'>Eleazar was the first to contend: and the mother of the seven children entered the contest; and the brethren contended.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.14'>The tyrant was the opposite; and the world and living men were the spectators.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.15'>And reverence for God conquered, and crowned her own athletes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.16'>Who did not admire those champions of true legislation? who were not astonied?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.17'>The tyrant himself, and all their council, admired their endurance;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.18'>through which, also, they now stand beside the divine throne, and live a blessed life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.19'>For Moses saith, And all the saints are under thine hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.20'>These, therefore, having been sanctified through God, have been honoured not only with this honour, but that also by their means the enemy did not overcome our nation;</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.21'>and that the tyrant was punished, and their country purified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.22'>For they became the atnipoised to the sin of the nation; and the Divine Providence saved Israel, aforetime afflicted, by the blood of those pious ones, and the propitiatory death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.23'>For the tyrant Antiochus, looking to their manly virtue, and to their endurance in torture, proclaimed that endurance as an example to his soldiers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.17.24'>And they proved to be to him noble and brave for land battles and for sieges; and he conquered and stormed the towns of all his enemies.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='4Macc.18'>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.1'>O Israelitish children, descendants of the seed of Abraham, obey this law, and in every way be religious.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.2'>Knowing that religious reasoning is lord of the passions, and those not only inward but outward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.3'>When those persons giving up their bodies to pains for the sake of religion, were not only admired by men, but were deemed worthy of a divine portion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.4'>And the nation through them obtained peace, and having renewed the observance of the law in their country, drove the enemy out of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.5'>And the tyrant Antiochus was both punished upon earth, and is punished now he is dead; for when he was quite unable to compel the Israelites to adopt foreign customs, and to desert the manner of life of their fathers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.6'>then, departing from Jerusalem, he made war against the Persians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.7'>And the righteous mother of the seven children spake also as follows to her offspring: I was a pure virgin, and went not beyond my father's house; but I took care of the built-up rib.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.8'>No destroyer of the desert, or ravisher of the plain, injured me; nor did the destructive, deceitful snake, make spoil of my chaste virginity; and I remained with my husband during the period of my prime.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.9'>And these my children, having arrive at maturity, their father died: blessed was he! for having sought out a life of fertility in children, he was not grieved with a period of loss of children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.10'>And he used to teach you, when yet with you, the law and the prophets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.11'>He used to read to you the slaying of Abel by Cain, and the offering up of Isaac, and the imprisonment of Joseph.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.12'>And he used to tell you of the zealous Phinehas; and informed you of Ananias and Azarias, and Misael in the fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.13'>And he used to glorify Daniel, who was in the den of lions, and pronounce him blessed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.14'>And he used to put you in mind of the scripture of Esaias, which saith, Even if thou pass through the fire, it shall not burn thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.15'>He chanted to you David, the hymn-writer, who saith, Many are the afflictions of the just.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.16'>He declared the proverbs of Solomon, who saith, He is a tree of life to all those who do His will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.17'>He used to verify Ezekiel, who said, Shall these dry bones live?</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.18'>For he did not forget the song which Moses taught, proclaiming, I will kill, and I will make to live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.19'>This is our life, and the length of our days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.20'>O that bitter, and yet not bitter, day when the bitter tyrant of the Greeks, quenching fire with fire in his cruel caldrons, brought with boiling rage the seven sons of the daughter of Abraham to the catapelt, and to all his torments!</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.21'>He pierced the balls of their eyes, and cut out their tongues, and put them to death with varied tortures.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.22'>Wherefore divine retribution pursued and will pursue the pestilent wretch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.23'>But the children of Abraham, with their victorious mother, are assembled together to the choir of their fathers; having received pure and immortal souls from God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='4Macc.18.24'>To whom be glory for ever and ever. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>