<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='LXXE' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='LXXE'>
        <title>Brenton's English Septuagint</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>

Introduction
~~~~~~~~~~~~

  The Septuagint is the most ancient translation of the Old Testament into
  Greek. The translators were likely Jews of the dispersion, living in
  Alexandria, Egypt.

  The beginning of the Jewish presence in Egypt is difficult to date
  precisely. There may have been a Jewish colony there as early as the tenth
  century BC, when Shishak (Shashanq) invaded Palestine and took treasures
  from the temple and the king's palace (2 Chronicles 12.1-8). But certainly a
  number of Jews lived in Egypt after the murder of Gedaliah (~586 BC), when
  "the captains of the forces set out and went to Egypt; for they were afraid
  of the Chaldeans" (2 Kings 25-26). Jeremiah, Baruch, and the princesses also
  went into Egypt at that time, though Jeremiah prophecied that they would all
  "perish by the sword and by famine, until not one is left" (Jeremiah 43.6,
  44.27). One expects, on the basis of that prophecy, that this was not the
  beginning of a permanent settlement. A lasting Jewish presence in Egypt can,
  however, be definitely dated from the the time of the founding of the city
  of Alexandria in 332 BC, when Alexander the Great granted them citizenship.

  In time, the Jews in Alexandria lost familiarity with Hebrew, and spoke
  Greek instead. It was natural, then, that they would require a translation
  of the scriptures into Greek for public worship in the synagogues and for
  private study. An account of the translation of the Septuagint is told in
  The Letter of Aristeas, which claims that Demetrius Phalereus, who ran the
  royal library in Alexandria, urged the king (Philadelphus (285-247 BC)) to
  obtain a copy of the Jewish law for the library. Philadelphus sent a
  deputation to the high priest Eleazar in Jerusalem, and the result was that
  seventy-two elders arrived in Egypt with a copy of the Hebrew law written on
  rolls of skins in golden letters. They were given accommodations on the
  island of Pharos, and completed their translation in seventy-two days. The
  same basic account is given in Aristobulus, Philo, and Josephus.

  Even if the account given in the Letter of Aristeas is inaccurate, it seems
  clear that the Hebrew Old Testament was available in Greek in Alexandria
  before the birth of Christ. As Christianity began to spread, the Septuagint
  was used with persuasive effect by Christian apologists - so well, in fact,
  that in time the Jews of the dispersion replaced it with newer works. For
  instance, a proselyte to Judaism named Aquila completed a extremely literal
  translation of the Old Testament into Greek about the year 128. Other
  translations were made by Theodotion of Ephesus and a certain Symmachus,
  called an Ebionite, also in the second century.

  The most ancient manuscripts of the complete (or nearly complete) Septuagint
  are known as Vaticanus, Sinaiticus, and Alexandrinus. Vaticanus and
  Sinaiticus have been dated to the mid-fourth century, and Alexandrinus to
  the fifth. 

  Based on an earlier Hebrew original, the Septuagint departs from the
  Masoretic text* frequently. "The book of Jeremiah is noteworthy," for
  instance, "in that the present Hebrew text differs substantially from the
  Greek version (the Septuagint) in both content and order. Thus the
  Septuagint omits several passages (e.g., 33.14-26) and combines the oracles
  against foreign nations into a single section following 25.14, though in a
  different order. In addition, there are many smaller differences from verse
  to verse. Remarkably, among the portions of the text of Jeremiah in Hebrew
  that are found among the Dead Sea Scrolls are not only those that reflect
  the standard Hebrew text but also those that reflect the text tradition
  represented by the Septuagint. It is likely, then, that these two text
  traditions represent the contrasting editorial work on the book of Jeremiah
  that took place in Egypt (the Septuagint tradition) and in Palestine or
  Babylon (the traditional Hebrew text)." [Introduction to the book of
  Jeremiah, The New Oxford Annotated Bible, page 960.] Around the end of the
  first century, the Hebrew text was standardized to a form nearly identical
  with the modern Masoretic text. Variant readings, such as those represented
  in the Septuagint, were no longer transmitted in the Hebrew language. 

      * The Masoretic text is the source from which modern translations intoEnglish are made. While the oldest complete manuscripts of theSeptuagint date from the fourth century, the oldest complete HebrewOld Testament, the Leningrad Codex, was copied in ~ 1008 A.D. ModernEnglish translations of the Old Testament rely primarily on theLeningrad Codex as published in the Hebraica Stuttgartensia. Forexamples of Septuagint departures from the Masoretic text supported bythe Dead Sea Scrolls, see the appendix.

      * Another contrast between the Septuagint and the modern Hebrew OldTestament involves the canon of scripture. The Septuagint includesseveral books and sections of books absent from the modern Hebrewtext: 1 Esdras; Tobit; Judith; 1-3 Maccabees; the Wisdom of Solomon;the Wisdom of Sirach (Ecclesiasticus); Baruch; the Epistle ofJeremiah; The Song of the Three Children; Daniel and Susanna; Daniel,Bel and the Dragon; Additions to the Book of Esther; Psalm 151; andthe Prayer of Manasseh. The difference in content has been explainedin various ways. Perhaps the most straightforward account is that theJews of Alexandria had a relatively broad canon, which was generallyadopted by the Christians as they employed the Septuagint as their OldTestament. The Jews of Palestine, when they established their canonaround the turn of the first century at the council of Jamnia, mayhave been reiterating the position that had been more or less settledin Palestine for some time - though some books just made (Esther,Ecclesiastes, the Song of Solomon, and Ezekiel, for instance) ormissed (Sirach) the cut. The conflict with Christians may have servedas a catalyst to push the Jews of the dispersion into the Palestiniancamp. This article - concerned with the text of the books within theHebrew canon - will not address the controversy surrounding the OldTestament canon in any depth.

  From the time of Jerome (early fifth century), Old Testament translations to
  the vernacular in the West have used the Hebrew as the primary source - the
  Septuagint has been relegated to a secondary role. (Incidentally, some are
  under the mistaken impression - given by misleading language in the preface
  to the 1899 edition - that the Douay Old Testament was translated from a
  Latin text based on the Septuagint. Unfortunately, Jerome's Vulgate - apart
  from the Psalms and the books then available only in Greek - by and large
  follows the Hebrew text.) It is hoped that the reader will reconsider the
  wisdom of this course of action, given the clear preference the New
  Testament displays for Septuagint readings. Fortunately, a new English
  translation of the Septuagint is being prepared for publication in 2004.

  This article comprises two main sections. The first deals with the early
  Church’s use of the Septuagint - particularly their sense that the Hebrew
  text was unreliable. It begins with the discussion between Jerome and
  Augustine regarding the former’s decision to craft his Latin translation
  from the available Hebrew text, rather than from the Septuagint. It is from
  Jerome’s fateful choice that the West derives its tradition of favoring the
  Hebrew to the Greek. The second part of this article provides a detailed
  comparison of the New Testament quotations from the Old. These were made to
  assess the extent to which the New Testament authors depended on the
  Septuagint instead of the Hebrew text. Conclusions are given in the The
  Septuagint in the New Testament.

    </description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>LXXE</identifier>
        <source>

http://www.answersingenesis.org/OnlineBible/files/lxxe.exe

The Septuagint LXX in English
http://www.christianmedia.us/LXXE/

The English Translation of the Septuagint Bible Online
http://www.ecmarsh.com/lxx/    

    </source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>
    
      1851 Brenton's English Septuagint

The Bible text designated LXXE is from an English
translation of The Septuagint by Sir Lancelot 
Charles Lee Brenton, originally published in 1851. 
The electronic text is copyright 1988 by FABS 
International, Inc. Footnotes, additions, and 
corrections to the main text copyright 1999 by Larry 
Nelson, Box 2083, Rialto, CA  92376. All rights 
reserved. Used by permission.

  </rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Song'>
      <chapter osisID='Song.1'>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.1'>The Song of songs, which is Solomon’s.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.2'>Let him kiss me with the kisses of his mouth: for thy breasts are better than wine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.3'>And the smell of thine ointments is <note>Gr. beyond</note> better than all spices: thy name is ointment poured forth; therefore do the young maidens love thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.4'>They have drawn thee: we will run after thee, for the smell of thine ointments: the king has brought me into closet: let us rejoice and be glad in thee; we will love thy breasts more than wine: righteousness loves thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.5'>I am black, but beautiful, ye daughters of Jerusalem, as the tents of Kedar, as the <note>Lit. skins</note> curtains of Solomon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.6'>Look not upon me, because I am dark, because the sun has looked unfavourably upon me: my mother’s sons strove with me; they made me keeper in the vineyards; I have not kept my own vineyard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.7'>Tell me, thou whom my soul loves, where thou tendest thy flock, where thou causest them to rest at noon, lest I become as one <note>Or, that veils herself</note> that is veiled by the flocks of thy companions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.8'>If thou know not thyself, thou fair one among women, go thou forth by the footsteps of the flocks, and feed thy kids by the shepherd’s tents.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.9'>I have likened thee, my companion, to my horses in the chariots of Pharao.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.10'>How are thy cheeks beautiful as those of a dove, thy neck as chains!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.11'>We will make thee figures of gold with studs of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.12'>So long as the king was at table, my spikenard gave forth its smell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.13'>My kinsman is to me a bundle of myrrh; he shall lie between my breasts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.14'>My kinsman is to me a cluster of camphor in the vineyards of Engaddi.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.15'>Behold, thou art fair, my companion; behold, thou art fair; thine eyes are doves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.16'>Behold, thou art fair, my kinsman, yea, beautiful, overshadowing our bed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.1.17'>The beams of our house are cedars, our <note>Or, wainscots</note> ceilings are of cypress.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Song.2'>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.1'>I am a flower of the plain, a lily of the valleys.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.2'>As a lily among thorns, so is my companion among the daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.3'>As the apple among the trees of the wood, so is my kinsman among the sons. I desired his shadow, and sat down, and his fruit was sweet in my throat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.4'>Bring me into the wine house; set love before me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.5'>Strengthen me with perfumes, stay me with apples: for I am wounded with love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.6'>His left hand shall be under my head, and his right hand shall embrace me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.7'>I have charged you, ye daughters of Jerusalem, by the <note>Comp. Heb. and A. V.</note> powers and by the virtues of the field, that ye do not rouse or wake my love, until he please.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.8'>The voice of my kinsman! behold, he comes leaping over the mountains, bounding over the hills.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.9'>My kinsman is like a roe or a young hart on the mountains of Baethel: behold, he is behind our wall, looking through the windows, peeping through the <note>Lit. nets</note> lattices.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.10'>My kinsman answers, and says to me, Rise up, come, my companion, my fair one, my dove.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.11'>For, behold, the winter is past, the rain is gone, it has departed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.12'>The flowers are seen in the land; the time of pruning has arrived; the voice of the turtle-dove has been heard in our land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.13'>The fig-tree has put forth its young figs, the vines put forth the tender grape, they yield a smell: arise, come, my companion, my fair one, my dove; yea, come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.14'>Thou art my dove, in the shelter of the rock, near the wall: shew me thy face, and cause me to hear thy voice; for thy voice is sweet, and thy countenance is beautiful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.15'>Take us the little foxes that spoil the vines: for our vines put forth tender grapes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.16'>My kinsman is mine, and I am his: he feeds his flock among the lilies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.2.17'>Until the day dawn, and the shadows depart, turn, my kinsman, be thou like to a roe or young hart on the mountains of the ravines.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Song.3'>
        <verse osisID='Song.3.1'>By night on my bed I sought him whom my soul loves: I sought him, but found him not; I called him, but he hearkened not to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.3.2'>I will rise now, and go about in the city, in the market-places, and in the streets, and I will seek him whom my soul loves: I sought him, but I found him not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.3.3'>The watchmen who go their rounds in the city found me. I said, Have ye seen him whom my soul loves?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.3.4'>It was as a little while after I parted from them, that I found him whom my soul loves: I held him, and did not let him go, until I brought him into my mother’s house, and into the chamber of her that conceived me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.3.5'>I have charged you, O daughters of Jerusalem, by the <note>Comp. Heb. and A. V.</note> powers and by the virtues of the field, that ye rouse not nor awake my love, until he please.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.3.6'>Who is this that comes up from the wilderness as pillars of smoke, perfumed with myrrh and frankincense, with all powders of the perfumer?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.3.7'>Behold Solomon’s bed; sixty mighty men of the mighty ones of Israel are round about it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.3.8'>They all hold a sword, being expert in war: every man has his sword upon his thigh because of fear by night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.3.9'>King Solomon made himself a litter of woods of Lebanon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.3.10'>He made the pillars of it silver, the bottom of it gold, the covering of it scarlet, in the midst of it a pavement of love, for the daughters of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.3.11'>Go forth, ye daughters of Sion, and behold king Solomon, with the crown wherewith his mother crowned him, in the day of his espousals, and in the day of the gladness of his heart.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Song.4'>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.1'>Behold, thou art fair, my companion; behold, thou art fair; thine eyes are doves, beside thy <note>Lit. silence</note> veil: thy hair is as flocks of goats, that have appeared from Galaad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.2'>Thy teeth are as flocks of shorn sheep, that have gone up from the washing; all of them bearing twins, and there is not a barren one among them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.3'>Thy lips are as a thread of scarlet, and thy speech is comely: like the rind of a pomegranate is thy cheek without thy <note>Lit. silence</note> veil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.4'>Thy neck is as the tower of David, that was built for an armoury: a thousand shields hang upon it, and all darts of mighty men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.5'>Thy two breasts are as two twin fawns, that feed among the lilies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.6'>Until the day dawn, and the shadows depart, I will betake me to the mountain of myrrh, and to the hill of frankincense.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.7'>Thou art all fair, my companion, and there is no spot in thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.8'>Come from Libanus, my bride, come from Libanus: thou shalt come and pass from the top of <note>Heb. Amana</note> Faith, from the top of Sanir and Hermon, from the lions’ dens, from the mountains of the leopards.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.9'>My sister, my spouse, thou hast ravished my heart; thou hast ravished my heart with one of thine eyes, with one chain of thy neck.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.10'>
          <note>Gr. Why have they been made beautiful, etc.</note> How beautiful are thy breasts, my sister, my spouse! how much more beautiful are thy breasts than wine, and the smell of thy garments than all spices!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.11'>Thy lips drop honeycomb, my spouse: honey and milk are under thy tongue; and the smell of thy garments is as the smell of Libanus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.12'>My sister, my spouse is a garden enclosed; a garden enclosed, a fountain sealed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.13'>Thy shoots are a garden of pomegranates, with the fruit of choice berries; camphor, with spikenard:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.14'>spikenard and saffron, calamus and cinnamon; with all woods of Libanus, myrrh, aloes, with all chief spices:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.15'>a fountain of a garden, and a well of water springing and gurgling from Libanus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.4.16'>Awake, O north wind; and come, O south; and blow through my garden, and let my spices flow out.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Song.5'>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.1'>Let my kinsman come down into his garden, and eat the fruit of his choice berries. I am come into my garden, my sister, my spouse: I have gathered my myrrh with my spices; I have eaten my bread with my honey; I have drunk my wine with my milk. Eat, O friends, and drink; yea, brethren, drink abundantly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.2'>I sleep, but my heart is awake: the voice of my kinsman knocks at the door, saying, Open, open to me, my companion, my sister, my dove, my perfect one: for my head is filled with dew, and my locks with the drops of the night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.3'>I have put off my coat; how shall I put it on? I have washed my feet, how shall I defile them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.4'>My kinsman put forth his hand by the hole of the door, and my belly moved for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.5'>I rose up to open to my kinsman; my hands dropped myrrh, my fingers choice myrrh, on the handles of the lock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.6'>I opened to my kinsman; my kinsman was gone: my soul <note>Gr. went forth</note> failed at his speech: I sought him, but found him not; I called him, but he answered me not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.7'>The watchman that go their rounds in the city found me, they smote me, they wounded me; the keepers of the walls took away my veil from me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.8'>I have charged you, O daughters of Jerusalem, by the powers and the virtues of the field: if ye should find my kinsman, what are ye to say to him? That I am wounded with love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.9'>What is thy kinsman more than another kinsman, O thou beautiful among women? what is thy kinsman more than another kinsman, that thou hast so charged us?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.10'>My kinsman is white and ruddy, chosen out from myriads.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.11'>His head is as very fine gold, his locks are flowing, black as a raven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.12'>His eyes are as doves, by the pools of waters, washed with milk, sitting by the pools.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.13'>His cheeks are as bowls of spices pouring forth perfumes: his lips are lilies, dropping choice myrrh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.14'>His hands are as <note>Or, gold rings</note> turned gold set with <note>q. d. from Tarshish</note> beryl: his belly is an ivory tablet on a sapphire stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.15'>His legs are marble pillars set on golden sockets: his form is as Libanus, choice as the cedars.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.16'>His throat is most sweet, and altogether desirable. This is my kinsman, and this is my companion, O daughters of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.5.17'>Whither is thy kinsman gone, thou beautiful among women? whither has thy kinsman <note>Gr. looked aside</note> turned aside? tell us, and we will seek him with thee.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Song.6'>
        <verse osisID='Song.6.1'>My kinsman is gone down to his garden, to the beds of spice, to feed his flock in the gardens, and to gather lilies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.6.2'>I am my kinsman’s, and my kinsman is mine, who feeds among the lilies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.6.3'>Thou art fair, my companion, as Pleasure, beautiful as Jerusalem, terrible as armies set in array.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.6.4'>Turn away thine eyes from before me, for they have ravished me: thy hair is as flocks of goats which have appeared from Galaad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.6.5'>Thy teeth are as flocks of shorn sheep, that have gone up from the washing, all of them bearing twins, and there is none barren among them: thy lips are as a thread of scarlet, and thy speech is comely.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.6.6'>Thy cheek is like the rind of a pomegranate, being seen without thy veil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.6.7'>There are sixty queens, and eighty concubines, and maidens without number.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.6.8'>My dove, my perfect one is one; she is the only one of her mother; she is the choice of her that bore her. The daughters saw her, and the queens will pronounce her blessed, yea, and the concubines, and they will praise her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.6.9'>Who is this that looks forth as the morning, fair as the moon, choice as the sun, terrible as armies set in array?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.6.10'>I went down to the garden of nuts, to look at the fruits of the valley, to see if the vine flowered, if the pomegranates blossomed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.6.11'>There I will give thee my breasts: my soul knew it not: it made me as the chariots of Aminadab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.6.12'>Return, return, O Sunamite; return, return, and we will look at thee. What will ye see in the Sunamite? <note>Or, O thou that comest, etc.</note> She comes as bands of armies.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Song.7'>
        <verse osisID='Song.7.1'>Thy steps are beautiful in shoes, O daughter of the prince: the joints of thy thighs are like chains, the work of the craftsman.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.7.2'>Thy navel is as a turned bowl, not wanting liquor; thy belly is as a heap of wheat set about with lilies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.7.3'>Thy two breasts are as two twin fawns.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.7.4'>Thy neck is as an ivory tower; thine eyes are as pools in Esebon, by the gates of the <note>Heb. Bath-rabbim</note> daughter of many: thy nose is as the tower of Libanus, looking toward Damascus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.7.5'>Thy head upon thee is as Carmel, and the curls of thy hair like scarlet; the king is bound in the <note>Or, corridors</note> galleries.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.7.6'>How beautiful art thou, and how sweet art thou, my love!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.7.7'>This is thy greatness in thy delights: thou wast made like a palm tree, and thy breasts to cluster.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.7.8'>I said, I will go up to the palm tree, I will take hold of its high boughs: and now shall thy breasts be as clusters of the vine, and the smell of thy nose of apples;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.7.9'>and thy throat as good wine, going well with my kinsman, suiting my lips and teeth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.7.10'>I am my kinsman’s, and his <note>Lit. turning</note> desire is toward me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.7.11'>Come, my kinsman, let us go forth into the field; let us lodge in the villages.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.7.12'>Let us go early into the vineyards; let us see if the vine has flowered, if the blossoms have appeared, if the pomegranates have blossomed; there will I give thee my breasts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.7.13'>The mandrakes have given a smell, and at our doors are all kinds of choice fruits, new and old. O my kinsman, I have kept them for thee.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Song.8'>
        <verse osisID='Song.8.1'>
          <note>Gr. Who will give, etc.</note> I would that thou, O my kinsman, wert he that sucked the breasts of my mother; when I found thee without, I would kiss thee; yea, they should not despise me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.8.2'>I would take thee, I would bring thee into my mother’s house, and into the chamber of her that conceived me; I would make thee to drink of spiced wine, of the juice of my pomegranates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.8.3'>His left hand should be under my head, and his right hand should embrace me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.8.4'>I have charged you, ye daughters of Jerusalem, by the virtues of the field, that ye stir not up, nor awake my love, until he please.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.8.5'>Who is this that comes up all white, leaning on her kinsman? I raised thee up under an apple-tree; there thy mother brought thee forth; there she that bore thee brought thee forth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.8.6'>Set me as a seal upon thy heart, as a seal upon thine arm; for love is strong as death; jealousy is cruel as the grave, her shafts are shafts of fire, even the flames thereof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.8.7'>Much water will not be able to quench love, and rivers shall not drown it; if a man would give all his substance for love, men would utterly despise it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.8.8'>Our sister is little, and has no breasts; what shall we do for our sister, in the day wherein she shall be spoken for?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.8.9'>If she is a wall, let us build upon her silver bulwarks; and if she is a door, let us carve for her cedar panels.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.8.10'>I am a wall, and my breasts are as towers; I was in their eyes as one that found peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.8.11'>Solomon had a vineyard in Beelamon; he let his vineyard to keepers; every one was to bring for its fruit a thousand pieces of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.8.12'>My vineyard, even mine, is before me; Solomon shall have a thousand, and they that keep its fruit two hundred.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.8.13'>Thou that dwellest in the gardens, the companions hearken to thy voice: make me hear it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Song.8.14'>Away, my kinsman, and be like a doe or a fawn on the mountains of spices.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>