<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText xml:lang='en' osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='GB'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='GB'>
        <title>Geneva Bible</title>
        <contributor>http://www.e-sword.net/files/bibles/geneva.exe
         http://www.e-sword.net/files/commentaries/geneva.exe</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>Geneva Bible, 1587,Geneva,

THE BIBLE: THAT IS, THE HOLY SCRIPTVRES CONTEINED IN THE OLDE AND NEWE TESTAMENT. 
TRANSLATED ACCORDING TO the Ebrew and Greeke, and conferred with the best 
translations in diuers languages.

FEARE YE NOT, STAND STILL, AND beholde the saluation of the Lorde, which he will 
shew to you this day. -- Exod.14.13.

Great are the troubles of the righteous: but the Lord deliuereth him out of them 
all. -- Psalme 34.19.

THE LORD SHALL FIGHT FOR YOV, therefore hold you your peace. -- Exodus 14.14.

IMPRINTED AT LONDON by Christopher Barker, Printer to the Qveenes Maiestie. 1587. 
Cum priuilegio.</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>GB</identifier>
        <source>http://www.e-sword.net/</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights/>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Jude'>
      <chapter osisID='Jude.1'>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.1'>Jude, the servant of Jesus Christ, and <note>This is to distinguish between him and Judas Iscariot.</note> brother of James, to them that are sanctified <note>By God the Father.</note> by God the Father, and preserved in Jesus Christ, [and] called:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.2'>Mercie vnto you, and peace and loue be multiplied.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.3'>
          <note>The goal of this epistle, is to affirm the godly as opposed to certain wicked men both in true doctrine and good conduct.</note>Beloved, when I gave all diligence to write unto you of the <note>Of those things that pertain to the salvation of all of us.</note> common salvation, it was needful for me to write unto you, and exhort [you] that ye should <note>That you should defend the faith with all the strength you can muster, both by true doctrine and good example of life.</note> earnestly contend for the faith which was <note>Which was once given, that it may never be changed.</note> once delivered unto the saints.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.4'>
          <note>It is by God's providence and not by chance, that many wicked men creep into the Church.</note>For there are certain men crept in unawares, who were before of old ordained to this condemnation, <note>He condemns this first in them, that they take opportunity or occasion to wax wanton, by the grace of God: which cannot be, but the chief empire of Christ must be cancelled, in that such men give themselves up to Satan, whom they call Libertines.</note> ungodly men, turning the grace of our God into lasciviousness, and denying the only Lord God, and our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.5'>
          <note>He presents the horrible punishment of those who have abused the grace of God to follow their own lusts.</note>I will therefore put you in remembrance, though ye once knew this, how that the Lord, having saved the people out of the land of Egypt, afterward destroyed them that believed not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.6'>
          <note>The fall of the angels was most severely punished, how much more then will the Lord punish wicked and faithless men?</note>And the angels which kept not their first estate, but left their own habitation, he hath reserved in everlasting chains under darkness unto the judgment of the great day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.7'>Even as Sodom and Gomorrha, and the cities about them in like manner, <note>Following the steps of Sodom and Gomorrah.</note> giving themselves over to fornication, and going after <note>Thus he sets forth their horrible and wicked perversions.</note> strange flesh, are set forth for an example, suffering the vengeance of eternal fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.8'>Likewise also these <note>Who are so stupid and void of reason as if all their fears and wits were asleep.</note> [filthy] dreamers defile the flesh, <note>Another most destructive doctrine of theirs, in that they take away the authority of the government and slander them.</note> despise <note>It is a greater matter to despise government than the governors, that is to say, the matter itself than the persons.</note> dominion, and speak evil of dignities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.9'>
          <note>An argument of comparison: Michael one of the chiefest angels, was content to deliver Satan, although a most accursed enemy, to the judgment of God to be punished: and these perverse men are not ashamed to speak evil of the powers who are ordained of God.</note>Yet Michael the archangel, when contending with the devil he disputed about the body of Moses, durst not bring against him a railing accusation, but said, The Lord rebuke thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.10'>
          <note>The conclusion: These men are doubly at fault, that is, both for their rash folly in condemning some, and for their impudent and shameless contempt of that knowledge, which when they had gotten, yet nonetheless they lived as brute beasts, serving their bellies.</note>But these speak evil of those things which they know not: but what they know naturally, as brute beasts, in those things they corrupt themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.11'>
          <note>He foretells their destruction, because they resemble or proclaim Cain's shameless malice, Balaam's filthy covetousness, and to be short, Core's seditious and ambitious head.</note>Woe unto them! for they have gone in the way of Cain, and ran greedily after the error of Balaam for reward, and perished in the gainsaying of Core.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.12'>
          <note>He rebukes most sharply with many other notes and marks, both their dishonesty or filthiness, and their sauciness, but especially, their vain bravery of words and vain pride, joining with it a grave and heavy threatening from an ancient prophecy of Enoch concerning the judgment to come.</note>These are spots in your <note>The feasts of charity were certain banquets, which the brethren who were members of the Church kept altogether, as Tertullian sets them forth in his apology, chap. 39.</note> feasts of charity, when they feast with you, feeding themselves without <note>Impudently, without all reverence either to God or man.</note> fear: clouds [they are] without water, carried about of winds; trees whose fruit withereth, without fruit, twice dead, plucked up by the roots;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.13'>Raging waves of the sea, foaming out their own shame; wandering stars, to whom is reserved the <note>Most gross darkness.</note> blackness of darkness for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.14'>And Enoch also, the seventh from Adam, prophesied of these, saying, Behold, the Lord <note>The present time, for the time to come.</note> cometh with ten thousands of his saints,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.15'>To giue iudgement against al men, and to rebuke all the vngodly among them of all their wicked deeds, which they haue vngodly committed, and of all their cruel speakings, which wicked sinners haue spoken against him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.16'>These are murmurers, complainers, walking after their owne lustes: Whose mouthes speake proud things, hauing mens persons in admiration, because of aduantage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.17'>
          <note>The rising up of such monsters was spoken of before, that we should not be troubled at the newness of the matter.</note>But, beloved, remember ye the words which were spoken before of the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.18'>How that they told you that there should be mockers in ye last time, which should walke after their owne vngodly lustes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.19'>
          <note>It is the habit of antichrists to separate themselves from the godly, because they are not governed by the Spirit of God: and contrariwise it is the habit of Christians to edify one another through godly prayers, both in faith and also in love, until the mercy of Christ appears to their full salvation.</note>These be they who separate themselves, sensual, having not the Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.20'>But, yee beloued, edifie your selues in your most holy faith, praying in the holy Ghost,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.21'>And keepe your selues in the loue of God, looking for the mercie of our Lorde Iesus Christ, vnto eternall life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.22'>
          <note>Among those who wander and go astray, the godly have to use this choice, that they handle some of them gently, and that others being even in the very flame, they endeavour to save with severe and sharp instruction of the present danger: yet so, that they do in such sort abhor the wicked and dishonest, that they avoid even the least thought of them.</note>And of some have compassion, making a difference:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.23'>And others save with <note>By fearing them and holding them back with godly severity.</note> fear, pulling [them] out of the fire; hating even the <note>An amplification, taken from the forbidden things of the law which did defile.</note> garment spotted by the flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.24'>
          <note>He commends them to the grace of God, declaring sufficiently that it is God only that can give us that constancy which he requires of us.</note>Now unto him that is able to keep you from falling, and to present [you] faultless before the presence of his glory with exceeding joy,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.25'>That is, to God only wise, our Sauiour, be glorie, and maiestie, and dominion, and power, both nowe and for euer, Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>