<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText xml:lang='en' osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='GB'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='GB'>
        <title>Geneva Bible</title>
        <contributor>http://www.e-sword.net/files/bibles/geneva.exe
         http://www.e-sword.net/files/commentaries/geneva.exe</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>Geneva Bible, 1587,Geneva,

THE BIBLE: THAT IS, THE HOLY SCRIPTVRES CONTEINED IN THE OLDE AND NEWE TESTAMENT. 
TRANSLATED ACCORDING TO the Ebrew and Greeke, and conferred with the best 
translations in diuers languages.

FEARE YE NOT, STAND STILL, AND beholde the saluation of the Lorde, which he will 
shew to you this day. -- Exod.14.13.

Great are the troubles of the righteous: but the Lord deliuereth him out of them 
all. -- Psalme 34.19.

THE LORD SHALL FIGHT FOR YOV, therefore hold you your peace. -- Exodus 14.14.

IMPRINTED AT LONDON by Christopher Barker, Printer to the Qveenes Maiestie. 1587. 
Cum priuilegio.</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>GB</identifier>
        <source>http://www.e-sword.net/</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights/>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Luke'>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.1'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.1'>Forasmuch as <note>Luke commends the witnesses that saw this present account.</note> many have <note>Many took it in hand, but did not perform: Luke wrote his gospel before Matthew and Mark.</note> taken in hand to set forth in order a declaration of those things which are most surely believed among us,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.2'>
          <note>Luke was not any eye witness, and therefore it was not he to whom the Lord appeared when Cleopas saw him: and he was taught not only by Paul, but by others of the apostles also.</note>Even as they delivered them unto us, which from the beginning were eyewitnesses, and ministers of the word;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.3'>It seemed good to me also, having had perfect understanding of all things <note>Luke began his gospel a great deal further in the past than the others did.</note> from the very first, to write unto thee in order, <note>It is «most mighty», and therefore Theophilus was a very honourable man, and in a place of great dignity.</note> most excellent Theophilus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.4'>That thou mightest <note>Have fuller knowledge of those things which you know only partially.</note> know the certainty of those things, wherein thou hast been instructed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.5'>There <note>John, who was another Elias and appointed to be the herald of Christ, coming from the family of Aaron, and of two famous and blameless parents, has shown in his conception (which was against the course of nature) a double miracle, to the end that men should be more readily prepared for the hearing of his preaching, according to the forewarning of the prophets.</note> was <note>This is a Hebrew idiom which shows us how short and frail a thing the power of princes is.</note> in the days of <note>Herod the great.</note> Herod, the king of Judaea, a certain priest named Zacharias, of the <note>For the posterity of Aaron was divided into courses.</note> course of Abia: and his wife [was] of the daughters of Aaron, and her name [was] Elisabeth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.6'>And they were both <note>The true mark of righteousness is demonstrated when one is liked and accepted in the judgment of God.</note> righteous before God, <note>Lived, as the Hebrews say, for our life is as a way in which we must walk until we come to the mark.</note> walking in all the <note>In all the moral and ceremonial law.</note> commandments and ordinances of the Lord <note>Whom no man could justly reprove: now so it is that the fruits of justification are set forth here, and not the cause, which is faith only, and nothing else.</note> blameless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.7'>And they had no childe, because that Elisabet was barren: and both were well stricken in age.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.8'>And it came to passe, as he executed the Priestes office before God, as his course came in order,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.9'>According to the custom of the priest's office, his lot was to burn incense when he went into the <note>The temple was one, and the court another, for Zacharias went out of the court (or outward room) where all the people were (and therefore they are said to be without) and into the temple.</note> temple of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.10'>And the whole multitude of the people were without in prayer, while the incense was burning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.11'>Then appeared vnto him an Angel of the Lorde standing at the right side of the altar of incense.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.12'>And when Zacharias sawe him, he was troubled, and feare fell vpon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.13'>But the Angel saide vnto him, Feare not, Zacharias: for thy prayer is heard, and thy wise Elisabet shall beare thee a sonne, and thou shalt call his name Iohn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.14'>And thou shalt haue ioy and gladnes, and many shall reioyce at his birth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.15'>For he shall be great in the <note>So the Hebrews say when a rare kind of excellency is signified: so it is said of Nimrod in (Gen_10:9), «He was a mighty hunter before the LORD».</note> sight of the Lord, and shall drink neither wine nor <note>Any drink that might make someone drunk.</note> strong drink; and he shall be filled with the Holy Ghost, even from his mother's womb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.16'>And many of the children of Israel shall he <note>Shall be a means to bring many to repentance, and they will turn themselves to the Lord, from whom they fell.</note> turn to the Lord their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.17'>And he shall go <note>As they used to go before kings, and when you see them, you know the king is not far off.</note> before him <note>This is spoken by the figure of speech metonymy, taking the spirit for the gift of the spirit; as you would say, the cause of that which comes from the cause.</note> in the spirit and power of Elias, to turn the <note>By the figure of speech synecdoche he shows that he will take away all types of enmities which used to breed great troubles and turmoils among men.</note> hearts of the fathers to the children, and the disobedient to the <note>Wisdom and goodness are two of the main causes which make men revere and honour their fathers.</note> wisdom of the just; to make ready a people prepared for the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.18'>Then Zacharias said vnto ye Angel, Whereby shall I knowe this? For I am an olde man, and my wife is of a great age.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.19'>And the angel answering said unto him, I am Gabriel, <note>That appears, for so the Hebrews use this saying «to stand» to mean that they are ready to do his commandment.</note> that stand in the presence of God; and am sent to speak unto thee, and to shew thee these glad tidings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.20'>And beholde, thou shalt be domme, &amp; not be able to speake, vntill the day that these things be done, because thou beleeuedst not my words, which shalbe fulfilled in their season.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.21'>Now the people waited for Zacharias, and marueiled that he taried so long in the Temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.22'>And when hee came out, hee coulde not speake vnto them: then they perceiued that hee had seene a vision in the Temple: For he made signes vnto them, and remained domme.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.23'>And it came to passe, when the daies of his office were fulfilled, that he departed to his owne house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.24'>And after those daies, his wife Elisabet conceiued, and hid her selfe fiue moneths, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.25'>Thus hath the Lorde dealt with me, in the daies wherein he looked on me, to take from me my rebuke among men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.26'>
          <note>The angel, serving the Lord who would be born, is sent to the virgin Mary, in whom the son of the most high promised to David is conceived by the power of the Holy Spirit.</note>And in the sixth month the angel Gabriel was sent from God unto a city of Galilee, named Nazareth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.27'>To a virgin espoused to a man whose name was Joseph, of the <note>The same can be said of Mary, otherwise Christ would not have been of the stock of David, nor his son.</note> house of David; and the virgin's name [was] Mary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.28'>And the angel came in unto her, and said, Hail, [thou that art] <note>It might be literally rendered, «full of favour and grace», and he shows immediately after, laying out plainly unto us, what that favour is in that he says, «The Lord is with thee».</note> highly favoured, the Lord [is] with thee: <note>Of God.</note> blessed [art] thou among women.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.29'>And when she saw [him], she was <note>Moved at the strangeness of the matter.</note> troubled at his saying, and cast in her mind what manner of salutation this should be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.30'>And the angel said unto her, Fear not, Mary: for thou hast <note>So the Hebrews said, saying that those men have found favour who are in favour.</note> found favour with God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.31'>For loe, thou shalt conceiue in thy wobe, and beare a sonne, and shalt call his name Iesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.32'>He shall be great, and shall be <note>He will be declared to be so, for he was the Son of God from everlasting, but was made manifest in the flesh in his time.</note> called the Son of the Highest: and the Lord God shall give unto him the throne of his father David:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.33'>And hee shall reigne ouer the house of Iacob for euer, and of his kingdome shall bee none ende.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.34'>Then said Mary unto the angel, <note>The greatness of the matter causes the virgin to ask this question, not that she distrusted by any means at all, for she asks only of the manner of the conceiving, so that it is plain she believed all the rest.</note> How shall this be, seeing <note>So speak the Hebrews, signifying by this modest kind of speech the company of man and wife together, and this is the meaning of it: how will this be, for as I will be Christ's mother I am very sure I will not know any man: for the godly virgin had learned by the prophets that the Messiah would be born of a virgin.</note> I know not a man?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.35'>And the angel answered and said unto her, The Holy Ghost <note>That is, the Holy Spirit will cause thee to conceive by his mighty power.</note> shall come upon thee, and the power of the Highest shall overshadow thee: therefore also that <note>That thing which is pure and void of all spot of uncleanliness: for he that was to take away sin must of necessity be void of sin.</note> holy thing which shall be born of thee shall be <note>Declared and shown to the world to be the Son of God.</note> called the Son of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.36'>And, behold, thy <note>Though Elisabeth was of the tribe of Levi, yet it was possible for her to be Mary's cousin: for whereas it was forbidden by the Law for maidens to be married to men of other tribes, there was an exception among the Levites, who could take for themselves wives out of any tribe: for the Levites had no portion allotted to them when the land was divided among the people.</note> cousin Elisabeth, she hath also conceived a son in her old age: and this is the <note>This is now the sixth month from the time when she conceived.</note> sixth month with her, who was called barren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.37'>For with God shall nothing be vnpossible.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.38'>Then Marie said, Behold the seruant of the Lord: be it vnto me according to thy woorde. So the Angel departed from her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.39'>
          <note>Elisabeth being many months pregnant with John, and Mary being pregnant with Christ, do rejoice for each other by the inspiration of the Holy Spirit.</note>And Mary arose in those days, and went into the <note>Which is on the south side of Jerusalem.</note> hill country with haste, into a <note>That is to say, Hebron: which was in times past called Kirjatharba: which was one of the towns that were given to the Levites in the tribe of Judah, and is said to be in the mountains of Judah; (Jos_14:15; Jos_21:11).</note> city of Juda;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.40'>And entred into the house of Zacharias, and saluted Elisabet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.41'>And it came to pass, that, when Elisabeth heard the salutation of Mary, the babe <note>This was no ordinary or usual type of moving.</note> leaped in her womb; and Elisabeth was filled with the Holy Ghost:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.42'>And she spake out with a loud voice, and said, Blessed [art] thou among women, and <note>Christ is blessed with respect to his humanity.</note> blessed [is] the fruit of thy womb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.43'>And whence commeth this to mee, that the mother of my Lord should come to me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.44'>For loe, assoone as the voice of thy salutation sounded in mine eares, the babe sprang in my bellie for ioye,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.45'>And blessed is shee that beleeued: for those things shall be perfourmed, which were tolde her from the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.46'>
          <note>Christ, the redeemer of the afflicted and revenger of the proud, promised long ago to the fathers, is now finally exhibited indeed.</note>And Mary said, My soul doth magnify the Lord,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.47'>And my spirite reioyceth in God my Sauiour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.48'>For he hath <note>Has freely and graciously loved.</note> regarded the <note>Literally, «My baseness», that is, my base estate: so that the virgin did not boast of her deserts, but the grace of God.</note> low estate of his handmaiden: for, behold, from henceforth all generations shall call me blessed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.49'>Because hee that is mightie, hath done for me great things, and holy is his Name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.50'>And his mercy [is] on them <note>To those that live godly and religiously, as the Hebrews say.</note> that fear him from generation to generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.51'>He hath shewed strength with his <note>Here many more words than necessary are used, which the Hebrews use very much: and «arm» here is taken for strength.</note> arm; he hath <note>Even as the wind does to the chaff.</note> scattered the proud in the <note>He has scattered them, and the imagination of their hearts; or, by and through the imagination of their own hearts; so that their wicked counsel turned to their own destruction.</note> imagination of their hearts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.52'>He hath <note>The mighty and rich men.</note> put down the mighty from [their] seats, and exalted them of <note>Those of no account, who are vile in men's eyes, who are indeed the poor in spirit, that is, those who claim nothing of themselves in the sight of God.</note> low degree.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.53'>He hath filled the <note>Those that are brought to extreme poverty.</note> hungry with good things; and the rich he hath sent empty away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.54'>
          <note>He has helped Israel up with his arm, who had been completely cast down.</note>He hath holpen his servant Israel, in remembrance of [his] mercy;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.55'>As he <note>Promised.</note> spake to our fathers, to Abraham, and to his seed for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.56'>And Marie abode with her about three moneths: after, shee returned to her owne house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.57'>
          <note>John's birth is accompanied by new miracles.</note>Now Elisabeth's full time came that she should be delivered; and she brought forth a son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.58'>And her neighbours, and cousins heard tell howe the Lorde had shewed his great mercie vpon her, and they reioyced with her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.59'>And it was so that on the eight day they came to circumcise the babe, and called him Zacharias after the name of his father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.60'>But his mother answered, and saide, Not so, but he shalbe called Iohn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.61'>And they saide vnto her, There is none of thy kindred, that is named with this name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.62'>Then they made signes to his father, howe he would haue him called.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.63'>So hee asked for writing tables, and wrote, saying, His name is Iohn, and they marueiled all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.64'>And his mouth was opened immediately, and his tongue, and he spake and praised God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.65'>And fear came on all that dwelt round about them: and all <note>All this which was said and done.</note> these sayings were noised abroad throughout all the hill country of Judaea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.66'>And all they that heard [them] <note>Thought upon them diligently and earnestly, and as it were, printed them in their hearts.</note> laid [them] up in their hearts, saying, What manner of child shall this be! And the <note>That is, the present favour of God, and a singular type of virtue appeared in him.</note> hand of the Lord was with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.67'>
          <note>John, having just been born, by the authority of the Holy Spirit is appointed to his office.</note>And his father Zacharias was filled with the Holy Ghost, and prophesied, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.68'>Blessed [be] the Lord God of Israel; for he hath <note>That he has shown himself mindful of his people, to the extent that he came down from heaven himself to visit us in person, and to redeem us.</note> visited and <note>Has paid the ransom, that is to say, the price of our redemption.</note> redeemed his people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.69'>And hath raised up an <note>This word «horn», in the Hebrew language, signifies strength, and it is a metaphor taken from beasts that fight with their horns: And by raising up the might of Israel is meant that the kingdom of Israel was defended, and the enemies of it laid on the ground, even then when the strength of Israel seemed to be utterly gone.</note> horn of salvation for us in the house of his servant David;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.70'>As he spake by ye mouth of his holy Prophets, which were since the world began, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.71'>That he would sende vs deliuerance fro our enemies, and from the hands of all that hate vs,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.72'>To perform the mercy [promised] to our fathers, and <note>Declare indeed that he was mindful.</note> to remember his holy covenant;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.73'>And the othe which he sware to our father Abraham.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.74'>Which was, that he would graunt vnto vs, that we being deliuered out of the handes of our enemies, should serue him without feare,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.75'>In holiness and righteousness <note>To God's good liking.</note> before him, all the days of our life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.76'>And thou, <note>Though you be at this present time ever so little.</note> child, shalt be called the prophet of the Highest: for thou shalt go before the face of the Lord to prepare his ways;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.77'>To <note>Open the way.</note> give knowledge of salvation unto his people by the <note>Forgiveness of sins is the means by which God saves us; (Rom_4:7).</note> remission of their sins,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.78'>Through the tender mercy of our God; whereby the <note>Or «bud», or «branch»; he alludes to (Jer_23:5) (Zec_3:8; Zec_6:12); and he is called a bud from on high, that is, sent from God unto us, and not as other buds which bud out of the earth.</note> dayspring from on high hath visited us,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.79'>To give light to them that sit in darkness and [in] the shadow of death, to guide our feet into the <note>Into the way which leads us to true happiness.</note> way of peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.1.80'>And the childe grewe, and waxed strong in spirit, and was in the wildernesse, til the day came that he should shewe him selfe vnto Israel.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.2'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.1'>And <note>Christ, the son of God, taking upon himself the form of a servant, and making himself of no reputation, is poorly born in a stable: and by the means of Augustus, the mightiest prince in the world, (thinking nothing of it) has his cradle prepared in Bethlehem, as the prophets foretold.</note> it came to pass in those days, that there went out a decree from Caesar Augustus, that all the <note>As far as the empire of the Romans stretched.</note> world should be <note>That is, the inhabitants of every city should have their names recorded, and their goods rated at a certain value, that the emperor might understand how rich every country, city, family, and house was.</note> taxed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.2'>(This first taxing was made when Cyrenius was gouernour of Syria.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.3'>Therefore went all to be taxed, euery man to his owne Citie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.4'>And Joseph also went up from Galilee, out of the city of Nazareth, into Judaea, unto the <note>Which David was born and brought up in.</note> city of David, which is called Bethlehem; (because he was of the house and lineage of David:)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.5'>To bee taxed with Marie that was giuen him to wife, which was with childe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.6'>And so it was, that while they were there, the daies were accomplished that shee shoulde be deliuered,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.7'>And she brought foorth her first begotten sonne, and wrapped him in swadling clothes, and laide him in a cratch, because there was no roome for them in the ynne.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.8'>
          <note>The angels themselves declare to poor shepherds (not at all regarding the pride of the mighty) the Godhead and office of the child lying in the crib.</note>And there were in the same country shepherds <note>Living outside, and in the open air.</note> abiding in the field, keeping watch over their flock by night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.9'>And, lo, the angel of the Lord <note>Came suddenly upon them, when they were not at all thinking about such a matter.</note> came upon them, and the glory of the Lord shone round about them: and they were sore afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.10'>Then the Angel saide vnto them, Be not afraid: for behold, I bring you glad tidings of great ioy, that shalbe to all the people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.11'>That is, that vnto you is borne this day in the citie of Dauid, a Sauiour, which is Christ the Lorde.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.12'>And this shalbe a signe to you, Yee shall finde the babe swadled, and laid in a cratch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.13'>And suddenly there was with the angel <note>Whole armies of angels, who compass the majesty of God round about, just as soldiers, as it were.</note> a multitude of the heavenly host praising God, and saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.14'>Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace, <note>God's ready, good, infinite, and gracious favour towards men.</note> good will toward men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.15'>And it came to passe whe the Angels were gone away from them into heauen, that the shepheards sayde one to another, Let vs goe then vnto Beth-leem, and see this thing that is come to passe which the Lord hath shewed vnto vs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.16'>So they came with haste, and founde both Marie and Ioseph, &amp; the babe laid in the cratch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.17'>And when they had seene it, they published abroade the thing, that was tolde them of that childe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.18'>And all that heard it, wondred at ye things which were tolde them of the shepheards.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.19'>But Mary kept all those sayings, and pondred them in her heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.20'>And the shepheardes returned glorifiyng and praising God, for all that they had heard and seene as it was spoken vnto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.21'>
          <note>Christ, the head of the Church, made subject to the law in order to deliver us from the curse of the law (as the name of Jesus well declares) being circumcised, ratifies and seals in his own flesh the circumcision of the flesh.</note>And when eight days were accomplished for the circumcising of the child, his name was called JESUS, which was so named of the angel before he was conceived in the womb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.22'>
          <note>Christ, upon whom all our sins were laid, being offered to God according to the law purifies both Mary and us all in himself.</note>And when the days of <note>This is meant for the fulfilling of the law: for otherwise the virgin was not defiled, nor unclean, by the birth of this child.</note> her purification according to the law of Moses were accomplished, they brought him to Jerusalem, to present [him] to the Lord;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.23'>(As it is written in the Lawe of the Lorde, Euery man childe that first openeth ye wombe, shalbe called holy to the Lord)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.24'>And to giue an oblation, as it is commanded in the Lawe of the Lorde, a paire of turtle doues, or two yong pigeons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.25'>
          <note>Simeon openly in the temple foretells the death of the coming of Messiah, of the casting out of the greatest part of Israel, and of the calling of the Gentiles.</note>And, behold, there was a man in Jerusalem, whose name [was] Simeon; and the same man [was] just and devout, waiting for the consolation of Israel: and the <note>He was endued with the gifts of the Holy Spirit, and this is said using the figure of speech metonymy.</note> Holy Ghost was upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.26'>And it was declared to him from God by the holy Ghost, that he shoulde not see death, before he had seene that Anointed of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.27'>And he came by the Spirit into the temple: and when the <note>Joseph and Mary: and he says «parents» because that is what most of the people then thought.</note> parents brought in the child Jesus, to do for him after the custom of the law,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.28'>Then hee tooke him in his armes, and praised God, and sayd,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.29'>Lord, now <note>Let me depart out of this life, to be joined to my Father.</note> lettest thou thy servant depart in peace, according to thy <note>As you promised me.</note> word:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.30'>For <note>That is, for I have seen with my very eyes: for he saw before in mind, as it is said of Abraham, «He saw my day and rejoiced.»</note> mine eyes have seen thy <note>That in which your salvation is contained.</note> salvation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.31'>Which thou hast prepared <note>As a sign set up in a high place for all men to look upon.</note> before the face of all people;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.32'>A light to be reueiled to the Gentiles, and the glory of thy people Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.33'>And Ioseph and his mother marueiled at those things, which were spoken touching him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.34'>And Simeon blessed them, and said unto Mary his mother, Behold, this [child] is <note>Is appointed and set by God for a mark.</note> set for the <note>Fall of the reprobate who perishes because of their own fault: and for the rising of the elect, unto whom God will give faith to believe.</note> fall and rising again of many in Israel; and for a <note>That is, a mark, which all men will strive earnestly to hit.</note> sign which shall be spoken against;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.35'>(Yea, a sword shall <note>Will most keenly wound and grieve.</note> pierce through thy own soul also,) that the thoughts of many hearts may be revealed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.36'>
          <note>Another witness besides Simeon, against whom no objection may be brought, inviting all men to the receiving of the Messiah.</note>And there was one Anna, a prophetess, the daughter of Phanuel, of the tribe of Aser: she was of a great age, and had lived with an husband seven years from her virginity;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.37'>And she was widowe about foure score and foure yeeres, and went not out of the Temple, but serued God with fastings &amp; prayers, night and day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.38'>She then coming at the same instant vpon them, confessed likewise the Lord, &amp; spake of him to all that looked for redemption in Hierusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.39'>And when they had performed all thinges according to the lawe of the Lorde, they returned into Galile to their owne citie Nazareth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.40'>And the child grew, and waxed strong in spirit, <note>As Christ grew up in age, so the virtue of his Godhead showed itself more and more.</note> filled with wisdom: and the grace of God was upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.41'>
          <note>The scribes and Pharisees are aroused to hear the wisdom of Christ in his time by an extraordinary deed.</note>Now his parents went to Jerusalem every year at the feast of the passover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.42'>And when hee was twelue yeere olde, and they were come vp to Hierusalem, after the custome of the feast,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.43'>And had finished the dayes thereof, as they returned, the childe Iesus remained in Hierusalem, and Ioseph knew not, nor his mother,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.44'>But they supposing, that he had bene in the company, went a dayes iourney, and sought him among their kinsfolke, and acquaintance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.45'>And when they found him not, they turned backe to Hierusalem, and sought him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.46'>And it came to passe three dayes after, that they found him in the Temple, sitting in the mids of the doctours, both hearing them, and asking them questions:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.47'>And all that heard him, were astonied at his vnderstanding and answeres.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.48'>
          <note>All duties which we owe to men, even though they are not to be neglected, so are they (according to the position in life which God has set us) not to be preferred before the glory of God.</note>And when they saw him, they were amazed: and his mother said unto him, Son, why hast thou thus dealt with us? behold, thy father and I have sought thee sorrowing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.49'>Then said he vnto them, Howe is it that ye sought me? knewe ye not that I must goe about my Fathers busines?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.50'>But they vnderstoode not the word that he spake to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.51'>
          <note>Christ, very man, is made like us in every way except sin.</note>And he went down with them, and came to Nazareth, and was subject unto them: but his mother kept all these sayings in her heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.2.52'>And Iesus increased in wisedome, and stature, and in fauour with God and men.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.3'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.1'>Now <note>John comes at the time foretold by the prophets and lays the foundation of the gospel which is exhibited unto us, setting forth the true observing of the law and free mercy in Christ, which comes after John, using also baptism which is the outward sign both of regeneration and also forgiveness of sins.</note> in the fifteenth year of the reign of Tiberius Caesar, Pontius Pilate being governor of Judaea, and Herod being tetrarch of Galilee, and his brother Philip tetrarch of Ituraea and of the region of Trachonitis, and Lysanias the tetrarch of Abilene,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.2'>
          <note>Josephus calls him Ananus.</note>Annas and Caiaphas being the high priests, the word of God came unto John the son of Zacharias in the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.3'>And hee came into all the coastes about Iordan, preaching the baptisme of repentance for the remission of sinnes,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.4'>As it is written in the booke of the sayings of Esaias the Prophet, which saith, The voyce of him that crieth in the wildernes is, Prepare ye the way of the Lord: make his paths straight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.5'>Euery valley shalbe filled, and euery mountaine and hill shall be brought lowe, and crooked things shalbe made straight, and the rough wayes shalbe made smoothe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.6'>And all flesh shall see the saluation of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.7'>Then said he to the people that were come out to be baptized of him, O generations of vipers, who hath forewarned you to flee from the wrath to come?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.8'>Bring foorth therefore fruites worthy amendement of life, and beginne not to say with your selues, We haue Abraham to our father: for I say vnto you, that God is able of these stones to raise vp children vnto Abraham.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.9'>Nowe also is the axe layed vnto the roote of the trees: therefore euery tree which bringeth not foorth good fruite, shalbe hewen downe, and cast into the fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.10'>Then the people asked him, saying, What shall we doe then?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.11'>And he answered, and said vnto them, He that hath two coates, let him part with him that hath none: and hee that hath meate, let him doe likewise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.12'>Then came there Publicanes also to bee baptized, and saide vnto him, Master, what shall we doe?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.13'>And he said unto them, Exact no more than that which is <note>Require no more than that sum that is appointed for the tribute money.</note> appointed you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.14'>And the soldiers likewise demanded of him, saying, And what shall we do? And he said unto them, Do violence to no man, neither accuse [any] falsely; and be content with your <note>Which was paid to them partly in money and partly in food.</note> wages.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.15'>
          <note>If we would rightly and fruitfully receive the sacraments, we must neither rest in the signs, neither in him that ministers the signs, but lift up our eyes to Christ, who is the author of the sacraments, and the giver of that which is represented by the sacraments.</note>And as the people were in expectation, and all men mused in their hearts of John, whether he were the Christ, or not;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.16'>Iohn answered, and saide to them all, In deede I baptize you with water, but one stronger then I, commeth, whose shoes latchet I am not worthy to vnloose: hee will baptize you with the holy Ghost, and with fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.17'>
          <note>The gospel is the fan of the world.</note>Whose fan [is] in his hand, and he will throughly purge his floor, and will gather the wheat into his garner; but the chaff he will burn with fire unquenchable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.18'>Thus then exhorting with many other things, he preached vnto the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.19'>
          <note>John's preaching is confirmed with his death.</note>But Herod the tetrarch, being reproved by him for Herodias his brother Philip's wife, and for all the evils which Herod had done,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.20'>He added yet this aboue all, that he shut vp Iohn in prison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.21'>
          <note>Our baptism is sanctified in the head of the Church, and Christ also by the voice of the Father is pronounced to be our everlasting King, Priest, and Prophet.</note>Now when all the people were baptized, it came to pass, that Jesus also being baptized, and praying, the heaven was opened,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.22'>And the holy Ghost came downe in a bodily shape like a doue, vpon him, and there was a voyce from heauen, saying, Thou art my beloued Sonne: in thee I am well pleased.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.23'>
          <note>Christ's lineage, according to the flesh, is traced back even to Adam, and so to God, that it might appear that it was only he whom God promised to Abraham and David, and appointed from everlasting to his Church, which is composed of all sorts of men.</note>And Jesus himself began to be about thirty years of age, being (as was supposed) the son of Joseph, which was [the son] of Heli,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.24'>The sonne of Matthat, the sonne of Leui, the sonne of Melchi, the sonne of Ianna, the sonne of Ioseph,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.25'>The sonne of Mattathias, the sonne of Amos, the sonne of Naum, the sonne of Esli, the sonne of Nagge,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.26'>The sonne of Maath, the sonne of Mattathias, the sonne of Semei, the sonne of Ioseph, the sonne of Iuda,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.27'>The sonne of Ioanna, the sonne of Rhesa, the sonne of Zorobabel, the sonne of Salathiel, the sonne of Neri,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.28'>The sonne of Melchi, the sonne of Addi, the sonne of Cosam, the sonne of Elmodam, the sonne of Er,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.29'>The sonne of Iose, the sonne of Eliezer, the sonne of Iorim, the sonne of Matthat, the son of Leui,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.30'>The sonne of Simeon, the sonne of Iuda, the sonne of Ioseph, the sonne of Ionan, the sonne of Eliacim,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.31'>The sonne of Melea, the sonne of Mainan, the sonne of Mattatha, the sonne of Nathan, the sonne of Dauid,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.32'>The sonne of Iesse, the sonne of Obed, the sonne of Booz, the sonne of Salmon, the sonne of Naasson,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.33'>The sonne of Aminadab, the sonne of Aram, the sonne of Esrom, the sonne of Phares, the sonne of Iuda,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.34'>The sonne of Iacob, the sonne of Isaac, the sonne of Abraham, the sonne of Thara, the sonne of Nachor,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.35'>The sonne of Saruch, the sonne of Ragau, the sonne of Phalec, the sonne of Eber, the sonne of Sala,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.36'>The sonne of Cainan, the sonne of Arphaxad, the sonne of Sem, the sonne of Noe, the sonne of Lamech,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.37'>The sonne of Mathusala, the sonne of Enoch, the sonne of Iared, the sonne of Maleleel, the sonne of Cainan,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.3.38'>The sonne of Enos, the sonne of Seth, the sonne of Adam, the sonne of God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.4'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.1'>And <note>Christ, being carried away (as it were out of the world) into the desert, comes suddenly as if from heaven, having fasted for forty days and overcoming Satan three times, and thus begins his office.</note> Jesus being full of the Holy Ghost returned from Jordan, and was led by the Spirit into the wilderness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.2'>And was there fourtie dayes tempted of the deuil, &amp; in those dayes he did eate nothing: but when they were ended, he afterward was hungry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.3'>
          <note>Christ, being tempted by Satan, first to distrust in God, secondly to the desire of riches and honour, and lastly to a vain confidence in himself, overcomes him three times by the word of God.</note>And the devil said unto him, If thou be the Son of God, command this stone that it be made bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.4'>But Iesus answered him, saying, It is written, That man shall not liue by bread only, but by euery word of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.5'>Then the deuill tooke him vp into an high mountaine, and shewed him all the kingdomes of the world, in the twinkeling of an eye.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.6'>And the devil said unto him, All this <note>By this word «power» are meant the kingdoms themselves which have the power: and so this is said using the figure of speech metonymy.</note> power will I give thee, and the glory of them: for that is <note>This is surely so, for he is prince of the world, but not absolutely, and is the sovereign of it only by permission and request, and therefore he does not truly say that he can give it to whom he will.</note> delivered unto me; and to whomsoever I will I give it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.7'>If thou therefore wilt worship me, all shall be <note>Out of a high place, from which would be seen a good and first-class country, and thus the devil showed him all countries.</note> thine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.8'>But Iesus answered him, and saide, Hence from mee, Satan: for it is written, Thou shalt worship the Lorde thy God, and him alone thou shalt serue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.9'>Then hee brought him to Hierusalem, and set him on a pinacle of the Temple, and said vnto him, If thou be the Sonne of God, cast thy selfe downe from hence,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.10'>For it is written, That hee will giue his Angels charge ouer thee to keepe thee:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.11'>And with their handes they shall lift thee vp, least at any time thou shouldest dash thy foote against a stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.12'>And Iesus answered, and said vnto him, It is said, Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.13'>And when the deuil had ended all the tentation, he departed from him for a litle season.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.14'>And Iesus returned by the power of the spirite into Galile: and there went a fame of him throughout all the region round about.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.15'>For he taught in their Synagogues, and was honoured of all men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.16'>
          <note>Who Christ is and for what reason he came he shows from the prophet Isaiah.</note>And he came to Nazareth, where he had been brought up: and, as his custom was, he went into the synagogue on the sabbath day, and stood up for to read.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.17'>And there was delivered unto him the book of the prophet Esaias. And when he had <note>Their books in those days were rolled up as scrolls upon a ruler: and so Christ unrolled or unfolded it, which is here called «opened».</note> opened the book, he found the place where it was written,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.18'>The Spirit of the Lorde is vpon mee, because he hath anoynted me, that I should preach the Gospel to the poore: he hath sent mee, that I should heale the broken hearted, that I should preach deliuerance to the captiues, and recouering of sight to the blinde, that I should set at libertie them that are bruised:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.19'>And that I should preache the acceptable yeere of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.20'>And hee closed the booke, and gaue it againe to the minister, and sate downe: and the eyes of all that were in the Synagogue were fastened on him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.21'>Then he began to say vnto them, This day is the Scripture fulfilled in your eares.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.22'>
          <note>Familiarity causes Christ to be condemned and therefore he often goes to strangers.</note>And all <note>Approved those things which he spoke with common consent and voice: for this word «witness» signifies in this place (and many others) «to allow and approve a thing with open confession».</note> bare him witness, and <note>Present at this meeting of the scriptures were not only the learned, but also the common people: and besides that, their mother tongue was used, for how else could the people have wondered? Paul appointed the same manner for doing things in the Church at Corinth; (1Co. 14:1-40).</note> wondered at the <note>Words full of the mighty power of God, which appeared in all his doings, and as well allured men marvellously unto him; see (Psa_45:2), «grace is poured into thy lips».</note> gracious words which proceeded out of his mouth. And they said, Is not this Joseph's son?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.23'>Then he said vnto them, Ye will surely say vnto mee this prouerbe, Physician, heale thy selfe: whatsoeuer we haue heard done in Capernaum, doe it here likewise in thine owne countrey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.24'>And he saide, Verely I say vnto you, No Prophet is accepted in his owne countrey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.25'>But I tell you of a truth, many widows were in Israel in the days of Elias, when the heaven was shut up three years and six months, when great famine was throughout all the <note>Land of Israel; {{See Mar_15:33}}.</note> land;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.26'>But vnto none of them was Elias sent, saue into Sarepta, a citie of Sidon, vnto a certaine widowe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.27'>Also many lepers were in Israel, in the time of Eliseus the Prophet: yet none of them was made cleane, sauing Naaman the Syrian.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.28'>
          <note>The more sharply the world is rebuked the more it openly rages: but the life of the godly is not always subject to the desires of the wicked.</note>And all they in the synagogue, when they heard these things, were filled with wrath,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.29'>And rose vp, and thrust him out of the citie, and led him vnto the edge of the hil, whereon their citie was built, to cast him downe headlong.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.30'>But he passed through the middes of them, and went his way,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.31'>And came downe into Capernaum a citie of Galile, and there taught them on the Sabbath dayes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.32'>And they were astonied at his doctrine: for his worde was with authoritie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.33'>And in the Synagogue there was a man which had a spirit of an vncleane deuill, which cryed with a loude voyce,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.34'>
          <note>Christ astonishes not only men, be they ever so stupid, but even the demons as well, whether or not they want to be.</note>Saying, Let [us] alone; what have we to do with thee, [thou] Jesus of Nazareth? art thou come to destroy us? I know thee who thou art; the Holy One of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.35'>And Iesus rebuked him, saying, Holde thy peace, and come out of him. Then the deuill throwing him in the middes of them, came out of him, and hurt him nothing at all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.36'>So feare came on them all, and they spake among themselues, saying, What thing is this: for with authoritie and power he commaundeth the foule spirits, and they come out?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.37'>And ye fame of him spred abroad throughout all the places of the countrey round about.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.38'>
          <note>In that Christ heals the diseases of the body with only his word, he proves that he is God Almighty, sent for man's salvation.</note>And he arose out of the synagogue, and entered into Simon's house. And Simon's wife's mother was taken with a great fever; and they besought him for her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.39'>Then he stoode ouer her, and rebuked the feuer, and it left her, and immediatly she arose, and ministred vnto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.40'>Now at the sunne setting, all they that had sicke folkes of diuers diseases, brought them vnto him, and he layd his hands on euery one of them, and healed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.41'>
          <note>Satan, who is a continual enemy of the truth, ought not to be heard, not even when he speaks the truth.</note>And devils also came out of many, crying out, and saying, Thou art Christ the Son of God. And he rebuking [them] suffered them not to speak: for they knew that he was Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.42'>
          <note>No zealous response on the part of the people ought to hinder us in the race that God has appointed unto us.</note>And when it was day, he departed and went into a desert place: and the people sought him, and came unto him, and stayed him, that he should not depart from them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.43'>But he sayd vnto them, Surely I must also preach the kingdome of God to other cities: for therefore am I sent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.4.44'>And hee preached in the Synagogues of Galile.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.5'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.1'>And <note>Christ reveals to the four disciples whom he had taken unto himself the office of the apostleship, which would be committed unto them in the future.</note> it came to pass, that, as the people <note>Did as it were lie upon him, so desirous were they both to see him and hear him, and therefore he taught them out of a ship.</note> pressed upon him to hear the word of God, he stood by the lake of Gennesaret,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.2'>And sawe two shippes stand by the lakes side, but the fishermen were gone out of them, and were washing their nettes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.3'>And he entred into one of the ships, which was Simons, &amp; required him that he would thrust off a litle from the land: and he sate downe, and taught the people out of the ship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.4'>Now when he had left speaking, he sayd vnto Simon, Lanch out into the deepe, and let downe your nettes to make a draught.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.5'>And Simon answering said unto him, <note>The word signifies someone that has rule over anything.</note> Master, we have toiled all the night, and have taken nothing: nevertheless at thy word I will let down the net.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.6'>And when they had so done, they enclosed a great multitude of fishes, so that their net brake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.7'>And they beckened to their parteners, which were in the other ship, that they shoulde come and helpe them, who came then, and filled both the ships, that they did sinke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.8'>Now when Simon Peter saw it, he fel down at Iesus knees, saying, Lord, go from me: for I am a sinfull man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.9'>For he was vtterly astonied, and all that were with him, for the draught of fishes which they tooke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.10'>And so was also Iames &amp; Iohn the sonnes of Zebedeus, which were companions with Simon. Then Iesus sayde vnto Simon, Feare not: from henceforth thou shalt catch men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.11'>And when they had brought the ships to land, they forsooke all, and followed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.12'>
          <note>Christ, by healing the leper with only his touch and sending him to the priest, witnesses that it is he, through whom and by whom, apprehended by faith, all we who are unclean according to the law are pronounced to be pure and clean by the witness of God himself.</note>And it came to pass, when he was in a certain city, behold a man full of leprosy: who seeing Jesus fell on [his] face, and besought him, saying, Lord, if thou wilt, thou canst make me clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.13'>So he stretched forth his hand, &amp; touched him, saying, I will, be thou cleane; immediately the leprosie departed from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.14'>And he commaunded him that hee should tell it no man: but Go, sayth he, and shew thy selfe to the Priest, and offer for thy clensing, as Moses hath commanded, for a witnes vnto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.15'>
          <note>Christ would rather be well known by his doctrine than by miracles, and therefore he departs from those that seek him as a physician of the body, and not as the author of salvation.</note>But so much the more went there a fame abroad of him: and great multitudes came together to hear, and to be healed by him of their infirmities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.16'>But he kept himselfe apart in the wildernes, and prayed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.17'>
          <note>Christ, in healing him that was sick from paralysis, shows the cause of all diseases, and the remedy.</note>And it came to pass on a certain day, as he was teaching, that there were Pharisees and doctors of the law sitting by, which were come out of every town of Galilee, and Judaea, and Jerusalem: and the power of the Lord <note>The mighty power of Christ's Godhead showed itself in him at that time.</note> was [present] to heal them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.18'>Then beholde, men brought a man lying in a bed, which was taken with a palsie, and they sought meanes to bring him in, and to lay him before him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.19'>And when they could not finde by what way they might bring him in, because of the preasse, they went vp on the house, and let him downe through the tyling, bed and all, in the middes before Iesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.20'>And when he sawe their faith, he sayd vnto him, Man, thy sinnes are forgiuen thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.21'>Then the Scribes &amp; the Pharises began to reason, saying, Who is this that speaketh blasphemies? who can forgiue sinnes, but God onely?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.22'>But when Iesus perceiued their reasoning, he answered, and sayd vnto them, What reason ye in your hearts?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.23'>Whether is easier to say, Thy sinnes are forgiuen thee, or to say, Rise and walke?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.24'>But that ye may know that that Sonne of man hath authoritie to forgiue sinnes in earth, (he sayd vnto the sicke of the palsie) I say to thee, Arise: take vp thy bed, and goe to thine house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.25'>And immediatly he rose vp before them, and tooke vp his bed whereon he lay, and departed to his owne house, praysing God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.26'>And they were all amased, &amp; praysed God, and were filled with feare, saying, Doutlesse we haue seene strange things to day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.27'>
          <note>The Church is a company of sinners who are repentant through the grace of Christ, who banquet with him to the great offence of the proud and envious people of the world.</note>And after these things he went forth, and saw a publican, named Levi, sitting at the receipt of custom: and he said unto him, Follow me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.28'>And he left all, rose vp, and folowed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.29'>Then Leui made him a great feast in his owne house, where there was a great company of Publicanes, and of other that sate at table with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.30'>But they that were Scribes and Pharises among them, murmured against his disciples, saying, Why eate ye and drinke ye with Publicanes and sinners?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.31'>Then Iesus answered, and sayd vnto them, They that are whole, neede not the Physician, but they that are sicke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.32'>I came not to call the righteous, but sinners to repentance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.33'>
          <note>Hypocrites and ignorant men make a point of making fasting and unimportant things a matter of holiness.</note>And they said unto him, Why do the disciples of John fast often, and make prayers, and likewise [the disciples] of the Pharisees; but thine eat and drink?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.34'>
          <note>Laws generally made without any consideration of circumstances; for fasting and other things of like sort are not only tyrannous but very harmful to the Church.</note>And he said unto them, Can ye make the children of the bridechamber fast, while the bridegroom is with them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.35'>But the dayes will come, euen when the bridegrome shalbe taken away from them: then shall they fast in those dayes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.36'>Againe he spake also vnto them a parable, No man putteth a piece of a newe garment into an olde vesture: for then the newe renteth it, and the piece taken out of the newe, agreeth not with the olde.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.37'>Also no man powreth newe wine into olde vessels: for then ye new wine wil breake the vessels, and it will runne out, and the vessels will perish:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.38'>But newe wine must be powred into newe vessels: so both are preserued.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.5.39'>Also no man that drinketh olde wine, straightway desireth newe: for he sayth, The olde is more profitable.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.6'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.1'>And <note>Christ shows against the superstitious, who dwell on every trifling matter, that the law of the very sabbath was not given to be kept without exception: much less that the salvation of man should consist in the outward keeping of it.</note> it came to pass on the second sabbath after the first, that he went through the corn fields; and his disciples <note>Epiphanius notes well in his treatise, where he refutes Ebion, that the time when the disciples plucked the ears of the corn was in the feast of unleavened bread. Now, in those feasts which were kept over a period of many days, as the feast of tabernacles and passover, their first day and the last were very solemn; see (Lev. 23:1-44). Luke then fitly calls the last day the second sabbath, though Theophylact understands it to be any of the sabbaths that followed the first.</note> plucked the ears of corn, and did eat, rubbing [them] in [their] hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.2'>And certaine of the Pharises sayde vnto them, Why doe ye that which is not lawfull to doe on the Sabbath dayes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.3'>Then Iesus answered them, and said, Haue ye not read this, that Dauid did when he himselfe was an hungred, and they which were with him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.4'>Howe he went into the house of God, and tooke, and ate the shewbread, and gaue also to them which were with him, which was not lawful to eate, but for the Priests onely?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.5'>And he sayd vnto them, The Sonne of man is Lord also of the Sabbath day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.6'>
          <note>Charity is the rule of all ceremonies.</note>And it came to pass also on another sabbath, that he entered into the synagogue and taught: and there was a man whose right hand was withered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.7'>And the Scribes &amp; Pharises watched him, whether he would heale on the Sabbath day, that they might finde an accusation against him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.8'>But he knew their thoughts, and sayd to the man which had the withered hand, Arise, and stand vp in the middes; hee arose, and stoode vp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.9'>Then said Jesus unto them, I will ask you one thing; Is it lawful on the sabbath days to do good, or to do evil? to save life, or to <note>Whoever does not help his neighbour when he can, he kills him.</note> destroy [it]?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.10'>And he behelde them all in compasse, and sayd vnto the man, Stretch forth thine hand; he did so, and his hand was restored againe, as whole as the other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.11'>Then they were filled full of madnes, and communed one with another, what they might doe to Iesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.12'>
          <note>In using earnest and long prayer in choosing twelve of his own company to the office of the apostleship, Christ shows how religiously we ought to behave ourselves in the choice of ecclesiastical persons.</note>And it came to pass in those days, that he went out into a mountain to pray, and continued all night in prayer to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.13'>And when it was day, he called his disciples, and of them he chose twelue which also he called Apostles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.14'>(Simon whome he named also Peter, and Andrewe his brother, Iames and Iohn, Philippe and Bartlemewe:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.15'>Matthewe and Thomas: Iames the sonne of Alpheus, and Simon called Zelous,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.16'>Iudas Iames brother, and Iudas Iscariot, which also was the traitour.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.17'>And he came down with them, and stood in the plain, and the company of his disciples, and a great multitude of people out of all Judaea and Jerusalem, and from the <note>From all the sea coast, which is called Syrophoenecia.</note> sea coast of Tyre and Sidon, which came to hear him, and to be healed of their diseases;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.18'>And they that were vexed with foule spirits, and they were healed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.19'>And the whole multitude sought to touch him: for there went vertue out of him, and healed them all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.20'>
          <note>Christ teaches against all philosophers, and especially the Epicureans, that the greatest happiness of man is laid up in no place here on earth, but in heaven, and that persecution for righteousness' sake is the right way to achieve it.</note>And he lifted up his eyes on his disciples, and said, Blessed [be ye] poor: for yours is the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.21'>Blessed are ye that hunger nowe: for ye shalbe satisfied: blessed are ye that weepe now: for ye shall laugh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.22'>Blessed are ye, when men shall hate you, and when they shall <note>Cast you out of their synagogues, as John expounds in (Joh_16:2), which is the severest punishment the Church has, if the elders judge rightfully, and by the word of God.</note> separate you [from their company], and shall reproach [you], and cast out your name as evil, for the Son of man's sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.23'>Rejoice ye in that day, and <note>Leap for exceeding joy, as cattle do who are spurred on by food.</note> leap for joy: for, behold, your reward [is] great in heaven: for in the like manner did their fathers unto the prophets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.24'>But woe unto you that are rich! for ye have <note>That is, you reap now of your riches all the convenience and blessing you are ever likely to have, and therefore you have no other reward to look for; (Mat_6:2).</note> received your consolation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.25'>Wo be to you that are full: for ye shall hunger. Wo be to you that now laugh: for ye shal wayle and weepe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.26'>Wo be to you when all men speake well of you: for so did their fathers to the false prophets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.27'>
          <note>Christian charity, which is very different from worldly charity, not only does not revenge injuries, but is even extended to our most grievous enemies, and that for our Father's sake who is in heaven: in well doing it is not at all seeking its own.</note>But I say unto you which hear, Love your enemies, do good to them which hate you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.28'>Blesse them that curse you, and pray for them which hurt you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.29'>And vnto him that smiteth thee on ye one cheeke, offer also the other: and him that taketh away thy cloke, forbid not to take thy coate also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.30'>Giue to euery man that asketh of thee: and of him that taketh away the things that be thine, aske them not againe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.31'>And as ye would that men should doe to you, so doe ye to them likewise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.32'>For if ye love them which love you, <note>What is there in this your work that is to be accounted of? For if you look to have reward by loving, seek those rewards which are indeed rewards: love your enemies, and so will you show to the world that you look for those rewards which come from God.</note> what thank have ye? for sinners also love those that love them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.33'>And if ye do good for them which do good for you, what thanke shall ye haue? for euen the sinners doe the same.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.34'>And if ye lend to them of whom ye hope to receiue, what thanke shall yee haue? for euen the sinners lend to sinners, to receiue the like.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.35'>But love ye your enemies, and do good, and lend, <note>When you will lend, do it only to benefit and please with it, and not with the hope of receiving the principal again.</note> hoping for nothing again; and your reward shall be great, and ye shall be the children of the Highest: for he is kind unto the unthankful and [to] the evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.36'>Be ye therefore mercifull, as your Father also is mercifull.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.37'>
          <note>Brotherly judgments must not proceed from curiosity nor rudeness nor malice, but they must be just, moderate and loving.</note>Judge not, and ye shall not be judged: condemn not, and ye shall not be condemned: <note>He does not speak here of civil judgments, and therefore by the word «forgive» is meant that good nature which the Christians use in patiently suffering and pardoning wrongs.</note> forgive, and ye shall be forgiven:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.38'>Give, and it shall be given unto you; good measure, <note>These are borrowed types of sayings, taken from those who used to measure dry things, as corn and such things, who do it in a rather forceful manner, and thrust it down and shake it together, and press it and put it into a pile.</note> pressed down, and shaken together, and running over, shall men give into your bosom. For with the same measure that ye mete withal it shall be measured to you again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.39'>
          <note>Unskillful reprehenders hurt both themselves and others: for as the teacher is, so is the student.</note>And he spake a parable unto them, Can the blind lead the blind? shall they not both fall into the ditch?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.40'>The disciple is not aboue his master: but whosoeuer will be a perfect disciple, shall bee as his master.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.41'>
          <note>Hypocrites who are very severe reprehenders of others are very quick to spitefully spot other men's faults, but very blind to see their own.</note>And why beholdest thou the mote that is in thy brother's eye, but perceivest not the beam that is in thine own eye?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.42'>Either howe canst thou say to thy brother, Brother, let me pull out the mote that is in thine eye, when thou seest not the beame that is in thine owne eye? Hypocrite, cast out the beame out of thine owne eye first, and then shalt thou see, perfectly to pull out the mote that is in thy brothers eye.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.43'>
          <note>Skill in reprehending others does not make a good man, but rather he that proves his uprightness both in word and deed.</note>For a good tree bringeth not forth corrupt fruit; neither doth a corrupt tree bring forth good fruit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.44'>For euery tree is knowen by his owne fruite: for neither of thornes gather men figges, nor of bushes gather they grapes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.45'>A good man out of the good treasure of his heart bringeth foorth good, and an euill man out of the euill treasure of his heart bringeth foorth euill: for of the aboundance of the heart his mouth speaketh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.46'>But why call ye me Lord, Lord, and do not the things that I speake?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.47'>
          <note>Affliction at length discerns true godliness from false and feigned godliness.</note>Whosoever cometh to me, and heareth my sayings, and doeth them, I will shew you to whom he is like:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.48'>He is like a man which built an house, and digged deepe, and layde the fundation on a rocke: and when the waters arose, the flood beat vpon that house, and coulde not shake it: for it was grounded vpon a rocke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.6.49'>But hee that heareth and doeth not, is like a man that built an house vpon the earth without foundation, against which the flood did beate, and it fell by and by: and the fall of that house was great.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.7'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.1'>Now <note>Christ admonishes the Jews that for their obstinacy and rebellion he will go to the Gentiles, by setting before them the example of the centurion.</note> when he had ended all his sayings in the audience of the people, he entered into Capernaum.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.2'>And a certaine Ceturions seruant was sicke and readie to die, which was deare vnto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.3'>And when he heard of Iesus, hee sent vnto him the Elders of the Iewes, beseeching him that he would come, and heale his seruant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.4'>So they came to Iesus, and besought him instantly, saying that hee was worthy that hee should doe this for him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.5'>For he loueth, said they, our nation, and he hath built vs a Synagogue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.6'>Then Iesus went with them: but when he was now not farre from the house, the Centurion sent friendes to him, saying vnto him, Lorde, trouble not thy selfe: for I am not worthy that thou shouldest enter vnder my roofe:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.7'>Wherefore I thought not my selfe worthy to come vnto thee: but say the word, and my seruant shalbe whole:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.8'>For I likewise am a man set vnder authoritie, and haue vnder mee souldiers, and I say vnto one, Goe, and he goeth: and to another, Come, and hee commeth: and to my seruant, Doe this, and he doeth it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.9'>When Iesus heard these things, he marueiled at him, and turned him, and said to the people, that followed him, I say vnto you, I haue not found so great faith, no not in Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.10'>And when they that were sent, turned backe to the house, they founde the seruant that was sicke, whole.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.11'>
          <note>Christ openly affirms his power over death.</note>And it came to pass the day after, that he went into a city called <note>Nain is the name of a town in Galilee which was situated on the other side of the Kishon, which runs into the sea of Galilee.</note> Nain; and many of his disciples went with him, and much people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.12'>Nowe when hee came neere to the gate of the citie, behold, there was a dead man caried out, who was the onely begotten sonne of his mother, which was a widowe, and much people of the citie was with her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.13'>And when the Lord sawe her, he had compassion on her, and said vnto her, Weepe not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.14'>And he went and touched the coffin (and they that bare him, stoode still) and he said, Yong man, I say vnto thee, Arise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.15'>And he that was dead, sate vp, and began to speake, and he deliuered him to his mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.16'>Then there came a feare on them all, and they glorified God, saying, A great Prophet is risen among vs, and God hath visited his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.17'>And this rumour of him went foorth throughout all Iudea, and throughout all the region round about.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.18'>
          <note>John sends from the prison his unbelieving disciples to be confirmed by Christ himself.</note>And the disciples of John shewed him of all these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.19'>So Iohn called vnto him two certaine men of his disciples, and sent them to Iesus, saying, Art thou hee that should come, or shall we waite for another?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.20'>And when the men were come vnto him, they said, Iohn Baptist hath sent vs vnto thee, saying, Art thou hee that should come, or shall we waite for another?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.21'>And <note>When John's disciples came to Christ.</note> in that same hour he cured many of [their] infirmities and plagues, and of evil spirits; and unto many [that were] blind he gave sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.22'>And Iesus answered, and saide vnto them, Goe your wayes and shewe Iohn, what things ye haue seene and heard: that the blinde see, the halt goe, the lepers are cleansed, the deafe heare, the dead are raised, and the poore receiue the Gospel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.23'>And blessed is hee, that shall not be offended in me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.24'>
          <note>That which the prophets showed long before, John shows presently: and Christ himself presents it daily unto us in the gospel, but for the most part in vain, because many seek nothing else than foolish toys and vain glory.</note>And when the messengers of John were departed, he began to speak unto the people concerning John, What went ye out into the wilderness for to see? A reed shaken with the wind?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.25'>But what went ye out to see? A man clothed in soft rayment? Beholde, they which are gorgeously apparelled, and liue delicately, are in Kings courtes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.26'>But what went ye foorth to see? A Prophet? Yea, I say to you, and greater then a Prophet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.27'>This is he of whom it is written, Beholde, I sende my messenger before thy face, which shall prepare thy way before thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.28'>For I say vnto you, there is no greater Prophet then Iohn, among them that are begotten of women: neuerthelesse, hee that is the least in the kingdome of God, is greater then he.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.29'>And all the people that heard [him], and the publicans, <note>Said that he was just, good, faithful and merciful.</note> justified God, being baptized with the baptism of John.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.30'>But the Pharisees and lawyers rejected the counsel of God <note>To their own hurt.</note> against themselves, being not baptized of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.31'>
          <note>Whatever manner God uses in offering us the gospel, most men bring offences upon themselves: yet nevertheless a Church is gathered together.</note>And the Lord said, Whereunto then shall I liken the men of this generation? and to what are they like?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.32'>They are like vnto litle children sitting in the market place, and crying one to another, and saying, We haue piped vnto you, and ye haue not daunced: we haue mourned to you, and ye haue not wept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.33'>For Iohn Baptist came, neither eating bread, nor drinking wine: and ye say, He hath the deuil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.34'>The Sonne of man is come, and eateth and drinketh: and ye say, Beholde, a man which is a glutton, and a drinker of wine, a friend of Publicanes and sinners:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.35'>But wisdome is iustified of all her children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.36'>
          <note>Proud men deprive themselves of the benefits of the presence of Christ, even when he is at home with them in their houses; and these benefits the humble and base enjoy.</note>And one of the Pharisees desired him that he would eat with him. And he went into the Pharisee's house, and sat down to meat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.37'>And beholde, a woman in the citie, which was a sinner, when she knewe that Iesus sate at table in the Pharises house, shee brought a boxe of oyntment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.38'>And shee stoode at his feete behinde him weeping, and began to wash his feete with teares, and did wipe them with the heares of her head, and kissed his feete, and anoynted them with the oyntment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.39'>
          <note>Rashness is the companion of pride.</note>Now when the Pharisee which had bidden him saw [it], he spake within himself, saying, This man, if he were a prophet, would have known who and what manner of woman [this is] that toucheth him: <note>The Pharisee respects the law, which holds that those who touch the defiled are defiled.</note> for she is a sinner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.40'>
          <note>To love Christ is a sure and perpetual witness of the remission of sins.</note>And Jesus answering said unto him, Simon, I have somewhat to say unto thee. And he saith, Master, say on.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.41'>There was a certaine lender which had two detters: the one ought fiue hundreth pence, and the other fiftie:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.42'>When they had nothing to pay, he forgaue them both: Which of them therefore, tell mee, will loue him most?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.43'>Simon answered, and said, I suppose that he, to whom he forgaue most; he said vnto him, Thou hast truely iudged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.44'>Then he turned to the woman, and said vnto Simon, Seest thou this woman? I entred into thine house, and thou gauest mee no water to my feete: but she hath washed my feete with teares, and wiped them with the heares of her head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.45'>Thou gauest me no kisse: but she, since the time I came in, hath not ceased to kisse my feete.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.46'>Mine head with oyle thou didest not anoint: but she hath anoynted my feete with oyntment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.47'>Wherefore I say unto thee, Her sins, which are many, are forgiven; <note>That is, says Theophylact, she has shown her faith abundantly: and Basil in his «Sermon of Baptism» says, «He that owes much has much forgiven him, that he may love much more». And therefore Christ's saying is so plain in light of this that it is a wonder to see the enemies of the truth so badly distort and misinterpret this place in such a thorough manner in order to establish their meritorious works: for the greater sum a man has forgiven him, the more he loves him that has been so gracious to him. And this woman shows by deeds of love how great the benefit was she had received: and therefore the charity that is here spoken of is not to be taken as the cause of her forgiveness, but as a sign of it: for Christ does not say as the Pharisees did that she was a sinner, but bears her witness that the sins of her past life are forgiven her.</note> for she loved much: but to whom little is forgiven, [the same] loveth little.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.48'>And he saide vnto her, Thy sinnes are forgiuen thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.49'>And they that sate at table with him, began to say within themselues, Who is this that euen forgiueth sinnes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.7.50'>And he said to the woman, Thy faith hath saved thee; <note>He confirms with a blessing the benefit which he had bestowed.</note> go in peace.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.8'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.1'>And it came to passe afterwarde, that hee himselfe went through euery citie and towne, preaching and publishing the kingdome of God, and the twelue were with him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.2'>And certaine women, which were healed of euill spirites, and infirmities, as Mary which was called Magdalene, out of whom went seuen deuils,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.3'>And Ioanna the wife of Chuza Herods steward, and Susanna, and many other which ministred vnto him of their substance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.4'>
          <note>The same gospel is sown everywhere, but does not everywhere yield the same fruit, and this is only due to the fault of men themselves.</note>And when much people were gathered together, and were come to him out of every city, he spake by a parable:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.5'>A sower went out to sowe his seede, and as he sowed, some fell by the wayes side, and it was troden vnder feete, and the foules of heauen deuoured it vp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.6'>And some fell on the stones, and when it was sprong vp, it withered away, because it lacked moystnesse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.7'>And some fell among thornes, and the thornes sprang vp with it, and choked it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.8'>And some fell on good ground, and sprang vp, and bare fruite, an hundreth folde; as hee sayd these things, he cryed, He that hath eares to heare, let him heare.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.9'>Then his disciples asked him, demaunding what parable that was.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.10'>And he said, Unto you it is given to know the <note>Those things are called secret which may not be uttered: for the word used here is equivalent to our saying, «to hold a man's peace».</note> mysteries of the kingdom of God: but to others in parables; that seeing they might not see, and hearing they might not understand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.11'>The parable is this, The seede is the worde of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.12'>And they that are beside the way, are they that heare: afterward commeth the deuill, and taketh away the worde out of their hearts, least they should beleeue, and be saued.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.13'>But they that are on the stones, are they which when they haue heard, receiue ye word with ioy: but they haue no rootes: which for a while beleeue, but in the time of tentation goe away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.14'>And that which fell among thorns are they, which, when they have heard, <note>That is, as soon as they have heard the word, they go about their business.</note> go forth, and are choked with cares and riches and pleasures of [this] life, and <note>They do not bring forth perfect and full fruit to the ripening: or, they begin, but they do not bring to an end.</note> bring no fruit to perfection.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.15'>But that on the good ground are they, which in an <note>Who seek not only to seem to be such, but are indeed so: so that this word «honest» refers to the outward life, and the word «good» refers to the good gifts of the mind.</note> honest and good heart, having heard the word, <note>With much difficulty, for the devil and the flesh fight against the Spirit of God, who is a new guest.</note> keep [it], and bring forth fruit with patience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.16'>
          <note>That which every man has received in private he ought to bestow to the use and profit of all men.</note>No man, when he hath lighted a candle, covereth it with a vessel, or putteth [it] under a bed; but setteth [it] on a candlestick, that they which enter in may see the light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.17'>For nothing is secret, that shall not be euident: neither any thing hid, that shall not be knowen, and come to light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.18'>
          <note>Heavenly gifts are lost when one is sparing with them, and increase when one is liberal with them.</note>Take <note>That is, with what minds you come to hear the word, and how you behave yourselves when you have heard it.</note> heed therefore how ye hear: for whosoever hath, to him shall be given; and whosoever hath not, from him shall be taken even that <note>Either to himself, or to others, or to both: for there are none so proud as these fellows, if it were possible to see those things which they disguise: neither are there those that deceive the simple more than they do.</note> which he seemeth to have.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.19'>
          <note>There is no relationship of flesh and blood among men so intimate and upright as the band which is between Christ and those who embrace him with a true faith.</note>Then came to him [his] mother and his brethren, and could not come at him for the press.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.20'>And it was tolde him by certaine which said, Thy mother and thy brethren stand without, and would see thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.21'>But he answered, and sayd vnto them, My mother and my brethren are these which heare the worde of God, and doe it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.22'>
          <note>It is expedient for us sometimes to come into extreme danger, as though Christ was not with us, that we may have a better test, both of his power, and also of our weakness.</note>Now it came to pass on a certain day, that he went into a ship with his disciples: and he said unto them, Let us go over unto the other side of the lake. And they launched forth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.23'>But as they sailed he fell <note>Jesus fell asleep, and it appears that he was very fast asleep, because they called him twice before he awoke.</note> asleep: and there came down a storm of wind on the lake; and <note>Not the disciples, but the ship.</note> they were filled [with water], and were in jeopardy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.24'>Then they went to him, and awoke him, saying, Master, Master, we perish; he arose, and rebuked the winde, and the waues of water: and they ceased, and it was calme.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.25'>Then he sayde vnto them, Where is your fayth? And they feared, &amp; wondered among them selues, saying, Who is this that commandeth both the windes and water, and they obey him!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.26'>So they sailed vnto the region of the Gadarenes, which is ouer against Galile.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.27'>
          <note>Christ shows by casting out a legion of demons by his word alone that his heavenly power was appointed to deliver men from the slavery of the devil: but foolish men for the most part will not redeem this so excellent grace freely offered unto them if it means the loss of even the least of their wealth.</note>And when he went forth to land, there met him out of the city a certain man, which had devils long time, and ware no clothes, neither abode in [any] house, but in the tombs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.28'>And when he sawe Iesus, he cryed out and fell downe before him, and with a loude voyce sayd, What haue I to doe with thee, Iesus the Sonne of God the most High? I beseech thee torment me not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.29'>(For he had commanded the unclean spirit to come out of the man. For oftentimes it had caught him: and he was kept bound with chains and in fetters; and he brake the bands, <note>By force and violence, as a horse when he is spurred.</note> and was driven of the devil into the wilderness.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.30'>Then Iesus asked him, saying, What is thy name? And he sayd, Legion, because many deuils were entred into him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.31'>And they besought him, that he would not commaund them to goe out into the deepe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.32'>And there was there by, an hearde of many swine, feeding on an hill: and the deuils besought him, that he would suffer them to enter into them. So he suffered them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.33'>Then went the deuils out of the man, and entred into the swine: and the hearde was caried with violence from a steepe downe place into the lake, and was choked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.34'>When the heardmen sawe what was done, they fled: and when they were departed, they tolde it in the citie and in the countrey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.35'>Then they came out to see what was done, and came to Iesus, and found the man, out of whom the deuils were departed, sitting at the feete of Iesus, clothed, and in his right minde: and they were afrayd.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.36'>They also which saw it, tolde them by what meanes he that was possessed with the deuill, was healed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.37'>Then the whole multitude of the countrey about the Gadarenes, besought him that he would depart from them: for they were taken with a great feare: and he went into the ship, and returned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.38'>Then the man, out of whome the deuils were departed, besought him that hee might be with him: but Iesus sent him away, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.39'>Return to thine own house, and shew how great things God hath done unto thee. And he went his way, and published <note>That is, the city of the Gadarenes: and though Mark says that he preached it in Decapolis, these accounts do not differ, for Pliny records in lib. 5, chap. 18, that Gadara is a town of Decapolis: so that Decapolis was partly on this side of Jordan, and partly on the other side.</note> throughout the whole city how great things Jesus had done unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.40'>And it came to pass, that, when Jesus was returned, the people <note>The multitude was glad he had come again, and greatly rejoiced.</note> [gladly] received him: for they were all waiting for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.41'>
          <note>Christ shows by a double miracle that he is Lord both of life and death.</note>And, behold, there came a man named Jairus, and he was a ruler of the synagogue: and he fell down at Jesus' feet, and besought him that he would come into his house:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.42'>For he had but a daughter onely, about twelue yeeres of age, and she lay a dying (and as he went, the people thronged him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.43'>And a woman having an issue of blood twelve years, which had spent all her <note>All that she had to live upon.</note> living upon physicians, neither could be healed of any,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.44'>When she came behind him, she touched the hemme of his garment, and immediatly her yssue of blood stanched.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.45'>Then Iesus sayd, Who is it that hath touched me? When euery man denied, Peter sayd and they that were with him, Master, the multitude thrust thee, and tread on thee, &amp; sayest thou, Who hath touched me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.46'>And Iesus sayde, Some one hath touched me: for I perceiue that vertue is gone out of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.47'>When the woman sawe that she was not hid, she came trembling, and fell downe before him, and tolde him before all the people, for what cause she had touched him, and how she was healed immediatly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.48'>And he said vnto her, Daughter, be of good comfort: thy faith hath saued thee: go in peace.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.49'>While he yet spake, there came one from the ruler of the Synagogues house, which sayde to him, Thy daughter is dead: disease not the Master.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.50'>When Iesus heard it, he answered him, saying, Feare not: beleeue onely, and she shall be saued.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.51'>And when he went into the house, he suffered no man to goe in with him, saue Peter, and Iames, and Iohn, and the father and mother of the maide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.52'>And all wept, and <note>The word signifies to beat and strike, and is used in the mournings and lamentations that are at burials, at which times men used this type of behaviour.</note> bewailed her: but he said, Weep not; she is not dead, but sleepeth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.53'>And they laught him to scorne, knowing that she was dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.54'>So he thrust them all out, and tooke her by the hand, and cryed, saying, Maide, arise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.55'>And her spirit came again, and she <note>The corpse was lying there, and then the young girl received life, and rose out of the bed, that all the world might see that she was not only restored to life, but also void of all sickness.</note> arose straightway: and he commanded to give her meat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.8.56'>Then her parents were astonied: but hee commaunded them that they should tell no man what was done.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.9'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.1'>Then <note>The twelve apostles are sent forth only at the commandment of Christ and equipped with the power of the Holy Spirit: both that none of the Israelites might pretend ignorance, and also that they might be better prepared for their general mission.</note> he called his twelve disciples together, and gave them power and authority over all devils, and to cure diseases.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.2'>And hee sent them foorth to preach the kingdome of God, and to cure the sicke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.3'>And he sayd to them, Take nothing to your iourney, neither staues, nor scrip, neither bread, nor siluer, neither haue two coates apiece.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.4'>And whatsoever house ye enter into, there <note>When you depart out of any city, depart from that place where you first took up your lodging: so that in these few words the Lord forbids them to change their lodgings: for this publishing of the gospel was as it were a publishing throughout the whole land, that no one in Judea might pretend ignorance, as though he had not heard that Christ had come.</note> abide, and thence depart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.5'>And howe many so euer will not receiue you, when ye goe out of that citie, shake off the very dust from your feete for a testimonie against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.6'>And they went out, &amp; went through euery towne preaching the Gospel, and healing euery where.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.7'>
          <note>As soon as the world hears tidings of the gospel it is divided into differing opinions, and the tyrants especially are afraid.</note>Now Herod the tetrarch heard of all that was done by him: and he <note>He stuck as it were fast in the mire.</note> was perplexed, because that it was said of some, that John was risen from the dead;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.8'>And of some, that Elias had appeared: and of some, that one of the olde Prophets was risen againe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.9'>Then Herod sayd, Iohn haue I beheaded: who then is this of whome I heare such things? And he desired to see him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.10'>
          <note>They that follow Christ will lack nothing, not even in the wilderness.</note>And the apostles, when they were returned, told him all that they had done. And he took them, and went aside privately into a <note>The word signifies a desert: note, this was not in the town Bethsaida, but part of the fields belonging to the town.</note> desert place belonging to the city called Bethsaida.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.11'>But when the people knewe it, they followed him: and he receiued them, and spake vnto them of the kingdome of God, and healed them that had neede to be healed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.12'>And when the day began to weare away, the twelue came, and sayd vnto him, Sende the people away, that they may goe into the townes and villages round about, and lodge, &amp; get meate: for we are here in a desart place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.13'>But he said unto them, Give ye them to eat. And they said, We have no more but five loaves and two fishes; <note>This is said imperfectly, and therefore we must understand it to mean something like this: «We cannot give them to eat unless we go and buy, etc.».</note> except we should go and buy meat for all this people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.14'>For they were about fiue thousand men. Then he sayde to his disciples, Cause them to sit downe by fifties in a company.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.15'>And they did so, and caused all to sit downe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.16'>Then he took the five loaves and the two fishes, and looking up to heaven, <note>He gave God thanks for these loaves and fishes, and prayed at the same time that God would feed this multitude which was so great with such a small quantity, and to put it briefly, that this whole banquet might be to the glory of God.</note> he blessed them, and brake, and gave to the disciples to set before the multitude.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.17'>So they did all eate, and were satisfied: and there was taken vp of that remained to them, twelue baskets full of broken meate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.18'>
          <note>Although the world be tossed up and down between different errors, yet we ought not to condemn the truth but be all the more desirous to know it, and be more steadfast to confess it.</note>And it came to pass, as he was <note>Alone from the people.</note> alone praying, his disciples were with him: and he asked them, saying, Whom say the people that I am?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.19'>They answered, and sayd, Iohn Baptist: and others say, Elias: and some say, that one of the olde Prophets is risen againe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.20'>And he sayd vnto them, But whom say ye that I am? Peter answered, and sayd, That Christ of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.21'>And he warned and commaunded them, that they should tell that to no man,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.22'>
          <note>Christ himself attained to the heavenly glory, by the cross and invincible perseverance.</note>Saying, The Son of man must suffer many things, and be rejected of the elders and chief priests and scribes, and be slain, and be raised the third day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.23'>And he said to [them] all, If any [man] will come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross <note>Even as one day follows another, so does one cross follow another, and the cross is by the figure of speech metonymy taken for the miseries of this life: for to be hanged on the cross was the most grievous and cruel punishment that there was amongst the Jews.</note> daily, and follow me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.24'>For whosoeuer will saue his life, shal lose it: and whosoeuer shall lose his life for my sake, the same shall saue it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.25'>For what auantageth it a man, if he win the whole worlde, and destroy himselfe, or lose himselfe?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.26'>For whosoeuer shall be ashamed of me, and of my wordes, of him shall the Sonne of man be ashamed, when hee shall come in his glorie, and in the glorie of the Father, and of the holy Angels.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.27'>And I tell you of a suretie, there be some standing here, which shall not taste of death, till they haue seene the kingdome of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.28'>
          <note>So that his disciples do not stumble at his debasing himself in his flesh, he teaches them that it is voluntary, showing in addition for a moment the brightness of his glory.</note>And it came to pass about an eight days after these sayings, he took Peter and John and James, and went up into a mountain to pray.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.29'>And as he prayed, the fashion of his countenance was changed, and his garment was white and glistered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.30'>And beholde, two men talked with him, which were Moses and Elias:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.31'>Who appeared in glory, and spake of his <note>What death he would die in Jerusalem.</note> decease which he should accomplish at Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.32'>But Peter &amp; they that were with him, were heauie with sleepe, and when they awoke, they saw his glorie, and the two men standing with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.33'>And it came to passe, as they departed fro him, Peter said vnto Iesus, Master, it is good for vs to be here: let vs therefore make three tabernacles, one for thee, and one for Moses, and one for Elias, and wist not what he said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.34'>Whiles he thus spake, there came a cloude and ouershadowed them, and they feared when they were entring into the cloude.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.35'>And there came a voyce out of the cloud, saying, This is that my beloued Sonne, heare him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.36'>And when the voice was past, Jesus was found alone. And they kept [it] close, and told no man in <note>Until Christ was risen again from the dead.</note> those days any of those things which they had seen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.37'>
          <note>Nothing offends Christ as much as incredulity, although he bears with it for a time.</note>And it came to pass, that on the next day, when they were come down from the hill, much people met him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.38'>And beholde, a man of the companie cried out, saying, Master, I beseech thee, beholde my sonne: for he is all that I haue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.39'>And, lo, a spirit taketh him, and he suddenly crieth out; and it teareth him that he foameth again, and <note>As it happens in the falling sickness.</note> bruising him hardly departeth from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.40'>Nowe I haue besought thy disciples to cast him out, but they could not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.41'>Then Iesus answered, &amp; said, O generation faithlesse, and crooked, howe long now shall I be with you, and suffer you? bring thy sonne hither.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.42'>And whiles he was yet comming, the deuill rent him, and tare him: and Iesus rebuked the vncleane spirite, and healed the childe, and deliuered him to his father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.43'>
          <note>We have no reason to promise ourselves rest and quietness in this world, seeing that they themselves who seemed to fawn upon Christ crucify him shortly after.</note>And they were all amazed at the mighty power of God. But while they wondered every one at all things which Jesus did, he said unto his disciples,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.44'>
          <note>Give diligent ear to them, and once you have heard them see that you keep them.</note>Let these sayings sink down into your ears: for the Son of man shall be delivered into the hands of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.45'>But they vnderstood not that word: for it was hid from them, so that they could not perceiue it: and they feared to aske him of that worde.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.46'>
          <note>Ambition results in dishonour, but the result of modest obedience is glory.</note>Then there arose a reasoning among them, which of them should be greatest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.47'>When Iesus sawe the thoughtes of their heartes, he tooke a litle childe, &amp; set him by him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.48'>And said vnto them, Whosoeuer receiueth this litle childe in my Name, receiueth me: and whosoeuer shall receiue me, receiueth him that sent me: for he that is least among you all, he shall be great.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.49'>
          <note>Extraordinary things are neither rashly to be allowed nor condemned.</note>And John answered and said, Master, we saw one casting out devils in thy name; and we forbad him, because he followeth not with us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.50'>Then Iesus saide vnto him, Forbid ye him not: for he that is not against vs, is with vs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.51'>
          <note>Christ goes willingly to death.</note>And it came to pass, when the time was come that he should be received up, he stedfastly <note>Literally, «he hardened his face»: that is, he resolved with himself to die, and therefore ventured upon his journey and cast away all fear of death, and went on.</note> set his face to go to Jerusalem,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.52'>And sent messengers before him: and they went and entred into a towne of the Samaritans, to prepare him lodging.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.53'>But they woulde not receiue him, because his behauiour was, as though he would go to Hierusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.54'>
          <note>We must take heed of zeal and fond imitation which is not moderated, even in good causes, that whatever we do, we do it to God's glory, and the profit of our neighbour.</note>And when his disciples James and John saw [this], they said, Lord, wilt thou that we command fire to come down from heaven, and consume them, even as Elias did?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.55'>But he turned, and rebuked them, and said, Ye know not what manner of <note>So the Hebrews say, that is, you do not know what will, mind, and counsel you are of: so the gifts of God are called the spirit because they are given by God's Spirit, and so are the things that are contrary to them also called the spirit, which proceed from the wicked spirit, such as the spirit of covetousness, of pride, and madness.</note> spirit ye are of.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.56'>For the Sonne of man is not come to destroy mens liues, but to saue them. Then they went to another towne.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.57'>
          <note>Those who follow Christ must prepare themselves to endure all discomforts.</note>And it came to pass, that, as they went in the way, a certain [man] said unto him, Lord, I will follow thee whithersoever thou goest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.58'>And Iesus saide vnto him, The foxes haue holes, and the birdes of the heauen nestes, but the Sonne of man hath not whereon to lay his head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.59'>
          <note>The calling of God ought to be preferred without any question, before all duties that we owe to men.</note>And he said unto another, Follow me. But he said, Lord, suffer me first to go and bury my father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.60'>Jesus said unto him, Let the dead bury <note>Who, even though they live in this frail life of man, yet are strangers from the true life, which is everlasting and heavenly.</note> their dead: but go thou and preach the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.61'>
          <note>Those who follow Christ must at once renounce all worldly cares.</note>And another also said, Lord, I will follow thee; but let me first go bid them farewell, which are at home at my house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.9.62'>And Iesus saide vnto him, No man that putteth his hand to the plough, and looketh backe, is apt to the kingdome of God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.10'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.1'>After <note>The seventy are sent as the second forewarners of the coming of Christ.</note> these things the Lord appointed other seventy also, and sent them two and two before his face into every city and place, whither he himself would come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.2'>And he said vnto them, The haruest is great, but the labourers are fewe: pray therefore the Lord of the haruest to sende foorth labourers into his haruest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.3'>
          <note>The faithful ministers of the word are in this world as lambs among wolves: but if they are diligent to do their duty, he who sent them will also preserve them.</note>Go your ways: behold, I send you forth as lambs among wolves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.4'>Carry neither purse, nor scrip, nor shoes: and salute <note>This is spoken figuratively, which manner of speech men use when they put down more in words than is meant. This is usual among the Hebrews when they command a thing to be done speedily without delay, as is found in (2Ki_4:29); for in any other case courteous and gentle salutations are matters of Christian duty: as for the calling, it was only for a limited time.</note> no man by the way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.5'>And into whatsoeuer house ye enter, first say, Peace be to this house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.6'>And if <note>So say the Hebrews: that is, he that favours the doctrine of peace and embraces it.</note> the son of peace be there, your peace shall rest upon it: if not, it shall turn to you again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.7'>And in the same house <note>Take up your lodging in that house which you enter into first, that is, do not be concerned about comfortable lodging, as men do who plan to stay in a place a long time: for here that solemn preaching of the gospel, which was used afterward when the Churches were settled, is not instituted: but these are sent abroad to all the coasts of Judea to show them that the last jubilee is at hand.</note> remain, eating and drinking such things as they give: for the labourer is worthy of his hire. Go not from house to house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.8'>And into whatsoever city ye enter, and they receive you, <note>Be content with the food that is set before you.</note> eat such things as are set before you:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.9'>And heale the sicke that are there, and say vnto them, The kingdome of God is come neere vnto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.10'>
          <note>God is a most severe avenger of the ministry of his gospel.</note>But into whatsoever city ye enter, and they receive you not, go your ways out into the streets of the same, and say,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.11'>Euen the very dust, which cleaueth on vs of your citie, we wipe off against you: notwithstanding knowe this, that the kingdome of God was come neere vnto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.12'>For I say to you, that it shall be easier in that day for them of Sodom, then for that citie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.13'>Woe be to thee, Chorazin: woe be to thee, Beth-saida: for if the miracles had bene done in Tyrus and Sidon, which haue bene done in you, they had a great while agone repented, sitting in sackecloth and ashes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.14'>Therefore it shall be easier for Tyrus, and Sidon, at the iudgement, then for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.15'>And thou, Capernaum, which art exalted to heauen, shalt be thrust downe to hell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.16'>He that heareth you, heareth me: and he that despiseth you, despiseth me: and he that despiseth me, despiseth him that sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.17'>
          <note>Neither the gift of miracles, neither any other excellent gift, but only our election gives us an occasion of true joy. And only the publishing of the gospel is the destruction of Satan.</note>And the seventy returned again with joy, saying, Lord, even the devils are subject unto us <note>For Christ's disciples used no absolute authority, but performed the miracles they did by calling upon Christ's name.</note> through thy name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.18'>And he said unto them, I beheld Satan as lightning <note>Paul writes that the location of the devil and his angels is in the air, as is found in (Eph_6:12), and he is said to be cast down from there by force, when his power is abolished by the voice of the Gospel.</note> fall from heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.19'>Behold, I give unto you power to tread on serpents and scorpions, and over all the power of the enemy: and nothing shall by any means <note>Will do you wrong.</note> hurt you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.20'>Neuerthelesse, in this reioyce not, that the spirits are subdued vnto you: but rather reioyce, because your names are written in heauen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.21'>
          <note>The Church is contemptible, if we consider its outward appearance, but the wisdom of God is most marvellous in it.</note>In that hour Jesus rejoiced in spirit, and said, I thank thee, O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, that thou hast hid these things from the <note>Of this world.</note> wise and prudent, and hast revealed them unto babes: even so, Father; for so it seemed good in thy sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.22'>
          <note>Whoever seeks the Father without the Son wanders out of the way.</note>All things are delivered to me of my Father: and no man knoweth who the Son is, but the Father; and who the Father is, but the Son, and [he] to whom the Son will reveal [him].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.23'>
          <note>The difference between the Old Testament and the New consists in the measure of revelation.</note>And he turned him unto [his] disciples, and said privately, Blessed [are] the eyes which see the things that ye see:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.24'>For I tell you that many Prophets and Kings haue desired to see those things, which ye see, and haue not seene them: and to heare those things which ye heare, and haue not heard them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.25'>
          <note>Faith does not take away but establishes the doctrine of the law.</note>And, behold, <note>One of those who proclaimed himself to be learned in the rites and laws of Moses.</note> a certain lawyer stood up, and tempted him, saying, Master, what shall I do to inherit eternal life?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.26'>And he saide vnto him, What is written in the Lawe? Howe readest thou?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.27'>And he answered, and saide, Thou shalt loue thy Lord God with all thine heart, and with all thy soule, and with all thy strength, and with all thy thought, and thy neighbour as thy selfe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.28'>Then he said vnto him, Thou hast answered right: this doe, and thou shalt liue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.29'>
          <note>The law defines our neighbour as anyone at all that we may help.</note>But he, willing <note>That is, to vouch his righteousness, or show that he was just, that is, void of all faults: and (Jam. 5:1-20) uses the word of justification in this sense.</note> to justify himself, said unto Jesus, And who is my neighbour?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.30'>And Iesus answered, and saide, A certaine man went downe from Hierusalem to Iericho, and fell among theeues, and they robbed him of his raiment, and wounded him, and departed, leauing him halfe dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.31'>Nowe so it fell out, that there came downe a certaine Priest that same way, and when he sawe him, he passed by on the other side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.32'>And likewise also a Leuite, when he was come neere to the place, went and looked on him, and passed by on the other side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.33'>Then a certaine Samaritane, as he iourneyed, came neere vnto him, and when he sawe him, he had compassion on him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.34'>And went to him, &amp; bound vp his wounds, and powred in oyle and wine, and put him on his owne beast, and brought him to an Inne, and made prouision for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.35'>And on the morowe when he departed, he tooke out two pence, and gaue them to the hoste, and said vnto him, Take care of him, and whatsoeuer thou spendest more, when I come againe, I will recompense thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.36'>Which nowe of these three, thinkest thou, was neighbour vnto him that fell among the theeues?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.37'>And he saide, He that shewed mercie on him. Then said Iesus vnto him, Goe, and do thou likewise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.38'>
          <note>Christ does not desire to be waited upon in a delicate manner, but to be heard diligently; this is that which he especially requires.</note>Now it came to pass, as they went, that he entered into a certain village: and a certain woman named Martha received him into her house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.39'>And she had a sister called Marie, which also sate at Iesus feete, and heard his preaching.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.40'>But Martha was combred about much seruing, and came to him, and saide, Master, doest thou not care that my sister hath left me to serue alone? bid her therefore, that she helpe me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.41'>And Iesus answered, and said vnto her, Martha, Martha, thou carest, and art troubled about many things:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.10.42'>But one thing is needefull, Marie hath chosen the good part, which shall not be taken away from her.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.11'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.1'>And so it was, that as he was praying in a certaine place, when he ceased, one of his disciples said vnto him, Lord, teache vs to pray, as Iohn also taught his disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.2'>And he said unto them, When ye pray, say, <note>A form of true prayer.</note> Our Father which art in heaven, Hallowed be thy name. Thy kingdom come. Thy will be done, as in heaven, so in earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.3'>Give us <note>That is, as much as is needed for us this day, by which we are not prevented from having an honest care for the maintenance of our lives; but that complaining care, which kills a number of men, is cut off and restrained.</note> day by day our daily bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.4'>And forgiue vs our sinnes: for euen we forgiue euery man that is indetted to vs: And leade vs not into temptation: but deliuer vs from euill.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.5'>
          <note>We must pray with faith.</note>And he said unto them, Which of you shall have a friend, and shall go unto him at midnight, and say unto him, Friend, lend me three loaves;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.6'>For a friende of mine is come out of the way to me, &amp; I haue nothing to set before him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.7'>And hee within shoulde answere, and say, Trouble mee not: the doore is nowe shut, and my children are with mee in bed: I can not rise and giue them to thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.8'>I say unto you, Though he will not rise and give him, because he is his friend, yet because of his <note>Literally, «impudence»: but that impudency which is spoken of here is not to be found fault with, but is very commendable before God, for he is well pleased by such importunity.</note> importunity he will rise and give him as many as he needeth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.9'>And I say vnto you, Aske, and it shall be giuen you: seeke, and yee shall finde: knocke, and it shalbe opened vnto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.10'>For euery one that asketh, receiueth: and he that seeketh, findeth: &amp; to him that knocketh, it shalbe opened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.11'>If a sonne shall aske bread of any of you that is a father, will he giue him a stone? Or if hee aske a fish, will he for a fish giue him a serpent?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.12'>Or if hee aske an egge, will hee giue him a scorpion?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.13'>If yee then which are euill, can giue good giftes vnto your children, howe much more shall your heauenly Father giue the holy Ghost to them, that desire him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.14'>Then hee cast out a deuill which was domme: and when the deuill was gone out, the domme spake, and the people wondered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.15'>
          <note>An example of horrible blindness, and such as cannot be healed, when the power of God is blasphemed by an evil conscience and pretended malice.</note>But some of them said, He casteth out devils through Beelzebub the chief of the devils.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.16'>And others tempted him, seeking of him a signe from heauen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.17'>
          <note>The true way to know the true Christ from the false is this, that the true Christ has no harmony or agreement with Satan: and once we know him it is left for us to acknowledge him.</note>But he, knowing their thoughts, said unto them, Every kingdom divided against itself is brought to desolation; and a house [divided] against a house falleth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.18'>If Satan also be divided against himself, how shall his kingdom stand? because ye say that I cast out devils <note>By the name and power of Beelzebub.</note> through Beelzebub.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.19'>If I through Beelzebub cast out deuils, by whome doe your children cast them out? Therefore shall they be your iudges.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.20'>But if I with the <note>That is, by the power of God: so it says in {{See Exo_8:19}}.</note> finger of God cast out devils, no doubt the kingdom of God is come upon you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.21'>When a strong man armed keepeth his <note>The word properly signifies an open and empty room in front of a house, and so in translation is taken for noblemen's houses.</note> palace, his goods are in peace:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.22'>But when a stronger then hee, commeth vpon him, and ouercommeth him: hee taketh from him all his armour wherein he trusted, and deuideth his spoiles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.23'>
          <note>Against indifferent men, and such as love to have a compromise, who seek means to reconcile Christ and Satan together.</note>He that is not with me is against me: and he that gathereth not with me scattereth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.24'>
          <note>He that does not continue, but is in a worse case, than he that never began.</note>When the unclean spirit is gone out of a man, he walketh through dry places, seeking rest; and finding none, he saith, I will return unto my house whence I came out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.25'>And when he cometh, he findeth it swept and garnished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.26'>Then goeth hee, and taketh to him seuen other spirites worse then himselfe: and they enter in, and dwel there: so the last state of that man is worse then the first.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.27'>
          <note>Christ does not seek praise for himself, but in our salvation.</note>And it came to pass, as he spake these things, a certain woman of the company lifted up her voice, and said unto him, Blessed [is] the womb that bare thee, and the paps which thou hast sucked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.28'>But hee saide, Yea, rather blessed are they that heare the woorde of God, and keepe it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.29'>And when the people were gathered thicke together, he began to say, This is a wicked generation: they seeke a signe, and there shall no signe be giuen them, but the signe of Ionas the Prophet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.30'>For as Ionas was a signe to the Niniuites: so shall also the Sonne of man bee to this generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.31'>The Queene of the South shall rise in iudgement, with the men of this generation, and shall condemne them: for shee came from the vtmost partes of the earth to heare the wisedome of Solomon, and beholde, a greater then Solomon is here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.32'>The men of Niniue shall rise in iudgement with this generation, and shall condemne it: for they repented at the preaching of Ionas: and beholde, a greater then Ionas is here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.33'>
          <note>Our minds are therefore lightened with the knowledge of God, that we should give light unto others, and therefore our main labour ought to be to pray for that light.</note>No man, when he hath lighted a candle, putteth [it] in a secret place, neither under a bushel, but on a candlestick, that they which come in may see the light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.34'>The light of the bodie is the eye: therefore when thine eye is single, then is thy whole bodie light: but if thine eye be euill, then thy bodie is darke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.35'>Take heede therefore, that the light which is in thee, be not darkenesse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.36'>If therefore thy whole body shall be light, hauing no part darke, then shall all be light, euen as when a candle doth light thee with the brightnesse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.37'>
          <note>The service of God consists not in outward cleanliness and planned rites or ceremonies, but in the spiritual righteousness of the heart and charity.</note>And as he spake, a certain Pharisee besought him to dine with him: and he went in, and sat down to meat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.38'>And when the Pharise saw it, he marueiled that he had not first washed before dinner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.39'>And the Lord saide to him, In deede yee Pharises make cleane the outside of the cuppe, and of the platter: but the inwarde part is full of rauening and wickednesse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.40'>Ye fooles, did not he that made that which is without, make that which is within also?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.41'>But rather give alms <note>That is, according to your ability: as one would say, instead of your extortion which hindered you so that you could not eat cleanly, use charity, and in accordance with your ability be good to the poor, and in this way will that which is within the platter be sanctified even though the platter is unwashed.</note> of such things as ye have; and, behold, all things are clean unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.42'>
          <note>It is the characteristic of hypocrites to stand firmly for little trifles and to let greater matters pass.</note>But woe unto you, Pharisees! for ye <note>You decide by God's law that the tenth part is due to be paid.</note> tithe mint and rue and <note>Of all types of herbs, some as Augustine expounds it in his Enchiridion to Laurence, chap. 99, where he shows in like manner how that place of Paul, (God «will have all men to be saved»), (1Ti_2:4), is to be expounded after the same manner.</note> all manner of herbs, and pass over <note>That is to say, that which is right and reasonable to do, for this word «judgment» contains the commandments of the second table, and the other words, «the love of God», contain the commandments of the first.</note> judgment and the love of God: these ought ye to have done, and not to leave the other undone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.43'>
          <note>Hypocrisy and ambition are commonly joined together.</note>Woe unto you, Pharisees! for ye love the uppermost seats in the synagogues, and greetings in the markets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.44'>
          <note>Hypocrites deceive men with an outward show.</note>Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye are as graves which appear not, and the men that walk over [them] are not aware [of them].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.45'>
          <note>Hypocrites are very severe against other men, but think that all things are lawful for themselves.</note>Then answered one of the lawyers, and said unto him, Master, thus saying thou reproachest us also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.46'>And he sayde, Wo be to you also, yee Lawyers: for yee lade men with burdens grieuous to be borne, and yee your selues touche not the burdens with one of your fingers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.47'>
          <note>Hypocrites honour those saints when they are dead whom they persecute most cruelly when they are alive.</note>Woe unto you! for ye build the sepulchres of the prophets, and your fathers killed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.48'>Truly <note>When you persecute God's servants like mad men, even as your fathers did, though you try and cover it with a pretence of godliness, yet nonetheless, by beautifying the sepulchres of the prophets, what else are you doing but glorying in your father's cruelty, and setting up monuments (as it were) in glory and triumph of it?</note> ye bear witness that ye allow the deeds of your fathers: for they indeed killed them, and ye build their sepulchres.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.49'>Therefore also said the wisdom of God, I will send them prophets and apostles, and [some] of them they shall slay and <note>They will so vex them and trouble them, that at length they will banish them.</note> persecute:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.50'>That the blood of all the prophets, which was <note>That you may be called to give an account for it, yea, and be punished for the shedding of that blood of the prophets.</note> shed from the foundation of the world, may be required of this generation;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.51'>From the blood of Abel vnto the blood of Zacharias, which was slaine betweene the altar and the Temple: verely I say vnto you, it shall be required of this generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.52'>
          <note>Those who ought to be the door keepers of the Church have for a long time mainly hindered the people from entering into the knowledge of God.</note>Woe unto you, lawyers! for ye have <note>You have hidden and taken away, so that it cannot be found anywhere.</note> taken away the key of knowledge: ye entered not in yourselves, and them that were entering in ye hindered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.53'>
          <note>The more the world is reprehended, the worse it is, and yet we must not betray the truth.</note>And as he said these things unto them, the scribes and the Pharisees began to urge [him] vehemently, and to <note>They proposed many questions to him, to draw something out of his mouth which they might traitorously find fault with.</note> provoke him to speak of many things:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.11.54'>Laying wait for him, and seeking to catche some thing of his mouth, whereby they might accuse him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.12'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.1'>In <note>The faithful teachers of God's word, who are appointed by him for his people, must both take good heed of those who corrupt the purity of doctrine with smooth speech, and also take pains through the help of God to set forth sincere doctrine, openly and without fear.</note> the mean time, when there were gathered together <note>Literally, «ten thousand of people», a certain number which is given for an uncertain number.</note> an innumerable multitude of people, insomuch that they trode one upon another, he began to say unto his disciples first of all, Beware ye of the leaven of the Pharisees, which is hypocrisy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.2'>For there is nothing couered, that shall not bee reueiled: neither hidde, that shall not be knowen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.3'>Wherefore whatsoeuer yee haue spoken in darkenesse, it shall be heard in the light: and that which ye haue spoken in the eare, in secret places, shall be preached on the houses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.4'>
          <note>Although hypocrites have princes to execute their cruelty, yet there is no reason why we should be afraid of them, even by the smallest amount that may be, seeing that they can do nothing except that which pleases God, and God does not will anything that may be against the salvation of his elect.</note>And I say unto you my friends, Be not afraid of them that kill the body, and after that have no more that they can do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.5'>But I will <note>He warns them of dangers that presently hang over their heads, for those that come upon one suddenly make a greater wound.</note> forewarn you whom ye shall fear: Fear him, which after he hath killed hath power to cast into hell; yea, I say unto you, Fear him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.6'>Are not fiue sparowes bought for two farthings, and yet not one of them is forgotten before God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.7'>Yea, and all the heares of your head are nombred: feare not therefore: yee are more of value then many sparowes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.8'>
          <note>Great is the reward of a constant confession: and horrible is the punishment for denying Christ; yea, it will be impossible to call the punishment back again, if on purpose, both with mouth and heart we blaspheme a known truth.</note>Also I say unto you, Whosoever shall confess me before men, him shall the Son of man also confess before the angels of God:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.9'>But hee that shall denie mee before men, shall be denied before the Angels of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.10'>And whosoeuer shall speake a woorde against the Sonne of man, it shall be forgiuen him: but vnto him, that shal blaspheme ye holy Ghost, it shall not be forgiuen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.11'>
          <note>It is a great and difficult conflict to confess the truth, yet God who can do all things and is almighty will provide strength to the weakest who struggle greatly and do battle in God's appointed time.</note>And when they bring you unto the synagogues, and [unto] magistrates, and powers, take ye no thought how or what thing ye shall answer, or what ye shall say:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.12'>For the holy Ghost shall teache you in the same houre, what yee ought to say.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.13'>
          <note>For three reasons Christ would not be a judge to divide an inheritance. First, because he would not support and uphold the fleshly opinion that the Jews had of Messiah: secondly, because he wanted to distinguish the civil government from the ecclesiastical: thirdly, to teach us to beware of those which abuse the show of the gospel, and also the name of ministers, for their own private well-being.</note>And one of the company said unto him, Master, speak to my brother, that he divide the inheritance with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.14'>And he said vnto him, Man, who made me a iudge, or a deuider ouer you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.15'>And he said unto them, Take heed, and beware of <note>By covetousness is meant that greedy desire to get, commonly causing hurt to other men.</note> covetousness: for a man's life <note>God is the author and preserver of man's life; goods are not.</note> consisteth not in the abundance of the things which he possesseth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.16'>
          <note>There are none more mad than rich men who depend upon their riches.</note>And he spake a parable unto them, saying, The <note>Or rather country, for here is set forth a man that possesses not only a piece of ground, but a whole country, as they do who join house to house, and field to field; (Isa_5:8).</note> ground of a certain rich man brought forth plentifully:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.17'>And he <note>Reckoned with himself, which is the characteristic of covetous surly men who spend their life in those trifles.</note> thought within himself, saying, What shall I do, because I have no room where to bestow my fruits?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.18'>And he said, This wil I do, I wil pul downe my barnes, and builde greater, and therein will I gather all my fruites, and my goods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.19'>And I will say to my soul, Soul, thou hast much goods laid up for many years; take thine ease, eat, drink, [and] <note>Be merry and make good cheer.</note> be merry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.20'>But God said vnto him, O foole, this night wil they fetch away thy soule fro thee: then whose shall those things be which thou hast prouided?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.21'>So [is] he that layeth up treasure <note>Caring for no man but for himself, and making sure to trust in himself.</note> for himself, and is not rich toward God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.22'>
          <note>Earnestly thinking upon the providence of God is a present remedy for this life against the most foolish and wasting worry of men.</note>And he said unto his disciples, Therefore I say unto you, Take no thought for your life, what ye shall eat; neither for the body, what ye shall put on.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.23'>The life is more then meate: and the body more then the raiment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.24'>Consider the rauens: for they neither sowe nor reape: which neither haue storehouse nor barne, &amp; yet God feedeth them: how much more are yee better then foules?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.25'>And which of you with taking thought, can adde to his stature one cubite?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.26'>If yee then bee not able to doe the least thing, why take yee thought for the remnant?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.27'>Consider the lilies howe they growe: they labour not, neither spin they: yet I say vnto you, that Solomon himselfe in all his royaltie was not clothed like one of these.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.28'>If then God so clothe the grasse which is to day in the field, and to morowe is cast into the ouen, howe much more will he clothe you, O yee of litle faith?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.29'>And seek not ye what ye shall eat, or what ye shall drink, neither <note>A metaphor taken of things that hang in the air, for those that care too much for this worldly life, and rely upon the arm of man, always have wavering and doubtful minds, swaying sometimes this way, and sometimes that way.</note> be ye of doubtful mind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.30'>For all such things the people of the world seeke for: and your Father knoweth that ye haue neede of these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.31'>
          <note>They will lack nothing who are diligent for the kingdom of heaven.</note>But rather seek ye the kingdom of God; and all these things shall be added unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.32'>
          <note>It is a foolish thing not to look for small things at the hands of him who freely gives us the greatest things.</note>Fear not, little flock; for it is your Father's good pleasure to give you the kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.33'>
          <note>A godly bountifulness is a proper way to get true riches.</note>Sell that ye have, and give <note>This is the figure of speech metonymy, for by this word «alms» is meant that compassion and friendliness of a heart that cares tenderly for the misery and poor condition of a man, and shows this feeling by some gift, and has the name given to it in the Greek language of mercy and compassion: and therefore he is said to give alms who gives something to another, and gives to the poor, showing by this that he pities their poor condition.</note> alms; provide yourselves bags which wax not old, a treasure in the heavens that faileth not, where no thief approacheth, neither moth corrupteth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.34'>For where your treasure is, there will your hearts be also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.35'>
          <note>The life of the faithful servants of God in this world is certainly a diligent journey, having the light of the word going before the journey.</note>Let your loins be girded about, and [your] lights burning;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.36'>And ye your selues like vnto men that waite for their master, when he will returne from the wedding, that when he commeth and knocketh, they may open vnto him immediatly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.37'>Blessed are those seruants, whom the Lord when he commeth shall finde waking: verely I say vnto you, he will girde himselfe about, and make them to sit downe at table, and will come forth, and serue them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.38'>And if he come in the seconde watch, or come in the third watch, and shall finde them so, blessed are those seruants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.39'>Nowe vnderstand this, that if the good man of the house had knowen at what houre the theefe would haue come, he would haue watched, and would not haue suffered his house to be digged through.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.40'>
          <note>None need to watch more than they that have some degree of honour in the household of God.</note>Be ye therefore ready also: for the Son of man cometh at an hour when ye think not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.41'>Then Peter saide vnto him, Master, tellest thou this parable vnto vs, or euen to all?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.42'>And the Lord said, Who then is that faithful and wise steward, whom [his] lord shall make ruler over his household, to give [them their] <note>That is, every month the measure of corn that was given to them.</note> portion of meat in due season?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.43'>Blessed is that seruant, whom his master when he commeth, shall finde so doing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.44'>Of a trueth I say vnto you, that he wil make him ruler ouer all that he hath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.45'>But if that seruant say in his heart, My master doeth deferre his comming, and ginne to smite the seruants, and maydens, and to eate, and drinke, and to be drunken,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.46'>The master of that seruant will come in a day when he thinketh not, and at an houre when he is not ware of, and will cut him off, and giue him his portion with the vnbeleeuers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.47'>And that seruant that knewe his masters will, and prepared not himselfe, neither did according to his will, shalbe beaten with many stripes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.48'>But he that knew not, and did commit things worthy of stripes, shall be beaten with few [stripes]. For unto whomsoever much is given, of him shall be much required: and to whom men have committed much, of him they will ask <note>More than the one who did not receive as much.</note> the more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.49'>
          <note>The gospel is the only reason of peace between the godly, and so it is the occasion of great trouble among the wicked.</note>I am come to send fire on the earth; and what will I, if it be already kindled?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.50'>Notwithstanding I must be baptized with a baptisme, &amp; how am I grieued, till it be ended?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.51'>Thinke ye that I am come to giue peace on earth? I tell you, nay, but rather debate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.52'>For from hencefoorth there shall be fiue in one house deuided, three against two, and two against three.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.53'>The father shalbe deuided against ye sonne, and the sonne against the father: the mother against the daughter, and the daughter against the mother: the mother in lawe against her daughter in lawe, and the daughter in lawe against her mother in lawe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.54'>
          <note>Men who are very quick to see with regard to earthly things are blind with regard to those things which pertain to the heavenly life, and this through their own malice.</note>And he said also to the people, When ye see a cloud <note>Which appears, and gathers itself together in that part of the air.</note> rise out of the west, straightway ye say, There cometh a shower; and so it is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.55'>And when ye see the South winde blowe, ye say, that it wilbe hoate: &amp; it commeth to passe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.56'>Hypocrites, ye can discerne the face of the earth, and of the skie: but why discerne ye not this time?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.57'>
          <note>Men that are blinded with the love of themselves, and therefore are detestable and stubborn, will bear the punishment of their folly.</note>Yea, and why even of yourselves judge ye not what is right?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.58'>When thou goest with thine adversary to the magistrate, [as thou art] in the way, give diligence that thou mayest be delivered from him; lest he hale thee to the judge, and the judge deliver thee to the <note>To him that has to demand and gather the fines from those who were fined at the discretion of the court, people who had wrongly troubled men: moreover, the magistrate's officers make those who are condemned pay what they owe, yea and often if they are obstinate, they not only take the fine, but also imprison them.</note> officer, and the officer cast thee into prison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.12.59'>I tell thee, thou shalt not depart thence, till thou hast payed the vtmost mite.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.13'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.1'>There <note>We must not rejoice at the just punishment of others, but rather we should be instructed by it to repent.</note> were present at that season some that told him of the Galilaeans, whose blood <note>Pontius Pilate was governor of Judea almost ten years, and about the fourth year of his government, which might be about the fifteenth year of Tiberius' reign, Christ finished the work of our redemption by his death.</note> Pilate had mingled with their sacrifices.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.2'>And Iesus answered, and saide vnto them, Suppose ye, that these Galileans were greater sinners then al the other Galileans, because they haue suffered such things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.3'>I tell you, nay: but except ye amend your liues, ye shall all likewise perish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.4'>Or those eighteen, upon whom the tower in <note>That is, in the place, or river: for Siloam was a small river from which the conduits of the city came; see (Joh_9:7; Isa_8:6); and therefore it was a tower or a castle, built upon the conduit side, which fell down suddenly and killed some.</note> Siloam fell, and slew them, think ye that they were sinners above all men that dwelt in Jerusalem?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.5'>I tell you, nay: but except ye amend your liues, ye shall all likewise perish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.6'>
          <note>Great and long suffering is the patience of God, but yet he eventually executes judgment.</note>He spake also this parable; A certain [man] had a fig tree planted in his vineyard; and he came and sought fruit thereon, and found none.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.7'>Then said he unto the dresser of his vineyard, Behold, these three years I come seeking fruit on this fig tree, and find none: cut it down; why <note>Make the ground barren in that part which is otherwise good for vines.</note> cumbereth it the ground?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.8'>And he answered, and said vnto him, Lord, let it alone this yeere also, till I digge round about it, and doung it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.9'>And if it beare fruite, well: if not, then after thou shalt cut it downe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.10'>
          <note>Christ came to deliver us from the hand of Satan.</note>And he was teaching in one of the synagogues on the sabbath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.11'>And, behold, there was a woman which had a <note>Troubled with a disease which Satan caused.</note> spirit of infirmity eighteen years, and was bowed together, and could in no wise lift up [herself].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.12'>And when Jesus saw her, he called [her to him], and said unto her, Woman, thou art <note>For Satan had the woman bound, as if she had been in chains, to the extent that for eighteen years time she could not hold up her head.</note> loosed from thine infirmity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.13'>And he laide his handes on her, and immediately she was made straight againe, and glorified God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.14'>
          <note>A graphic image of hypocrisy, and the reward of it.</note>And the <note>One of the rulers of the synagogue, for it appears that there were many rulers of the synagogue, see (Mar_5:22) (Act_13:15).</note> ruler of the synagogue answered with indignation, because that Jesus had healed on the sabbath day, and said unto the people, There are six days in which men ought to work: in them therefore come and be healed, and not on the sabbath day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.15'>Then answered him the Lord, and said, Hypocrite, doth not eche one of you on the Sabbath day loose his oxe or his asse from the stall, &amp; leade him away to the water?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.16'>And ought not this daughter of Abraham, whom Satan had bound, loe, eighteene yeeres, be loosed from this bond on the Sabbath day?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.17'>And when he said these things, all his aduersaries were ashamed: but all the people reioyced at all the excellent things, that were done by him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.18'>Then said he, What is the kingdome of God like? Or whereto shall I compare it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.19'>
          <note>God begins his kingdom with small beginnings so that its growth, which is not looked for, may better set forth his power.</note>It is like a grain of mustard seed, which a man took, and cast into his garden; and it grew, and waxed a great tree; and the fowls of the air lodged in the branches of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.20'>And againe he said, Whereunto shall I liken the kingdome of God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.21'>It is like leauen, which a woman tooke, and hid in three peckes of floure, till all was leauened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.22'>
          <note>Against those who had rather err with many than go right with a few, and because of this through their own indifference they are shut out of the kingdom of God.</note>And he went through the cities and villages, teaching, and journeying toward Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.23'>Then saide one vnto him, Lorde, are there fewe that shalbe saued? And he said vnto them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.24'>Striue to enter in at the straite gate: for many, I say vnto you, will seeke to enter in, and shall not be able.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.25'>When the good man of the house is risen vp, and hath shut to the doore, and ye begin to stand without, and to knocke at the doore, saying, Lord, Lord, open to vs, and he shall answere and say vnto you, I know you not whence ye are,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.26'>
          <note>It is vain to be in the Church if one is not of the Church; and whether or not one is in the Church is shown by the purity of life.</note>Then shall ye begin to say, We have eaten and drunk in thy presence, and thou hast taught in our streets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.27'>But he shall say, I tell you, I knowe you not whence ye are: depart from me, all ye workers of iniquitie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.28'>
          <note>The casting off of the Jews and the calling of the Gentiles is foretold.</note>There shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth, when ye shall see Abraham, and Isaac, and Jacob, and all the prophets, in the kingdom of God, and you [yourselves] thrust out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.29'>And they shall come from the <note>From all the corners of the world, and the places mentioned here are four of the main ones.</note> east, and [from] the west, and from the north, and [from] the south, and shall sit down in the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.30'>And beholde, there are last, which shalbe first, and there are first, which shalbe last.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.31'>
          <note>We must go forward in regards to our calling, through the midst of terrors, whether they be real or imagined.</note>The same day there came certain of the Pharisees, saying unto him, Get thee out, and depart hence: for Herod will kill thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.32'>And he said unto them, Go ye, and tell that <note>That deceitful and treacherous man.</note> fox, Behold, I cast out devils, and I do cures <note>That is, a small time, and Theophylact says it is a proverb: or else by «to day» we may understand the present time, and by tomorrow the time to come, meaning by this the entire time of his ministry and office.</note> to day and to morrow, and the third [day] I shall be <note>That is, when the sacrifice for sin is finished.</note> perfected.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.33'>
          <note>Nowhere else are there more cruel enemies of the godly than within the sanctuary and Church itself: but God sees it and will in his time have an account for it from them.</note>Nevertheless I must walk to day, and to morrow, and the [day] following: for it cannot be that a prophet perish out of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.34'>O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, which killest the prophets, and stonest them that are sent unto thee; how often would I have gathered thy children together, as a hen [doth gather] her <note>Literally, «the nest»: now the brood of chickens is the nest.</note> brood under [her] wings, and ye would not!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.13.35'>Beholde, your house is left vnto you desolate: and verely I tell you, ye shall not see me vntill the time come that ye shall say, Blessed is he that commeth in the Name of the Lord.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.14'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.1'>And <note>The law of the very sabbath ought not to hinder the offices of charity.</note> it came to pass, as he went into the house of <note>Either one of the elders, whom they called the sanhedrin, or one of the chiefs of the synagogue: for all the Pharisees were not chief men of the synagogue (Joh_7:48); for this word Pharisee was the name of a sect, though it appears by viewing the whole history of the matter that the Pharisees had much authority.</note> one of the chief Pharisees to eat bread on the sabbath day, that they watched him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.2'>And beholde, there was a certaine man before him, which had the dropsie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.3'>Then Iesus answering, spake vnto the Lawyers and Pharises, saying, Is it lawfull to heale on the Sabbath day?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.4'>And they held their peace. Then he tooke him, and healed him, and let him goe,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.5'>And answered them, saying, Which of you shall haue an asse, or an oxe fallen into a pit, &amp; wil not straightway pull him out on the Sabbath day?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.6'>And they could not answere him againe to those things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.7'>
          <note>The reward of pride is dishonour, and the reward of true modesty is glory.</note>And he put forth a parable to those which were bidden, when he marked how they chose out the chief rooms; saying unto them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.8'>When thou shalt be bidden of any man to a wedding, set not thy selfe downe in the chiefest place, lest a more honourable man then thou, be bidden of him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.9'>And he that bade both him &amp; thee, come, and say to thee, Giue this man roome, and thou then begin with shame to take the lowest roome.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.10'>But when thou art bidden, goe and sit downe in the lowest roome, that when he that bade thee, cometh, he may say vnto thee, Friende, sit vp hier: then shalt thou haue worship in the presence of them that sit at table with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.11'>For whosoeuer exalteth himselfe, shall be brought lowe, and he that humbleth himselfe, shal be exalted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.12'>
          <note>Against those who spend their goods either for the glory of man or for hope of recompence, whereas Christian charity considers only the glory of God, and the profit of our neighbour.</note>Then said he also to him that bade him, When thou makest a dinner or a supper, call not thy friends, nor thy brethren, neither thy kinsmen, nor [thy] rich neighbours; lest they also bid thee again, and a recompence be made thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.13'>But when thou makest a feast, call ye poore, the maimed, the lame, and the blind,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.14'>And thou shalt be blessed, because they cannot recompense thee: for thou shalt be recompensed at the resurrection of the iust.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.15'>Nowe when one of them that sate at table, heard these things, he said vnto him, Blessed is he that eateth bread in the kingdome of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.16'>Then saide he to him, A certaine man made a great supper, and bade many,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.17'>And sent his seruant at supper time to say to them that were bidden, Come: for all things are nowe readie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.18'>
          <note>For the most part even those to whom God has revealed himself are so mad, that any help which they have received of God they willingly turn into obstructions and hindrances.</note>And they all with <note>On purpose, and a thing agreed upon before: for though they give different reasons why they cannot come, yet all of them agree in this, that they have their excuses so that they may not come to supper.</note> one [consent] began to make excuse. The first said unto him, I have bought a piece of ground, and I must needs go and see it: I pray thee have me excused.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.19'>And another said, I haue bought fiue yoke of oxen, and I goe to proue them: I pray thee, haue me excused.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.20'>And another said, I haue maried a wife, and therefore I can not come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.21'>So that servant came, and shewed his lord these things. Then the master of the house being angry said to his servant, Go out quickly into the <note>Wide and broad areas.</note> streets and lanes of the city, and bring in hither the poor, and the maimed, and the halt, and the blind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.22'>And the seruaunt saide, Lorde, it is done as thou hast commaunded, and yet there is roome.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.23'>Then the master sayd to the seruaunt, Goe out into the hie wayes, and hedges, and compell them to come in, that mine house may bee filled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.24'>For I say vnto you, that none of those men which were bidden, shall taste of my supper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.25'>
          <note>Even those affections which are in themselves worthy of praise and commendation must be controlled and kept in order, so that godliness may have the upper hand and have preeminence.</note>And there went great multitudes with him: and he turned, and said unto them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.26'>If any [man] come to me, and <note>If anything stands between God and him, as Theophylact says: and therefore these words are spoken in a comparative way, and not by themselves.</note> hate not his father, and mother, and wife, and children, and brethren, and sisters, yea, and his own life also, he cannot be my disciple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.27'>
          <note>The true followers of Christ must at once build and fight, and therefore be ready and prepared to endure all types of miseries.</note>And whosoever doth not bear his cross, and come after me, cannot be my disciple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.28'>For which of you, intending to build a tower, <note>At home, and calculates all his costs before he begins the work.</note> sitteth not down first, and counteth the cost, whether he have [sufficient] to finish [it]?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.29'>Lest that after he hath laide the foundation, and is not able to performe it, all that behold it, begin to mocke him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.30'>Saying, This man began to builde, and was not able to make an end?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.31'>Or what King going to make warre against another King, sitteth not downe first, and taketh counsell, whether he be able with ten thousande, to meete him that commeth against him with twentie thousand?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.32'>Or els while hee is yet a great way off, hee sendeth an ambassage, and desireth peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.33'>So likewise, whosoeuer hee be of you, that forsaketh not all that he hath, he cannot be my disciple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.34'>
          <note>The disciples of Christ must be wise, both for themselves and for others: otherwise they become the most foolish of all.</note>Salt [is] good: but if the salt have lost his savour, wherewith shall it be seasoned?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.14.35'>It is neither meete for the land, nor yet for the dunghill, but men cast it out. He that hath eares to heare, let him heare.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.15'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.1'>Then drew near unto <note>We must not give up on those who have gone out of the way, but according to the example of Christ we must take great pains for them.</note> him <note>Some publicans and sinners came to Christ from all areas.</note> all the publicans and sinners for to hear him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.2'>Therefore the Pharises and Scribes murmured, saying, Hee receiueth sinners, and eateth with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.3'>Then spake hee this parable to them, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.4'>What man of you hauing an hundreth sheepe, if hee lose one of them, doeth not leaue ninetie and nine in the wildernesse, and goe after that which is lost, vntill he finde it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.5'>And when he hath found it, he laieth it on his shoulders with ioye.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.6'>And when he commeth home, he calleth together his friendes and neighbours, saying vnto them, Reioyce with mee: for I haue founde my sheepe which was lost.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.7'>I say vnto you, that likewise ioy shall be in heauen for one sinner that conuerteth, more then for ninetie and nine iust men, which neede none amendement of life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.8'>Either what woma hauing ten groates, if she lose one groate, doth not light a candle, &amp; sweepe the house, and seeke diligently till shee finde it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.9'>And when shee hath found it, shee calleth her friendes, and neighbours, saying, Reioyce with me: for I haue found the groate which I had lost.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.10'>Likewise I say vnto you, there is ioy in the presence of the Angels of God, for one sinner that conuerteth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.11'>
          <note>Men by their voluntary falling from God, having robbed themselves of the benefits which they received from him, cast themselves headlong into infinite calamities: but God of his singular goodness, offering himself freely to those whom he called to repentance, through the greatness of their misery with which they were humbled, not only gently receives them, but also enriches them with far greater gifts and blesses them with the greatest bliss.</note>And he said, A certain man had two sons:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.12'>And the yonger of them sayde to his father, Father, giue mee the portion of the goods that falleth to mee. So he deuided vnto them his substance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.13'>So not many daies after, when the yonger sonne had gathered all together, hee tooke his iourney into a farre countrey, and there hee wasted his goods with riotous liuing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.14'>Nowe when hee had spent all, there arose a great dearth throughout that land, and he began to be in necessitie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.15'>Then hee went and claue to a citizen of that conntrey, and hee sent him to his farme, to feede swine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.16'>And hee would faine haue filled his bellie with the huskes, that the swine ate: but no man gaue them him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.17'>
          <note>The beginning of repentance is the acknowledging of the mercy of God, which encourages us to hope expectantly.</note>And when he came to himself, he said, How many hired servants of my father's have bread enough and to spare, and I perish with hunger!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.18'>I will arise and go to my father, and will say unto him, Father, I have sinned against <note>Against God, because he is said to dwell in heaven.</note> heaven, and before thee,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.19'>And am no more worthy to be called thy sonne: make me as one of thy hired seruants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.20'>So hee arose and came to his father, and when hee was yet a great way off, his father sawe him, and had compassion, and ranne and fell on his necke, and kissed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.21'>
          <note>In true repentance there is a consciousness of our sins, joined with sorrow and shame, and from this springs a confession, after which follows forgiveness.</note>And the son said unto him, Father, I have sinned against heaven, and in thy sight, and am no more worthy to be called thy son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.22'>Then the father said to his seruaunts, Bring foorth the best robe, and put it on him, and put a ring on his hand, and shoes on his feete,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.23'>And bring the fat calfe, and kill him, &amp; let vs eate, and be merie:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.24'>For this my sonne was dead, and is aliue againe: and he was lost, but he is found; they began to be merie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.25'>
          <note>Those who truly fear God desire to have all men join them in fearing him.</note>Now his elder son was in the field: and as he came and drew nigh to the house, he heard musick and dancing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.26'>And called one of his seruaunts, and asked what those things meant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.27'>And hee sayde vnto him, Thy brother is come, and thy father hath killed the fatte calfe, because he hath receiued him safe and sound.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.28'>Then he was angry, and would not goe in: therefore came his father out and entreated him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.29'>But he answered &amp; said to his father, Loe, these many yeeres haue I done thee seruice, neither brake I at any time thy commadement, and yet thou neuer gauest mee a kidde that I might make merie with my friends.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.30'>But when this thy sonne was come, which hath deuoured thy good with harlots, thou hast for his sake killed the fat calfe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.31'>And he said vnto him, Sonne, thou art euer with me, and al that I haue, is thine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.15.32'>It was meete that we shoulde make merie, and be glad: for this thy brother was dead, and is aliue againe: and hee was lost, but he is found.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.16'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.1'>And he said also unto his disciples, <note>Seeing that men often purchase friendship for themselves at the expense of others, we are to be ashamed if we do not please the Lord or procure the good will of our neighbours with the goods which the Lord has bestowed on us freely and liberally, making sure that by this means riches, which are often occasions of sin, are used for another end and purpose.</note> There was a certain rich man, which had a steward; and the same was accused unto him that he had wasted his goods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.2'>And hee called him, and saide vnto him, Howe is it that I heare this of thee? Giue an accounts of thy stewardship: for thou maiest be no longer steward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.3'>Then the stewarde saide within himselfe, What shall I doe? for my master taketh away from me the stewardship. I cannot digge, and to begge I am ashamed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.4'>I knowe what I will doe, that when I am put out of the stewardship, they may receiue mee into their houses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.5'>Then called he vnto him euery one of his masters detters, &amp; said vnto the first, Howe much owest thou vnto my master?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.6'>And he said, An hudreth measures of oyle; he saide to him, Take thy writing, and sitte downe quickely, and write fiftie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.7'>Then said he to another, How much owest thou? And hee sayde, An hundreth measures of wheate. Then he saide to him, Take thy writing, and write foure score.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.8'>And the lord commended <note>This parable does not approve the steward's evil dealing, for it was definitely theft: but parables are set forth to show a thing in a secret way, and as it were, to present the truth by means of an allegory, even though it may not be exact: so that by this parable Christ means to teach us that worldly men are more clever in the affairs of this world than the children of God are diligent for everlasting life.</note> the unjust steward, because he had done wisely: for the <note>Men that are given to this present life, contrary to whom are the children of light: Paul calls the former carnal and the latter spiritual.</note> children of this world are in their generation wiser than the children of light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.9'>And I say unto you, Make to yourselves friends of the mammon <note>This is not spoken of goods that are gotten wrongly, for God will have our bountifulness to the poor proceed and come from a good fountain: but he calls those things riches of iniquity which men use wickedly.</note> of unrighteousness; that, when ye fail, they may receive you into everlasting <note>That is, the poor Christians: for they are the inheritors of these habitations; Theophylact.</note> habitations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.10'>
          <note>We ought to take heed that we do not abuse our earthly work and duty and so be deprived of heavenly gifts: for how can they properly use spiritual gifts who abuse worldly things?</note>He that is faithful in that which is least is faithful also in much: and he that is unjust in the least is unjust also in much.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.11'>If therefore ye have not been faithful in the unrighteous mammon, who will commit to your trust the <note>That is, heavenly and true riches, which are contrary to material wealth which is worldly and quickly departing.</note> true [riches]?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.12'>And if ye have not been faithful in that which is <note>In worldly goods, which are called other men's because they are not ours, but rather entrusted to our care.</note> another man's, who shall give you that which is your own?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.13'>
          <note>No man can love God and riches simultaneously.</note>No servant can serve two masters: for either he will hate the one, and love the other; or else he will hold to the one, and despise the other. Ye cannot serve God and mammon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.14'>All these thinges heard the Pharises also which were couetous, and they scoffed at him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.15'>
          <note>Our sins are not hidden to God, although they may be hidden to men, yea although they may be hidden to those who committed them.</note>And he said unto them, Ye are they which justify yourselves before men; but God knoweth your hearts: for that which is highly esteemed among men is abomination in the sight of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.16'>
          <note>The Pharisees despised the excellency of the new covenant with respect to the old, being ignorant of the perfect righteousness of the law; and Christ declares by the seventh commandment how they were false expounders of the law.</note>The law and the prophets [were] until John: since that time the kingdom of God is preached, and every man presseth into it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.17'>Nowe it is more easie that heauen and earth shoulde passe away, then that one title of the Lawe should fall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.18'>Whosoever putteth away his wife, and marrieth another, committeth adultery: and whosoever marrieth her <note>They that gather by this passage that a man cannot be married again after he has divorced his wife for adultery, while she lives, reason incorrectly: for Christ speaks of those divorces which the Jews had which were not because of adultery, for adulterers were put to death by the law.</note> that is put away from [her] husband committeth adultery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.19'>
          <note>The end of the poverty and misery of the godly will be everlasting joy, as the end of riotous living and the cruel pride of the rich will be everlasting misery, without any hope of mercy.</note>There was a certain rich man, which was clothed in <note>Very gorgeously and sumptuously, for purple garments were costly, and this fine linen, which was a kind of linen that came out of Achaia, was as precious as gold.</note> purple and fine linen, and fared sumptuously every day:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.20'>Also there was a certaine begger named Lazarus, which was laide at his gate full of sores,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.21'>And desired to bee refreshed with the crommes that fell from the riche mans table: yea, and the dogges came and licked his sores.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.22'>And it was so that the begger died, and was caried by the Angels into Abrahams bosome. The rich man also died, and was buried.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.23'>And in hell <note>Heavenly and spiritual things are expressed and set forth using language fit for our senses.</note> he lift up his eyes, being in torments, and seeth Abraham afar off, and Lazarus in his bosom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.24'>Then he cried, and saide, Father Abraham, haue mercie on mee, and sende Lazarus that hee may dippe the tip of his finger in water, &amp; coole my tongue: for I am tormented in this flame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.25'>But Abraham saide, Sonne, remember that thou in thy life time receiuedst thy pleasures, and likewise Lazarus paines: now therefore is he comforted, and thou art tormented.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.26'>Besides all this, betweene you &amp; vs there is a great gulfe set, so that they which would goe from hence to you, can not: neither ca they come from thence to vs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.27'>
          <note>Seeing that we have a most sure rule to live by, laid forth for us in the word of God, men seek rashly and vainly for other revelations.</note>Then he said, I pray thee therefore, father, that thou wouldest send him to my father's house:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.28'>(For I haue fiue brethren) that he may testifie vnto them, least they also come into this place of torment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.29'>Abraham said vnto him, They haue Moses and the Prophets: let them heare them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.30'>And he sayde, Nay, father Abraham: but if one came vnto them from the dead, they will amend their liues.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.16.31'>Then he saide vnto him, If they heare not Moses and the Prophets, neither will they be persuaded, though one rise from the dead againe.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.17'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.1'>Then said he unto the disciples, <note>The Church is of necessity subject to offences, but the Lord will not suffer them unpunished, if any of the least be offended.</note> It is impossible but that offences will come: but woe [unto him], through whom they come!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.2'>It is better for him that a great milstone were hanged about his necke, and that he were cast into ye sea, then that he should offende one of these litle ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.3'>
          <note>Our reprehensions must be just and proceed from love and charity.</note>Take heed to yourselves: If thy brother trespass against thee, rebuke him; and if he repent, forgive him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.4'>And though he sinne against thee seuen times in a day, and seuen times in a day turne againe to thee, saying, It repenteth mee, thou shalt forgiue him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.5'>
          <note>God will never be utterly lacking to the godly (although he may not be as thorough with them as they wish) even in those difficulties which cannot be overcome by man's reason.</note>And the apostles said unto the Lord, Increase our faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.6'>And the Lord said, If ye had faith as <note>If you had no more faith, but the quantity of the grain of mustard seed.</note> a grain of mustard seed, ye might say unto this sycamine tree, Be thou plucked up by the root, and be thou planted in the sea; and it should obey you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.7'>
          <note>Seeing that God may rightfully claim for himself both us and all that is ours, he cannot be indebted to us for anything, although we labour mightily until we die.</note>But which of you, having a servant plowing or feeding cattle, will say unto him by and by, when he is come from the field, Go and sit down to meat?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.8'>And woulde not rather say to him, Dresse wherewith I may suppe, and girde thy selfe, and serue mee, till I haue eaten and drunken, and afterward eate thou, and drinke thou?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.9'>Doeth he thanke that seruant, because hee did that which was commaunded vnto him? I trowe not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.10'>
          <note>No matter how perfectly we may keep the law, it deserves no reward.</note>So likewise ye, when ye shall have done all those things which are commanded you, say, We are unprofitable servants: we have done that which was our duty to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.11'>
          <note>Christ does good even to those who will be unthankful, but the benefits of God to salvation only profit those who are thankful.</note>And it came to pass, as he went to Jerusalem, that he passed through the midst of Samaria and Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.12'>And as hee entred into a certaine towne, there met him tenne men that were lepers, which stoode a farre off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.13'>And they lift vp their voyces and saide, Iesus, Master, haue mercie on vs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.14'>And when he saw them, he said vnto them, Goe, shewe your selues vnto the Priestes; it came to passe, that as they went, they were clensed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.15'>Then one of them, when hee sawe that hee, was healed, turned backe, and with a loude voyce praised God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.16'>And fell downe on his face at his feete, and gaue him thankes: and he was a Samaritan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.17'>And Iesus answered, and said, Are there not tenne clensed? but where are the nine?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.18'>There is none founde that returned to giue God praise, saue this stranger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.19'>And he saide vnto him, Arise, goe thy way, thy faith hath saued thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.20'>
          <note>The kingdom of God is not discerned by many although it is most present before their eyes, because they foolishly persuade themselves that it is to come with outward pomp.</note>And when he was demanded of the Pharisees, when the kingdom of God should come, he answered them and said, The kingdom of God cometh not with <note>With any outward pomp and show of majesty to be known by: for there were still many plain and evident tokens by which men might have understood that Christ was the Messiah, whose kingdom had been so long looked for: but he speaks in this place of those signs which the Pharisees dreamed of, who looked for an earthly Messianic kingdom.</note> observation:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.21'>Neither shall they say, Lo here! or, lo there! for, behold, the kingdom of God is <note>You look around for the Messiah as though he were absent, but he is amongst you in the midst of you.</note> within you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.22'>
          <note>We often neglect those things when they are present which we afterward desire when they are gone, but in vain.</note>And he said unto the disciples, The days will come, when ye shall desire to see <note>The time will come when you will seek for the Son of Man with great sorrow of heart, and will not find him.</note> one of the days of the Son of man, and ye shall not see [it].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.23'>
          <note>Christ forewarns us that false Christs will come, and that his glory will suddenly be spread far and wide through the world after the shame of the cross is put out and extinguished.</note>And they shall say to you, See here; or, see there: go not after [them], nor follow [them].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.24'>For as the lightening that lighteneth out of the one part vnder heauen, shineth vnto the other part vnder heauen, so shall the Sonne of man be in his day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.25'>But first must he suffer many things, and be reprooued of this generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.26'>
          <note>The world will be taken by surprise with the sudden judgment of God, and therefore the faithful ought to continually watch.</note>And as it was in the days of Noe, so shall it be also in the days of the Son of man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.27'>They ate, they dranke, they married wiues, and gaue in marriage vnto the day that Noe went into the Arke: and the flood came, and destroyed them all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.28'>Likewise also, as it was in the dayes of Lot: they ate, they dranke, they bought, they solde, they planted, they built.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.29'>But in the day that Lot went out of Sodom, it rained fire and brimstone from heauen, and destroyed them all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.30'>After these ensamples shall it be in the day when the Sonne of man is reueiled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.31'>
          <note>We must pay careful attention that neither distrust nor the enticements of this world, nor any consideration of friendship hinder us in the least way.</note>In that day, he which shall be upon the housetop, and his stuff in the house, let him not come down to take it away: and he that is in the field, let him likewise not return back.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.32'>Remember Lots wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.33'>Whosoever shall seek to save his life shall lose it; and whosoever shall lose his life shall <note>That is, will save it, as Matthew expounds it: for the life that is spoken of here is everlasting salvation.</note> preserve it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.34'>I tell you, in that night there shall be two in one bed: the one shalbe receiued, and the other shalbe left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.35'>Two women shalbe grinding together: the one shalbe taken, and the other shalbe left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.36'>Two shalbe in the fielde: one shalbe receiued, and another shalbe left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.17.37'>
          <note>The only way to continue is to cleave to Christ.</note>And they answered and said unto him, Where, Lord? And he said unto them, Wheresoever the body [is], thither will the eagles be gathered together.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.18'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.1'>And <note>God will have us to continue in prayer, not to weary us, but to exercise us; therefore we must fight against impatience so that a long delay does not cause us to quit our praying.</note> he spake a parable unto them [to this end], that men ought always to pray, and not to <note>Yield to afflictions and adversities as those do who have lost heart.</note> faint;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.2'>
          <note>He does not compare things that are of equal stature, but the less with the greater: If a man receives what is rightfully his at the hands of a most unrighteous judge, much more will the prayers of the godly prevail before God.</note>Saying, There was in a city a judge, which feared not God, neither regarded man:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.3'>And there was a widowe in that citie, which came vnto him, saying, Doe mee iustice against mine aduersarie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.4'>And hee would not of a long time: but afterward he said with himselfe, Though I feare not God, nor reuerence man,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.5'>Yet because this widow troubleth me, I will avenge her, lest by her continual coming she <note>Literally, «beat me down with her blows», and it is a metaphor taken of wrestlers who beat their adversaries with their fists or clubs: in the same way those that are persistent beat the judge's ears with their crying out, even as it were with blows.</note> weary me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.6'>And the Lord said, Heare what the vnrighteous iudge saith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.7'>And shall not God avenge his own elect, which cry day and night unto him, though <note>Though he seems slow in avenging the harm done to his own.</note> he bear long with them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.8'>I tell you he will auenge them quickly: but when the Sonne of man commeth, shall he finde faith on the earth?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.9'>
          <note>Two things especially make our prayers void and of no effect: confidence of our own righteousness, and our contempt of others; but a humble heart is contrary to both of these.</note>And he spake this parable unto certain which trusted in themselves that they were righteous, and despised others:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.10'>Two men went vp into the Temple to pray: the one a Pharise, and the other a Publican.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.11'>
          <note>Although we confess that whatever we have, we have it from God, yet we are despised by God as proud and arrogant if we put even the least trust in our own works before God.</note>The Pharisee stood and prayed thus with himself, God, I thank thee, that I am not as other men [are], extortioners, unjust, adulterers, or even as this publican.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.12'>I fast twise in the weeke: I giue tithe of all that euer I possesse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.13'>And the publican, standing <note>Far from the Pharisee in a lower place.</note> afar off, would not lift up so much as [his] eyes unto heaven, but smote upon his breast, saying, God be merciful to me a sinner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.14'>I tell you, this man departed to his house iustified, rather then the other: for euery man that exalteth himselfe, shall be brought lowe, and he that humbleth himselfe, shalbe exalted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.15'>
          <note>The children were tender and young in that they were brought, which appears more evidently in that they were infants. (Ed.)</note>And they brought unto him also infants, that he would touch them: <note>To judge or think of Christ after the reason of the flesh is the cause of infinite corruptions.</note> but when [his] disciples saw [it], they rebuked them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.16'>
          <note>The elect children of the faithful are included in the free covenant of God. (Ed.)</note>But Jesus <note>Those that carried the children, whom the disciples drove away.</note> called them [unto him], and said, Suffer little children to come unto me, and forbid them not: for of such is the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.17'>
          <note>Childlike innocence is an ornament of Christians.</note>Verily I say unto you, Whosoever shall not receive the kingdom of God as a little child shall in no wise enter therein.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.18'>Then a certaine ruler asked him, saying, Good Master, what ought I to doe, to inherite eternall life?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.19'>And Iesus said vnto him, Why callest thou me good? none is good, saue one, euen God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.20'>Thou knowest the comandements, Thou shalt not commit adulterie: Thou shalt not kill: Thou shalt not steale: Thou shalt not beare false witnes: Honour thy father and thy mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.21'>
          <note>The enticement of riches carries many away from the right way.</note>And he said, All these have I kept from my youth up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.22'>Nowe when Iesus heard that, he saide vnto him, Yet lackest thou one thing. Sell all that euer thou hast, and distribute vnto the poore, and thou shalt haue treasure in heauen, and come followe mee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.23'>But when he heard those things, he was very heauie: for he was marueilous riche.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.24'>
          <note>To be both rich and godly is a singular gift of God.</note>And when Jesus saw that he was very sorrowful, he said, How hardly shall they that have riches enter into the kingdom of God!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.25'>Surely it is easier for a camel to go through a needles eye, then for a riche man to enter into the kingdome of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.26'>Then said they that heard it, And who then can be saued?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.27'>And he said, The things which are vnpossible with men, are possible with God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.28'>Then Peter said, Loe, we haue left all, and haue followed thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.29'>
          <note>They become the richest of all who do not refuse to be poor for Christ's sake.</note>And he said unto them, Verily I say unto you, There is no man that hath left house, or parents, or brethren, or wife, or children, for the kingdom of God's sake,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.30'>Which shall not receiue much more in this world, and in the world to come life euerlasting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.31'>
          <note>As sure and certain as persecution is, so sure is the glory which remains for the conquerors.</note>Then he took [unto him] the twelve, and said unto them, Behold, we go up to Jerusalem, and all things that are written by the prophets concerning the Son of man shall be accomplished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.32'>For he shal be deliuered vnto the Gentiles, and shalbe mocked, and shalbe spitefully entreated, and shalbe spitted on.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.33'>And when they haue scourged him, they will put him to death: but the thirde day hee shall rise againe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.34'>And they understood <note>By this we see how ignorant the disciples were.</note> none of these things: and this saying was hid from them, neither knew they the things which were spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.35'>
          <note>Christ shows by a visible miracle that he is the light of the world.</note>And it came to pass, that as he was come nigh unto Jericho, a certain blind man sat by the way side begging:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.36'>And when he heard the people passe by, he asked what it meant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.37'>And they saide vnto him, that Iesus of Nazareth passed by.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.38'>Then hee cried, saying, Iesus the Sonne of Dauid, haue mercie on me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.39'>
          <note>The more snares and hindrances that Satan lays in our way, even by those who profess Christ's name, so much the more ought we to go forward.</note>And they which went before rebuked him, that he should hold his peace: but he cried so much the more, [Thou] Son of David, have mercy on me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.40'>And Iesus stoode stil, and commanded him to be brought vnto him; when he was come neere, he asked him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.41'>Saying, What wilt thou that I doe vnto thee? And he said, Lord, that I may receiue my sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.42'>And Iesus said vnto him, Receiue thy sight: thy faith hath saued thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.18.43'>Then immediatly he receiued his sight, and followed him, praysing God: and all the people, when they sawe this, gaue praise to God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.19'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.1'>And <note>Christ especially guides by his grace those who seem to be furthest from it.</note> [Jesus] entered and passed through Jericho.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.2'>And, behold, [there was] a man named Zacchaeus, which was the <note>The overseer and head of the publicans who were there together: for the publicans were divided into companies, as we may gather from many places in the orations of Cicero.</note> chief among the publicans, and he was rich.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.3'>And he sought to see Iesus, who hee should be, and coulde not for the preasse, because he was of a lowe stature.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.4'>Wherefore he ranne before, and climed vp into a wilde figge tree, that he might see him: for he should come that way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.5'>And when Iesus came to the place, he looked vp, and saw him, and said vnto him, Zaccheus, come downe at once: for to day I must abide at thine house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.6'>Then he came downe hastily, and receiued him ioyfully.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.7'>
          <note>The world forsakes the grace of God, and yet is unwilling that it should be bestowed upon others.</note>And when they saw [it], they all murmured, saying, That he was gone to be guest with a man that is a sinner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.8'>
          <note>The example of true repentance is known by the effect.</note>And Zacchaeus stood, and said unto the Lord; Behold, Lord, the half of my goods I give to the poor; and if I have taken any thing from any man by <note>By falsely accusing any man: and this agrees most fitly to the master of the tax gatherers: for commonly they have this practice among them when they rob and spoil the commonwealth, that they claim to be concerned for nothing else except the profit of the commonwealth, and under this pretence they are thieves, and to such an extent that if men reprove them and try to redress their robbery and thievery, they cry out that the commonwealth is hindered.</note> false accusation, I restore [him] fourfold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.9'>And Jesus said unto him, This day is salvation come to this house, forsomuch as he also is a <note>Beloved of God, one that walks in the steps of Abraham's faith: and we gather that salvation came to that house because they received the blessing as Abraham had. (Ed.)</note> son of Abraham.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.10'>For the Sonne of man is come to seeke, and to saue that which was lost.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.11'>
          <note>We must patiently wait for the judgment of God which will be revealed in his time.</note>And as they heard these things, he added and spake a parable, because he was nigh to Jerusalem, and because they thought that the kingdom of God should immediately appear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.12'>He saide therefore, A certaine noble man went into a farre countrey, to receiue for himselfe a kingdome, and so to come againe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.13'>
          <note>There are three sorts of men in the Church: the one sort fall from Christ whom they do not see; the other, according to their God given position, bestow the gifts which they have received from God to his glory, with great pains and diligence; the third live idly and do no good. As for the first, the Lord when he comes will justly punish them in his time; the second he will bless according to the pains which they have taken; and as for the slothful and idle persons, he will punish them like the first.</note>And he called his ten servants, and delivered them ten pounds, and said unto them, Occupy till I come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.14'>Nowe his citizens hated him, and sent an ambassage after him, saying, We will not haue this man to reigne ouer vs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.15'>And it came to passe, when hee was come againe, and had receiued his kingdome, that he commanded the seruants to be called to him, to whome he gaue his money, that he might knowe what euery man had gained.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.16'>Then came the first, saying, Lord, <note>This was a piece of money which the Greeks used, and was worth about one hundred pence, which is about ten crowns.</note> thy pound hath gained ten pounds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.17'>And he sayd vnto him, Well, good seruant: because thou hast bene faithfull in a very litle thing, take thou authoritie ouer ten cities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.18'>And the second came, saying, Lord, thy piece hath encreased fiue pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.19'>And to the same he sayd, Be thou also ruler ouer fiue cities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.20'>
          <note>Against those who idly spend their life in deliberating and in contemplation.</note>And another came, saying, Lord, behold, [here is] thy pound, which I have kept laid up in a napkin:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.21'>For I feared thee, because thou art a straight man: thou takest vp, that thou layedst not downe, and reapest that thou diddest not sowe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.22'>Then he sayde vnto him, Of thine owne mouth will I iudge thee, O euill seruant. Thou knewest that I am a straight man, taking vp that I layd not downe, &amp; reaping that I did not sowe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.23'>Wherefore then gavest not thou my money into the <note>To the bankers and money changers. Usury or loaning money at interest is strictly forbidden by the Bible, (Exo_22:25-27; Deu_23:19-20). Even a rate as low as one per cent interest was disallowed, (Neh_5:11). This servant had already told two lies. First he said the master was an austere or harsh man. This is a lie for the Lord is merciful and gracious. Next he called his master a thief because he reaped where he did not sow. Finally the master said to him that why did you not add insult to injury and loan the money out at interest so you could call your master a «usurer» too! If the servant had done this, his master would have been responsible for his servant's actions and guilty of usury. (Ed.)</note> bank, that at my coming I might have required mine own with usury?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.24'>And he sayd to them that stoode by, Take from him that piece, and giue it him that hath ten pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.25'>(And they sayd vnto him, Lord, hee hath ten pieces.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.26'>For I say vnto you, that vnto all them that haue, it shalbe giuen: and from him that hath not, euen that he hath, shalbe taken from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.27'>Moreouer, those mine enemies, which would not that I should reigne ouer them, bring hither, and slay them before me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.28'>And when he had thus spoken, <note>The disciples were staggered and stopped by what Christ said, but Christ goes on boldly even though death was before his eyes.</note> he went before, ascending up to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.29'>
          <note>Christ shows in his own person that his kingdom is not of this world.</note>And it came to pass, when he was come nigh to Bethphage and Bethany, at the mount called [the mount] of Olives, he sent two of his disciples,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.30'>Saying, Goe ye to the towne which is before you, wherein, assoone as ye are come, ye shall finde a colte tied, whereon neuer man sate: loose him, and bring him hither.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.31'>And if any man aske you, why ye loose him, thus shall ye say vnto him, Because the Lord hath neede of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.32'>So they that were sent, went their way, and found it as he had sayd vnto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.33'>And as they were loosing the colte, the owners thereof sayd vnto them, Why loose ye the colte?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.34'>And they sayd, The Lorde hath neede of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.35'>So they brought him to Iesus, and they cast their garments on the colte, and set Iesus thereon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.36'>And as he went, they spred their clothes in the way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.37'>And when he was nowe come neere to the going downe of the mount of Oliues, the whole multitude of the disciples began to reioyce, and to prayse God with a loude voyce, for all the great workes that they had seene,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.38'>Saying, Blessed be the King that commeth in the Name of the Lord: peace in heauen, and glory in the highest places.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.39'>
          <note>When those linger who ought to preach and set forth the kingdom of God the most, he will extraordinarily raise up others in spite of them.</note>And some of the Pharisees from among the multitude said unto him, Master, rebuke thy disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.40'>But he answered, and sayd vnto them, I tell you, that if these should holde their peace, the stones would crie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.41'>
          <note>Christ is not delighted with destruction, no not even of the wicked.</note>And when he was come near, he beheld the city, and wept over it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.42'>
          <note>Christ stops his speech, which partly shows how moved he was with compassion over the destruction of the city that was surely to come: and partly to reprove them for their treachery and stubbornness against him, such as has not been heard of before.</note>Saying, <note>You at the very least, O Jerusalem, to whom the message was properly sent.</note> If thou hadst known, even thou, <note>If after slaying so many prophets, and so often refusing me, the Lord of the prophets, if only now, especially in my last coming to you, you had any concern for yourself.</note> at least in this <note>The good and prosperous time is called the day of this city.</note> thy day, the things [which belong] unto thy <note>That is, those things in which your happiness stands.</note> peace! but now they are hid from thine eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.43'>For the dayes shall come vpon thee, that thine enemies shall cast a trench about thee, and compasse thee round, and keepe thee in on euery side,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.44'>And shall lay thee even with the ground, and thy children within thee; and they shall not leave in thee one stone upon another; because thou knewest not <note>That is, this very instant in which God visited you.</note> the time of thy visitation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.45'>
          <note>Christ shows after his entry into Jerusalem by a visible sign that it is his duty, given and admonished unto him by his Father, to purge the temple.</note>And he went into the temple, and began to cast out them that sold therein, and them that bought;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.46'>Saying vnto them, It is written, Mine house is the house of prayer, but ye haue made it a denne of theeues.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.47'>And he taught dayly in the Temple; the hie Priests and the Scribes, and the chiefe of the people sought to destroy him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.19.48'>But they could not finde what they might doe to him: for all the people hanged vpon him when they heard him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.20'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.1'>And <note>The Pharisees, being overcome with the truth of Christ's doctrine, propose a question about his outward calling, and are overcome by the witness of their own conscience.</note> it came to pass, [that] on one of those days, as he taught the people in the temple, and preached the gospel, the chief priests and the scribes came upon [him] with the elders,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.2'>And spake vnto him, saying, Tell vs by what authoritie thou doest these things, or who is hee that hath giuen thee this authoritie?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.3'>And he answered, and sayde vnto them, I also will aske you one thing: tell me therefore:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.4'>The baptisme of Iohn, was it from heauen, or of men?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.5'>And they reasoned within themselues, saying, If we shall say, From heauen, he will say, Why then beleeued ye him not?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.6'>But if we shall say, Of men, all the people will stone vs: for they be perswaded that Iohn was a Prophet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.7'>Therefore they answered, that they could not tell whence it was.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.8'>Then Iesus sayd vnto them, Neither tell I you, by what authoritie I doe these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.9'>
          <note>It is nothing new for those who are knowledgable of the very sanctuary of God's holy place to be the greatest enemies of Christ, but in due time they will be punished.</note>Then began he to speak to the people this parable; A certain man planted a vineyard, and let it forth to husbandmen, and went into a far country for a long time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.10'>And at the time conuenient he sent a seruant to the husbandmen, that they should giue him of the fruite of the vineyard: but the husbandmen did beate him, &amp; sent him away emptie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.11'>Againe he sent yet another seruant: and they did beate him, and foule entreated him, and sent him away emptie.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.12'>Moreouer he sent the third, and him they wounded, and cast out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.13'>Then sayd the Lord of the vineyard, What shall I doe? I will send my beloued sonne: it may be that they will doe reuerence, when they see him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.14'>But when the husbandmen sawe him, they reasoned with themselues, saying, This is the heire: come, let vs kill him, that the inheritance may be ours.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.15'>So they cast him out of the vineyarde, and killed him. What shall the Lord of the vineyarde therefore doe vnto them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.16'>He will come and destroy these husbandmen, and wil giue out his vineyard to others. But when they heard it, they sayd, God forbid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.17'>And he beheld them, &amp; said, What meaneth this then that is written, The stone that the builders refused, that is made the head of the corner?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.18'>Whosoeuer shall fall vpon that stone, shall be broken: and on whomsoeuer it shall fall, it will grinde him to pouder.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.19'>Then the hie Priests, and the Scribes the same houre went about to lay hands on him: (but they feared the people) for they perceiued that he had spoken this parable against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.20'>
          <note>The last refuge the false prophets have to destroy the true prophets is to charge them with rebellion and treason against the state.</note>And they <note>An appropriate time to take him in.</note> watched [him], and sent forth <note>Whom they had hired deceitfully.</note> spies, which should feign themselves just men, <note>That they might latch on to something he said, and by this forge some false accusation against him.</note> that they might take hold of his words, that so they might deliver him unto the power and <note>Put him to death.</note> authority of the governor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.21'>And they asked him, saying, Master, we know that thou sayest and teachest rightly, neither acceptest thou the <note>You are not moved by favour of any man: and by «person» he means outward circumstances, for if a man judges according to these, there will be those who are truly alike whom he will judge to be different.</note> person [of any], but teachest the way of God truly:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.22'>Is it lawfull for vs to giue Cesar tribute or no?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.23'>But he perceived their <note>Craftiness is a certain diligence and subtle knowledge to do evil, which is achieved by much use and great practise in matters.</note> craftiness, and said unto them, Why tempt ye me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.24'>Shew me a penie. Whose image and superscription hath it? They answered, and sayd, Cesars.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.25'>Then he sayd vnto them, Giue then vnto Cesar the things which are Cesars, and to God those which are Gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.26'>And they could not reproue his saying before the people: but they marueiled at his answere, and helde their peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.27'>
          <note>The resurrection of the flesh is affirmed against the Sadducees.</note>Then came to [him] certain of the Sadducees, which deny that there is any resurrection; and they asked him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.28'>Saying, Master, Moses wrote vnto vs, If any mans brother die hauing a wife, and hee die without children, that his brother should take his wife, and raise vp seede vnto his brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.29'>Now there were seuen brethren, &amp; the first tooke a wife, and he dyed without children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.30'>And the second tooke the wife, and he dyed childelesse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.31'>Then the third tooke her: and so likewise the seuen dyed, and left no children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.32'>And last of all the woman dyed also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.33'>Therefore at the resurrection, whose wife of them shall she be? For seuen had her to wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.34'>And Jesus answering said unto them, The <note>«The children of this world» refers here to those who live in this world, and not those that are wholly given to the world (and therefore contrary to the children of light), as above in (Luk_16:8).</note> children of this world marry, and are given in marriage:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.35'>But they which shalbe counted worthy to enioy that world, and the resurrection from the dead, neither marry wiues, neither are married.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.36'>Neither can they die any more: for they are equal unto the angels; and are the children of God, being the <note>That is, men who partake in the resurrection: for as we truly say that they will indeed live who will enjoy everlasting bliss, so do those indeed rise who rise to life; though if this word «resurrection» is taken generally, it refers also to the wicked, who will rise to condemnation, which is not properly life, but death.</note> children of the resurrection.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.37'>And that the dead shall rise againe, euen Moses shewed it besides the bush, when he said, The Lord is the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Iacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.38'>For he is not a God of the dead, but of the living: for all <note>That is, before him: a saying to take note of, for the godly do not die, though they die here on earth.</note> live unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.39'>Then certaine of the Scribes answered, and sayd, Master, thou hast well sayd.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.40'>And after that, durst they not aske him any thing at all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.41'>
          <note>Even though Christ is the son of David according to the flesh he is also his Lord (because he is the everlasting Son of God) according to the spirit.</note>And he said unto them, How say they that Christ is David's son?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.42'>And Dauid himselfe sayth in the booke of the Psalmes, The Lord sayd vnto my Lorde, Sit at my right hand,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.43'>Till I shall make thine enemies thy footestoole.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.44'>Seeing Dauid called him Lord, howe is he then his sonne?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.45'>Then in the audience of all the people he sayd vnto his disciples,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.46'>
          <note>We must avoid the example of the glory-seeking and covetous pastors.</note>Beware of the scribes, which desire to walk in long robes, and love greetings in the markets, and the highest seats in the synagogues, and the chief rooms at feasts;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.20.47'>Which devour widows' <note>By the figure of speech metonymy, «houses» is understood to mean the goods and substance.</note> houses, and for a shew make long prayers: the same shall receive greater damnation.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.21'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.1'>And <note>According to the judgment of God, the poor may even exceed the rich in generosity and liberality.</note> he looked up, and saw the rich men casting their gifts into the treasury.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.2'>And he sawe also a certaine poore widowe which cast in thither two mites:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.3'>And he sayd, Of a trueth I say vnto you, that this poore widowe hath cast in more then they all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.4'>For they all haue of their superfluitie cast into the offerings of God: but she of her penurie hath cast in all the liuing that she had.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.5'>
          <note>The destruction of the temple is foretold so that the true spiritual building may be built, whose chief builders must and ought to be cautious.</note>And as some spake of the temple, how it was adorned with goodly stones and <note>These were things that were hung up on walls and pillars.</note> gifts, he said,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.6'>Are these ye things that ye looke vpon? the dayes will come wherein a stone shall not be left vpon a stone, that shall not be throwen downe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.7'>Then they asked him, saying, Master, but when shall these things be? and what signe shall there be when these things shall come to passe?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.8'>And he said, Take heed that ye be not deceived: for many shall come <note>Using my name.</note> in my name, saying, I am [Christ]; and the time draweth near: go ye not therefore after them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.9'>
          <note>The true temple of God is built up even in the midst of incredible tumults and most severe miseries, and this through invincible patience, so that the end result can be nothing else but most happy.</note>But when ye shall hear of wars and commotions, be not terrified: for these things must first come to pass; but the end [is] not by and by.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.10'>Then said hee vnto them, Nation shall rise against nation, and kingdome against kingdome,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.11'>And great earthquakes shall be in diuers places, and hunger, and pestilence, and fearefull things, &amp; great signes shall there be from heauen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.12'>But before all these, they shal lay their hands on you, and persecute you, deliuering you vp to the assemblies, and into prisons, and bring you before Kings and rulers for my Names sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.13'>And it shall turn to you for <note>This will be the result of your troubles and afflictions: they will be witnesses both before God and man of the treacherous and cruel dealing of your enemies, as well as of your steadfastness: A noble saying, that the afflictions of the godly and holy men pertain to the witness of the truth.</note> a testimony.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.14'>Lay it vp therefore in your heartes, that ye cast not before hand, what ye shall answere.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.15'>For I will giue you a mouth and wisdome, where against all your aduersaries shall not be able to speake, nor resist.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.16'>Yea, ye shalbe betrayed also of your parents, and of your brethren, and kinsmen, and friendes, and some of you shall they put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.17'>And ye shall bee hated of all men for my Names sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.18'>Yet there shall not one heare of your heads perish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.19'>In your patience <note>Though you are surrounded on all sides with many miseries, yet nonetheless be valiant and courageous, and bear out these things bravely.</note> possess ye your souls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.20'>
          <note>The final destruction of the whole city is foretold.</note>And when ye shall see Jerusalem compassed with armies, then know that the desolation thereof is nigh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.21'>Then let them which are in Iudea, flee to the mountaines: and let them which are in the middes thereof, depart out: and let not them that are in the countrey, enter therein.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.22'>For these be the dayes of vengeance, to fulfill all things that are written.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.23'>But woe unto them that are with child, and to them that give suck, in those days! for there shall be great distress in the land, and <note>By «wrath» are meant those things which God sends when he is displeased.</note> wrath upon this people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.24'>And they shall fall by the <note>Literally, «mouth», for the Hebrews call the edge of a sword the mouth because the edge of the sword bites.</note> edge of the sword, and shall be led away captive into all nations: and Jerusalem shall be trodden down of the Gentiles, until the times of the Gentiles be fulfilled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.25'>
          <note>When the times have expired which are appointed for the salvation of the Gentiles and the punishment of the Jews: And so he changes topics from the destruction of Jerusalem to the history of the latter judgment.</note>And there shall be signs in the sun, and in the moon, and in the stars; and upon the earth distress of nations, with perplexity; the sea and the waves roaring;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.26'>
          <note>After various severe trials the Lord will at last plainly appear to deliver his Church.</note>Men's hearts failing them for fear, and for looking after those things which are coming on the earth: for the powers of heaven shall be shaken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.27'>And then shall they see the Sonne of man come in a cloude, with power and great glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.28'>And when these things beginne to come to passe, then looke vp, and lift vp your heades: for your redemption draweth neere.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.29'>
          <note>We must be sober and watchful both day and night for the Lord's coming, so that we are not taken unexpectedly.</note>And he spake to them a parable; Behold the fig tree, and all the trees;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.30'>When they nowe shoote foorth, ye seeing them, knowe of your owne selues, that sommer is then neere.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.31'>So likewise yee, when yee see these thinges come to passe, knowe ye that the kingdome of God is neere.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.32'>Verely I say vnto you, This age shall not passe, till all these things be done:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.33'>Heauen and earth shall passe away, but my wordes shall not passe away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.34'>Take heede to your selues, lest at any time your hearts be oppressed with surfeting and drunkennesse, and cares of this life, and least that day come on you at vnwares.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.35'>For as a snare shall it come <note>On all men wherever they may be.</note> on all them that dwell on the face of the whole earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.36'>Watch ye therefore, and pray always, that ye may be accounted worthy to escape all these things that shall come to pass, and to <note>You will appear before him in a condition such that you will abide the presence and sentence of the Judge without fear.</note> stand before the Son of man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.37'>Nowe in the day time hee taught in the Temple, and at night hee went out, and abode in the mount that is called the mount of Oliues.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.21.38'>And all the people came in the morning to him, to heare him in the Temple.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.22'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.1'>Now the <note>Christ is taken upon the day of the Passover rather by the providence of his Father, than by the will of men.</note> feast of unleavened bread drew nigh, which is called the Passover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.2'>And the hie Priests and Scribes sought how they might kill him: for they feared the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.3'>
          <note>God by his wonderful providence causes him to be the minister of our salvation who was the author of our destruction.</note>Then entered Satan into Judas surnamed Iscariot, being of the number of the twelve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.4'>And he went his way, and communed with the chief priests and <note>Those that had the charge of keeping the temple, who were not from among the priests and bishops, as is shown below in (Luk_22:52).</note> captains, how he might betray him unto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.5'>So they were glad, and agreed to giue him money.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.6'>And he promised, and sought opportunity to betray him unto them in the <note>Without tumult, doing it without the knowledge of the people who used to follow him: and therefore they indeed waited patiently until they knew he was alone in the garden.</note> absence of the multitude.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.7'>
          <note>Christ teaches his disciples by an obvious miracle that although he is going to be crucified, yet nothing is hidden from him, and therefore that he is going willingly to death.</note>Then came the day of unleavened bread, when the passover <note>By the order appointed by the law.</note> must be killed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.8'>And he sent Peter and John, saying, Go and prepare us the <note>The lamb which was the symbol of the passover: And this is said using the figure of speech metonymy, which is often used when talking about the sacraments.</note> passover, that we may eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.9'>And they saide to him, Where wilt thou, that we prepare it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.10'>Then he said vnto them, Beholde, when ye be entred into the citie, there shall a man meete you, bearing a pitcher of water: folowe him into the house that he entreth in,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.11'>And say vnto the good man of the house, The Master saith vnto thee, Where is the lodging where I shall eate my Passeouer with my disciples?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.12'>Then he shall shewe you a great hie chamber trimmed: there make it ready.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.13'>So they went, and found as he had said vnto them, and made readie the Passeouer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.14'>
          <note>Christ, having ended the passover according to the order of the law, forewarns them that this will be his last banquet with them in terms of this earthly life.</note>And when the <note>The evening and twilight, at which time this supper was to be kept.</note> hour was come, he sat down, and the twelve apostles with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.15'>And he said unto them, With desire I have desired to eat this passover with you before I <note>I am put to death.</note> suffer:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.16'>For I say vnto you, Hencefoorth I will not eate of it any more, vntill it bee fulfilled in the kingdome of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.17'>And hee tooke the cup, and gaue thankes, and said, Take this, and deuide it among you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.18'>For I say vnto you, I will not drinke of the fruite of the vine, vntill the kingdome of God be come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.19'>
          <note>Christ establishes his new covenant and his communication with us by new symbols.</note>And he took bread, and gave thanks, and brake [it], and gave unto them, saying, This is my body which is given for you: this do in remembrance of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.20'>Likewise also the cup after supper, saying, This <note>Here is a double use of metonymy: for first, the vessel is taken for that which is contained in the vessel, as the cup is spoken of for the wine which is within the cup. Second, the wine is called the covenant or testament, whereas in reality it is but the sign of the testament, or rather of the blood of Christ by which the testament was made: neither is it a vain sign, although it is not the same as the thing that it represents.</note> cup [is] <note>This word «the» shows the excellency of the testament, and corresponds to (Jer_31:31) where the new testament is promised.</note> the new testament in my blood, which is shed for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.21'>
          <note>Christ shows again that he goes willingly to die, although he is not ignorant of Judas' treason.</note>But, behold, the <note>That is, his practice; the Hebrews used to speak in this way, as in (2Sa_14:19): «Is not the hand of Joab with thee in all this?»</note> hand of him that betrayeth me [is] with me on the table.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.22'>
          <note>Although the decree of God's providence necessarily comes to pass, yet it does not excuse the fault of those who bring it to pass.</note>And truly the Son of man goeth, as it was determined: but woe unto that man by whom he is betrayed!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.23'>Then they began to enquire among themselues which of them it should be, that should do that.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.24'>
          <note>The pastors are not called to rule but to serve.</note>And there was also a strife among them, which of them should be accounted the greatest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.25'>And he said unto them, The kings of the Gentiles exercise lordship over them; and they that exercise authority upon them are called <note>Have great titles, for so it was the custom to honour princes with some great titles.</note> benefactors.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.26'>But yee shall not be so: but let the greatest among you be as the least: and the chiefest as he that serueth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.27'>For who is greater, he that sitteth at table, or he that serueth? Is not he that sitteth at table? And I am among you as he that serueth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.28'>
          <note>Those who are partakers of the affliction of Christ will also be partakers of his kingdom.</note>Ye are they which have continued with me in my temptations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.29'>Therefore I appoint vnto you a kingdome, as my Father hath appointed vnto me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.30'>That ye may eate, and drinke at my table in my kingdome, and sit on seates, and iudge the twelue tribes of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.31'>
          <note>We must always think about the ambush that Satan lays for us.</note>And the Lord said, Simon, Simon, behold, Satan hath desired [to have] you, that he may <note>To toss you and scatter you, and also to cast you out.</note> sift [you] as wheat:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.32'>
          <note>It is through the prayers of Christ that the elect never utterly fall away from the faith: and because of this they should encourage one another on.</note>But I have prayed for thee, that thy faith fail not: and when thou art converted, strengthen thy brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.33'>
          <note>In setting before us the grievous example of Peter, Christ shows that faith differs much from a vain security.</note>And he said unto him, Lord, I am ready to go with thee, both into prison, and to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.34'>But he said, I tell thee, Peter, the cocke shall not crowe this day, before thou hast thrise denied that thou knewest me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.35'>And he saide vnto them, When I sent you without bagge, and scrip, and shooes, lacked ye any thing? And they said, Nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.36'>
          <note>He says all this using an allegory, as if he said, «O my friends and fellow soldiers, you have lived until now in relative peace: but now there is at hand a most severe battle to be fought, and you must therefore lay all other things aside and think about dressing yourselves in armour.» And what this armour is, is shown by his own example, when he prayed afterward in the garden and reproved Peter for striking with the sword.</note>Then said he unto them, But now, he that hath a purse, let him take [it], and likewise [his] scrip: and he that hath no sword, let him sell his garment, and buy one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.37'>For I say vnto you, That yet the same which is written, must be perfourmed in me, Euen with the wicked was he nombred: for doubtlesse those things which are written of me, haue an ende.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.38'>And they said, Lord, beholde, here are two swordes; he said vnto them, It is ynough.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.39'>And he came out, and went (as he was wont) to the mount of Oliues: and his disciples also followed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.40'>
          <note>Christ has made death acceptable unto us by overcoming for our sake all the horrors of death, which had the curse of God accompanying them.</note>And when he was at the place, he said unto them, Pray that ye enter not into temptation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.41'>
          <note>Prayers are a sure help against the most perilous assaults of our enemies.</note>And he was withdrawn from them about a stone's cast, and kneeled down, and prayed,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.42'>Saying, Father, if thou wilt, take away this cuppe from mee: neuerthelesse, not my will, but thine be done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.43'>And there appeared an Angell vnto him from heauen, comforting him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.44'>And being in an <note>This agony shows that Christ struggled hard and was in great distress: for Christ struggled hard not only with the fears of death as other men do (for in this regard many martyrs might seem more constant then Christ), but also with the fearful judgment of his angry Father, which is the most fearful thing in the world: and this was because he took the burden of all our sins upon himself.</note> agony he prayed more earnestly: and his sweat was as it were great <note>These do not only show that Christ was true man, but also other things which the godly have to consider of, in which the secret of the redemption of all mankind is contained in the Son of God when he debased himself to the state of a servant: such things as these no man can sufficiently declare.</note> drops of blood falling down to the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.45'>
          <note>Men are utterly sluggish, even in their greatest dangers.</note>And when he rose up from prayer, and was come to his disciples, he found them sleeping for sorrow,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.46'>And he said vnto them, Why sleepe ye? rise and pray, least ye enter into tentation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.47'>
          <note>Christ is willingly betrayed and taken so that by his obedience he might deliver us who were guilty of betraying God's glory.</note>And while he yet spake, behold a multitude, and he that was called Judas, one of the twelve, went before them, and drew near unto Jesus to kiss him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.48'>And Iesus saide vnto him, Iudas, betrayest thou the Sonne of man with a kisse?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.49'>
          <note>That zeal which carries us out of the bounds of our God-given position does not please Christ.</note>When they which were about him saw what would follow, they said unto him, Lord, shall we smite with the sword?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.50'>And one of them smote a seruant of the hie Priest, and strooke off his right eare.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.51'>Then Iesus answered, and said, Suffer them thus farre: and he touched his eare, &amp; healed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.52'>
          <note>Even the very fear of those who took Christ partly proves their evil conscience, and partly also that all these things were done by God's providence.</note>Then Jesus said unto the chief priests, and captains of the temple, and the elders, which were come to him, Be ye come out, as against a thief, with swords and staves?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.53'>When I was daily with you in the temple, ye stretched forth no hands against me: but this is your hour, and the <note>The power that was given to darkness to oppress the light for a time.</note> power of darkness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.54'>Then took they him, and led [him], and brought him into the high priest's house. <note>We have to behold in Peter an example both of the fragility of man's nature, and the singular goodness of God towards his elect.</note> And Peter followed afar off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.55'>And when they had kindled a fire in the middes of the hall, and were set downe together, Peter also sate downe among them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.56'>And a certaine mayde behelde him as hee sate by the fire, and hauing well looked on him, said, This man was also with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.57'>But he denied him, saying, Woman, I know him not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.58'>And after a little while, another man sawe him, and saide, Thou art also of them. But Peter said, Man, I am not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.59'>And about the space of an houre after, a certaine other affirmed, saying. Verely euen this man was with him: for he is also a Galilean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.60'>And Peter saide, Man, I knowe not what thou sayest; immediatly while hee yet spake, the cocke crewe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.61'>Then the Lorde turned backe, and looked vpon Peter: and Peter remembred the worde of the Lord, how he had said vnto him, Before the cocke crowe, thou shalt denie me thrise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.62'>And Peter went out, and wept bitterly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.63'>
          <note>Christ bore the shame that was due for our sins.</note>And the men that held Jesus mocked him, and smote [him].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.64'>And when they had blindfolded him, they smote him on the face, and asked him, saying, Prophecie who it is that smote thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.65'>And many other thinges blasphemously spake they against him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.66'>
          <note>Christ is wrongly condemned of blasphemy before the high priest's judgment seat in order that we might be acquitted before God from the blasphemy which we deserved.</note>And as soon as it was day, the elders of the people and the chief priests and the scribes came together, and led him into their council, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.67'>Saying, Art thou that Christ? tell vs; he said vnto them, If I tell you, ye wil not beleeue it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.68'>And if also I aske you, you will not answere me, nor let me goe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.69'>Hereafter shall the Sonne of man sit at the right hand of the power of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.70'>Then sayd they all, Art thou then ye Sonne of God? And he sayd to them, Ye say, that I am.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.22.71'>Then sayd they, What neede we any further witnes? for we our selues haue heard it of his owne mouth.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.23'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.1'>And <note>Christ, who is now ready to suffer for the rebellion which we raised in this world, is first of all pronounced guiltless, so that it might appear that he suffered not for his own sins (which were none) but for ours.</note> the whole multitude of them arose, and led him unto Pilate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.2'>And they began to accuse him, saying, We found this [fellow] <note>Corrupting the people, and leading them into errors.</note> perverting the nation, and forbidding to give tribute to Caesar, saying that he himself is Christ a King.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.3'>And Pilate asked him, saying, Art thou the King of the Iewes? And hee answered him, and sayd, Thou sayest it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.4'>Then sayd Pilate to the hie Priests, and to the people, I finde no fault in this man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.5'>But they were the more fierce, saying, He moueth the people, teaching throughout all Iudea, beginning at Galile, euen to this place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.6'>
          <note>Christ is a laughing stock to princes, but to their great pain.</note>When Pilate heard of Galilee, he asked whether the man were a Galilaean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.7'>And as soon as he knew that he belonged unto <note>This was Herod Antipas the Tetrarch, in the time of whose period of rule (which was almost twenty-two years long) John the Baptist preached and was put to death, and Jesus Christ also died and rose again, and the apostles began to preach, and various things were done at Jerusalem almost seven years after Christ's death. This Herod was sent into banishment to Lyons, about the second year of Gaius Caesar.</note> Herod's jurisdiction, he sent him to Herod, who himself also was at Jerusalem at that time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.8'>And when Herod sawe Iesus, hee was exceedingly glad: for he was desirous to see him of a long season, because he had heard many things of him, and trusted to haue seene some signe done by him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.9'>Then questioned hee with him of many things: but he answered him nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.10'>The hie Priests also &amp; Scribes stood forth, and accused him vehemently.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.11'>And Herod with his <note>Accompanied with his nobles and soldiers who followed him from Galilee.</note> men of war set him at nought, and mocked [him], and arrayed him in a gorgeous robe, and sent him again to Pilate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.12'>
          <note>The hatred of godliness binds the wicked together.</note>And the same day Pilate and Herod were made friends together: for before they were at enmity between themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.13'>
          <note>Christ is acquitted the second time, even by him of whom he is condemned, so that it might appear in what way he who is just, redeemed us who were unjust.</note>And Pilate, when he had called together the chief priests and the <note>Those whom the Jews called the sanhedrin.</note> rulers and the people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.14'>And sayd vnto them, Ye haue brought this man vnto me, as one that peruerted the people: and beholde, I haue examined him before you, and haue found no fault in this man, of those things whereof ye accuse him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.15'>No, nor yet Herod: for I sent you to him: and loe, nothing worthy of death is done of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.16'>
          <note>The wisdom of the flesh is to choose the lesser of two evils, but God curses such plans.</note>I will therefore chastise him, and release [him].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.17'>(For of necessitie hee must haue let one loose vnto them at the feast.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.18'>Then all ye multitude cried at once, saying, Away with him, and deliuer vnto vs Barabbas:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.19'>Which for a certaine insurrection made in the citie, and murther, was cast in prison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.20'>Then Pilate spake againe to them, willing to let Iesus loose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.21'>But they cried, saying, Crucifie, crucifie him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.22'>
          <note>Christ is acquitted the third time before he is condemned, so that it might appear that it was for our sins that were condemned in him.</note>And he said unto them the third time, Why, what evil hath he done? I have found no cause of death in him: I will therefore chastise him, and let [him] go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.23'>But they were instant with loude voyces, and required that he might be crucified: and the voyces of them and of the hie Priests preuailed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.24'>So Pilate gaue sentence, that it should be as they required.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.25'>And he let loose vnto them him that for insurrection and murther was cast into prison, whome they desired, and deliuered Iesus to doe with him what they would.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.26'>
          <note>An example of the outrageousness and disorder of the soldiers.</note>And as they led him away, they laid hold upon one Simon, a Cyrenian, coming out of the country, and on him they laid the cross, that he might bear [it] after Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.27'>
          <note>The triumph of the wicked has a most horrible end.</note>And there followed him a great company of people, and of women, which also bewailed and lamented him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.28'>But Iesus turned backe vnto them, &amp; said, Daughters of Hierusalem, weepe not for me, but weepe for your selues, and for your children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.29'>For behold, the dayes wil come, when men shall say, Blessed are the barren, and the wombes that neuer bare, and the pappes which neuer gaue sucke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.30'>Then shall they begin to say to the mountaines, Fall on vs: and to the hilles, Couer vs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.31'>For if they do these things in a <note>As if he said, «If they do this to me who is always fruitful and flourishing, and who lives forever by reason of my Godhead, what will they do to you who are unfruitful and void of all active righteousness?»</note> green tree, what shall be done in the dry?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.32'>And there were two others, which were euill doers, led with him to be slaine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.33'>
          <note>Christ became accursed for us upon the cross, suffering the punishment which the ones who would belong to God deserved.</note>And when they were come to the place, which is called Calvary, there they crucified him, and the malefactors, one on the right hand, and the other on the left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.34'>
          <note>Christ, in praying for his enemies, shows that he is both the Sacrifice and the Priest.</note>Then said Jesus, Father, forgive them; for they know not what they do. And they parted his raiment, and cast lots.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.35'>And the people stood beholding. And the rulers also with them derided [him], saying, He saved others; let him save himself, if he be Christ, the <note>Whom God loves more than all others.</note> chosen of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.36'>The souldiers also mocked him, and came and offered him vineger,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.37'>And said, If thou be the King of the Iewes, saue thy selfe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.38'>
          <note>Pilate is unknowingly made a preacher of the kingdom of Christ.</note>And a superscription also was written over him in letters of Greek, and Latin, and Hebrew, THIS IS THE KING OF THE JEWS.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.39'>
          <note>Therefore we must either take Matthew's account to be using the figure of speech synecdoche, or that both of them mocked Christ. But one of them who was eventually overcome with the great patience of God breaks forth in that confession worthy all memory.</note>And <note>Christ, in the midst of the humbling of himself upon the cross, indeed shows that he has both the power of life to save the believers and the power of death to avenge the rebellious.</note> one of the malefactors which were hanged railed on him, saying, If thou be Christ, save thyself and us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.40'>But the other answered, and rebuked him, saying, Fearest thou not God, seeing thou art in the same condemnation?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.41'>And we indeed justly; for we receive the due reward of our deeds: but this man hath done nothing <note>More than he ought.</note> amiss.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.42'>And he sayd vnto Iesus, Lorde, remember me, when thou commest into thy kingdome.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.43'>And Jesus said unto him, Verily I say unto thee, To day shalt thou be with me in <note>God made the visible paradise in the eastern part of the world: but that which we behold with the eyes of our mind is the place of everlasting joy and salvation, through the goodness and mercy of God, a most pleasant rest for the souls of the godly, and a most quiet and joyful dwelling.</note> paradise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.44'>
          <note>Christ, even being at the point of death, shows himself to be God almighty even to the blind.</note>And it was about the sixth hour, and there was a darkness over all the earth until the ninth hour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.45'>
          <note>Christ enters bravely and resolutely into the very darkness of death, and he does this so that he might overcome death even within its most secret places.</note>And the sun was darkened, and the veil of the temple was rent in the midst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.46'>And Iesus cryed with a loude voyce, and sayd, Father, into thine hands I commend my spirit; when hee thus had sayd, hee gaue vp the ghost.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.47'>
          <note>Christ, as often as it pleases him, causes his very enemies to give honourable witness that he is right.</note>Now when the centurion saw what was done, he glorified God, saying, Certainly this was a righteous man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.48'>And all the people that came together to that sight, beholding the things, which were done, smote their brestes, and returned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.49'>
          <note>Christ gathers together and defends his little flock in the midst of the tormentors.</note>And all his acquaintance, and the women that followed him from Galilee, stood afar off, beholding these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.50'>
          <note>Christ, through his well known burial, confirms both the truth of his death as well as his resurrection, by the plain and evident witness of Pilate.</note>And, behold, [there was] a man named Joseph, a counsellor; [and he was] a good man, and a just:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.51'>Hee did not consent to the counsell and deede of them, which was of Arimathea, a citie of the Iewes: who also himselfe waited for the kingdome of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.52'>He went vnto Pilate, and asked the body of Iesus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.53'>And tooke it downe, &amp; wrapped it in a linnen cloth, and laide it in a tombe hewen out of a rocke, wherein was neuer man yet laide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.54'>And that day was the preparation, and the sabbath <note>Literally, «dawning», and now beginning, for the light of the former day drew toward the going down of the sun, and that was the day of preparation for the feast, that is, the feast which was to be kept the following day.</note> drew on.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.55'>
          <note>Christ, being set upon by the devil and all his instruments, and being even in death's mouth, places weak women in his service, bearing in mind to immediately triumph over these terrible enemies, and that without any great endeavour.</note>And the women also, which came with him from Galilee, followed after, and beheld the sepulchre, and how his body was laid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.23.56'>And they returned and prepared odours, and ointments, and rested the Sabbath day according to the commandement.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Luke.24'>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.1'>Now upon the <note>Poor humble women, who were certainly not expecting it, are chosen to be the first witnesses of the resurrection, so that there might not be any suspicion of either deceit or violence.</note> first [day] of the week, very <note>Very early, as Mark says: or as John says, while it was yet dark, that is, when it was yet hardly the dawning of day.</note> early in the morning, they came unto the sepulchre, bringing the spices which they had prepared, and certain [others] with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.2'>And they found the stone rolled away from the sepulchre,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.3'>And went in, but found not the body of the Lord Iesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.4'>And it came to passe, that as they were amased thereat, beholde, two men suddenly stood by them in shining vestures.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.5'>And as they were afraide, &amp; bowed downe their faces to the earth, they sayd to them, Why seeke ye him that liueth, among the dead?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.6'>He is not here, but is risen: remember how he spake vnto you, when he was yet in Galile,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.7'>Saying, that the sonne of man must be deliuered into the hands of sinfull men, and be crucified, and the third day rise againe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.8'>And they remembred his wordes,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.9'>
          <note>The cowardly and dastardly mind of the disciples is reproved by the brave courage of women (made so by God's great mercies) to show that the kingdom of God consists in an extraordinary power.</note>And returned from the sepulchre, and told all these things unto the eleven, and to all the rest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.10'>Now it was Mary Magdalene, and Ioanna, and Mary the mother of Iames, and other women with them, which tolde these things vnto the Apostles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.11'>But their wordes seemed vnto them, as a fained thing, neither beleeued they them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.12'>
          <note>Christ uses the incredulity of his disciples for the fuller setting forth of the truth of his resurrection, lest they should seem to have believed that too lightly which they preached afterward to all the world.</note>Then arose Peter, and ran unto the sepulchre; and <note>As it were holding down his head, and bowing his neck, looked diligently in.</note> stooping down, he beheld the linen clothes laid by themselves, and departed, wondering in himself at that which was come to pass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.13'>
          <note>The resurrection is proved by two other witnesses who saw it, and all the circumstances surrounding it declare that it was no forged event thought up on purpose in their own minds.</note>And, behold, two of them went that same day to a village called Emmaus, which was from Jerusalem [about] threescore furlongs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.14'>And they talked together of al these things that were done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.15'>And it came to passe, as they communed together, and reasoned, that Iesus himselfe drewe neere, and went with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.16'>
          <note>Were held back and stayed, God no doubt appointing this to be so: and therefore his body was not invisible, but rather their eyes were dimmed.</note>But their eyes were holden that they should not know him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.17'>And he sayd vnto them, What maner of communications are these that ye haue one to another as ye walke and are sad?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.18'>And <note>Some of the old fathers think that the other disciple was the same evangelist who wrote this book, but Epiphanius, writing against the Saturnilians, says it was Nathanael; but none of these are certainties.</note> the one of them, whose name was Cleopas, answering said unto him, Art thou only a stranger in Jerusalem, and hast not known the things which are come to pass there in these days?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.19'>And he said vnto them, What things? And they sayd vnto him, Of Iesus of Nazareth, which was a Prophet, mightie in deede and in word before God, and all people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.20'>
          <note>It appears by conferring the prophecies of the prophets that all those things are true and certain which the evangelist have put down in writing about Christ.</note>And how the chief priests and our rulers delivered him to be condemned to death, and have crucified him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.21'>But we trusted that it had bene he that should haue deliuered Israel, and as touching all these things, to day is ye third day, that they were done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.22'>Yea, &amp; certaine women among vs made vs astonied, which came early vnto the sepulchre.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.23'>And when they found not his body, they came, saying, that they had also seene a vision of Angels, which sayd, that he was aliue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.24'>Therefore certaine of them which were with vs, went to the sepulchre, and found it euen so as the women had sayd, but him they saw not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.25'>Then he sayd vnto them, O fooles and slowe of heart to beleeue all that the Prophets haue spoken!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.26'>Ought not Christ to haue suffered these things, and to enter into his glory?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.27'>And he began at Moses, &amp; at all the Prophets, and interpreted vnto them in all the Scriptures the things which were written of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.28'>And they drew neere vnto ye towne, which they went to, but he made as though hee would haue gone further.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.29'>But they constrained him, saying, Abide with vs: for it is towards night, &amp; the day is farre spent. So he went in to tarie with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.30'>And it came to passe, as hee sate at table with them, he tooke the bread, and blessed, and brake it, and gaue it to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.31'>And their eyes were opened, and they knew him; and he <note>Suddenly taken away, and we may not therefore imagine that he was there in an invisible body, but indeed believe that he suddenly changed the place where he was.</note> vanished out of their sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.32'>And they saide betweene themselues, Did not our heartes burne within vs, while he talked with vs by the way, and when he opened to vs the Scriptures?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.33'>And they rose vp the same houre, and returned to Hierusalem, and found the Eleuen gathered together, and them that were with them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.34'>Which said, The Lord is risen in deede, and hath appeared to Simon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.35'>And they told what things [were done] in the way, and how he was known of them in <note>When he broke bread, which that people used to do, and as the Jews still do today at the beginning of their meals and say a prayer.</note> breaking of bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.36'>
          <note>The Lord himself shows by certain and necessary signs that he was risen again, and risen in the same body which he had taken upon himself.</note>And as they thus spake, Jesus himself stood in the midst of them, and saith unto them, Peace [be] unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.37'>But they were abashed and afraide, supposing that they had seene a spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.38'>And he said unto them, Why are ye troubled? and why do <note>Various and doubtful thoughts which fall often into men's heads, when any strange thing occurs, thoughts of which there is no great likelihood.</note> thoughts arise in your hearts?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.39'>Beholde mine handes and my feete: for it is I my selfe: handle me, and see: for a spirit hath not flesh and bones, as ye see me haue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.40'>And when he had thus spoken, he shewed them his hands and feete.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.41'>And while they yet beleeued not for ioy, and wondred, he saide vnto them, Haue ye here any meate?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.42'>And they gaue him a piece of a broyled fish, and of an honie combe,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.43'>And hee tooke it, and did eate before them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.44'>
          <note>The preaching of the gospel, which was promised to the prophets, and performed in his time, is committed unto the apostles, the sum of which is repentance and remission of sins.</note>And he said unto them, These [are] the words which I spake unto you, while I was yet with you, that all things must be fulfilled, which were written in the law of Moses, and [in] the prophets, and [in] the psalms, concerning me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.45'>Then opened he their vnderstanding, that they might vnderstand the Scriptures,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.46'>And said vnto them, Thus is it written, and thus it behoued Christ to suffer, and to rise againe from the dead the third day,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.47'>And that repentance and remission of sins should be preached in his name among all nations, <note>The apostles, who are the preachers of the gospel, beginning at Jerusalem.</note> beginning at Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.48'>Nowe ye are witnesses of these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.49'>And, behold, I send the promise of my Father upon you: but tarry ye in the city of Jerusalem, <note>Until the Holy Spirit comes down from heaven upon you.</note> until ye be endued with power from on high.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.50'>
          <note>Christ ascends into heaven, and departing bodily from his disciples, fills their hearts with the Holy Spirit.</note>And he led them out as far as to Bethany, and he lifted up his hands, and blessed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.51'>And it came to passe, that as he blessed them, he departed from them, and was caried vp into heauen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.52'>And they worshipped him, and returned to Hierusalem with great ioy,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Luke.24.53'>And were continually in the Temple, praysing, and lauding God, Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>