<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='darby' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='darby'>
        <title>Darby Bible</title>
        <contributor>The Unbound Bible
Biola University:
13800 Biola Ave.
La Mirada, CA 90639
United States of America
562-903-4722 </contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>The Holy Bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>First published in 1890 by John Nelson Darby, an Anglo-Irish bible teacher associated with the early years of the Plymouth Brethren. Darby also published translations of the Bible in French and German.</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>darby</identifier>
        <source>http://unbound.biola.edu/zips/index.cfm?lang=English</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='2Tim'>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.1'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.1'>Paul, apostle of Jesus Christ by God's will, according to promise of life, the [life] which [is] in Christ Jesus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.2'>to Timotheus, [my] beloved child: grace, mercy, peace, from God [the] Father, and Christ Jesus our Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.3'>I am thankful to God, whom I serve from [my] forefathers with pure conscience, how unceasingly I have the remembrance of thee in my supplications night and day,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.4'>earnestly desiring to see thee, remembering thy tears, that I may be filled with joy;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.5'>calling to mind the unfeigned faith which [has been] in thee, which dwelt first in thy grandmother Lois, and in thy mother Eunice, and I am persuaded that in thee also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.6'>For which cause I put thee in mind to rekindle the gift of God which is in thee by the putting on of my hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.7'>For God has not given us a spirit of cowardice, but of power, and of love, and of wise discretion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.8'>Be not therefore ashamed of the testimony of our Lord, nor of me his prisoner; but suffer evil along with the glad tidings, according to the power of God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.9'>who has saved us, and has called us with a holy calling, not according to our works, but according to [his] own purpose and grace, which [was] given to us in Christ Jesus before [the] ages of time,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.10'>but has been made manifest now by the appearing of our Saviour Jesus Christ, who has annulled death, and brought to light life and incorruptibility by the glad tidings;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.11'>to which *I* have been appointed a herald and apostle and teacher of [the] nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.12'>For which cause also I suffer these things; but I am not ashamed; for I know whom I have believed, and am persuaded that he is able to keep for that day the deposit I have entrusted to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.13'>Have an outline of sound words, which [words] thou hast heard of me, in faith and love which [are] in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.14'>Keep, by the Holy Spirit which dwells in us, the good deposit entrusted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.15'>Thou knowest this, that all who [are] in Asia, of whom is Phygellus and Hermogenes, have turned away from me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.16'>The Lord grant mercy to the house of Onesiphorus, for he has often refreshed me, and has not been ashamed of my chain;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.17'>but being in Rome sought me out very diligently, and found [me]</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.18'>the Lord grant to him to find mercy from [the] Lord in that day and how much service he rendered in Ephesus *thou* knowest best.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.2'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.1'>Thou therefore, my child, be strong in the grace which [is] in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.2'>And the things thou hast heard of me in the presence of many witnesses, these entrust to faithful men, such as shall be competent to instruct others also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.3'>Take thy share in suffering as a good soldier of Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.4'>No one going as a soldier entangles himself with the affairs of life, that he may please him who has enlisted him as a soldier.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.5'>And if also any one contend [in the games], he is not crowned unless he contend lawfully.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.6'>The husbandman must labour before partaking of the fruits.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.7'>Think of what I say, for the Lord will give thee understanding in all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.8'>Remember Jesus Christ raised from among [the] dead, of [the] seed of David, according to my glad tidings,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.9'>in which I suffer even unto bonds as an evil-doer: but the word of God is not bound.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.10'>For this cause I endure all things for the sake of the elect, that *they* also may obtain the salvation which [is] in Christ Jesus with eternal glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.11'>The word [is] faithful; for if we have died together with [him], we shall also live together;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.12'>if we endure, we shall also reign together; if we deny, *he* also will deny us;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.13'>if we are unfaithful, *he* abides faithful, for he cannot deny himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.14'>Of these things put in remembrance, testifying earnestly before the Lord not to have disputes of words, profitable for nothing, to the subversion of the hearers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.15'>Strive diligently to present thyself approved to God, a workman that has not to be ashamed, cutting in a straight line the word of truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.16'>But profane, vain babblings shun, for they will advance to greater impiety,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.17'>and their word will spread as a gangrene; of whom is Hymenaeus and Philetus;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.18'>[men] who as to the truth have gone astray, saying that the resurrection has taken place already; and overthrow the faith of some.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.19'>Yet the firm foundation of God stands, having this seal, [The] Lord knows those that are his; and, Let every one who names the name of [the] Lord withdraw from iniquity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.20'>But in a great house there are not only gold and silver vessels, but also wooden and earthen; and some to honour, and some to dishonour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.21'>If therefore one shall have purified himself from these, [in separating himself from them], he shall be a vessel to honour, sanctified, serviceable to the Master, prepared for every good work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.22'>But youthful lusts flee, and pursue righteousness, faith, love, peace, with those that call upon the Lord out of a pure heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.23'>But foolish and senseless questionings avoid, knowing that they beget contentions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.24'>And a bondman of [the] Lord ought not to contend, but be gentle towards all; apt to teach; forbearing;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.25'>in meekness setting right those who oppose, if God perhaps may sometime give them repentance to acknowledgment of [the] truth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.26'>and that they may awake up out of the snare of the devil, [who are] taken by him, for *his* will.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.3'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.1'>But this know, that in [the] last days difficult times shall be there;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.2'>for men shall be lovers of self, lovers of money, boastful, arrogant, evil speakers, disobedient to parents, ungrateful, profane,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.3'>without natural affection, implacable, slanderers, of unsubdued passions, savage, having no love for what is good,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.4'>traitors, headlong, of vain pretensions, lovers of pleasure rather than lovers of God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.5'>having a form of piety but denying the power of it: and from these turn away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.6'>For of these are they who are getting into houses, and leading captive silly women, laden with sins, led by various lusts,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.7'>always learning, and never able to come to [the] knowledge of [the] truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.8'>Now in the same manner in which Jannes and Jambres withstood Moses, thus these also withstand the truth; men corrupted in mind, found worthless as regards the faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.9'>But they shall not advance farther; for their folly shall be completely manifest to all, as that of those also became.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.10'>But *thou* hast been thoroughly acquainted with my teaching, conduct, purpose, faith, longsuffering, love, endurance,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.11'>persecutions, sufferings: what [sufferings] happened to me in Antioch, in Iconium, in Lystra; what persecutions I endured; and the Lord delivered me out of all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.12'>And all indeed who desire to live piously in Christ Jesus will be persecuted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.13'>But wicked men and juggling impostors shall advance in evil, leading and being led astray.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.14'>But *thou*, abide in those things which thou hast learned, and [of which] thou hast been fully persuaded, knowing of whom thou hast learned [them];</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.15'>and that from a child thou hast known the sacred letters, which are able to make thee wise unto salvation, through faith which [is] in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.16'>Every scripture [is] divinely inspired, and profitable for teaching, for conviction, for correction, for instruction in righteousness;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.17'>that the man of God may be complete, fully fitted to every good work.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.4'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.1'>I testify before God and Christ Jesus, who is about to judge living and dead, and by his appearing and his kingdom,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.2'>proclaim the word; be urgent in season [and] out of season, convict, rebuke, encourage, with all longsuffering and doctrine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.3'>For the time shall be when they will not bear sound teaching; but according to their own lusts will heap up to themselves teachers, having an itching ear;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.4'>and they will turn away their ear from the truth, and will have turned aside to fables.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.5'>But *thou*, be sober in all things, bear evils, do [the] work of an evangelist, fill up the full measure of thy ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.6'>For *I* am already being poured out, and the time of my release is come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.7'>I have combated the good combat, I have finished the race, I have kept the faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.8'>Henceforth the crown of righteousness is laid up for me, which the Lord, the righteous Judge, will render to me in that day; but not only to me, but also to all who love his appearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.9'>Use diligence to come to me quickly;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.10'>for Demas has forsaken me, having loved the present age, and is gone to Thessalonica; Crescens to Galatia, Titus to Dalmatia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.11'>Luke alone is with me. Take Mark, and bring [him] with thyself, for he is serviceable to me for ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.12'>But Tychicus I have sent to Ephesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.13'>The cloak which I left behind [me] in Troas at Carpus's, bring when thou comest, and the books, especially the parchments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.14'>Alexander the smith did many evil things against me. The Lord will render to him according to his works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.15'>Against whom be *thou* also on thy guard, for he has greatly withstood our words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.16'>At my first defence no man stood with me, but all deserted me. May it not be imputed to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.17'>But the Lord stood with [me], and gave me power, that through me the proclamation might be fully made, and all [those of] the nations should hear; and I was delivered out of the lion's mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.18'>The Lord shall deliver me from every wicked work, and shall preserve [me] for his heavenly kingdom; to whom [be] glory for the ages of ages. Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.19'>Salute Prisca and Aquila, and the house of Onesiphorus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.20'>Erastus remained in Corinth, but Trophimus I left behind in Miletus sick.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.21'>Use diligence to come before winter. Eubulus salutes thee, and Pudens, and Linus, and Claudia, and the brethren all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.22'>The Lord Jesus Christ [be] with your spirit. Grace [be] with you.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>