<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='darby' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='darby'>
        <title>Darby Bible</title>
        <contributor>The Unbound Bible
Biola University:
13800 Biola Ave.
La Mirada, CA 90639
United States of America
562-903-4722 </contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>The Holy Bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>First published in 1890 by John Nelson Darby, an Anglo-Irish bible teacher associated with the early years of the Plymouth Brethren. Darby also published translations of the Bible in French and German.</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>darby</identifier>
        <source>http://unbound.biola.edu/zips/index.cfm?lang=English</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='3John'>
      <chapter osisID='3John.1'>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.1'>The elder to the beloved Gaius, whom I love in truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.2'>Beloved, I desire that in all things thou shouldest prosper and be in health, even as thy soul prospers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.3'>For I rejoiced exceedingly when [the] brethren came and bore testimony to thy [holding fast the] truth, even as *thou* walkest in truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.4'>I have no greater joy than these things that I hear of my children walking in the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.5'>Beloved, thou doest faithfully [in] whatever thou mayest have wrought towards the brethren and that strangers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.6'>(who have witnessed of thy love before [the] assembly,) in setting forward whom on their journey worthily of God, thou wilt do well;</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.7'>for for the name have they gone forth, taking nothing of those of the nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.8'>*We* therefore ought to receive such, that we may be fellow-workers with the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.9'>I wrote something to the assembly; but Diotrephes, who loves to have the first place among them, receives us not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.10'>For this reason, if I come, I will bring to remembrance his works which he does, babbling against us with wicked words; and not content with these, neither does he himself receive the brethren; and those who would he prevents, and casts [them] out of the assembly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.11'>Beloved, do not imitate what is evil, but what is good. He that does good is of God. He that does evil has not seen God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.12'>Demetrius has witness borne to him by all, and by the truth itself; and *we* also bear witness, and thou knowest that our witness is true.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.13'>I had many things to write to thee, but I will not with ink and pen write to thee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.14'>but I hope soon to see thee, and we will speak mouth to mouth. Peace [be] to thee. The friends greet thee. Greet the friends by name.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>