<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='darby' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='darby'>
        <title>Darby Bible</title>
        <contributor>The Unbound Bible
Biola University:
13800 Biola Ave.
La Mirada, CA 90639
United States of America
562-903-4722 </contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>The Holy Bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>First published in 1890 by John Nelson Darby, an Anglo-Irish bible teacher associated with the early years of the Plymouth Brethren. Darby also published translations of the Bible in French and German.</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>darby</identifier>
        <source>http://unbound.biola.edu/zips/index.cfm?lang=English</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Eph'>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.1'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.1'>Paul, apostle of Jesus Christ by God's will, to the saints and faithful in Christ Jesus who are at Ephesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.2'>Grace to you and peace from God our Father, and [the] Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.3'>Blessed [be] the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who has blessed us with every spiritual blessing in the heavenlies in Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.4'>according as he has chosen us in him before [the] world's foundation, that we should be holy and blameless before him in love;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.5'>having marked us out beforehand for adoption through Jesus Christ to himself, according to the good pleasure of his will,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.6'>to [the] praise of [the] glory of his grace, wherein he has taken us into favour in the Beloved:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.7'>in whom we have redemption through his blood, the forgiveness of offences, according to the riches of his grace;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.8'>which he has caused to abound towards us in all wisdom and intelligence,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.9'>having made known to us the mystery of his will, according to his good pleasure which he purposed in himself</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.10'>for [the] administration of the fulness of times; to head up all things in the Christ, the things in the heavens and the things upon the earth; in him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.11'>in whom we have also obtained an inheritance, being marked out beforehand according to the purpose of him who works all things according to the counsel of his own will,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.12'>that we should be to [the] praise of his glory who have pre-trusted in the Christ:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.13'>in whom *ye* also [have trusted], having heard the word of the truth, the glad tidings of your salvation; in whom also, having believed, ye have been sealed with the Holy Spirit of promise,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.14'>who is [the] earnest of our inheritance to the redemption of the acquired possession to [the] praise of his glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.15'>Wherefore *I* also, having heard of the faith in the Lord Jesus which [is] in you, and the love which [ye have] towards all the saints,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.16'>do not cease giving thanks for you, making mention [of you] at my prayers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.17'>that the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of glory, would give you [the] spirit of wisdom and revelation in the full knowledge of him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.18'>being enlightened in the eyes of your heart, so that ye should know what is the hope of his calling, [and] what the riches of the glory of his inheritance in the saints,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.19'>and what the surpassing greatness of his power towards us who believe, according to the working of the might of his strength,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.20'>[in] which he wrought in the Christ [in] raising him from among [the] dead, and he set him down at his right hand in the heavenlies,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.21'>above every principality, and authority, and power, and dominion, and every name named, not only in this age, but also in that to come;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.22'>and has put all things under his feet, and gave him [to be] head over all things to the assembly,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.23'>which is his body, the fulness of him who fills all in all:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.2'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.1'>and *you*, being dead in your offences and sins</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.2'>in which ye once walked according to the age of this world, according to the ruler of the authority of the air, the spirit who now works in the sons of disobedience:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.3'>among whom *we* also all once had our conversation in the lusts of our flesh, doing what the flesh and the thoughts willed to do, and were children, by nature, of wrath, even as the rest:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.4'>but God, being rich in mercy, because of his great love wherewith he loved us,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.5'>(we too being dead in offences,) has quickened us with the Christ, (ye are saved by grace,)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.6'>and has raised [us] up together, and has made [us] sit down together in the heavenlies in Christ Jesus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.7'>that he might display in the coming ages the surpassing riches of his grace in kindness towards us in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.8'>For ye are saved by grace, through faith; and this not of yourselves; it is God's gift:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.9'>not on the principle of works, that no one might boast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.10'>For we are his workmanship, having been created in Christ Jesus for good works, which God has before prepared that we should walk in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.11'>Wherefore remember that *ye*, once nations in [the] flesh, who [are] called uncircumcision by that called circumcision in [the] flesh done with the hand;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.12'>that ye were at that time without Christ, aliens from the commonwealth of Israel, and strangers to the covenants of promise, having no hope, and without God in the world:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.13'>but now in Christ Jesus *ye* who once were afar off are become nigh by the blood of the Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.14'>For *he* is our peace, who has made both one, and has broken down the middle wall of enclosure,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.15'>having annulled the enmity in his flesh, the law of commandments in ordinances, that he might form the two in himself into one new man, making peace;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.16'>and might reconcile both in one body to God by the cross, having by it slain the enmity;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.17'>and, coming, he has preached the glad tidings of peace to you who [were] afar off, and [the glad tidings of] peace to those [who were] nigh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.18'>For through him we have both access by one Spirit to the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.19'>So then ye are no longer strangers and foreigners, but ye are fellow-citizens of the saints, and of the household of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.20'>being built upon the foundation of the apostles and prophets, Jesus Christ himself being the corner-stone,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.21'>in whom all [the] building fitted together increases to a holy temple in the Lord;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.22'>in whom *ye* also are built together for a habitation of God in [the] Spirit.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.3'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.1'>For this reason *I* Paul, prisoner of the Christ Jesus for you nations,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.2'>(if indeed ye have heard of the administration of the grace of God which has been given to me towards you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.3'>that by revelation the mystery has been made known to me, (according as I have written before briefly,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.4'>by which, in reading it, ye can understand my intelligence in the mystery of the Christ,)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.5'>which in other generations has not been made known to the sons of men, as it has now been revealed to his holy apostles and prophets in [the power of the] Spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.6'>that [they who are of] the nations should be joint heirs, and a joint body, and joint partakers of [his] promise in Christ Jesus by the glad tidings;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.7'>of which I am become minister according to the gift of the grace of God given to me, according to the working of his power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.8'>To me, less than the least of all saints, has this grace been given, to announce among the nations the glad tidings of the unsearchable riches of the Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.9'>and to enlighten all [with the knowledge of] what is the administration of the mystery hidden throughout the ages in God, who has created all things,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.10'>in order that now to the principalities and authorities in the heavenlies might be made known through the assembly the all-various wisdom of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.11'>according to [the] purpose of the ages, which he purposed in Christ Jesus our Lord,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.12'>in whom we have boldness and access in confidence by the faith of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.13'>Wherefore I beseech [you] not to faint through my tribulations for you, which is your glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.14'>For this reason I bow my knees to the Father [of our Lord Jesus Christ],</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.15'>of whom every family in [the] heavens and on earth is named,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.16'>in order that he may give you according to the riches of his glory, to be strengthened with power by his Spirit in the inner man;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.17'>that the Christ may dwell, through faith, in your hearts, being rooted and founded in love,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.18'>in order that ye may be fully able to apprehend with all the saints what [is] the breadth and length and depth and height;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.19'>and to know the love of the Christ which surpasses knowledge; that ye may be filled [even] to all the fulness of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.20'>But to him that is able to do far exceedingly above all which we ask or think, according to the power which works in us,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.21'>to him be glory in the assembly in Christ Jesus unto all generations of the age of ages. Amen).</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.4'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.1'>*I*, the prisoner in [the] Lord, exhort you therefore to walk worthy of the calling wherewith ye have been called,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.2'>with all lowliness and meekness, with long-suffering, bearing with one another in love;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.3'>using diligence to keep the unity of the Spirit in the uniting bond of peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.4'>[There is] one body and one Spirit, as ye have been also called in one hope of your calling;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.5'>one Lord, one faith, one baptism;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.6'>one God and Father of all, who is over all, and through all, and in us all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.7'>But to each one of us has been given grace according to the measure of the gift of the Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.8'>Wherefore he says, Having ascended up on high, he has led captivity captive, and has given gifts to men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.9'>But that he ascended, what is it but that he also descended into the lower parts of the earth?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.10'>He that descended is the same who has also ascended up above all the heavens, that he might fill all things;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.11'>and *he* has given some apostles, and some prophets, and some evangelists, and some shepherds and teachers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.12'>for the perfecting of the saints; with a view to [the] work of [the] ministry, with a view to the edifying of the body of Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.13'>until we all arrive at the unity of the faith and of the knowledge of the Son of God, at [the] full-grown man, at [the] measure of the stature of the fulness of the Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.14'>in order that we may be no longer babes, tossed and carried about by every wind of *that* teaching [which is] in the sleight of men, in unprincipled cunning with a view to systematized error;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.15'>but, holding the truth in love, we may grow up to him in all things, who is the head, the Christ:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.16'>from whom the whole body, fitted together, and connected by every joint of supply, according to [the] working in [its] measure of each one part, works for itself the increase of the body to its self-building up in love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.17'>This I say therefore, and testify in [the] Lord, that ye should no longer walk as [the rest of] the nations walk in [the] vanity of their mind,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.18'>being darkened in understanding, estranged from the life of God by reason of the ignorance which is in them, by reason of the hardness of their hearts,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.19'>who having cast off all feeling, have given themselves up to lasciviousness, to work all uncleanness with greedy unsatisfied lust.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.20'>But *ye* have not thus learnt the Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.21'>if ye have heard him and been instructed in him according as [the] truth is in Jesus;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.22'>[namely] your having put off according to the former conversation the old man which corrupts itself according to the deceitful lusts;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.23'>and being renewed in the spirit of your mind;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.24'>and [your] having put on the new man, which according to God is created in truthful righteousness and holiness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.25'>Wherefore, having put off falsehood, speak truth every one with his neighbour, because we are members one of another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.26'>Be angry, and do not sin; let not the sun set upon your wrath,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.27'>neither give room for the devil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.28'>Let the stealer steal no more, but rather let him toil, working what is honest with [his] hands, that he may have to distribute to him that has need.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.29'>Let no corrupt word go out of your mouth, but if [there be] any good one for needful edification, that it may give grace to those that hear [it].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.30'>And do not grieve the Holy Spirit of God, with which ye have been sealed for [the] day of redemption.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.31'>Let all bitterness, and heat of passion, and wrath, and clamour, and injurious language, be removed from you, with all malice;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.32'>and be to one another kind, compassionate, forgiving one another, so as God also in Christ has forgiven you.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.5'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.1'>Be ye therefore imitators of God, as beloved children,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.2'>and walk in love, even as the Christ loved us, and delivered himself up for us, an offering and sacrifice to God for a sweet-smelling savour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.3'>But fornication and all uncleanness or unbridled lust, let it not be even named among you, as it becomes saints;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.4'>and filthiness and foolish talking, or jesting, which are not convenient; but rather thanksgiving.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.5'>For this ye are [well] informed of, knowing that no fornicator, or unclean person, or person of unbridled lust, who is an idolater, has inheritance in the kingdom of the Christ and God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.6'>Let no one deceive you with vain words, for on account of these things the wrath of God comes upon the sons of disobedience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.7'>Be not ye therefore fellow-partakers with them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.8'>for ye were once darkness, but now light in [the] Lord; walk as children of light,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.9'>(for the fruit of the light [is] in all goodness and righteousness and truth,)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.10'>proving what is agreeable to the Lord;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.11'>and do not have fellowship with the unfruitful works of darkness, but rather also reprove [them],</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.12'>for the things that are done by them in secret it is shameful even to say.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.13'>But all things having their true character exposed by the light are made manifest; for that which makes everything manifest is light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.14'>Wherefore he says, Wake up, [thou] that sleepest, and arise up from among the dead, and the Christ shall shine upon thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.15'>See therefore how ye walk carefully, not as unwise but as wise,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.16'>redeeming the time, because the days are evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.17'>For this reason be not foolish, but understanding what [is] the will of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.18'>And be not drunk with wine, in which is debauchery; but be filled with the Spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.19'>speaking to yourselves in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing and chanting with your heart to the Lord;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.20'>giving thanks at all times for all things to him [who is] God and [the] Father in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.21'>submitting yourselves to one another in [the] fear of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.22'>Wives, [submit yourselves] to your own husbands, as to the Lord,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.23'>for a husband is head of the wife, as also the Christ [is] head of the assembly. *He* [is] Saviour of the body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.24'>But even as the assembly is subjected to the Christ, so also wives to their own husbands in everything.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.25'>Husbands, love your own wives, even as the Christ also loved the assembly, and has delivered himself up for it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.26'>in order that he might sanctify it, purifying [it] by the washing of water by [the] word,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.27'>that *he* might present the assembly to himself glorious, having no spot, or wrinkle, or any of such things; but that it might be holy and blameless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.28'>So ought men also to love their own wives as their own bodies: he that loves his own wife loves himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.29'>For no one has ever hated his own flesh, but nourishes and cherishes it, even as also the Christ the assembly:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.30'>for we are members of his body; [we are of his flesh, and of his bones.]</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.31'>Because of this a man shall leave his father and mother, and shall be united to his wife, and the two shall be one flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.32'>This mystery is great, but *I* speak as to Christ, and as to the assembly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.33'>But *ye* also, every one of you, let each so love his own wife as himself; but as to the wife [I speak] that she may fear the husband.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.6'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.1'>Children, obey your parents in [the] Lord, for this is just.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.2'>Honour thy father and thy mother, which is the first commandment with a promise,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.3'>that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayest be long-lived on the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.4'>And [ye] fathers, do not provoke your children to anger, but bring them up in [the] discipline and admonition of [the] Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.5'>Bondmen, obey masters according to flesh, with fear and trembling, in simplicity of your heart as to the Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.6'>not with eye-service as men-pleasers; but as bondmen of Christ, doing the will of God from [the] soul,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.7'>serving with good will as to the Lord, and not to men;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.8'>knowing that whatever good each shall do, this he shall receive of [the] Lord, whether bond or free.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.9'>And, masters, do the same things towards them, giving up threatening, knowing that both their and your Master is in heaven, and there is no acceptance of persons with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.10'>For the rest, brethren, be strong in [the] Lord, and in the might of his strength.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.11'>Put on the panoply of God, that ye may be able to stand against the artifices of the devil:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.12'>because our struggle is not against blood and flesh, but against principalities, against authorities, against the universal lords of this darkness, against spiritual [power] of wickedness in the heavenlies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.13'>For this reason take [to you] the panoply of God, that ye may be able to withstand in the evil day, and, having accomplished all things, to stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.14'>Stand therefore, having girt about your loins with truth, and having put on the breastplate of righteousness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.15'>and shod your feet with [the] preparation of the glad tidings of peace:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.16'>besides all [these], having taken the shield of faith with which ye will be able to quench all the inflamed darts of the wicked one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.17'>Have also the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the Spirit, which is God's word;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.18'>praying at all seasons, with all prayer and supplication in [the] Spirit, and watching unto this very thing with all perseverance and supplication for all the saints;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.19'>and for me in order that utterance may be given to me in [the] opening of my mouth to make known with boldness the mystery of the glad tidings,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.20'>for which I am an ambassador [bound] with a chain, that I may be bold in it as I ought to speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.21'>But in order that *ye* also may know what concerns me, how I am getting on, Tychicus, the beloved brother and faithful minister in [the] Lord, shall make all things known to you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.22'>whom I have sent to you for this very thing, that ye may know of our affairs and that he may encourage your hearts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.23'>Peace to the brethren, and love with faith, from God [the] Father and [the] Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.24'>Grace with all them that love our Lord Jesus Christ in incorruption.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>