<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='darby' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='darby'>
        <title>Darby Bible</title>
        <contributor>The Unbound Bible
Biola University:
13800 Biola Ave.
La Mirada, CA 90639
United States of America
562-903-4722 </contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>The Holy Bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>First published in 1890 by John Nelson Darby, an Anglo-Irish bible teacher associated with the early years of the Plymouth Brethren. Darby also published translations of the Bible in French and German.</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>darby</identifier>
        <source>http://unbound.biola.edu/zips/index.cfm?lang=English</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Isa'>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.1'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.1'>The vision of Isaiah the son of Amos, which he saw concerning Judah and Jerusalem in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, Hezekiah, kings of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.2'>Hear, [ye] heavens, and give ear, [thou] earth! for Jehovah hath spoken: I have nourished and brought up children; and they have rebelled against me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.3'>The ox knoweth his owner, and the ass his master's crib; Israel doth not know, my people hath no intelligence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.4'>Ah sinful nation, a people laden with iniquity, a seed of evildoers, children that corrupt themselves! They have forsaken Jehovah; they have despised the Holy One of Israel; they are turned away backward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.5'>Why should ye be smitten any more? ye will revolt more and more: the whole head is sick, and the whole heart faint.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.6'>From the sole of the foot even unto the head there is no soundness in him; wounds, and weals, and open sores: they have not been dressed, nor bound up, nor mollified with oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.7'>Your country is desolate; your cities are burned with fire; your land, strangers eat it up in your presence, and it is desolate, as overthrown by strangers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.8'>And the daughter of Zion is left, as a booth in a vineyard, as a night-lodge in a cucumber-garden, as a besieged city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.9'>Unless Jehovah of hosts had left us a very small residue, we should have been as Sodom, we should have been like unto Gomorrah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.10'>Hear the word of Jehovah, rulers of Sodom; give ear unto the law of our God, people of Gomorrah!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.11'>To what purpose is the multitude of your sacrifices unto me? saith Jehovah. I am sated with burnt-offerings of rams, and the fat of fed beasts; and in the blood of bullocks, and of lambs, and of he-goats I take no pleasure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.12'>When ye come to appear before me, who hath required this from your hand to tread my courts?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.13'>Bring no more vain oblations! Incense is an abomination unto me, new moon and sabbath, the calling of convocations wickedness and the solemn meeting I cannot bear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.14'>Your new moons and your set feasts my soul hateth: they are a burden to me; I am wearied of bearing [them].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.15'>And when ye spread forth your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you; yea, when ye make many prayers, I will not hear: your hands are full of blood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.16'>Wash you, make you clean; put away the evil of your doings from before mine eyes; cease to do evil,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.17'>learn to do well: seek judgment, gladden the oppressed, do justice to the fatherless, plead for the widow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.18'>Come now, let us reason together, saith Jehovah: though your sins be as scarlet, they shall be as white as snow; though they be red like crimson, they shall be as wool.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.19'>If ye be willing and hearken, ye shall eat the good of the land;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.20'>but if ye refuse and rebel, ye shall be devoured with the sword: for the mouth of Jehovah hath spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.21'>How is the faithful city become a harlot! It was full of judgment; righteousness used to lodge in it, but now murderers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.22'>Thy silver is become dross, thy wine is mixed with water:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.23'>thy princes are rebellious, and companions of thieves; every one loveth presents, and hunteth after rewards; they judge not the fatherless, and the cause of the widow cometh not unto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.24'>Therefore saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, the Mighty One of Israel: Ah! I will ease me of mine adversaries, and avenge me of mine enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.25'>And I will turn my hand upon thee, and will thoroughly purge away thy dross, and take away all thine alloy;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.26'>and I will restore thy judges as at the first, and thy counsellors as at the beginning. Afterwards thou shalt be called, Town of righteousness, Faithful city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.27'>Zion shall be redeemed with judgment, and they that return of her with righteousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.28'>But the ruin of the transgressors and of the sinners [shall be] together; and they that forsake Jehovah shall be consumed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.29'>For they shall be ashamed of the terebinths that ye have desired, and ye shall blush for the gardens that ye have chosen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.30'>For ye shall be as a terebinth whose leaf fadeth, and as a garden that hath no water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.1.31'>And the strong shall be for tow, and his work a spark; and they shall both burn together, and there shall be none to quench [them].</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.2'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.1'>The word that Isaiah the son of Amoz saw concerning Judah and Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.2'>And it shall come to pass in the end of days, [that] the mountain of Jehovah's house shall be established on the top of the mountains, and shall be lifted up above the hills; and all the nations shall flow unto it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.3'>And many peoples shall go and say, Come, and let us go up to the mountain of Jehovah, to the house of the God of Jacob; and he will teach us of his ways, and we will walk in his paths. For out of Zion shall go forth the law, and Jehovah's word from Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.4'>And he shall judge among the nations, and shall reprove many peoples; and they shall forge their swords into ploughshares, and their spears into pruning-knives: nation shall not lift up sword against nation, neither shall they learn war any more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.5'>House of Jacob, come ye, and let us walk in the light of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.6'>For thou hast cast off thy people, the house of Jacob, because they are filled [with what comes] from the east, and use auguries like the Philistines, and ally themselves with the children of foreigners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.7'>And their land is full of silver and gold, and there is no end of their treasures: their land also is full of horses, and there is no end of their chariots.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.8'>And their land is full of idols; they bow themselves down to the work of their own hands, to that which their fingers have made.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.9'>And the mean man shall be bowed down, and the great man shall be brought low: and do not thou forgive them!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.10'>Enter into the rock, and hide thee in the dust, from before the terror of Jehovah, and from the glory of his majesty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.11'>The lofty eyes of man shall be brought low, and the haughtiness of men shall be bowed down, and Jehovah alone shall be exalted in that day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.12'>For there shall be a day of Jehovah of hosts upon everything proud and lofty, and upon everything lifted up, and it shall be brought low;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.13'>and upon all the cedars of Lebanon, high and lifted up, and upon all the oaks of Bashan;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.14'>and upon all the lofty mountains, and upon all the hills that are lifted up;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.15'>and upon every high tower, and upon every fenced wall;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.16'>and upon all the ships of Tarshish, and upon all pleasant works of art.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.17'>And the loftiness of man shall be bowed down, and the haughtiness of men shall be brought low; and Jehovah alone shall be exalted in that day:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.18'>and the idols shall utterly pass away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.19'>And they shall go into the caves of the rocks, and into the holes of the earth, from before the terror of Jehovah, and from the glory of his majesty, when he shall arise to terrify the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.20'>In that day men shall cast away their idols of silver and their idols of gold, which they made [each] for himself to worship, to the moles and to the bats;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.21'>to go into the clefts of the rocks, and into the fissures of the cliffs, from before the terror of Jehovah, and from the glory of his majesty, when he shall arise to terrify the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.2.22'>Cease ye from man, whose breath is in his nostrils; for what account is to be made of him?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.3'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.1'>For behold, the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, will take away from Jerusalem and from Judah stay and staff, the whole stay of bread, and the whole stay of water,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.2'>the mighty man and the man of war, the judge and the prophet, and the diviner and the elder,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.3'>the captain of fifty, and the honourable man, and the counsellor, and the clever among artificers, and the one versed in enchantments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.4'>And I will appoint youths as their princes, and children shall rule over them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.5'>And the people shall be oppressed one by the other, and each by his neighbour; the child will be insolent against the elder, and the base against the honourable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.6'>When a man shall take hold of his brother, in his father's house, [and shall say:] Thou hast clothing; be our chief, and let this ruin be under thy hand;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.7'>he will lift up [his hand] in that day, saying, I cannot be a healer, and in my house there is neither bread nor clothing; ye shall not make me a chief of the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.8'>For Jerusalem stumbleth and Judah falleth, because their tongue and their doings are against Jehovah, to provoke the eyes of his glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.9'>The look of their face doth witness against them, and they declare their sin as Sodom: they hide it not. Woe unto their soul! for they have brought evil upon themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.10'>Say ye of the righteous that it shall be well [with him], for they shall eat the fruit of their doings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.11'>Woe unto the wicked! it shall be ill [with him], because the desert of his hands shall be rendered unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.12'>[As for] my people, children are their oppressors, and women rule over them. My people! they that guide thee mislead [thee], and destroy the way of thy paths.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.13'>Jehovah setteth himself to plead, and standeth to judge the peoples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.14'>Jehovah will enter into judgment with the elders of his people and their princes, [saying:] It is ye that have eaten up the vineyard: the spoil of the poor is in your houses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.15'>What mean ye that ye crush my people, and grind the faces of the afflicted? saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.16'>And Jehovah said, Because the daughters of Zion are haughty, and walk with stretched-out neck and wanton eyes, and go along mincing, and making a tinkling with their feet;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.17'>therefore the Lord will make bald the crown of the head of the daughters of Zion, and Jehovah will lay bare their secret parts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.18'>In that day the Lord will take away the ornament of anklets, and the little suns and crescents,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.19'>the pearl-drops, and the bracelets, and the veils,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.20'>the head-dresses, and the stepping chains, and the girdles, and the scent-boxes, and the amulets;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.21'>the finger-rings, and the nose-rings;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.22'>the festival-robes, and the tunics, and the mantles, and the wallets;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.23'>the mirrors, and the fine linen bodices, and the turbans, and the flowing veils.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.24'>And it shall come to pass, instead of perfume there shall be rottenness; and instead of a girdle, a rope; and instead of well-set hair, baldness; and instead of a robe of display, a girding of sackcloth; brand instead of beauty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.25'>Thy men shall fall by the sword, and thy mighty in the fight;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.3.26'>and her gates shall lament and mourn; and, stripped, she shall sit upon the ground.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.4'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.4.1'>And seven women shall take hold of one man in that day, saying, Our own bread will we eat, and with our own garments will we be clothed; only let us be called by thy name; take away our reproach!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.4.2'>In that day there shall be a sprout of Jehovah for beauty and glory, and the fruit of the earth for excellency and for ornament for those that are escaped of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.4.3'>And it shall come to pass that he who remaineth in Zion, and he that is left in Jerusalem, shall be called holy, every one that is written among the living in Jerusalem;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.4.4'>when the Lord shall have washed away the filth of the daughters of Zion, and shall have scoured out the blood of Jerusalem from its midst, by the spirit of judgment, and by the spirit of burning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.4.5'>And Jehovah will create over every dwelling-place of mount Zion, and over its convocations, a cloud by day and a smoke, and the brightness of a flame of fire by night: for over all the glory shall be a covering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.4.6'>And there shall be a tabernacle for shade by day from the heat, and for a shelter and for a covert from storm and from rain.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.5'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.1'>I will sing to my well-beloved a song of my beloved touching his vineyard: My well-beloved had a vineyard upon a fruitful hill.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.2'>And he dug it, and gathered out the stones thereof, and planted it with the choicest vine; and he built a tower in the midst of it, and also hewed out a winepress therein; and he looked that it should bring forth grapes, but it brought forth wild grapes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.3'>And now, inhabitants of Jerusalem and men of Judah, judge, I pray you, between me and my vineyard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.4'>What was there yet to do to my vineyard that I have not done in it? Wherefore, when I looked that it should bring forth grapes, brought it forth wild grapes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.5'>And now, let me tell you what I am about to do to my vineyard: I will take away its hedge, and it shall be eaten up; I will break down its wall, and it shall be trodden under foot;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.6'>and I will make it a waste it shall not be pruned nor cultivated, but there shall come up briars and thorns; and I will command the clouds that they rain no rain upon it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.7'>For the vineyard of Jehovah of hosts is the house of Israel, and the men of Judah the plant of his delight: and he looked for justice, and behold, blood-shedding; for righteousness, and behold, a cry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.8'>Woe unto them that add house to house, that join field to field, until there is no more room, and that ye dwell yourselves alone in the midst of the land!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.9'>In mine ears Jehovah of hosts [hath said], Many houses shall assuredly become a desolation, great and excellent ones, without inhabitant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.10'>Yea, ten acres of vineyard shall yield one bath, and a homer of seed shall yield an ephah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.11'>Woe unto them that, rising early in the morning, run after strong drink; that linger till twilight, [till] wine inflameth them!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.12'>And harp and lyre, tambour and flute, and wine are in their banquets; but they regard not the work of Jehovah, nor do they see the operation of his hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.13'>Therefore my people are led away captive from lack of knowledge, and their nobility die of famine, and their multitude are parched with thirst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.14'>Therefore doth Sheol enlarge its desire, and open its mouth without measure; and her splendour shall descend [into it], and her multitude, and her tumult, and [all] that is joyful within her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.15'>And the mean man shall be bowed down, and the great man brought low, and the eyes of the lofty shall be brought low;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.16'>and Jehovah of hosts shall be exalted in judgment, and the holy God hallowed in righteousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.17'>And the lambs shall feed as on their pasture, and the waste places of the fat ones shall strangers eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.18'>Woe unto them that draw iniquity with cords of vanity, and sin as with cart-ropes!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.19'>who say, Let him hasten, let him speed his work, that we may see [it]; and let the counsel of the Holy One of Israel draw nigh and come, that we may know it!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.20'>Woe unto them who call evil good, and good evil; who put darkness for light, and light for darkness; who put bitter for sweet, and sweet for bitter!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.21'>Woe unto them that are wise in their own eyes, and intelligent in their own esteem!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.22'>Woe unto them that are mighty for drinking wine, and men valiant to mix strong drink;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.23'>who justify the wicked for a bribe, and turn away the righteousness of the righteous from them!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.24'>Therefore as a tongue of fire devoureth the stubble, and dry grass sinketh down in the flame, their root shall be as rottenness, and their blossom shall go up as dust; for they have rejected the law of Jehovah of hosts, and despised the word of the Holy One of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.25'>Therefore is the anger of Jehovah kindled against his people, and he hath stretched out his hand against them and hath smitten them; and the mountains trembled, and their carcases are become as dung in the midst of the streets. For all this his anger is not turned away, and his hand is stretched out still.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.26'>And he will lift up a banner to the nations afar off, and will hiss for one from the end of the earth; and behold, it will come rapidly [and] lightly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.27'>None among them is weary, none stumbleth; they slumber not, nor sleep; none hath the girdle of his loins loosed, nor the thong of his sandals broken;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.28'>their arrows are sharp, and all their bows bent; their horses' hoofs are reckoned as the flint, and their wheels as a whirlwind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.29'>Their roaring is like a lioness, they roar as the young lions; yea, they growl, and snatch the prey, and carry it away safe, and there is none to deliver;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.5.30'>and they shall roar against them in that day like the roaring of the sea. And if one look upon the earth, behold darkness [and] distress, and the light is darkened in the heavens thereof.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.6'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.6.1'>In the year of the death of king Uzziah, I saw the Lord sitting upon a throne, high and lifted up; and his train filled the temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.6.2'>Seraphim were standing above him: each had six wings; with twain he covered his face, and with twain he covered his feet, and with twain he flew.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.6.3'>And one called to the other and said, Holy, holy, holy is Jehovah of hosts; the whole earth is full of his glory!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.6.4'>And the foundations of the thresholds shook at the voice of him that cried, and the house was filled with smoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.6.5'>And I said, Woe unto me! for I am undone; for I am a man of unclean lips, and I dwell in the midst of a people of unclean lips: for mine eyes have seen the King, Jehovah of hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.6.6'>And one of the seraphim flew unto me, and he had in his hand a glowing coal, which he had taken with the tongs from off the altar;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.6.7'>and he made it touch my mouth, and said, Behold, this hath touched thy lips; and thine iniquity is taken away, and thy sin expiated.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.6.8'>And I heard the voice of the Lord saying, Whom shall I send, and who will go for us? And I said, Here am I; send me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.6.9'>And he said, Go; and thou shalt say unto this people, Hearing ye shall hear and shall not understand, and seeing ye shall see and shall not perceive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.6.10'>Make the heart of this people fat, and make their ears heavy, and blind their eyes; lest they see with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and understand with their heart, and be converted, and healed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.6.11'>And I said, Lord, how long? And he said, Until the cities be wasted, without inhabitant, and the houses without man, and the land become an utter desolation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.6.12'>and Jehovah have removed men far away, and the solitude be great in the midst of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.6.13'>But a tenth part shall still be therein, and it shall return and be eaten; as the terebinth and as the oak whose trunk [remaineth] after the felling: the holy seed shall be the trunk thereof.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.7'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.1'>And it came to pass in the days of Ahaz, the son of Jotham, the son of Uzziah, king of Judah, [that] Rezin the king of Syria, and Pekah the son of Remaliah, king of Israel, came up to Jerusalem to make war against it, but they were not able to fight against it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.2'>And it was told the house of David saying, Syria is allied with Ephraim. Then his heart and the heart of his people shook, as the trees of the forest are shaken with the wind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.3'>And Jehovah said to Isaiah, Go out now to meet Ahaz, thou and thy son Shear-jashub, at the end of the aqueduct of the upper pool, on the highway of the fuller's field;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.4'>and thou shalt say unto him, Take heed and be quiet; fear not, and let not thy heart faint before these two ends of smoking firebrands, because of the fierce anger of Rezin and Syria, and of the son of Remaliah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.5'>Inasmuch as Syria hath taken evil counsel against thee, Ephraim [also] and the son of Remaliah, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.6'>Let us go up against Judah, and harass it, and make a breach therein for us, and set up a king therein the son of Tabeal;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.7'>thus saith the Lord Jehovah: It shall not stand, nor come to pass;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.8'>for the head of Syria is Damascus, and the head of Damascus is Rezin; and within sixty-five years shall Ephraim be broken, so as to be no [more a] people;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.9'>and the head of Ephraim is Samaria, and the head of Samaria is Remaliah's son. If ye believe not, surely ye shall not be established.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.10'>And Jehovah spoke again to Ahaz, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.11'>Ask for thee a sign from Jehovah thy God; ask for it in the deep, or in the height above.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.12'>And Ahaz said, I will not ask, and will not tempt Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.13'>And he said, Hear then, house of David: Is it a small matter for you to weary men, that ye weary also my God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.14'>Therefore will the Lord himself give you a sign: Behold, the virgin shall conceive and shall bring forth a son, and call his name Immanuel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.15'>Butter and honey shall he eat, that he may know to refuse the evil, and to choose the good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.16'>For before the child knoweth to refuse the evil and to choose the good, the land whose two kings thou fearest shall be forsaken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.17'>Jehovah will bring upon thee, and upon thy people, and upon thy father's house, days which have not come since the day when Ephraim turned away from Judah [even] the king of Assyria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.18'>And it shall come to pass in that day, that Jehovah will hiss for the fly which is at the extremity of the streams of Egypt, and for the bee which is in the land of Assyria;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.19'>and they shall come and settle all of them in the desolate valleys, and in the holes of the rocks, and on all thorn-bushes, and on all the pastures.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.20'>In that day will the Lord, with a razor which is hired beyond the river, with the king of Assyria, shave the head and the hair of the feet, yea, the beard also will it take away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.21'>And it shall come to pass in that day, [that] a man shall nourish a young cow and two sheep,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.22'>and it shall come to pass, from the abundance of milk they shall give, [that] he shall eat butter; for every one that remaineth in the midst of the land shall eat butter and honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.23'>And it shall come to pass in that day, [that] every place, where there were a thousand vines at a thousand silver pieces, shall become briars and thorns:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.24'>with arrows and with the bow shall they come thither, for the whole land shall become briars and thorns.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.7.25'>And all mountains that have been dug up with the hoe thither will they not come, from fear of briars and thorns; and they shall be for the sending forth of oxen, and for the treading of small cattle.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.8'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.1'>And Jehovah said to me, Take thee a great tablet, and write thereon with a man's style, concerning Maher-shalal-hash-baz.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.2'>And I took unto me to witness, sure witnesses, Urijah the priest, and Zechariah the son of Jeberechiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.3'>And I came near to the prophetess, and she conceived and bore a son; and Jehovah said unto me, Call his name, Maher-shalal-hash-baz.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.4'>For before the lad knoweth to cry, My father! and, My mother! the riches of Damascus and the spoil of Samaria shall be taken away before the king of Assyria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.5'>And Jehovah spoke again to me, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.6'>Forasmuch as this people refuseth the waters of Shiloah which flow softly, and rejoiceth in Rezin and in the son of Remaliah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.7'>therefore behold, the Lord will bring up upon them the waters of the river, strong and many, the king of Assyria and all his glory; and he shall mount up over all his channels, and go over all his banks:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.8'>and he shall pass through Judah; he shall overflow it and go further, he shall reach even to the neck; and the stretching out of his wings shall fill the breadth of thy land, O Immanuel!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.9'>Rage, ye peoples, and be broken in pieces! And give ear, all ye distant parts of the earth: Gird yourselves, and be broken in pieces; gird yourselves, and be broken in pieces!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.10'>Settle a plan, and it shall come to nought; speak a word, and it shall not stand: for God is with us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.11'>For Jehovah spoke thus to me with a strong hand, and he instructed me not to walk in the way of this people, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.12'>Ye shall not say, Conspiracy, of everything of which this people saith, Conspiracy; and fear ye not their fear, and be not in dread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.13'>Jehovah of hosts, him shall ye sanctify; and let him be your fear, and let him be your dread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.14'>And he will be for a sanctuary; and for a stone of stumbling, and for a rock of offence to both the houses of Israel, for a gin and for a snare to the inhabitants of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.15'>And many among them shall stumble, and fall, and be broken, and snared, and taken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.16'>Bind up the testimony, seal the law among my disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.17'>And I will wait for Jehovah, who hideth his face from the house of Jacob; and I will look for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.18'>Behold, I and the children that Jehovah hath given me are for signs and for wonders in Israel, from Jehovah of hosts, who dwelleth in mount Zion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.19'>And when they shall say unto you, Seek unto the necromancers and unto the soothsayers, who chirp and who mutter, [say,] Shall not a people seek unto their God? [Will they go] for the living unto the dead?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.20'>To the law and the testimony! If they speak not according to this word, for them there is no daybreak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.21'>And they shall pass through it, hard pressed and hungry; and it shall come to pass when they are hungry, they will fret themselves, and curse their king and their God, and will gaze upward:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.8.22'>and they will look to the earth; and behold, trouble and darkness, gloom of anguish; and they shall be driven into thick darkness.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.9'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.1'>Nevertheless the darkness shall not be as when the distress was in the [land], at the time he at first lightly, and afterwards heavily, visited the land of Zebulun and the land of Naphtali, the way of the sea, beyond the Jordan, Galilee of the nations:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.2'>the people that walked in darkness have seen a great light; they that dwelt in the land of the shadow of death, upon them light hath shone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.3'>Thou hast multiplied the nation, hast increased its joy: they joy before thee like to the joy in harvest; as [men] rejoice when they divide the spoil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.4'>For thou hast broken the yoke of his burden and the staff of his shoulder, the rod of his oppressor, as in the day of Midian.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.5'>For every boot of him that is shod for the tumult, and the garment rolled in blood, shall be for burning, fuel for fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.6'>For unto us a child is born, unto us a son is given; and the government shall be upon his shoulder; and his name is called Wonderful, Counsellor, Mighty God, Father of Eternity, Prince of Peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.7'>Of the increase of his government and of peace there shall be no end, upon the throne of David and over his kingdom, to establish it, and to uphold it with judgment and with righteousness, from henceforth even for ever. The zeal of Jehovah of hosts will perform this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.8'>The Lord sent a word unto Jacob, and it lighteth upon Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.9'>And all the people shall know [it], Ephraim and the inhabitant of Samaria, that say in pride and stoutness of heart,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.10'>The bricks are fallen down, but we will build with hewn stones; the sycamore trees are cut down, but we will replace them with cedars.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.11'>And Jehovah will set up the adversaries of Rezin against him, and arm his enemies,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.12'>the Syrians on the east, and the Philistines on the west; and they shall devour Israel with open mouth. For all this his anger is not turned away, and his hand is stretched out still.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.13'>But the people turneth not unto him that smiteth them, and they do not seek Jehovah of hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.14'>And Jehovah will cut off from Israel head and tail, palm-branch and rush, in one day:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.15'>the ancient and honourable, he is the head; and the prophet that teacheth lies, he is the tail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.16'>For the guides of this people mislead [them]; and they that are guided by them are swallowed up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.17'>Therefore the Lord will not rejoice in their young men, neither will he have mercy on their fatherless and on their widows; for every one is a hypocrite and an evildoer, and every mouth speaketh folly. For all this his anger is not turned away, and his hand is stretched out still.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.18'>For wickedness burneth as a fire: it devoureth briars and thorns, and kindleth in the thickets of the forest, and they go rolling up like a pillar of smoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.19'>Through the wrath of Jehovah of hosts is the land burned up, and the people is as fuel for fire: a man spareth not his brother;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.20'>and he snatcheth on the right hand, and is hungry, and eateth on the left hand; and they are not satisfied. They eat every man the flesh of his own arm:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.9.21'>Manasseh, Ephraim, and Ephraim, Manasseh; [and] they together are against Judah. For all this his anger is not turned away, and his hand is stretched out still.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.10'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.1'>Woe unto them that decree iniquitous decrees, and to the writers that prescribe oppression,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.2'>to turn away the poor from judgment, and to take away the right from the afflicted of my people; that widows may be their prey, and that they may rob the fatherless!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.3'>And what will ye do in the day of visitation, and in the sudden destruction [which] shall come from far? To whom will ye flee for help, and where will ye leave your glory?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.4'>They can but crouch under the prisoners, and they shall fall under the slain. For all this his anger is not turned away, and his hand is stretched out still.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.5'>Ah! the Assyrian! the rod of mine anger! and the staff in their hand is mine indignation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.6'>I will send him against a hypocritical nation, and against the people of my wrath will I give him a charge; to take the spoil, and to seize the prey, and to tread them down like the mire of the streets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.7'>But he meaneth not so, neither doth his heart think so; for it is in his heart to extirpate and cut off nations not a few.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.8'>For he saith, Are not my princes all kings?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.9'>Is not Calno as Karkemish? Is not Hamath as Arpad? Is not Samaria as Damascus?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.10'>As my hand hath found the kingdoms of the idols, and their graven images exceeded those of Jerusalem and Samaria,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.11'>shall I not, as I have done unto Samaria and her idols, so do to Jerusalem and her images?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.12'>And it shall come to pass, when the Lord hath performed his whole work upon mount Zion and upon Jerusalem, I will punish the fruit of the stoutness of heart of the king of Assyria, and the glory of his high looks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.13'>For he saith, By the strength of my hand I have done [it], and by my wisdom, for I am intelligent; and I have removed the bounds of the peoples, and have robbed their treasures, and, like a valiant man, I have brought down them that sit [on thrones];</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.14'>and my hand hath found as a nest the riches of the peoples, and as one gathereth forsaken eggs, have I gathered all the earth; and there was none that moved the wing, or opened the mouth, or chirped.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.15'>Shall the axe boast itself against him that heweth therewith? shall the saw magnify itself against him that wieldeth it? As if the rod should wield them that lift it up; as if the staff should lift up [him who is] not wood!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.16'>Therefore shall the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, send among his fat ones leanness, and under his glory he shall kindle a burning, like the burning of a fire:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.17'>and the light of Israel shall be for a fire, and his Holy One for a flame; and it shall burn and devour his thorns and his briars in one day,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.18'>and it shall consume the glory of his forest, and of his fruitful field, both soul and body; and they shall be as when a sick man fainteth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.19'>And the remainder of the trees of his forest shall be few: yea, a child might write them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.20'>And it shall come to pass in that day, [that] the remnant of Israel and such as are escaped of the house of Jacob shall no more again rely upon him that smote them; but they shall rely upon Jehovah, the Holy One of Israel, in truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.21'>The remnant shall return, the remnant of Jacob, unto the mighty God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.22'>For though thy people Israel be as the sand of the sea, [only] a remnant of them shall return: the consumption determined shall overflow in righteousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.23'>For a consumption, and [one] determined, will the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, accomplish in the midst of all the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.24'>Therefore thus saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts: O my people that dwellest in Zion, be not afraid of the Assyrian; he shall smite thee with a rod, and shall lift up his staff against thee, after the manner of Egypt:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.25'>for yet a very little while, and the indignation shall be accomplished, and mine anger, in their destruction.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.26'>And Jehovah of hosts will stir up a scourge against him, according to the slaughter of Midian at the rock of Oreb; and his rod [shall be] upon the sea, and he will lift it up after the manner of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.27'>And it shall come to pass in that day, [that] his burden shall be taken away from off thy shoulder, and his yoke from off thy neck; and the yoke shall be destroyed because of the anointing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.28'>He is come to Aiath, he hath passed through Migron; at Michmash he layeth up his baggage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.29'>They are gone through the pass; they make their lodging at Geba: Ramah trembleth, Gibeah of Saul is fled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.30'>Lift up thy voice, daughter of Gallim! Hearken, O Laish! Poor Anathoth!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.31'>Madmenah is fugitive; the inhabitants of Gebim take to flight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.32'>Still a day of halting at Nob; he shaketh his hand [against] the mount of the daughter of Zion, the hill of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.33'>Behold the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, shall lop the boughs with violence; and the high ones of stature shall be hewn down, and the haughty shall be brought low;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.10.34'>and he shall make clearings in the thickets of the forest with iron; and Lebanon shall fall by a mighty one.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.11'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.1'>And there shall come forth a shoot out of the stock of Jesse, and a branch out of his roots shall be fruitful;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.2'>and the Spirit of Jehovah shall rest upon him, the spirit of wisdom and understanding, the spirit of counsel and might, the spirit of knowledge and of the fear of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.3'>And his delight will be in the fear of Jehovah; and he shall not judge after the sight of his eyes, neither reprove after the hearing of his ears;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.4'>but with righteousness shall he judge the poor, and reprove with equity the meek of the earth: and he shall smite the earth with the rod of his mouth, and with the breath of his lips shall he slay the wicked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.5'>And righteousness shall be the girdle of his reins, and faithfulness the girdle of his loins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.6'>The wolf also shall dwell with the lamb, and the leopard shall lie down with the kid, and the calf and the young lion and the fatted beast together, and a little child shall lead them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.7'>And the cow and the she-bear shall feed; their young ones shall lie down together; and the lion shall eat straw like the ox.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.8'>And the sucking child shall play on the hole of the adder, and the weaned child shall put forth its hand to the viper's den.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.9'>They shall not hurt nor destroy in all my holy mountain; for the earth shall be full of the knowledge of Jehovah, as the waters cover the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.10'>And in that day there shall be a root of Jesse, standing as a banner of the peoples: the nations shall seek it; and his resting-place shall be glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.11'>And it shall come to pass in that day, [that] the Lord shall set his hand again the second time to acquire the remnant of his people which shall be left, from Assyria, and from Egypt, and from Pathros, and from Cush, and from Elam, and from Shinar, and from Hamath, and from the islands of the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.12'>And he shall lift up a banner to the nations, and shall assemble the outcasts of Israel, and gather together the dispersed of Judah from the four corners of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.13'>And the envy of Ephraim shall depart, and the troublers of Judah shall be cut off; Ephraim will not envy Judah, and Judah will not trouble Ephraim:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.14'>but they shall fly upon the shoulder of the Philistines towards the west; together shall they spoil the sons of the east; they shall lay their hand upon Edom and Moab, and the children of Ammon shall obey them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.15'>And Jehovah will utterly destroy the tongue of the Egyptian sea; and with his mighty wind will he shake his hand over the river, and will smite it into seven streams, and make [men] go over dryshod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.11.16'>And there shall be a highway for the remnant of his people which will be left, from Assyria; like as it was to Israel in the day when he went up out of the land of Egypt.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.12'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.12.1'>And in that day thou shalt say, Jehovah, I will praise thee; for though thou wast angry with me, thine anger is turned away, and thou hast comforted me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.12.2'>Behold, God is my salvation: I will trust, and not be afraid; for Jah, Jehovah, is my strength and song, and he is become my salvation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.12.3'>And with joy shall ye draw water out of the wells of salvation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.12.4'>And in that day shall ye say, Give ye thanks to Jehovah, call upon his name, declare his deeds among the peoples, make mention that his name is exalted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.12.5'>Sing psalms of Jehovah, for he hath done excellent things: this is known in all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.12.6'>Cry out and shout, thou inhabitress of Zion; for great is the Holy One of Israel in the midst of thee.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.13'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.1'>The burden of Babylon, which Isaiah the son of Amoz saw.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.2'>Lift up a banner upon a bare mountain, raise the voice unto them, shake the hand, that they may enter the gates of the nobles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.3'>I have commanded my hallowed ones, I have also called my mighty men for mine anger, them that rejoice in my highness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.4'>The noise of a multitude on the mountains, as of a great people; a tumultuous noise of the kingdoms of nations assembled together: Jehovah of hosts mustereth the host of the battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.5'>They come from a far country, from the end of the heavens Jehovah, and the weapons of his indignation to destroy the whole land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.6'>Howl, for the day of Jehovah is at hand; it cometh as destruction from the Almighty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.7'>Therefore shall all hands be feeble, and every heart of man shall melt,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.8'>and they shall be terrified: pangs and sorrows shall take hold of them, they shall writhe as a woman that travaileth; they shall be amazed one at another, their faces shall be as flames.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.9'>Behold, the day of Jehovah cometh, cruel both with wrath and fierce anger, to lay the earth desolate; and he will destroy the sinners thereof out of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.10'>For the stars of the heavens and the constellations thereof shall not give their light; the sun shall be darkened in his going forth, and the moon shall not cause her light to shine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.11'>And I will punish the world for evil, and the wicked for their iniquity; and I will make the arrogance of the proud to cease, and will bring low the haughtiness of the violent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.12'>I will make a man more precious than fine gold, even man than the gold of Ophir.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.13'>Therefore I will make the heavens to shake, and the earth shall be removed out of her place, at the wrath of Jehovah of hosts, and in the day of his fierce anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.14'>And it shall be as with a chased roe, and as with a flock that no man gathereth together; every one shall turn to his own people, and every one flee into his own land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.15'>All that are found shall be thrust through; and every one that is in league [with them] shall fall by the sword.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.16'>And their infants shall be dashed in pieces before their eyes, their houses shall be rifled, and their women ravished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.17'>Behold, I will stir up the Medes against them, who do not regard silver, and as for gold, they have no delight in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.18'>And [their] bows shall dash the young men to pieces, and they shall have no pity on the fruit of the womb: their eye shall not spare children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.19'>And Babylon, the glory of kingdoms, the beauty of the Chaldeans' pride, shall be as when God overthrew Sodom and Gomorrah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.20'>It shall never be inhabited, neither shall it be dwelt in, even to generation and generation; nor shall Arabian pitch tent there, nor shepherds make fold there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.21'>But beasts of the desert shall lie there, and their houses shall be full of owls; and ostriches shall dwell there, and wild goats shall dance there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.13.22'>And jackals shall cry to one another in their palaces, and wild dogs in the pleasant castles. And her time is near to come, and her days shall not be prolonged.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.14'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.1'>For Jehovah will have mercy on Jacob, and will yet choose Israel, and set them in rest in their own land; and the stranger shall be united to them, and they shall be joined to the house of Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.2'>And the peoples shall take them and bring them to their place; and the house of Israel shall possess them in the land of Jehovah for servants and handmaids; and they shall take them captive whose captives they were, and they shall rule over their oppressors.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.3'>And it shall come to pass in the day that Jehovah shall give thee rest from thy sorrow and from thy trouble and from the hard bondage wherein thou wast made to serve,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.4'>that thou shalt take up this proverb against the king of Babylon, and say, How hath the oppressor ceased, the exactress of gold ceased!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.5'>Jehovah hath broken the staff of the wicked, the sceptre of the rulers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.6'>He that smote the peoples in wrath with a relentless stroke, he that ruled the nations in anger, is persecuted unsparingly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.7'>The whole earth is at rest, is quiet: they break forth into singing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.8'>Even the cypresses rejoice at thee, the cedars of Lebanon, [saying,] Since thou art laid down, no feller is come up against us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.9'>Sheol from beneath is moved for thee to meet [thee] at thy coming, stirring up the dead for thee, all the he-goats of the earth; making to rise from their thrones all the kings of the nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.10'>All of them shall answer and say unto thee, Art thou also become powerless as we; art thou become like unto us!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.11'>Thy pomp is brought down to Sheol, the noise of thy lyres: the maggot is spread under thee, and worms cover thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.12'>How art thou fallen from heaven, Lucifer, son of the morning! Thou art cut down to the ground, that didst prostrate the nations!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.13'>And thou that didst say in thy heart, I will ascend into the heavens, I will exalt my throne above the stars of God, and I will sit upon the mount of assembly, in the recesses of the north;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.14'>I will ascend above the heights of the clouds, I will be like the Most High:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.15'>none the less art thou brought down to Sheol, to the recesses of the pit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.16'>They that see thee shall narrowly look upon thee; they shall consider thee, [saying,] Is this the man that made the earth to tremble, that shook kingdoms;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.17'>[that] made the world as a wilderness, and overthrew the cities thereof; [that] dismissed not his prisoners homewards?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.18'>All the kings of the nations, all of them, lie in glory, every one in his own house;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.19'>but thou art cast out of thy grave like an abominable branch, covered with the slain those thrust through with the sword, that go down to the stones of the pit: like a carcase trodden under foot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.20'>Thou shalt not be joined with them in burial; for thou hast destroyed thy land, hast slain thy people. Of the seed of evildoers no mention shall be made for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.21'>Prepare ye slaughter for his children, because of the iniquity of their fathers; that they may not rise up and possess the earth, nor fill the face of the world with cities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.22'>For I will rise up against them, saith Jehovah of hosts, and cut off from Babylon name and remnant, and scion and descendant, saith Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.23'>And I will make it a possession for the bittern, and pools of water; and I will sweep it with the besom of destruction, saith Jehovah of hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.24'>Jehovah of hosts hath sworn saying, Assuredly as I have thought, so shall it come to pass; and as I have purposed, it shall stand:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.25'>to break the Assyrian in my land; and upon my mountains will I tread him under foot; and his yoke shall depart from off them, and his burden depart from off their shoulders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.26'>This is the counsel which is purposed concerning the whole earth; and this is the hand which is stretched out upon all the nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.27'>For Jehovah of hosts hath purposed, and who shall frustrate [it]? And his hand is stretched out, and who shall turn it back?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.28'>In the year of the death of king Ahaz was this burden:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.29'>Rejoice not thou, Philistia, all of thee, because the rod that smote thee is broken; for out of the serpent's root shall come forth a viper, and his fruit shall be a fiery flying serpent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.30'>And the firstborn of the poor shall feed, and the needy shall lie down in safety; but I will kill thy root with famine, and thy remnant shall be slain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.31'>Howl, O gate! cry, O city! thou, Philistia, art wholly dissolved; for there cometh from the north a smoke, and none remaineth apart in his gatherings [of troops].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.14.32'>And what shall be answered to the messengers of the nation? That Jehovah hath founded Zion, and the afflicted of his people find refuge in it.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.15'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.15.1'>The burden of Moab: For in the night of being laid waste, Ar of Moab is destroyed; for in the night of being laid waste, Kir of Moab is destroyed!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.15.2'>He is gone up to Bajith, and to Dibon, to the high places, to weep; Moab howleth over Nebo, and over Medeba; on all their heads is baldness, every beard is cut off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.15.3'>In their streets they are girded with sackcloth; on their roofs, and in their broadways, every one howleth, melted into tears.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.15.4'>And Heshbon crieth, and Elealeh: their voice is heard unto Jahaz. Therefore the armed men of Moab cry out: his soul trembleth in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.15.5'>My heart crieth out for Moab; their fugitives [have fled] unto Zoar, unto Eglath-Sheli-shijah: for by the ascent of Luhith, with weeping they go up by it; for in the way of Horonaim they raise up a cry of destruction.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.15.6'>For the waters of Nimrim shall be desolate; for the herbage is withered away, the grass hath failed, there is no green thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.15.7'>Therefore the abundance they have gotten, and that which they have laid up, do they carry away to the torrent of the willows.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.15.8'>For the cry goeth round about the borders of Moab; the howling thereof unto Eglaim, and the howling thereof unto Beer-elim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.15.9'>For the waters of Dimon are full of blood, for I will lay yet more upon Dimon: a lion upon them that are escaped of Moab, and upon that which remaineth of the land.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.16'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.16.1'>Send the lamb of the ruler of the land from the rock to the wilderness, unto the mount of the daughter of Zion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.16.2'>And it shall be [that] as a wandering bird, [as] a scattered nest, so shall the daughters of Moab be at the fords of the Arnon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.16.3'>Bring in counsel, execute justice; make thy shadow as the night in the midst of noonday; hide the outcasts, discover not the fugitive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.16.4'>Let mine outcasts dwell with thee, Moab; be thou a covert to them from the face of the waster. For the extortioner is at an end, the wasting hath ceased, the oppressors are consumed out of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.16.5'>And a throne shall be established in mercy: and in the tent of David there shall sit upon it, in truth, one judging and seeking justice and hastening righteousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.16.6'>We have heard of the arrogance of Moab, [he is] very proud, of his pride, and his arrogance, and his wrath: his pratings are vain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.16.7'>Therefore shall Moab howl for Moab; every one of them shall howl. For the foundations of Kirhareseth shall ye mourn, verily afflicted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.16.8'>For the fields of Heshbon languish, the vine of Sibmah; the lords of the nations have broken down its choice plants: they reached unto Jaazer, they wandered [through] the wilderness; its shoots stretched out, they went beyond the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.16.9'>Therefore I will weep with the weeping of Jaazer for the vine of Sibmah; with my tears will I water thee, Heshbon, and Elealeh, for a cry is fallen upon thy summer fruits and upon thy harvest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.16.10'>And joy and gladness is taken away out of the fruitful field; and in the vineyards there is no singing, neither is there shouting: the treaders tread out no wine in the presses, I have made the cry [of the winepress] to cease.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.16.11'>Therefore my bowels sound like a harp for Moab, and mine inward parts for Kirheres.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.16.12'>And it shall come to pass, when Moab shall appear, shall weary himself on the high place, and enter into his sanctuary to pray, that he shall not prevail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.16.13'>This is the word which Jehovah hath spoken from of old concerning Moab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.16.14'>And now Jehovah speaketh saying, Within three years, as the years of a hired servant, and the glory of Moab shall be brought to nothing, with all that great multitude; and the remnant shall be small, few, of no account.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.17'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.17.1'>The burden of Damascus. Behold, Damascus is taken away from [being] a city, and it shall be a ruinous heap.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.17.2'>The cities of Aroer are forsaken: they shall be for flocks; and they shall lie down and there shall be none to make them afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.17.3'>The fortress also shall cease from Ephraim, and the kingdom from Damascus, and the remnant of Syria: they shall be as the glory of the children of Israel, saith Jehovah of hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.17.4'>And in that day it shall come to pass, that the glory of Jacob shall be made thin, and the fatness of his flesh shall become lean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.17.5'>And it shall be as when the reaper gathereth the corn, and reapeth the ears with his arm; yea, it shall be as he that gathereth ears in the valley of Rephaim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.17.6'>And a gleaning shall be left in it, as at the shaking of an olive-tree: two, three berries above, in the tree-top; four, five in its fruitful boughs, saith Jehovah, the God of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.17.7'>In that day shall man look to his Maker, and his eyes shall have regard to the Holy One of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.17.8'>And he will not look to the altars, the work of his hands, nor have regard to what his fingers have made, neither the Asherahs nor the sun-images.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.17.9'>In that day shall his strong cities be as the forsaken tract in the woodland, and the mountain-top which they forsook before the children of Israel; and there shall be desolation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.17.10'>For thou hast forgotten the God of thy salvation, and hast not been mindful of the rock of thy strength; therefore shalt thou plant pleasant plantations, and shalt set them with foreign slips:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.17.11'>in the day of thy planting wilt thou make [them] to grow, and on the morrow wilt thou make thy seed to flourish; [but] the harvest will flee in the day of taking possession, and the sorrow will be incurable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.17.12'>Ha! a tumult of many peoples! they make a noise as the noise of the seas; and the rushing of nations! they rush as the rushing of mighty waters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.17.13'>The nations rush as the rushing of many waters; but he will rebuke them, and they shall flee far away, and shall be chased as the chaff of the mountains before the wind, and like a whirling [of dust] before the whirlwind:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.17.14'>behold, at eventide, trouble; before the morning they are not. This is the portion of them that spoil us, and the lot of them that rob us.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.18'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.18.1'>Ha! land shadowing with wings, which art beyond the rivers of Cush,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.18.2'>that sendest ambassadors over the sea, and in vessels of papyrus upon the waters, [saying,] Go, swift messengers, to a nation scattered and ravaged, to a people terrible from their existence and thenceforth; to a nation of continued waiting and of treading down, whose land the rivers have spoiled!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.18.3'>All ye inhabitants of the world, and dwellers on the earth, when a banner is lifted up on the mountains, see ye, and when a trumpet is blown, hear ye!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.18.4'>For thus hath Jehovah said unto me: I will take my rest, and I will observe from my dwelling-place like clear heat upon herbs, like a cloud of dew in the heat of harvest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.18.5'>For before the harvest, when the blossoming is over, and the flower becometh a ripening grape, he shall both cut off the sprigs with pruning-knives, and take away [and] cut down the branches.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.18.6'>They shall be left together unto the mountain birds of prey, and to the beasts of the earth; and the birds of prey shall summer upon them, and all the beasts of the earth shall winter upon them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.18.7'>In that time shall a present be brought unto Jehovah of hosts of a people scattered and ravaged, and from a people terrible from their existence and thenceforth, a nation of continued waiting and of treading down, whose land the rivers have spoiled, to the place of the name of Jehovah of hosts, the mount Zion.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.19'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.1'>The burden of Egypt. Behold, Jehovah rideth upon a swift cloud, and cometh to Egypt; and the idols of Egypt are moved at his presence, and the heart of Egypt melteth in the midst of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.2'>And I will incite the Egyptians against the Egyptians; and they shall fight every one against his brother, and every one against his neighbour; city against city, kingdom against kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.3'>And the spirit of Egypt shall fail in the midst of it, and I will destroy the counsel thereof; and they shall seek unto the idols and unto the conjurers, and unto the necromancers, and unto the soothsayers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.4'>And the Egyptians will I give over into the hand of a cruel lord, and a fierce king shall rule over them, saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.5'>And the waters shall fail from the sea, and the river shall be wasted and dried up;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.6'>and the rivers shall stink, and the streams of Egypt shall be diminished and drain away: the reeds and sedges shall wither.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.7'>The meadows by the Nile, on the banks of the Nile, and everything sown by the Nile, shall be dried up, be driven away, and be no [more].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.8'>And the fishers shall mourn, and all they that cast fish-hook into the Nile shall lament, and they that spread net upon the waters shall languish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.9'>And they that work in fine flax, and they that weave white stuffs shall be ashamed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.10'>And her pillars shall be broken in pieces, and all workers for hire shall be sad of soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.11'>They are but fools, the princes of Zoan, the wise counsellors of Pharaoh: [their] counsel is become senseless. How say ye unto Pharaoh, I am the son of the wise, the son of ancient kings?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.12'>Where are they then, thy wise [men]? Let them now tell thee, and let them make known what Jehovah of hosts hath purposed upon Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.13'>The princes of Zoan are become foolish, the princes of Noph are deceived; and the corner-stones of its tribes have caused Egypt to err.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.14'>Jehovah hath mingled a spirit of perverseness in the midst thereof; and they have caused Egypt to err in every work thereof, as a drunkard staggereth in his vomit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.15'>Neither shall there be any work for Egypt, which the head or tail, palm-branch or rush, may do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.16'>In that day shall Egypt be like unto women; and it shall tremble and fear because of the shaking of the hand of Jehovah of hosts, which he shaketh over it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.17'>And the land of Judah shall be a dismay unto Egypt: every one that thinketh of it shall be afraid for himself, because of the counsel of Jehovah of hosts, which he hath purposed against it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.18'>In that day shall there be five cities in the land of Egypt speaking the language of Canaan, and swearing by Jehovah of hosts: one shall be called, The city of Heres.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.19'>In that day shall there be an altar to Jehovah in the midst of the land of Egypt, and a pillar at the border thereof to Jehovah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.20'>and it shall be for a sign and for a witness to Jehovah of hosts in the land of Egypt; for they shall cry unto Jehovah because of the oppressors, and he will send them a saviour and defender, who shall deliver them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.21'>And Jehovah shall be known to the Egyptians, and the Egyptians shall know Jehovah in that day, and shall serve with sacrifice and oblation; and they shall vow a vow unto Jehovah, and perform it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.22'>And Jehovah will smite Egypt; he will smite and heal: and they shall return to Jehovah, and he will be entreated of them, and will heal them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.23'>In that day shall there be a highway out of Egypt to Assyria; and the Assyrian shall come into Egypt, and the Egyptian into Assyria; and Egypt shall serve with Assyria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.24'>In that day shall Israel be the third with Egypt and with Assyria, a blessing in the midst of the earth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.19.25'>whom Jehovah of hosts will bless, saying, Blessed be Egypt my people, and Assyria the work of my hands, and Israel mine inheritance!</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.20'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.20.1'>In the year that Tartan came to Ashdod, when Sargon the king of Assyria sent him, (and he fought against Ashdod and took it,)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.20.2'>at that time spoke Jehovah by Isaiah the son of Amoz, saying, Go and loose the sackcloth from off thy loins, and put off thy sandal from thy foot. And he did so, walking naked and barefoot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.20.3'>And Jehovah said, Like as my servant Isaiah hath walked naked and barefoot three years, a sign and a wonder concerning Egypt and concerning Ethiopia,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.20.4'>so shall the king of Assyria lead away the captives of Egypt and the exiles of Ethiopia, young and old, naked and barefoot, and with buttocks uncovered, [to] the shame of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.20.5'>And they shall be terrified and ashamed of Ethiopia their confidence, and of Egypt their boast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.20.6'>And the inhabitants of this coast shall say in that day, Behold, such is our confidence, whither we fled for help to be delivered from the king of Assyria; and how shall we escape?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.21'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.1'>The burden of the desert of the sea. As whirlwinds in the south pass through, so it cometh from the desert, from a terrible land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.2'>A grievous vision is declared unto me: the treacherous dealeth treacherously, and the spoiler spoileth. Go up, Elam! besiege, Media! All the sighing thereof have I made to cease.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.3'>Therefore are my loins filled with pain; anguish hath taken hold upon me, as the anguish of a woman in travail: I am bowed down so as not to hear, I am dismayed so as not to see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.4'>My heart panteth, horror affrighteth me: the night of my pleasure hath he turned into trembling unto me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.5'>Prepare the table, appoint the watch; eat, drink: arise, ye princes, anoint the shield.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.6'>For thus hath the Lord said unto me: Go, set a watchman, let him declare what he seeth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.7'>And he saw chariots, horsemen by pairs, a chariot with asses, a chariot with camels; and he hearkened diligently with much heed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.8'>And he cried [as] a lion, Lord, I stand continually upon the watchtower in the daytime, and I am set in my ward whole nights.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.9'>And behold, there cometh a chariot of men; horsemen by pairs. And he answered and said, Babylon is fallen, is fallen; and all the graven images of her gods he hath broken unto the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.10'>O my threshing, and the corn of my floor! What I have heard of Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, have I declared unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.11'>The burden of Dumah. He calleth to me out of Seir, Watchman, what of the night? Watchman, what of the night?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.12'>The watchman said, The morning cometh, and also the night: if ye will inquire, inquire; return, come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.13'>The burden against Arabia. In the forest of Arabia shall ye lodge, [ye] caravans of Dedanites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.14'>Bring ye water to meet the thirsty! The inhabitants of the land of Tema come forth with their bread for him that fleeth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.15'>For they flee from the swords, from the drawn sword, and from the bent bow, and from the grievousness of war.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.16'>For thus hath the Lord said unto me: Within a year, according to the years of a hired servant, and all the glory of Kedar shall fail;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.21.17'>and the residue of the number of the archers, the mighty men of the sons of Kedar, shall be diminished: for Jehovah, the God of Israel, hath spoken.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.22'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.1'>The burden of the valley of vision. What aileth thee now, that thou art wholly gone up to the housetops?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.2'>Thou that wast full of stir, a town of tumult, a joyous city: thy slain men are not slain with the sword, nor dead in battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.3'>All thy rulers have fled together, they are taken prisoners without the bow: all that are found of thee are made prisoners together; they were fleeing far off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.4'>Therefore said I, Look away from me; let me weep bitterly: labour not to comfort me, because of the spoiling of the daughter of my people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.5'>For it is a day of trouble, and of treading down, and of perplexity, from the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, in the valley of vision; [a day of] breaking down the wall, and of crying to the mountain:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.6'>Elam beareth the quiver with chariots of men [and] horsemen; and Kir uncovereth the shield.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.7'>And it shall come to pass [that] thy choicest valleys shall be full of chariots, and the horsemen shall set themselves in array at the gate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.8'>And he uncovereth the covering of Judah: and thou didst look in that day to the armour in the house of the forest;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.9'>and ye have seen the breaches of the city of David, that they are many; and ye have gathered together the waters of the lower pool;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.10'>and ye have numbered the houses of Jerusalem, and have broken down the houses to fortify the wall;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.11'>and ye have made a reservoir between the two walls for the water of the old pool: but ye have not had regard unto the maker thereof, neither have ye looked unto him that fashioned it long ago.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.12'>And in that day did the Lord Jehovah of hosts call to weeping, and to mourning, and to baldness, and to girding with sackcloth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.13'>and behold joy and rejoicing, slaying oxen, and killing sheep, eating flesh, and drinking wine: Let us eat and drink, for to-morrow we die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.14'>And it was revealed in mine ears by Jehovah of hosts: Assuredly this iniquity shall not be purged from you till ye die, saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.15'>Thus saith the Lord Jehovah of hosts: Go, get thee in unto this steward, unto Shebna, who is over the house, [and say,]</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.16'>What hast thou here? and whom hast thou here, that thou hast hewn thee out a sepulchre here, [as] he that heweth out his sepulchre on high, cutting out in the rock a habitation for himself?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.17'>Behold, Jehovah will hurl thee with the force of a mighty man, and will cover thee entirely.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.18'>Rolling thee up completely, he will roll thee as a ball into a wide country: there shalt thou die, and there shall be the chariots of thy glory, O shame of thy lord's house!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.19'>And I will drive thee from thine office, and from thy station will I pull thee down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.20'>And it shall come to pass in that day, that I will call my servant Eliakim the son of Hilkijah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.21'>and I will clothe him with thy robe, and strengthen him with thy girdle, and I will commit thy government into his hand; and he shall be a father to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and to the house of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.22'>And the key of the house of David will I lay upon his shoulder; and he shall open, and none shall shut; and he shall shut, and none shall open.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.23'>And I will fasten him [as] a nail in a sure place; and he shall be for a throne of glory to his father's house:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.24'>and they shall hang upon him all the glory of his father's house, the offspring and the issue, all the small vessels, as well the vessels of cups as all the vessels of flagons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.22.25'>In that day, saith Jehovah of hosts, shall the nail that is fastened in a sure place be removed, and be cut down, and fall; and the burden that was upon it shall be cut off: for Jehovah hath spoken.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.23'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.1'>The burden of Tyre. Howl, ye ships of Tarshish! for it is laid waste, so that there is no house, none entering in. From the land of Chittim it is revealed to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.2'>Be still, ye inhabitants of the isle! The merchants of Sidon, that pass over the sea, have replenished thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.3'>And on great waters, the seed of Shihor, the harvest of the Nile, was her revenue; and she was the market of the nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.4'>Be thou ashamed, Sidon, for the sea hath spoken, the strength of the sea, saying, I have not travailed nor brought forth, neither have I nourished young men [nor] brought up virgins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.5'>When the report came into Egypt, they were sorely pained at the news of Tyre.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.6'>Pass over to Tarshish; howl, ye inhabitants of the coast!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.7'>Is this your joyous [city], whose antiquity is of ancient days? Her feet shall carry her afar off to sojourn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.8'>Who hath purposed this against Tyre, the distributor of crowns, whose merchants were princes, whose dealers were the honourable of the earth?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.9'>Jehovah of hosts hath purposed it, to profane the pride of all glory, to bring to nought all the honourable of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.10'>Overflow thy land like the Nile, daughter of Tarshish: there is no more restraint.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.11'>He hath stretched out his hand over the sea, he shaketh the kingdoms. Jehovah hath given a commandment concerning Canaan, to destroy the strongholds thereof,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.12'>and hath said, Thou shalt no more exult, [thou] oppressed virgin, daughter of Sidon: get thee up, pass over to Chittim; even there shalt thou have no rest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.13'>Behold the land of the Chaldeans: this people did not exist; the Assyrian founded it for the dwellers in the desert: they set up their towers, they destroyed the palaces thereof; he brought it to ruin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.14'>Howl, ships of Tarshish! for your fortress is laid waste.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.15'>And it shall come to pass in that day, that Tyre shall be forgotten seventy years, according to the days of one king. At the end of seventy years it shall be for Tyre as the harlot's song.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.16'>Take a harp, go about the city, thou forgotten harlot! Make sweet melody, sing many songs, that thou mayest be remembered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.17'>And it shall come to pass at the end of seventy years, that Jehovah will visit Tyre; and she will return to her hire, and will commit fornication with all the kingdoms of the earth upon the face of the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.23.18'>And her merchandise and her hire shall be holy to Jehovah: it shall not be treasured nor laid up; for her merchandise shall be for them that dwell before Jehovah, to eat and be sufficed, and for excellent clothing.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.24'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.1'>Behold, Jehovah maketh the land empty, and maketh it waste, and turneth it upside down, and scattereth abroad its inhabitants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.2'>And it shall be, as with the people, so with the priest; as with the servant, so with his master; as with the maid, so with her mistress; as with the buyer, so with the seller; as with the lender, so with the borrower; as with the taker of usury, so with him from whom usury is taken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.3'>The land shall be utterly emptied, and utterly spoiled; for Jehovah hath spoken this word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.4'>The land mourneth, it fadeth away; the world languisheth, it fadeth away: the haughty people of the land do languish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.5'>And the land is polluted under the inhabitants thereof; for they have violated the laws, changed the statute, broken the everlasting covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.6'>Therefore doth the curse devour the earth, and they that dwell therein are held guilty; therefore the inhabitants of the earth are consumed, and few men are left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.7'>The new wine mourneth, the vine languisheth, all that were merry-hearted do sigh;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.8'>the mirth of tambours ceaseth, the noise of them that rejoice endeth, the joy of the harp ceaseth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.9'>They do not drink wine with a song; strong drink is bitter to them that drink it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.10'>The city of solitude is broken down; every house is shut up, so that none entereth in.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.11'>There is a crying for wine in the streets; all joy is darkened, the mirth of the land is gone;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.12'>desolation remaineth in the city, and the gate is smitten, a ruin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.13'>For so will it be in the midst of the land among the peoples, as the shaking of an olive-tree, as the grape-gleanings when the vintage is done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.14'>These shall lift up their voice, they shall shout for the majesty of Jehovah, they shall cry aloud from the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.15'>Therefore glorify Jehovah in the east, the name of Jehovah, the God of Israel, in the isles of the west.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.16'>From the end of the earth have we heard songs: Glory to the righteous! And I said, My leanness, my leanness, woe unto me! The treacherous have dealt treacherously; yea, the treacherous have dealt very treacherously.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.17'>Fear, and the pit, and the snare are upon thee, inhabitant of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.18'>And it shall come to pass, [that] he who fleeth from the sound of the fear shall fall into the pit; and he that cometh up out of the midst of the pit shall be taken in the snare; for the windows on high are open, and the foundations of the earth shake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.19'>The earth is utterly broken down, the earth is completely dissolved, the earth is violently moved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.20'>The earth reeleth to and fro like a drunkard, and is shaken like a night hut; and its transgression is heavy upon it; and it falleth and shall not rise again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.21'>And it shall come to pass in that day, [that] Jehovah will punish the host of the high ones on high, and the kings of the earth upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.22'>And they shall be brought together, [as] an assemblage of prisoners for the pit, and shall be shut up in prison, and after many days shall they be visited.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.24.23'>And the moon shall be confounded, and the sun ashamed; for Jehovah of hosts shall reign on mount Zion, and in Jerusalem, and before his ancients in glory.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.25'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.25.1'>Jehovah, thou art my God: I will exalt thee; I will celebrate thy name, for thou hast done wonderful things; counsels of old [which are] faithfulness [and] truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.25.2'>For thou hast made of the city a heap, of the fortified town a ruin, the palace of strangers to be no city; it shall never be built up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.25.3'>Therefore shall the mighty people glorify thee, the city of terrible nations shall fear thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.25.4'>For thou hast been a fortress to the poor, a fortress for the needy in his distress, a refuge from the storm, a shadow from the heat: for the blast of the terrible ones [has been] as the storm [against] a wall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.25.5'>Thou hast subdued the tumult of strangers, as the heat in a dry place; [as] the heat, by the shadow of a cloud, [so] the song of the terrible ones is brought low.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.25.6'>And in this mountain will Jehovah of hosts make unto all peoples a feast of fat things, a feast of wines on the lees, of fat things full of marrow, of wines on the lees well refined.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.25.7'>And he will destroy in this mountain the face of the veil which veileth all the peoples, and the covering that is spread over all the nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.25.8'>He will swallow up death in victory. And the Lord Jehovah will wipe away tears from off all faces; and the reproach of his people will he take away from off all the earth: for Jehovah hath spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.25.9'>And it shall be said in that day, Behold, this is our God; we have waited for him, and he will save us: this is Jehovah, we have waited for him; we will be glad and rejoice in his salvation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.25.10'>For in this mountain shall the hand of Jehovah rest, and Moab shall be trodden down under him, as straw is trodden down in the dunghill;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.25.11'>and he shall spread forth his hands in the midst of them, as he that swimmeth spreadeth them forth to swim; and he shall bring down their pride together with the plots of their hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.25.12'>And the fortress of the high defences of thy walls will he bring down, lay low, bring to the ground, into the dust.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.26'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.1'>In that day shall this song be sung in the land of Judah: We have a strong city; salvation doth he appoint for walls and bulwarks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.2'>Open ye the gates, and the righteous nation which keepeth faithfulness shall enter in.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.3'>Thou wilt keep in perfect peace the mind stayed [on thee], for he confideth in thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.4'>Confide ye in Jehovah for ever; for in Jah, Jehovah, is the rock of ages.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.5'>For he bringeth down them that dwell on high; the lofty city, he layeth it low, he layeth it low to the ground, he bringeth it even to the dust.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.6'>The foot shall tread it down, the feet of the afflicted, the steps of the poor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.7'>The way of the just is uprightness: thou, the Upright, dost make the path of the just even.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.8'>Yea, in the way of thy judgments, O Jehovah, have we waited for thee; the desire of [our] soul is to thy name, and to thy memorial.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.9'>With my soul have I desired thee in the night; yea, with my spirit within me I seek thee early: for when thy judgments are in the earth, the inhabitants of the world learn righteousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.10'>If favour be shewn to the wicked, he doth not learn righteousness: in the land of uprightness he dealeth unjustly, and beholdeth not the majesty of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.11'>Jehovah, thy hand is lifted up, but they do not see: [yet] they shall see [thy] jealousy [for] the people, and be ashamed; yea, the fire which is for thine adversaries shall devour them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.12'>Jehovah, thou wilt ordain peace for us; for thou also hast wrought all our works for us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.13'>Jehovah our God, other lords than thee have had dominion over us; by thee only will we make mention of thy name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.14'>[They are] dead, they shall not live; deceased, they shall not rise: for thou hast visited and destroyed them, and made all memory of them to perish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.15'>Thou hast increased the nation, Jehovah, thou hast increased the nation: thou art glorified. Thou hadst removed [it] far [unto] all the ends of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.16'>Jehovah, in trouble they sought thee; they poured out [their] whispered prayer when thy chastening was upon them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.17'>As a woman with child, that draweth near her delivery, is in travail, [and] crieth out in her pangs; so have we been before thee, Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.18'>We have been with child, we have been in travail, we have as it were brought forth wind; we have not wrought the deliverance of the land, neither have the inhabitants of the world fallen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.19'>Thy dead shall live, my dead bodies shall arise. Awake and sing in triumph, ye that dwell in dust; for thy dew is the dew of the morning, and the earth shall cast forth the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.20'>Come, my people, enter into thy chambers, and shut thy doors about thee; hide thyself just for a little moment, until the indignation be past.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.26.21'>For behold, Jehovah cometh out of his place to visit the iniquity of the inhabitants of the earth upon them; and the earth shall disclose her blood, and shall no more cover her slain.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.27'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.27.1'>In that day Jehovah, with his sore and great and strong sword, will visit leviathan the fleeing serpent, and leviathan the crooked serpent; and he will slay the monster that is in the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.27.2'>In that day [there shall be] a vineyard of pure wine; sing concerning it:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.27.3'>I Jehovah keep it, I will water it every moment; lest any harm it, I will keep it night and day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.27.4'>Fury is not in me. Oh that I had briars [and] thorns in battle against me! I would march against them, I would burn them together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.27.5'>Or let him take hold of my strength; let him make peace with me: [yea,] let him make peace with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.27.6'>In the future Jacob shall take root; Israel shall blossom and bud, and they shall fill the face of the world with fruit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.27.7'>Hath he smitten him according to the smiting of those that smote him? Is he slain according to the slaughter of those slain by him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.27.8'>In measure, when sending her away, didst thou contend with her: he hath taken [her] away with his rough wind in the day of the east wind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.27.9'>By this, therefore, shall the iniquity of Jacob be purged; and this is all the fruit of the taking away of his sin: when he shall make all the stones of the altar as chalkstones that are crumbled in pieces, the Asherahs and the sun-images shall not stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.27.10'>For the fortified city is solitary, a habitation abandoned and forsaken like a wilderness; there shall the calf feed, and there shall he lie down, and consume its boughs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.27.11'>When its branches are withered they shall be broken off; women shall come [and] set them on fire. For it is a people of no intelligence; therefore he that made them will not have mercy on them, and he who formed them will shew them no favour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.27.12'>And it shall come to pass in that day, that Jehovah shall beat out from the flood of the river unto the torrent of Egypt, and ye shall be gathered one by one, [ye] children of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.27.13'>And it shall come to pass in that day, [that] the great trumpet shall be blown; and they shall come that were perishing in the land of Assyria, and the outcasts in the land of Egypt, and they shall worship Jehovah in the holy mountain at Jerusalem.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.28'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.1'>Woe to the crown of pride of the drunkards of Ephraim, and to the fading flower of his glorious adornment, which is on the head of the fat valley of them that are overcome with wine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.2'>Behold, the Lord hath a mighty and strong one, as a storm of hail [and] a destroying tempest; as a storm of mighty waters overflowing, shall he cast down to the earth with might.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.3'>The crown of pride of the drunkards of Ephraim shall be trodden under feet;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.4'>and the fading flower of his glorious adornment which is on the head of the fat valley shall be like an early fig before the summer: as soon as he that seeth it perceiveth it, scarcely is it in his hand, he swalloweth it down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.5'>In that day will Jehovah of hosts be for a crown of glory, and for a diadem of beauty, unto the remnant of his people;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.6'>and for a spirit of judgment to him that sitteth in judgment, and for strength to them that turn the battle to the gate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.7'>But these also have erred through wine, and through strong drink are they gone astray. The priest and the prophet have erred through strong drink; they are overpowered by wine, they are gone astray through strong drink; they have erred in vision, they have stumbled [in] judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.8'>For all tables are full of filthy vomit, so that there is no [more] place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.9'>Whom shall he teach knowledge? and whom shall he make to understand the report? Them that are weaned from the milk, withdrawn from the breasts?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.10'>For [it is] precept upon precept, precept upon precept; line upon line, line upon line; here a little, there a little.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.11'>For with stammering lips and a strange tongue will he speak to this people;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.12'>to whom he said, This is the rest: cause the weary to rest; and this is the refreshing. But they would not hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.13'>And the word of Jehovah was unto them precept upon precept, precept upon precept, line upon line, line upon line, here a little, there a little: that they might go, and fall backward, and be broken, and snared, and taken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.14'>Therefore hear the word of Jehovah, ye scornful men, that rule this people which is in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.15'>For ye have said, We have made a covenant with death, and with Sheol have we made an agreement; when the overflowing scourge shall pass through, it shall not come unto us; for we have made lies our refuge, and under falsehood have we hid ourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.16'>Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I lay for foundation in Zion a stone, a tried stone, a precious corner-stone, a sure foundation: he that trusteth shall not make haste.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.17'>And I will appoint judgment for a line, and righteousness for a plummet; and the hail shall sweep away the refuge of lies, and the waters shall overflow the hiding-place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.18'>And your covenant with death shall be annulled, and your agreement with Sheol shall not stand; when the overflowing scourge shall pass through, ye shall be trodden down by it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.19'>As it passeth through it shall take you; for morning by morning shall it pass through, by day and by night; and it shall be terror only to understand the report.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.20'>For the bed is too short to stretch oneself on, and the covering too narrow when he would wrap himself in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.21'>For Jehovah will rise up as on mount Perazim, he will be moved with anger as in the valley of Gibeon; that he may do his work, his strange work, and perform his act, his unwonted act.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.22'>Now therefore be ye not scorners, lest your bonds be made strong; for I have heard from the Lord Jehovah of hosts a consumption, and [one] determined, upon the whole land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.23'>Give ear, and hear my voice; hearken, and hear my speech.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.24'>Doth the ploughman plough all day to sow? Is he [all day] opening and breaking the clods of his land?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.25'>Doth he not, when he hath levelled the face thereof, cast abroad dill, and scatter cummin, and set the wheat in rows, and the barley in an appointed place, and the rye in its border?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.26'>His God doth instruct him in [his] judgment, he doth teach him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.27'>For the dill is not threshed with a threshing instrument, neither is a cart-wheel turned about upon the cummin; but dill is beaten out with a staff, and cummin with a rod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.28'>Bread [corn] is crushed, because he will not ever be threshing it; and if he drove the wheels of his cart and his horses [over it], he would not crush it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.28.29'>This also cometh forth from Jehovah of hosts; he is wonderful in counsel, great in wisdom.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.29'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.1'>Woe to Ariel, to Ariel, the city of David's encampment! Add ye year to year; let the feasts come round.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.2'>But I will distress Ariel, and there shall be sorrow and sadness; and it shall be unto me as an Ariel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.3'>And I will camp against thee round about, and will lay siege against thee with watch-posts, and I will raise forts against thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.4'>And thou shalt be brought low, thou shalt speak out of the ground, and thy speech shall come low out of the dust, and thy voice shall be as of one that hath a familiar spirit, out of the ground, and thy speech shall whisper out of the dust.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.5'>And the multitude of thine enemies shall be like small dust, and the multitude of the terrible ones as chaff that passeth away; and it shall be in an instant, suddenly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.6'>Thou shalt be visited by Jehovah of hosts with thunder and with earthquake and great noise, with whirlwind and tempest, and the flame of devouring fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.7'>And the multitude of all the nations that war against Ariel, even all that war against her and her fortifications, and that distress her, shall be as a dream of a night vision.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.8'>It shall even be as when the hungry dreameth, and, behold, he eateth; and he awaketh, and his soul is empty; or as when the thirsty dreameth, and, behold, he drinketh; and he awaketh, and, behold, he is faint, and his soul craveth: so shall the multitude of all the nations be that war against mount Zion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.9'>Be astounded and astonished, blind yourselves and be blind! They are drunken, but not with wine; they stagger, but not with strong drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.10'>For Jehovah hath poured out upon you a spirit of deep sleep, and hath closed your eyes; the prophets and your chiefs, the seers, hath he covered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.11'>And the whole vision is become unto you as the words of a book that is sealed, which they give to one that can read, saying, Read this, I pray thee; and he saith, I cannot, for it is sealed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.12'>And they give the book to him that cannot read, saying, Read this, I pray thee; and he saith, I cannot read.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.13'>And the Lord saith, Forasmuch as this people draw near with their mouth, and honour me with their lips, but their heart is removed far from me, and their fear of me is a commandment taught of men;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.14'>therefore, behold, I will proceed to do marvellously with this people, to do marvellously, even with wonder, and the wisdom of their wise [men] shall perish, and the understanding of their intelligent ones shall be hid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.15'>Woe unto them that hide deep, far from Jehovah, their counsel! And their works are in the dark, and they say, Who seeth us? and who knoweth us?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.16'>[Oh] your perverseness! Shall the potter be esteemed as the clay, so that the work should say of him that made it, He made me not; or the thing formed say of him that formed it, He hath no understanding?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.17'>Is it not yet a very little while, and Lebanon shall be turned into a fruitful field, and the fruitful field shall be esteemed as a forest?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.18'>And in that day shall the deaf hear the words of the book, and, out of obscurity and out of darkness, the eyes of the blind shall see;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.19'>and the meek shall increase their joy in Jehovah, and the needy among men shall rejoice in the Holy One of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.20'>For the terrible one shall come to nought, and the scorner shall be no more, and all that watch for iniquity shall be cut off,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.21'>that make a man an offender for a word, and lay a snare for him that reproveth in the gate, and pervert [the judgment of] the righteous by futility.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.22'>Therefore thus saith Jehovah who redeemed Abraham, concerning the house of Jacob: Jacob shall not now be ashamed, neither shall his face now be pale;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.23'>for when he seeth his children, the work of my hands, in the midst of him, they shall hallow my name, and hallow the Holy One of Jacob, and shall fear the God of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.29.24'>And they that are of erring spirit shall know understanding, and the disobedient shall learn doctrine.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.30'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.1'>Woe to the rebellious children, saith Jehovah, who take counsel, but not of me, and who make leagues, but not by my Spirit, that they may heap sin upon sin;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.2'>who walk to go down into Egypt, and have not asked of my mouth, to take refuge under the protection of Pharaoh, and trust in the shadow of Egypt!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.3'>For to you the protection of Pharaoh shall be a shame, and the trust in the shadow of Egypt a confusion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.4'>For his princes were at Zoan, and his ambassadors came to Hanes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.5'>They were all ashamed of a people [that] did not profit them, nor were a help or profit, but a shame, and also a reproach.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.6'>The burden of the beasts of the south: Through a land of trouble and anguish, whence come the lioness and lion, the viper and fiery flying serpent, they carry their riches upon the shoulders of asses, and their treasures upon the bunches of camels, to the people that shall not profit [them].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.7'>For Egypt shall help in vain, and to no purpose; therefore have I named her, Arrogance, that doeth nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.8'>Now go, write it before them on a tablet, and record it in a book, that it may be for the time to come, as a witness for ever,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.9'>that this is a rebellious people, lying children, children that will not hear the law of Jehovah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.10'>who say to the seers, See not; and to the prophets, Prophesy not unto us right things; speak unto us smooth things, prophesy deceits;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.11'>get you out of the way, turn aside out of the path, cause the Holy One of Israel to cease from before us!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.12'>Therefore thus saith the Holy One of Israel: Because ye reject this word, and confide in oppression and wilfulness, and depend thereon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.13'>therefore this iniquity shall be to you as a breach ready to fall, swelling out in a towering wall, whose breaking shall come suddenly in an instant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.14'>And he shall break it as the breaking of a potter's vessel, that is broken in pieces unsparingly; and in the pieces of it there shall not be found a sherd to take fire from the hearth, or to scoop water out of the cistern.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.15'>For thus saith the Lord Jehovah, the Holy One of Israel: In returning and rest shall ye be saved, in quietness and confidence shall be your strength; but ye would not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.16'>And ye said, No, but we will flee upon horses, therefore shall ye flee; and, We will ride upon the swift, therefore shall they that pursue you be swift.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.17'>One thousand [shall flee] at the rebuke of one; at the rebuke of five shall ye flee: till ye be left as a beacon upon the top of a mountain, and as a banner on a hill.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.18'>And therefore will Jehovah wait, that he may be gracious unto you, and therefore will he lift himself up, that he may have mercy upon you; for Jehovah is a God of judgment: blessed are all they that wait for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.19'>For the people shall dwell in Zion, at Jerusalem. Thou shalt weep no more; he will be very gracious unto thee at the voice of thy cry; as he heareth it, he will answer thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.20'>And the Lord will give you the bread of adversity, and the water of oppression; yet thy teachers shall not be hidden any more, but thine eyes shall see thy teachers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.21'>And when ye turn to the right hand or when ye turn to the left, thine ears shall hear a word behind thee, saying, This is the way, walk ye in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.22'>And ye shall defile the silver covering of your graven images, and the gold overlaying of your molten images; thou shalt cast them away as a menstruous cloth: Out! shalt thou say unto it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.23'>And he will give the rain of thy seed with which thou shalt sow the ground; and bread, the produce of the ground, and it shall be fat and rich. In that day shall thy cattle feed in large pastures;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.24'>and the oxen and the asses that till the ground shall eat salted provender, which hath been winnowed with the shovel and with the fan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.25'>And there shall be upon every high mountain and upon every hill that is lifted up, brooks [and] water-courses, in the day of the great slaughter, when the towers fall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.26'>And the light of the moon shall be as the light of the sun, and the light of the sun shall be sevenfold, as the light of seven days, in the day that Jehovah bindeth up the breach of his people, and healeth the wound of their stroke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.27'>Behold, the name of Jehovah cometh from far, burning [with] his anger a grievous conflagration; his lips are full of indignation, and his tongue as a consuming fire;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.28'>and his breath as an overflowing torrent, which reacheth even to the neck, to sift the nations with the sieve of destruction, and [to put] a bridle into the jaws of the peoples, that causeth them to go astray.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.29'>Ye shall have a song, as in the night when a feast is sanctified; and joy of heart, as of one who goeth with a pipe to come unto the mountain of Jehovah, to the Rock of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.30'>And Jehovah will cause the majesty of his voice to be heard, and will shew the lighting down of his arm with indignation of anger, and a flame of consuming fire, with waterflood and storm and hailstones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.31'>For through the voice of Jehovah shall the Assyrian be broken down: he will smite [him] with the rod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.32'>And wherever shall pass the appointed staff, which Jehovah shall lay upon him, it shall be with tambours and harps; and with tumultuous battles will he fight with it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.30.33'>For Topheth is prepared of old; for the king also it is prepared: he hath made it deep and large; its pile is fire and much wood; the breath of Jehovah, like a stream of brimstone, doth kindle it.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.31'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.31.1'>Woe to them that go down to Egypt for help, and depend on horses, and confide in chariots because [they are] many, and in horsemen because they are very strong; and who look not unto the Holy One of Israel, neither seek Jehovah!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.31.2'>But he also is wise, and he bringeth evil, and recalleth not his words; and he will arise against the house of evildoers, and against the help of workers of iniquity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.31.3'>And the Egyptians are men, and not God, and their horses flesh, and not spirit; and Jehovah shall stretch forth his hand, and he that helpeth shall stumble, and he that is helped shall fall, and they all shall perish together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.31.4'>For thus hath Jehovah said unto me: Like as the lion and the young lion growling over his prey, when a multitude of shepherds is called forth against him, is not afraid of their voice, nor giveth way before the multitude of them; so will Jehovah of hosts come down to war upon mount Zion, and on the hill thereof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.31.5'>As birds with outstretched wings, so will Jehovah of hosts cover Jerusalem; covering, he will also deliver, passing over, he will rescue [it].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.31.6'>Turn unto him from whom ye have deeply revolted, ye children of Israel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.31.7'>for in that day every man shall cast away his idols of silver and his idols of gold, which your sinful hands have made unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.31.8'>And Asshur shall fall by the sword, not of a great man; and the sword, not of a mean man, shall devour him: and he shall flee from the sword, and his young men shall become tributary;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.31.9'>and for fear, he shall pass over to his rock, and his princes shall be afraid of the banner, saith Jehovah, whose fire is in Zion, and his furnace in Jerusalem.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.32'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.1'>Behold, a king shall reign in righteousness, and princes shall rule in judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.2'>And a man shall be as a hiding-place from the wind, and a covert from the storm; as brooks of water in a dry place, as the shadow of a great rock in a thirsty land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.3'>And the eyes of them that see shall not be dim, and the ears of them that hear shall hearken;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.4'>and the heart of the rash shall understand knowledge, and the tongue of the stammerers shall be ready to speak plainly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.5'>The vile man shall be no more called noble, nor the churl said to be bountiful:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.6'>for the vile man will speak villainy, and his heart will work iniquity, to practise hypocrisy, and to utter error against Jehovah, to make empty the soul of the hungry, and to cause the drink of the thirsty to fail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.7'>The instruments also of the churl are evil: he deviseth wicked devices to destroy the meek with lying words, even when the needy speaketh right.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.8'>But the noble deviseth noble things; and to noble things doth he stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.9'>Rise up, ye women that are at ease, hear my voice; ye careless daughters, give ear unto my speech.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.10'>In a year and [some] days shall ye be troubled, ye careless women; for the vintage shall fail, the ingathering shall not come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.11'>Tremble, ye women that are at ease; be troubled, ye careless ones; strip you, and make you bare, and gird [sackcloth] on your loins!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.12'>They shall smite on the breasts [in lamentation] for the pleasant fields, for the fruitful vineyards.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.13'>Upon the land of my people shall come up thistles [and] briars, yea, upon all the houses of joy in the joyous city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.14'>For the palace shall be deserted, the multitude of the city shall be forsaken; hill and watchtower shall be caves for ever, a joy of wild asses, a pasture of flocks;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.15'>until the Spirit be poured upon us from on high, and the wilderness become a fruitful field, and the fruitful field be counted for a forest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.16'>And judgment shall inhabit the wilderness, and righteousness dwell in the fruitful field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.17'>And the work of righteousness shall be peace; and the effect of righteousness, quietness and assurance for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.18'>And my people shall dwell in a peaceable habitation, and in sure dwellings, and in quiet resting-places.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.19'>And it shall hail, coming down on the forest; and the city shall be low in a low place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.32.20'>Blessed are ye that sow beside all waters, that send forth the feet of the ox and the ass.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.33'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.1'>Woe to thee that spoilest, and thou wast not spoiled; and that dealest treacherously, and they dealt not treacherously with thee! When thou shalt cease to spoil, thou shalt be spoiled; when thou shalt make an end of dealing treacherously, they shall deal treacherously with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.2'>Jehovah, be gracious unto us; we have waited for thee: be their arm every morning, yea, our salvation in the time of trouble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.3'>At the noise of the tumult the peoples fled; at the lifting up of thyself the nations were scattered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.4'>And your spoil shall be gathered [like] the gathering of the caterpillar: as the running of locusts shall they run upon it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.5'>Jehovah is exalted; for he dwelleth on high: he hath filled Zion with justice and righteousness;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.6'>and he shall be the stability of thy times, the riches of salvation, wisdom and knowledge: the fear of Jehovah shall be your treasure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.7'>Behold, their valiant ones cry without; the messengers of peace weep bitterly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.8'>The highways are desolate, the wayfaring man ceaseth. He hath broken the covenant, he hath despised the cities, he regardeth no man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.9'>The land mourneth, it languisheth; Lebanon is ashamed, is withered; the Sharon is become as a desert, and Bashan and Carmel are stripped.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.10'>Now will I arise, saith Jehovah; now will I be exalted, now will I lift up myself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.11'>Ye shall conceive dry grass, ye shall bring forth stubble: your breath shall devour you [as] fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.12'>And the peoples shall be [as] burnings of lime, [as] thorns cut up shall they be burned in the fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.13'>Hear, ye that are far off, what I have done; and ye that are near, acknowledge my might.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.14'>The sinners in Zion are afraid; trembling hath surprised the hypocrites: Who among us shall dwell with the consuming fire? who among us shall dwell with everlasting flames?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.15'>He that walketh righteously, and speaketh uprightly; he that despiseth the gain of oppressions, that shaketh his hands from taking hold of bribes, that stoppeth his ears from hearing of blood, and shutteth his eyes from seeing evil:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.16'>he shall dwell on high, the fortresses of the rocks shall be his high retreat; bread shall be given him, his water shall be sure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.17'>Thine eyes shall see the King in his beauty; they shall behold the land that is far off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.18'>Thy heart shall meditate on terror: Where is the scribe? where is the receiver? where is he that counted the towers?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.19'>Thou shalt no more see the fierce people, a people of a deeper speech than thou canst comprehend, of a stammering tongue that cannot be understood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.20'>Look upon Zion, the city of our solemnities: thine eyes shall see Jerusalem a quiet habitation, a tent that shall not be removed, the stakes whereof shall never be pulled up, neither shall any of its cords be broken;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.21'>but there Jehovah is unto us glorious, a place of rivers, of broad streams: no galley with oars shall go there, neither shall gallant ship pass thereby.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.22'>For Jehovah is our judge, Jehovah, our lawgiver, Jehovah, our king: he will save us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.23'>Thy tacklings are loosed; they strengthen not the socket of their mast, they cannot spread the sail: then is the prey of a great spoil divided; the lame take the prey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.33.24'>And the inhabitant shall not say, I am sick: the people that dwell therein shall be forgiven [their] iniquity.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.34'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.1'>Come near, ye nations, to hear; and hearken, ye peoples: let the earth hear, and all its fulness; the world, and all that cometh forth of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.2'>For the wrath of Jehovah is against all the nations, and [his] fury against all their armies: he hath devoted them to destruction, he hath delivered them to the slaughter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.3'>And their slain shall be cast out, and their stink shall come up from their carcases, and the mountains shall be melted with their blood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.4'>And all the host of the heavens shall be dissolved, and the heavens shall be rolled together as a scroll; and all their host shall fade away, as a leaf fadeth from off the vine, and as the withered [fruit] from the fig-tree.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.5'>For my sword is bathed in the heavens; behold, it shall come down upon Edom, and upon the people of my ban, to judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.6'>The sword of Jehovah is filled with blood, it is made fat with fatness, with the blood of lambs and goats, with the fat of the kidneys of rams; for Jehovah hath a sacrifice in Bozrah, and a great slaughter in the land of Edom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.7'>And the buffaloes shall come down with them, and the bullocks with the bulls; and their land shall be soaked with blood, and their dust made fat with fatness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.8'>For it is the day of Jehovah's vengeance, the year of recompenses for the controversy of Zion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.9'>And the torrents thereof shall be turned into pitch, and its dust into brimstone; yea, the land thereof shall become burning pitch:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.10'>it shall not be quenched night nor day; the smoke thereof shall go up for ever: from generation to generation it shall lie waste; none shall pass through it for ever and ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.11'>And the pelican and the bittern shall possess it, and the great owl and the raven shall dwell in it. And he shall stretch out upon it the line of waste, and the plummets of emptiness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.12'>Of her nobles who should proclaim the kingdom, none are there; and all her princes shall be nought.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.13'>And thorns shall come up in her palaces, nettles and brambles in her fortresses; and it shall be a dwelling-place of wild dogs, a court for ostriches.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.14'>And there shall the beasts of the desert meet with the jackals, and the wild goat shall cry to his fellow; the lilith also shall settle there, and find for herself a place of rest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.15'>There shall the arrow-snake make her nest, and lay, and hatch, and gather under her shadow; there also shall the vultures be gathered one with another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.16'>Search ye in the book of Jehovah and read: not one of these shall fail, one shall not have to seek for the other; for my mouth, it hath commanded, and his Spirit, it hath gathered them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.34.17'>For he himself hath cast the lot for them, and his hand hath divided it unto them with the line: they shall possess it for ever; from generation to generation shall they dwell therein.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.35'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.35.1'>The wilderness and the dry land shall be gladdened; and the desert shall rejoice, and blossom as the rose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.35.2'>It shall blossom abundantly and rejoice even with joy and shouting: the glory of Lebanon shall be given unto it, the excellency of Carmel and Sharon. They shall see the glory of Jehovah, the excellency of our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.35.3'>Strengthen the weak hands and confirm the tottering knees.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.35.4'>Say to them that are of a timid heart, Be strong, fear not; behold your God: vengeance cometh, the recompense of God! He will come himself, and save you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.35.5'>Then the eyes of the blind shall be opened, and the ears of the deaf be unstopped;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.35.6'>then shall the lame [man] leap as a hart, and the tongue of the dumb sing: for in the wilderness shall waters break out, and torrents in the desert.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.35.7'>And the mirage shall become a pool, and the thirsty land springs of water: in the habitation of wild dogs, where they lay down, shall be grass with reeds and rushes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.35.8'>And a highway shall be there and a way, and it shall be called, The way of holiness: the unclean shall not pass through it; but it shall be for these. Those that go [this] way even fools, shall not err [therein].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.35.9'>No lion shall be there, nor shall ravenous beast go up thereon, nor be found there; but the redeemed shall walk [there].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.35.10'>And the ransomed of Jehovah shall return, and come to Zion with singing; and everlasting joy shall be upon their heads: they shall obtain gladness and joy, and sorrow and sighing shall flee away.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.36'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.1'>And it came to pass in the fourteenth year of king Hezekiah, that Sennacherib king of Assyria came up against all the fortified cities of Judah, and took them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.2'>And the king of Assyria sent Rab-shakeh from Lachish to Jerusalem, to king Hezekiah, with a strong force. And he stood by the aqueduct of the upper pool, on the highway of the fuller's field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.3'>Then came forth to him Eliakim the son of Hilkijah, who was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah the son of Asaph, the chronicler.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.4'>And Rab-shakeh said to them, Say now to Hezekiah, Thus says the great king, the king of Assyria: What confidence is this in which thou trustest?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.5'>Thou sayest, but it is a word of the lips, [There is] counsel and strength for war. Now on whom dost thou rely, that thou hast revolted against me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.6'>Behold, thou reliest upon the staff of that broken reed, upon Egypt, on which if a man lean, it goes into his hand, and pierces it: so is Pharaoh king of Egypt to all that rely upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.7'>And if thou say to me, We rely upon Jehovah our God: is it not he, whose high places and whose altars Hezekiah has removed, saying to Judah and Jerusalem, Ye shall worship before this altar?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.8'>And now engage, I pray thee, with my master the king of Assyria, and I will give thee two thousand horses, if thou be able on thy part to set riders upon them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.9'>How then wilt thou turn away the face of one captain of the least of my master's servants? And thou reliest upon Egypt for chariots and for horsemen!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.10'>And now am I come up without Jehovah against this land to destroy it? Jehovah said to me, Go up against this land and destroy it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.11'>And Eliakim and Shebna and Joah said to Rab-shakeh, Speak, we pray thee, to thy servants in Syriac, for we understand it; and speak not to us in the Jewish [language] in the ears of the people that are upon the wall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.12'>And Rab-shakeh said, Is it to thy master and to thee that my master sent me to speak these words? Is it not to the men that sit on the wall, that they may eat their own dung, and drink their own urine with you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.13'>And Rab-shakeh stood and cried with a loud voice in the Jewish [language], and said, Hear the words of the great king, the king of Assyria!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.14'>Thus says the king: Let not Hezekiah deceive you; for he will not be able to deliver you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.15'>Neither let Hezekiah make you rely upon Jehovah, saying, Jehovah will certainly deliver us; this city shall not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.16'>Hearken not to Hezekiah; for thus says the king of Assyria: Make peace with me and come out to me; and eat every one of his vine, and every one of his fig-tree, and drink every one the waters of his own cistern;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.17'>until I come and take you away to a land like your own land, a land of corn and wine, a land of bread and vineyards.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.18'>Let not Hezekiah persuade you, saying, Jehovah will deliver us. Has any of the gods of the nations delivered his land out of the hand of the king of Assyria?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.19'>Where are the gods of Hamath and of Arpad? where are the gods of Sepharvaim? and have they delivered Samaria out of my hand?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.20'>Who are they among all the gods of these countries that have delivered their country out of my hand, that Jehovah should deliver Jerusalem out of my hand?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.21'>And they were silent, and answered him not a word; for the king's command was, saying, Answer him not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.36.22'>And Eliakim the son of Hilkijah, who was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah the son of Asaph, the chronicler, came to Hezekiah, with their garments rent, and told him the words of Rab-shakeh.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.37'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.1'>And it came to pass when king Hezekiah heard [it], that he rent his garments, and covered himself with sackcloth, and went into the house of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.2'>And he sent Eliakim, who was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and the elders of the priests, covered with sackcloth, to the prophet Isaiah the son of Amoz.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.3'>And they said to him, Thus says Hezekiah: This day is a day of trouble, and of rebuke, and of reviling; for the children are come to the birth, and there is not strength to bring forth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.4'>It may be Jehovah thy God will hear the words of Rab-shakeh, whom the king of Assyria his master has sent to reproach the living God, and will rebuke the words which Jehovah thy God hath heard. Therefore lift up a prayer for the remnant that is left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.5'>And the servants of king Hezekiah came to Isaiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.6'>And Isaiah said to them, Thus shall ye say to your master, Thus saith Jehovah: Be not afraid of the words that thou hast heard, wherewith the servants of the king of Assyria have blasphemed me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.7'>Behold, I will put a spirit into him, and he shall hear tidings, and shall return to his own land; and I will cause him to fall by the sword in his own land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.8'>And Rab-shakeh returned, and found the king of Assyria warring against Libnah; for he had heard that he had departed from Lachish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.9'>And he heard say of Tirhakah king of Ethiopia, He has come forth to make war with thee. And when he heard [it], he sent messengers to Hezekiah, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.10'>Thus shall ye speak to Hezekiah king of Judah, saying: Let not thy God, upon whom thou reliest, deceive thee, saying, Jerusalem shall not be delivered into the hand of the king of Assyria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.11'>Behold, thou hast heard what the kings of Assyria have done to all countries, destroying them utterly; and shalt thou be delivered?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.12'>Have the gods of the nations which my fathers have destroyed delivered them, Gozan, and Haran, and Rezeph, and the children of Eden that were in Thelassar?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.13'>Where is the king of Hamath, and the king of Arpad, and the king of the city of Sepharvaim, of Hena, and Ivvah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.14'>And Hezekiah received the letter from the hand of the messengers, and read it; and Hezekiah went up into the house of Jehovah, and spread it before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.15'>And Hezekiah prayed to Jehovah, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.16'>Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, who sittest [between] the cherubim, thou, the Same, thou alone art the God of all the kingdoms of the earth: thou hast made the heavens and the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.17'>Incline thine ear, O Jehovah, and hear; open, Jehovah, thine eyes, and see; and hear all the words of Sennacherib, who hath sent to reproach the living God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.18'>Of a truth, Jehovah, the kings of Assyria have laid waste all the lands, and their countries,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.19'>and have cast their gods into the fire; for they were no gods, but the work of men's hands, wood and stone; and they have destroyed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.20'>And now, Jehovah our God, save us out of his hand, that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that thou art Jehovah, thou only.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.21'>And Isaiah the son of Amoz sent to Hezekiah, saying, Thus saith Jehovah the God of Israel, Whereas thou hast prayed to me concerning Sennacherib king of Assyria,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.22'>this is the word which Jehovah hath spoken against him: The virgin-daughter of Zion despiseth thee, laugheth thee to scorn; the daughter of Jerusalem shaketh her head at thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.23'>Whom hast thou reproached and blasphemed? and against whom hast thou exalted the voice? Against the Holy One of Israel hast thou lifted up thine eyes on high.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.24'>By thy servants thou hast reproached the Lord, and hast said, With the multitude of my chariots am I come up to the height of the mountains, to the recesses of Lebanon; and I will cut down its tall cedars, the choice of its cypresses; and I will enter into its furthest height, [into] the forest of its fruitful field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.25'>I have digged and drunk water; and with the sole of my feet have I dried up all the streams of Matsor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.26'>Hast thou not heard that long ago I did it, and that from ancient days I formed it? Now have I brought it to pass, that thou shouldest lay waste fortified cities [into] ruinous heaps.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.27'>And their inhabitants were powerless, they were dismayed and put to shame; they were [as] the grass of the field and the green herb, [as] the grass on the housetops, and grain blighted before it be grown up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.28'>But I know thine abode, and thy going out, and thy coming in, and thy raging against me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.29'>Because thy raging against me and thine arrogance is come up into mine ears, I will put my ring in thy nose, and my bridle in thy lips, and I will make thee go back by the way by which thou camest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.30'>And this [shall be] the sign unto thee: there shall be eaten this year such as groweth of itself; and in the second year that which springeth of the same; but in the third year sow ye, and reap, and plant vineyards and eat the fruit thereof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.31'>And the remnant that is escaped of the house of Judah shall again take root downward, and bear fruit upward;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.32'>for out of Jerusalem shall go forth a remnant, and out of mount Zion they that escape: the zeal of Jehovah of hosts shall do this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.33'>Therefore thus saith Jehovah concerning the king of Assyria: He shall not come into this city, nor shoot an arrow there, nor come before it with shield, nor cast a bank against it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.34'>By the way that he came, by the same shall he return, and shall not come into this city, saith Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.35'>And I will defend this city, to save it, for mine own sake, and for my servant David's sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.36'>And an angel of Jehovah went forth, and smote in the camp of the Assyrians a hundred and eighty-five thousand. And when they arose early in the morning, behold, they were all dead bodies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.37'>And Sennacherib king of Assyria departed, and went and returned, and abode at Nineveh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.37.38'>And it came to pass, as he was worshipping in the house of Nisroch his god, that Adrammelech and Sharezer his sons smote him with the sword; and they escaped into the land of Ararat. And Esarhaddon his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.38'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.1'>In those days Hezekiah was sick unto death. And the prophet Isaiah the son of Amoz came to him, and said to him, Thus saith Jehovah: Set thy house in order; for thou shalt die, and not live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.2'>And Hezekiah turned his face to the wall, and prayed to Jehovah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.3'>and said, Ah, Jehovah, remember, I beseech thee, how I have walked before thee in truth and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy sight. And Hezekiah wept much.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.4'>And the word of Jehovah came to Isaiah, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.5'>Go and say to Hezekiah, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of David thy father: I have heard thy prayer, I have seen thy tears: behold, I will add to thy days fifteen years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.6'>And I will deliver thee and this city out of the hand of the king of Assyria, and I will defend this city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.7'>And this [shall be] the sign to thee from Jehovah, that Jehovah will do this thing that he hath spoken:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.8'>behold, I will bring again the shadow of the degrees which hath gone down with the sun on the dial of Ahaz, ten degrees backward. So the sun returned on the dial ten degrees, by which it had gone down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.9'>The writing of Hezekiah king of Judah, when he had been sick and had recovered from his sickness:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.10'>I said, In the meridian of my days I shall go to the gates of Sheol: I am deprived of the rest of my years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.11'>I said, I shall not see Jah, Jah in the land of the living. With those who dwell where all has ceased to be, I shall behold man no more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.12'>Mine age is departed, and is removed from me as a shepherd's tent. I have cut off like a weaver my life. He separateth me from the thrum: from day to night thou wilt make an end of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.13'>I kept still until the morning; as a lion, so doth he break all my bones. From day to night thou wilt make an end of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.14'>Like a swallow [or] a crane, so did I chatter; I mourned as a dove; mine eyes failed [with looking] upward: Lord, I am oppressed; undertake for me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.15'>What shall I say? He hath both spoken unto me, and himself hath done [it]. I shall go softly all my years in the bitterness of my soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.16'>Lord, by these things [men] live, and in all these things is the life of my spirit; and thou hast recovered me, and made me to live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.17'>Behold, instead of peace I had bitterness upon bitterness; but thou hast in love delivered my soul from the pit of destruction; for thou hast cast all my sins behind thy back.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.18'>For not Sheol shall praise thee, nor death celebrate thee; they that go down into the pit do not hope for thy truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.19'>The living, the living, he shall praise thee, as I this day: the father to the children shall make known thy truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.20'>Jehovah was [purposed] to save me. And we will play upon my stringed instruments all the days of our life, in the house of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.21'>Now Isaiah had said, Let them take a cake of figs, and lay it for a plaster upon the boil, and he shall recover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.38.22'>And Hezekiah had said, What is the sign that I shall go up into the house of Jehovah?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.39'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.39.1'>At that time Merodach-Baladan, the son of Baladan, king of Babylon, sent a letter and a present to Hezekiah; for he had heard that he had been sick and had recovered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.39.2'>And Hezekiah was glad of them, and shewed them the house of his precious things, the silver and the gold, and the spices and the fine oil, and all the house of his armour, and all that was found amongst his treasures: there was nothing in his house, nor in all his dominion, that Hezekiah did not shew them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.39.3'>Then came the prophet Isaiah to king Hezekiah, and said to him, What said these men? and from whence came they to thee? And Hezekiah said, They came from a far country to me, from Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.39.4'>And he said, What have they seen in thy house? And Hezekiah said, All that is in my house have they seen: there is nothing among my treasures that I have not shewn them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.39.5'>And Isaiah said to Hezekiah, Hear the word of Jehovah of hosts:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.39.6'>Behold, days come when all that is in thy house, and that which thy fathers have laid up until this day, shall be carried to Babylon: nothing shall be left, saith Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.39.7'>And of thy sons that shall issue from thee, whom thou shalt beget, shall they take away; and they shall be eunuchs in the palace of the king of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.39.8'>And Hezekiah said to Isaiah, Good is the word of Jehovah which thou hast spoken. And he said, For there shall be peace and truth in my days.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.40'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.1'>Comfort ye, comfort ye my people, saith your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.2'>Speak to the heart of Jerusalem, and cry unto her, that her time of suffering is accomplished, that her iniquity is pardoned; for she hath received of Jehovah's hand double for all her sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.3'>The voice of one crying in the wilderness: Prepare ye the way of Jehovah, make straight in the desert a highway for our God!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.4'>Every valley shall be raised up, and every mountain and hill shall be brought low; and the crooked shall be made straight, and the rough places a plain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.5'>And the glory of Jehovah shall be revealed, and all flesh shall see [it] together: for the mouth of Jehovah hath spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.6'>A voice saith, Cry. And he saith, What shall I cry? All flesh is grass, and all the comeliness thereof as the flower of the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.7'>The grass withereth, the flower fadeth, for the breath of Jehovah bloweth upon it: surely the people is grass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.8'>The grass withereth, the flower fadeth; but the word of our God abideth for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.9'>O Zion, that bringest glad tidings, get thee up into a high mountain; O Jerusalem, that bringest glad tidings, lift up thy voice with strength: lift it up, be not afraid; say unto the cities of Judah, Behold your God!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.10'>Behold, the Lord Jehovah will come with might, and his arm shall rule for him; behold, his reward is with him, and his recompence before him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.11'>He will feed his flock like a shepherd: he will gather the lambs with his arm, and carry them in his bosom; he will gently lead those that give suck.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.12'>Who hath measured the waters in the hollow of his hand, and meted out the heavens with [his] span, and grasped the dust of the earth in a measure, and weighed the mountains in a balance, and the hills in scales?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.13'>Who hath directed the Spirit of Jehovah, and, [as] his counsellor, hath taught him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.14'>With whom took he counsel, and [who] gave him intelligence, and instructed him in the path of judgment, and taught him knowledge, and shewed him the way of understanding?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.15'>Behold, the nations are esteemed as a drop of the bucket, and as the fine dust on the scales; behold, he taketh up the isles as an atom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.16'>And Lebanon is not sufficient to burn, nor the beasts thereof sufficient for a burnt-offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.17'>All the nations are as nothing before him; they are esteemed by him less than a cipher, and vanity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.18'>To whom then will ye liken God? and what likeness will ye compare unto him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.19'>The workman casteth a graven image, and the goldsmith spreadeth it over with gold, and casteth silver chains [for it].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.20'>He that is impoverished, so that he hath no offering, chooseth a tree that doth not rot; he seeketh unto him a skilled workman to prepare a graven image that shall not be moved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.21'>Do ye not know? Have ye not heard? Hath it not been told you from the beginning? Have ye not understood the foundation of the earth?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.22'>[It is] he that sitteth upon the circle of the earth, and the inhabitants thereof are as grasshoppers; that stretcheth out the heavens as a gauze curtain, and spreadeth them out as a tent to dwell in;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.23'>that bringeth the princes to nothing, that maketh the judges of the earth as vanity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.24'>Scarcely are they planted, scarcely are they sown, scarcely hath their stock taken root in the earth, but he also bloweth upon them and they wither, and the whirlwind taketh them away as stubble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.25'>To whom then will ye liken me, or shall I be equal? saith the Holy One.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.26'>Lift up your eyes on high, and see! Who hath created these things, bringing out their host by number? He calleth them all by name; through the greatness of his might and strength of power, not one faileth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.27'>Why sayest thou, Jacob, and speakest, O Israel, My way is hid from Jehovah, and my right is passed away from my God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.28'>Dost thou not know, hast thou not heard, that the everlasting God, Jehovah, the Creator of the ends of the earth, fainteth not nor tireth? There is no searching of his understanding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.29'>He giveth power to the faint; and to him that hath no might he increaseth strength.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.30'>Even the youths shall faint and shall tire, and the young men shall stumble and fall;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.40.31'>but they that wait upon Jehovah shall renew [their] strength: they shall mount up with wings as eagles; they shall run, and not tire; they shall walk, and not faint.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.41'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.1'>Keep silence before me, islands; and let the peoples renew [their] strength: let them come near; then let them speak: let us draw near together to judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.2'>Who raised up from the east him whom righteousness calleth to its foot? He gave the nations before him, and caused him to have dominion over kings; he gave them as dust to his sword, as driven stubble to his bow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.3'>He pursued them, he passed on in safety, by a way he had never come with his feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.4'>Who hath wrought and done [it], calling the generations from the beginning? I, Jehovah, the first; and with the last, I [am] HE.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.5'>The isles saw [it], and feared; the ends of the earth trembled: they drew near, and came.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.6'>They helped every one his neighbour, and [each] said to his brother, Take courage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.7'>And the artizan encouraged the founder, he that smootheth [with] the hammer him that smiteth on the anvil, saying of the soldering, It is good; and he fasteneth it with nails, that it be not moved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.8'>But thou, Israel, my servant, Jacob, whom I have chosen, the seed of Abraham, my friend</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.9'>thou whom I have taken from the ends of the earth, and called from the extremities thereof, and to whom I said, Thou art my servant, I have chosen thee and not rejected thee,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.10'>Fear not, for I [am] with thee; be not dismayed, for I [am] thy God: I will strengthen thee, yea, I will help thee, yea, I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.11'>Lo, all that are incensed against thee shall be ashamed and confounded; they that strive with thee shall be as nothing, and shall perish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.12'>Thou shalt seek them, and shalt not find them them that contend with thee; they that war against thee shall be as nothing, and as a thing of nought.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.13'>For I, Jehovah, thy God, hold thy right hand, saying unto thee, Fear not; I will help thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.14'>Fear not, thou worm Jacob, ye men of Israel; I will help thee, saith Jehovah, and thy Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.15'>Behold, I have made of thee a new sharp threshing instrument having double teeth: thou shalt thresh and beat small the mountains, and shalt make the hills as chaff;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.16'>thou shalt fan them, and the wind shall carry them away, and the whirlwind shall scatter them; and thou shalt rejoice in Jehovah, thou shalt glory in the Holy One of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.17'>The afflicted and the needy seek water, and there is none; their tongue faileth for thirst: I, Jehovah, will answer them, [I], the God of Israel, will not forsake them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.18'>I will open rivers on the bare heights, and fountains in the midst of the valleys; I will make the wilderness into a pool of water, and the dry land into water-springs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.19'>I will give in the wilderness the cedar, acacia, myrtle, and oleaster; I will set in the desert the cypress, pine, and box-tree together;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.20'>that they may see, and know, and consider, and understand together, that the hand of Jehovah hath done this, and the Holy One of Israel hath created it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.21'>Produce your cause, saith Jehovah; bring forward your arguments, saith the King of Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.22'>Let them bring them forward, and declare to us what shall happen: shew the former things, what they are, that we may give attention to them, and know the end of them; or let us hear things to come:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.23'>declare the things that are to happen hereafter, that we may know that ye are gods; yea, do good, or do evil, that we may be astonished, and behold it together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.24'>Behold, ye are less than nothing, and your work is of nought; an abomination is he that chooseth you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.25'>I have raised up one from the north, and he shall come, from the rising of the sun, he who will call upon my name; and he shall come upon princes as on mortar, and as the potter treadeth clay.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.26'>Who hath declared [it] from the beginning, that we may know? and beforetime, that we may say, [It is] right? Indeed, there is none that declareth; no, none that sheweth; no, none that heareth your words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.27'>The first, [I said] to Zion, Behold, behold them! and to Jerusalem, I will give one that bringeth glad tidings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.28'>And I beheld, and there was no man; even among them, and there was no counsellor, that, when I asked of them, could answer a word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.41.29'>Behold, they are all vanity, their works are nought, their molten images are wind and emptiness.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.42'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.1'>Behold my servant whom I uphold, mine elect [in whom] my soul delighteth! I will put my Spirit upon him; he shall bring forth judgment to the nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.2'>He shall not cry, nor lift up, nor cause his voice to be heard in the street.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.3'>A bruised reed shall he not break, and smoking flax shall he not quench: he shall bring forth judgment according to truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.4'>He shall not faint nor be in haste, till he have set justice in the earth: and the isles shall wait for his law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.5'>Thus saith God, Jehovah, he that created the heavens and stretched them out, he that spread forth the earth and its productions, he that giveth breath unto the people upon it, and spirit to them that walk therein:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.6'>I, Jehovah, have called thee in righteousness, and will take hold of thy hand; and I will preserve thee, and give thee for a covenant of the people, for a light of the nations,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.7'>to open the blind eyes, to bring forth the prisoner from the prison, them that sit in darkness out of the house of restraint.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.8'>I am Jehovah, that is my name; and my glory will I not give to another, neither my praise to graven images.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.9'>Behold, the former things are come to pass, and new things do I declare: before they spring forth will I cause you to hear them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.10'>Sing unto Jehovah a new song, his praise from the end of the earth, ye that go down to the sea, and all that is therein, the isles and their inhabitants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.11'>Let the wilderness and the cities thereof lift up [their voice], the villages that Kedar doth inhabit; let the inhabitants of the rock sing, let them shout from the top of the mountains:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.12'>let them give glory unto Jehovah, and declare his praise in the islands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.13'>Jehovah will go forth as a mighty man, he will stir up jealousy like a man of war: he will cry, yea, he will shout; he will shew himself mighty against his enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.14'>Long time have I holden my peace; I have been still, I have restrained myself: I will cry like a woman that travaileth; I will blow and pant at once.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.15'>I will lay waste mountains and hills, and dry up all their herbs; and I will make the rivers islands, and I will dry up the pools.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.16'>And I will bring the blind by a way that they know not, in paths that they know not will I lead them; I will make darkness light before them, and crooked things straight. These things will I do unto them, and not forsake them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.17'>They shall be turned back, they shall be covered with shame, that confide in graven images, that say to the molten images, Ye are our gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.18'>Hear, ye deaf; and look, ye blind, that ye may see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.19'>Who is blind, but my servant? and deaf, as my messenger whom I sent? Who is blind as he in whom I have trusted, and blind as Jehovah's servant,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.20'>seeing many things, and thou observest not? With opened ears, he heareth not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.21'>Jehovah had delight [in him] for his righteousness' sake: he hath magnified the law, and made it honourable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.22'>But this is a people robbed and spoiled; they are all of them snared in holes, and hidden in prison-houses; they are become a prey, and none delivereth, a spoil, and none saith, Restore.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.23'>Who among you will give ear to this, [who] will hearken and hear what is to come?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.24'>Who gave Jacob for a spoil, and Israel to the robbers? Did not Jehovah, he against whom we have sinned? And they would not walk in his ways, neither did they hearken unto his law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.42.25'>And he hath poured upon him the fury of his anger, and the strength of battle: and it set him on fire round about, yet he knew not; and it burned him, yet he took it not to heart.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.43'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.1'>But now thus saith Jehovah, that created thee, O Jacob, and he that formed thee, O Israel: Fear not, for I have redeemed thee, I have called [thee] by thy name; thou art mine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.2'>When thou passest through the waters, I [will be] with thee; and through the rivers, they shall not overflow thee; when thou walkest through the fire, thou shalt not be burned, neither shall the flame kindle upon thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.3'>For I [am] Jehovah thy God, the Holy One of Israel, thy Saviour: I gave Egypt for thy ransom, Ethiopia and Seba for thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.4'>Since thou wast precious in my sight, thou hast been honourable, and I have loved thee; and I will give men for thee, and peoples for thy life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.5'>Fear not, for I [am] with thee: I will bring thy seed from the east, and gather thee from the west;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.6'>I will say to the north, Give up; and to the south, Keep not back: bring my sons from afar, and my daughters from the end of the earth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.7'>every one that is called by my name, and whom I have created for my glory: I have formed him, yea, I have made him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.8'>Bring forth the blind people that have eyes, and the deaf that have ears.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.9'>Let all the nations be gathered together, and let the peoples be assembled: who among them declareth this, or causeth us to hear former things? let them bring forth their witnesses, that they may be justified; or let them hear, and say, [It is] truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.10'>Ye are my witnesses, saith Jehovah, and my servant whom I have chosen; that ye may know and believe me, and understand that I [am] HE: before me there was no God formed, neither shall there be after me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.11'>I, I [am] Jehovah; and besides me there is no saviour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.12'>It is I that have declared, and have saved, and have shewed, when there was no strange [god] among you; and ye are my witnesses, saith Jehovah, that I [am] God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.13'>Yea, since the day was, I [am] HE, and there is none that delivereth out of my hand: I will work, and who shall hinder it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.14'>Thus saith Jehovah, your Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel: For your sake I have sent to Babylon, and have brought all of them down as fugitives, even the Chaldeans, whose cry is in the ships.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.15'>I [am] Jehovah, your Holy One, the Creator of Israel, your King.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.16'>Thus saith Jehovah, who maketh a way in the sea, and a path in the mighty waters,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.17'>who bringeth forth chariot and horse, army and power they lie down together, they shall not rise; they are extinct, they are quenched as tow:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.18'>Remember not the former things, neither consider the ancient things:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.19'>behold, I do a new thing; now it shall spring forth: shall ye not know it? I will even make a way in the wilderness, rivers in the waste.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.20'>The beast of the field shall glorify me, the jackals and the ostriches; for I will give waters in the wilderness, rivers in the waste, to give drink to my people, my chosen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.21'>This people have I formed for myself: they shall shew forth my praise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.22'>But thou hast not called upon me, Jacob; for thou hast been weary of me, O Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.23'>thou hast not brought me the small cattle of thy burnt-offerings, neither hast thou glorified me with thy sacrifices. I have not caused thee to toil with an oblation, nor wearied thee with incense.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.24'>Thou hast bought me no sweet cane with money, neither hast thou filled me with the fat of thy sacrifices; but thou hast made me to toil with thy sins, thou hast wearied me with thine iniquities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.25'>I, I [am] He that blotteth out thy transgressions for mine own sake, and I will not remember thy sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.26'>Put me in remembrance, let us plead together; rehearse thine own [cause], that thou mayest be justified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.27'>Thy first father hath sinned, and thy mediators have rebelled against me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.43.28'>And I have profaned the princes of the sanctuary, and have given Jacob to the ban, and Israel to reproaches.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.44'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.1'>And now hear, Jacob, my servant, and Israel, whom I have chosen:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.2'>thus saith Jehovah, that made thee, and formed thee from the womb, who helpeth thee, Fear not, Jacob, my servant, and thou, Jeshurun, whom I have chosen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.3'>For I will pour water upon him that is thirsty, and floods upon the dry ground; I will pour my Spirit upon thy seed, and my blessing upon thine offspring.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.4'>And they shall spring up among the grass, as willows by the water-courses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.5'>One shall say, I am Jehovah's; and another shall call [himself] by the name of Jacob; and another shall write with his hand: [I am] Jehovah's, and surname [himself] by the name of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.6'>Thus saith Jehovah, the King of Israel, and his Redeemer, Jehovah of hosts: I [am] the first, and I [am] the last, and beside me there is no God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.7'>And who, as I, shall call, and shall declare it, and set it in order for me, since I appointed the ancient people? And the coming things, and those that shall happen, let them declare unto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.8'>Fear not, neither be afraid. Have I not caused thee to hear from that time, and have declared it? and ye are my witnesses. Is there a God beside me? yea, there is no Rock: I know not any.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.9'>They that form a graven image are all of them vanity, and their delectable things are of no profit; and they are their own witnesses: they see not, nor know; that they may be ashamed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.10'>Who hath formed a God, or molten a graven image that is profitable for nothing?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.11'>Behold, all his fellows shall be ashamed; and the workmen are but men. Let them all be gathered together, let them stand up: they shall fear, they shall be ashamed together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.12'>The iron-smith [hath] a chisel, and he worketh in the coals, and he fashioneth it with hammers, and worketh it with his strong arm; but he is hungry, and his strength faileth; he hath not drunk water, and he is faint.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.13'>The worker in wood stretcheth out a line; he marketh it out with red chalk; he formeth it with sharp tools, and he marketh it out with the compass, and maketh it after the figure of a man, according to the beauty of man: that it may remain in the house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.14'>When he heweth him down cedars, he taketh also a holm-oak and a terebinth he chooseth for himself among the trees of the forest: he planteth a pine, and the rain maketh [it] grow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.15'>And it shall be for a man to burn, and he taketh thereof, and warmeth himself; he kindleth it also, and baketh bread; he maketh also a God, and worshippeth it; he maketh it a graven image, and falleth down thereto.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.16'>He burneth part thereof in the fire; with part thereof he eateth flesh, he roasteth roast, and is satisfied; yea, he is warm, and saith, Aha, I am become warm, I have seen the fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.17'>And with the remainder thereof he maketh a God, his graven image; he falleth down unto it, and worshippeth it, and prayeth unto it, and saith, Deliver me, for thou art my God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.18'>They have no knowledge, and understand not; for he hath plastered their eyes, that they may not see; and their hearts, that they may not understand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.19'>And none taketh it to heart, neither is there knowledge nor understanding to say, I have burned part of it in the fire, and have also baked bread upon the coals thereof, I have roasted flesh, and eaten [it], and with the rest thereof shall I make an abomination? shall I bow down to a block of wood?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.20'>He feedeth on ashes; a deceived heart hath turned him aside, that he cannot deliver his soul, nor say, Is there not a lie in my right hand?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.21'>Remember these things, O Jacob, and Israel, for thou art my servant; I have formed thee: thou art my servant, Israel; thou shalt not be forgotten of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.22'>I have blotted out, as a thick cloud, thy transgressions, and, as a cloud, thy sins: return unto me; for I have redeemed thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.23'>Sing, ye heavens; for Jehovah hath done it: shout, ye lower parts of the earth; break forth into singing, ye mountains, the forest, and every tree therein! For Jehovah hath redeemed Jacob, and glorified himself in Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.24'>Thus saith Jehovah, thy Redeemer, and he that formed thee from the womb: I [am] Jehovah, the maker of all things; who alone stretched out the heavens, who did spread forth the earth by myself;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.25'>he that frustrateth the tokens of the liars, and maketh diviners mad; that turneth wise men backward, and maketh their knowledge foolish;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.26'>that confirmeth the word of his servant, and performeth the counsel of his messengers; that saith to Jerusalem, Thou shalt be inhabited; and to the cities of Judah, Ye shall be built up, and I will raise up their ruins;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.27'>that saith to the deep, Be dry, and I will dry up thy rivers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.44.28'>that saith of Cyrus, [He is] my shepherd, and he shall perform all my pleasure; even saying to Jerusalem, Thou shalt be built; and to the temple, Thy foundation shall be laid.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.45'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.1'>Thus saith Jehovah to his anointed, to Cyrus, whose right hand I have holden, to subdue nations before him and I will loose the loins of kings; to open before him the two-leaved doors, and the gates shall not be shut:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.2'>I will go before thee, and make the elevated places plain; I will break in pieces the brazen doors, and cut asunder the bars of iron;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.3'>and I will give thee the treasures of darkness, and hidden riches of secret places; that thou mayest know that I, Jehovah, who call thee by name, [am] the God of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.4'>For Jacob my servant's sake, and Israel mine elect, I have called thee by thy name; I surnamed thee, though thou didst not know me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.5'>I [am] Jehovah, and there is none else; there is no God beside me: I girded thee, and thou hast not known me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.6'>that they may know from the rising of the sun, and from the going down, that there is none beside me. I [am] Jehovah, and there is none else;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.7'>forming the light and creating darkness, making peace and creating evil: I, Jehovah, do all these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.8'>Drop down, [ye] heavens, from above, and let the skies pour down righteousness; let the earth open, and let them bring forth salvation, and with it let righteousness spring up. I, Jehovah, have created it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.9'>Woe unto him that striveth with his Maker! Let a potsherd [strive] with the potsherds of the earth. Shall the clay say to him that formeth it, What makest thou? Or thy work, He hath no hands?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.10'>Woe unto him that saith unto [his] father, What begettest thou? Or to [his] mother, What hast thou brought forth?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.11'>Thus saith Jehovah, the Holy One of Israel, and his Maker: Ask me of the things to come; concerning my sons, and concerning the work of my hands, command ye me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.12'>It is I that have made the earth, and created man upon it; it is I, my hands, that have stretched out the heavens, and all their host have I commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.13'>It is I that have raised him up in righteousness, and I will make all his ways straight: he shall build my city, and he shall let go my captives, not for price nor reward, saith Jehovah of hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.14'>Thus saith Jehovah: The wealth of Egypt, and the merchandise of Ethiopia and the Sabeans, men of stature, shall come over unto thee, and they shall be thine: they shall walk after thee; in chains they shall come over, and they shall bow down unto thee, they shall make supplication unto thee, [saying,] Surely God is in thee; and there is none else, no other God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.15'>Verily thou art a God that hidest thyself, O God of Israel, the Saviour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.16'>They shall be ashamed, and also confounded, all of them; they shall go away in confusion together, the makers of idols.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.17'>Israel shall be saved by Jehovah with an everlasting salvation: ye shall not be ashamed nor confounded, unto the ages of ages.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.18'>For thus saith Jehovah who created the heavens, God himself who formed the earth and made it, he who established it, not as waste did he create it: he formed it to be inhabited: I [am] Jehovah, and there is none else.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.19'>I have not spoken in secret, in a dark place of the earth; I said not unto the seed of Jacob, Seek me in vain: I [am] Jehovah, speaking righteousness, declaring things which are right.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.20'>Gather yourselves and come; draw near together, ye that are escaped of the nations. They have no knowledge that carry the wood of their graven image, and pray unto a God that cannot save.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.21'>Declare and bring [them] near; yea, let them take counsel together: who hath caused this to be heard from ancient time? [who] hath declared it long ago? Is it not I, Jehovah? And there is no God else beside me; a just God and a Saviour, there is none besides me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.22'>Look unto me, and be ye saved, all the ends of the earth: for I [am] God, and there is none else.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.23'>I have sworn by myself, the word is gone out of my mouth [in] righteousness and shall not return, that unto me every knee shall bow, every tongue shall swear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.24'>Only in Jehovah, shall one say, have I righteousness and strength. To him shall [men] come; and all that are incensed against him shall be ashamed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.45.25'>In Jehovah shall all the seed of Israel be justified, and shall glory.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.46'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.46.1'>Bel is bowed down, Nebo bendeth; their idols are upon the beasts, and upon the cattle: the things ye carried are laid on, a burden to the weary [beast].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.46.2'>They bend, they are bowed down together; they could not deliver the burden, and themselves are gone into captivity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.46.3'>Hearken unto me, house of Jacob, and all the remnant of the house of Israel, ye who have been borne from the belly, who have been carried from the womb:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.46.4'>Even to old age, I [am] HE, and unto hoary hairs I will carry [you]: It is I that have made, and I will bear, and I will carry, and will deliver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.46.5'>To whom will ye liken me and make me equal, or compare me, that we may be like?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.46.6'>They lavish gold out of the bag, and weigh silver in the balance; they hire a goldsmith, and he maketh it a God: they fall down, yea, they worship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.46.7'>They bear him on the shoulder, they carry him, and set him in his place; there he standeth, he doth not remove from his place: yea, one crieth unto him, and he answereth not; he saveth him not out of his trouble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.46.8'>Remember this, and shew yourselves men; call it to mind, ye transgressors.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.46.9'>Remember the former things of old; for I [am] God, and there is none else; [I am] God, and there is none like me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.46.10'>declaring the end from the beginning, and from ancient times the things that are not yet done, saying, My counsel shall stand, and I will do all my pleasure;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.46.11'>calling a bird of prey from the east, the man of my counsel from a far country. Yea, I have spoken, I will also bring it to pass; I have purposed it, I will also do it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.46.12'>Hearken unto me, ye stout-hearted, that are far from righteousness:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.46.13'>I bring near my righteousness; it shall not be far off, and my salvation shall not delay; and I will give salvation in Zion, [and] unto Israel my glory.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.47'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.47.1'>Come down and sit in the dust, virgin-daughter of Babylon! Sit on the ground, [there is] no throne, O daughter of the Chaldeans; for thou shalt no more be called tender and delicate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.47.2'>Take the millstones, and grind meal; remove thy veil, lift up the train, uncover the leg, pass over rivers:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.47.3'>thy nakedness shall be uncovered, yea, thy shame shall be seen. I will take vengeance, and I will meet none [to stay me].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.47.4'>Our Redeemer, Jehovah of hosts is his name, the Holy One of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.47.5'>Sit silent, and get thee into darkness, daughter of the Chaldeans; for thou shalt no more be called, Mistress of kingdoms.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.47.6'>I was wroth with my people, I polluted mine inheritance, and gave them into thy hand: thou didst shew them no mercy; upon the aged didst thou very heavily lay thy yoke;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.47.7'>and thou saidst, I shall be a mistress for ever; so that thou didst not take these things to heart, thou didst not remember the end thereof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.47.8'>And now hear this, thou voluptuous one, that dwellest carelessly, that sayest in thy heart, It is I, and there is none but me; I shall not sit as a widow, neither shall I know loss of children:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.47.9'>yet these two things shall come upon thee in a moment, in one day, loss of children and widowhood; they shall come upon thee in full measure for the multitude of thy sorceries, for the great abundance of thine enchantments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.47.10'>For thou hast confided in thy wickedness: thou hast said, None seeth me. Thy wisdom and thy knowledge, it hath seduced thee; and thou hast said in thy heart, It is I, and there is none but me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.47.11'>But evil shall come upon thee thou shalt not know from whence it riseth; and mischief shall fall upon thee, which thou shalt not be able to ward off; and desolation that thou suspectest not shall come upon thee suddenly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.47.12'>Stand now with thine enchantments and with the multitude of thy sorceries, wherein thou hast laboured from thy youth; if so be thou shalt be able to turn them to profit, if so be thou mayest cause terror.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.47.13'>Thou art wearied in the multitude of thy counsels. Let now the interpreters of the heavens, the observers of the stars, who predict according to the new moons what shall come upon thee, stand up, and save thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.47.14'>Behold, they shall be as stubble, the fire shall burn them; they shall not deliver themselves from the power of the flame: there shall not be a coal to warm at, [nor] fire to sit before it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.47.15'>Thus shall they be unto thee with whom thou hast laboured, they that trafficked with thee from thy youth: they shall wander every one to his own quarter; there is none to save thee.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.48'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.1'>Hear ye this, house of Jacob, who are called by the name of Israel, and are come forth out of the waters of Judah, who swear by the name of Jehovah, and make mention of the God of Israel, not in truth, nor in righteousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.2'>For they are named after the holy city, and stay themselves upon the God of Israel: Jehovah of hosts is his name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.3'>I have declared the former things long ago; and they went forth out of my mouth, and I caused them to be heard: I wrought suddenly, and they came to pass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.4'>Because I knew that thou art obstinate, and thy neck is an iron sinew, and thy brow brass,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.5'>so I have long ago declared [them] to thee; before they came to pass I caused thee to hear [them]; lest thou shouldest say, Mine idol hath done them, and my graven image, or my molten image hath commanded them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.6'>Thou heardest, see all this; and ye, will not ye declare [it]? I have caused thee to hear new things from this time, and things hidden, and that thou knewest not:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.7'>they are created now, and not long ago; and before this day thou hast not heard them, lest thou shouldest say, Behold, I knew them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.8'>Yea, thou heardest not, yea, thou knewest not, yea, from of old thine ear was not opened; for I knew that thou wouldest ever deal treacherously, and thou wast called a transgressor from the womb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.9'>For my name's sake I will defer mine anger, and [for] my praise will I refrain as to thee, that I cut thee not off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.10'>Behold, I have refined thee, but not as silver; I have chosen thee in the furnace of affliction.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.11'>For mine own sake, for mine own sake, will I do [it]; for how should [my name] be profaned? and I will not give my glory unto another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.12'>Hearken unto me, Jacob, and [thou] Israel, my called. I [am] HE; I, the first, and I, the last.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.13'>Yea, my hand hath laid the foundation of the earth, and my right hand hath spread abroad the heavens: I call unto them, they stand up together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.14'>All ye, gather yourselves together, and hear: which among them hath declared these things? He whom Jehovah hath loved shall execute his pleasure on Babylon, and his arm [shall be on] the Chaldeans.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.15'>I, [even] I, have spoken; yea, I have called him; I have brought him, and his way shall be prosperous.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.16'>Come near unto me, hear ye this: I have not spoken in secret from the beginning; from the time that it was, there am I; and now the Lord Jehovah hath sent me, and his Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.17'>Thus saith Jehovah, thy Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel; I [am] Jehovah thy God, who teacheth thee for [thy] profit, who leadeth thee in the way that thou shouldest go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.18'>Oh that thou hadst hearkened to my commandments! Then would thy peace have been as a river, and thy righteousness as the waves of the sea;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.19'>and thy seed would have been as the sand, and the offspring of thy bowels like the gravel thereof: their name should not have been cut off nor destroyed from before me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.20'>Go ye forth from Babylon, flee from the Chaldeans, with a voice of singing; declare, cause this to be heard, utter it to the end of the earth; say ye, Jehovah hath redeemed his servant Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.21'>And they thirsted not when he led them through the deserts; he caused the waters to flow out of the rock for them; yea, he clave the rock, and the waters gushed out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.48.22'>There is no peace, saith Jehovah, unto the wicked.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.49'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.1'>Listen, O isles, unto me; and hearken, ye peoples from afar. Jehovah hath called me from the womb; from the bowels of my mother hath he made mention of my name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.2'>And he hath made my mouth like a sharp sword, he hath concealed me under the shadow of his hand, and he hath made me a polished shaft: in his quiver hath he hidden me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.3'>And he said unto me, Thou art my servant, Israel, in whom I will glorify myself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.4'>And I said, I have laboured in vain, I have spent my strength for nought and in vain; nevertheless my judgment is with Jehovah, and my work with my God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.5'>And now, saith Jehovah, that formed me from the womb to be his servant, that I should bring Jacob again to him; (though Israel be not gathered, yet shall I be glorified in the eyes of Jehovah, and my God shall be my strength;)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.6'>and he saith, It is a small thing that thou shouldest be my servant to raise up the tribes of Jacob, and to restore the preserved of Israel; I have even given thee for a light of the nations, that thou mayest be my salvation unto the end of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.7'>Thus saith Jehovah, the Redeemer of Israel, his Holy One, to him whom man despiseth, to him whom the nation abhorreth, to the servant of rulers: Kings shall see and arise, princes, and they shall worship, because of Jehovah who is faithful, the Holy One of Israel, who hath chosen thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.8'>Thus saith Jehovah: In a time of acceptance have I answered thee, and in the day of salvation have I helped thee; and I will preserve thee, and give thee for a covenant of the people, to establish the land, to cause to inherit the desolate heritages;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.9'>saying to the prisoners, Go forth; to them that are in darkness, Shew yourselves. They shall feed in the ways, and their pasture shall be on all bare hills.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.10'>They shall not hunger nor thirst, neither shall the heat nor sun smite them; for he that hath mercy on them will lead them, and by the springs of water will he guide them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.11'>And I will make all my mountains a way, and my highways shall be raised up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.12'>Behold, these shall come from afar; and behold, these from the north and from the west; and these from the land of Sinim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.13'>Shout, ye heavens; and be joyful, thou earth; and break forth into singing, ye mountains: for Jehovah hath comforted his people, and will have mercy upon his afflicted ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.14'>But Zion said, Jehovah hath forsaken me, and the Lord hath forgotten me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.15'>Can a woman forget her sucking child, that she should not have compassion on the son of her womb? Even these forget, but I will not forget thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.16'>Lo, I have graven thee upon the palms of [my] hands; thy walls are continually before me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.17'>Thy sons shall make haste; thy destroyers and they that laid thee waste shall go forth from thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.18'>Lift up thine eyes round about and behold: they all gather themselves together, they come to thee. As I live, saith Jehovah, thou shalt indeed clothe thee with them all as with an ornament, and bind them on as a bride doth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.19'>For [in] thy waste and thy desolate places, and thy destroyed land, thou shalt even now be too straitened by reason of the inhabitants, and they that swallowed thee up shall be far away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.20'>The children of thy bereavement shall yet say in thine ears, The place is too narrow for me: make room for me, that I may dwell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.21'>And thou shalt say in thy heart, Who hath borne me these, seeing I had lost my children and was desolate, an exile, and driven about? and who hath brought up these? behold, I was left alone; these, where were they?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.22'>Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will lift up my hand to the nations, and set up my banner to the peoples; and they shall bring thy sons in [their] bosom, and thy daughters shall be carried upon the shoulder.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.23'>And kings shall be thy nursing-fathers, and their princesses thy nursing-mothers: they shall bow down to thee with the face toward the earth, and lick up the dust of thy feet. And thou shalt know that I [am] Jehovah; for they shall not be ashamed who wait on me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.24'>Shall the prey be taken from the mighty? and shall he that is rightfully captive be delivered?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.25'>For thus saith Jehovah: Even the captive of the mighty shall be taken away, and the prey of the terrible shall be delivered; and I will strive with him that striveth with thee, and I will save thy children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.49.26'>And I will feed them that oppress thee with their own flesh; and they shall be drunken with their own blood, as with new wine. And all flesh shall know that I, Jehovah, [am] thy Saviour and thy Redeemer, the Mighty One of Jacob.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.50'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.50.1'>Thus saith Jehovah: Where is the bill of your mother's divorce, whom I have put away? or which of my creditors is it to whom I have sold you? Behold, through your iniquities have ye sold yourselves, and for your transgressions is your mother put away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.50.2'>Wherefore did I come, and there was no man? I called, and there was none to answer? Is my hand at all shortened that I cannot redeem, or have I no power to deliver? behold, at my rebuke I dry up the sea, I make rivers a wilderness; their fish stink because there is no water, and die for thirst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.50.3'>I clothe the heavens with blackness, and I make sackcloth their covering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.50.4'>The Lord Jehovah hath given me the tongue of the instructed, that I should know how to succour by a word him that is weary. He wakeneth morning by morning, he wakeneth mine ear to hear as the instructed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.50.5'>The Lord Jehovah hath opened mine ear, and I was not rebellious; I turned not away back.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.50.6'>I gave my back to smiters, and my cheeks to them that plucked off the hair; I hid not my face from shame and spitting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.50.7'>But the Lord Jehovah will help me: therefore shall I not be confounded; therefore have I set my face like a flint, and I know that I shall not be ashamed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.50.8'>He is near that justifieth me: who will contend with me? let us stand together; who is mine adverse party? let him draw near unto me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.50.9'>Behold, the Lord Jehovah will help me; who is he that shall condemn me? Behold, they all shall grow old as a garment; the moth shall eat them up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.50.10'>Who is among you that feareth Jehovah, that hearkeneth to the voice of his servant? he that walketh in darkness, and hath no light, let him confide in the name of Jehovah, and stay himself upon his God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.50.11'>Behold, all ye that kindle a fire, that compass yourselves about with sparks: walk in the light of your fire, and among the sparks [that] ye have kindled. This shall ye have of my hand: ye shall lie down in sorrow.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.51'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.1'>Hearken unto me, ye that follow after righteousness, ye that seek Jehovah: look unto the rock [whence] ye were hewn, and to the hole of the pit [whence] ye were digged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.2'>Look unto Abraham your father, and unto Sarah that bore you; for I called him when he was alone, and blessed him, and multiplied him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.3'>For Jehovah shall comfort Zion, he shall comfort all her waste places; and he will make her wilderness like Eden, and her desert like the garden of Jehovah: gladness and joy shall be found therein, thanksgiving, and the voice of song.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.4'>Listen unto me, my people; and give ear unto me, my nation: for a law shall proceed from me, and I will establish my judgment for a light of the peoples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.5'>My righteousness is near, my salvation is gone forth, and mine arms shall judge the peoples: the isles shall wait for me, and in mine arm shall they trust.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.6'>Lift up your eyes to the heavens, and look on the earth beneath: for the heavens shall vanish away like smoke, and the earth shall grow old like a garment, and they that dwell therein shall die in like manner; but my salvation shall be for ever, and my righteousness shall not be abolished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.7'>Hearken unto me, ye that know righteousness, the people in whose heart is my law; fear not the reproach of men, and be not afraid of their revilings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.8'>For the moth shall eat them up like a garment, and the worm shall eat them like wool; but my righteousness shall be for ever, and my salvation from generation to generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.9'>Awake, awake, put on strength, O arm of Jehovah; awake, as in the days of old, [as in] the generations of passed ages. Is it not thou that hath hewn Rahab in pieces, [and] pierced the monster?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.10'>Is it not thou that dried up the sea, the waters of the great deep; that made the depths of the sea a way for the redeemed to pass over?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.11'>So the ransomed of Jehovah shall return, and come to Zion with singing; and everlasting joy shall be upon their heads: they shall obtain gladness and joy; sorrow and sighing shall flee away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.12'>I, [even] I, am he that comforteth you: who art thou, that thou fearest a man that shall die, and the son of man that shall become as grass;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.13'>and forgettest Jehovah thy Maker, who hath stretched out the heavens, and laid the foundations of the earth; and thou art afraid continually all the day because of the fury of the oppressor, when he prepareth to destroy? And where is the fury of the oppressor?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.14'>He that is bowed down shall speedily be loosed, and he shall not die in the pit, nor shall his bread fail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.15'>And I am Jehovah thy God, who raiseth the sea, so that its waves roar: Jehovah of hosts is his name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.16'>And I have put my words in thy mouth, and covered thee with the shadow of my hand, to plant the heavens, and to lay the foundations of the earth, and to say unto Zion, Thou art my people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.17'>Arouse thyself, arouse thyself, stand up, Jerusalem, which hast drunk at the hand of Jehovah the cup of his fury. Thou hast drunk, hast drained out the goblet-cup of bewilderment:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.18'>there is none to guide her among all the children that she hath brought forth; neither is there any to take her by the hand of all the children that she hath brought up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.19'>These two [things] are come unto thee; who will bemoan thee? desolation and destruction, and famine and sword: how shall I comfort thee?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.20'>Thy children have fainted, they lie at the head of all the streets, as an oryx in a net: they are full of the fury of Jehovah, the rebuke of thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.21'>Therefore hear now this, thou afflicted, and drunken, but not with wine:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.22'>thus saith thy Lord, Jehovah, and thy God, who pleadeth the cause of his people, Behold, I take out of thy hand the cup of bewilderment, the goblet-cup of my fury; thou shalt no more drink it again:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.51.23'>and I will put it into the hand of them that afflict thee; who have said to thy soul, Bow down, that we may go over; and thou hast laid thy body as the ground, and as the street to them that went over.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.52'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.52.1'>Awake, awake; put on thy strength, O Zion; put on thy beautiful garments, Jerusalem, the holy city: for henceforth there shall no more come into thee the uncircumcised and the unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.52.2'>Shake thyself from the dust; arise, sit down, Jerusalem: loose thyself from the bands of thy neck, captive daughter of Zion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.52.3'>For thus saith Jehovah: Ye have sold yourselves for nought, and ye shall be redeemed without money.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.52.4'>For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: My people went down at the first into Egypt to sojourn there, and Assyria oppressed them without cause;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.52.5'>and now, what have I here, saith Jehovah, that my people hath been taken away for nought? They that rule over them make them to howl, saith Jehovah; and continually all the day is my name scorned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.52.6'>Therefore my people shall know my name; therefore [they shall know] in that day that I [am] HE, that saith, Here am I.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.52.7'>How beautiful upon the mountains are the feet of him that announceth glad tidings, that publisheth peace; that announceth glad tidings of good, that publisheth salvation, that saith unto Zion, Thy God reigneth!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.52.8'>The voice of thy watchmen, they lift up the voice, they sing aloud together; for they shall see eye to eye, when Jehovah shall bring again Zion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.52.9'>Break forth, sing aloud together, waste places of Jerusalem; for Jehovah comforteth his people, he hath redeemed Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.52.10'>Jehovah hath made bare his holy arm in the sight of all the nations; and all the ends of the earth shall see the salvation of our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.52.11'>Depart, depart, go out from thence, touch not what is unclean; go out of the midst of her, be ye clean, that bear the vessels of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.52.12'>For ye shall not go out with haste, nor go by flight; for Jehovah will go before you, and the God of Israel will be your rear-guard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.52.13'>Behold, my servant shall deal prudently; he shall be exalted and be lifted up, and be very high.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.52.14'>As many were astonished at thee his visage was so marred more than any man, and his form more than the children of men</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.52.15'>so shall he astonish many nations; kings shall shut their mouths at him: for what had not been told them shall they see, and what they had not heard shall they consider.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.53'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.53.1'>Who hath believed our report? and to whom hath the arm of Jehovah been revealed?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.53.2'>For he shall grow up before him as a tender sapling, and as a root out of dry ground: he hath no form nor lordliness, and when we see him, there is no beauty that we should desire him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.53.3'>He is despised and left alone of men; a man of sorrows, and acquainted with grief, and like one from whom [men] hide their faces; despised, and we esteemed him not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.53.4'>Surely *he* hath borne our griefs and carried our sorrows; and we, we did regard him stricken, smitten of God, and afflicted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.53.5'>But he was wounded for our transgressions, he was bruised for our iniquities; the chastisement of our peace was upon him, and with his stripes we are healed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.53.6'>All we like sheep have gone astray, we have turned every one to his own way; and Jehovah hath laid upon him the iniquity of us all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.53.7'>He was oppressed, and he was afflicted, but he opened not his mouth; he was led as a lamb to the slaughter, and was as a sheep dumb before her shearers, and he opened not his mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.53.8'>He was taken from oppression and from judgment; and who shall declare his generation? for he was cut off out of the land of the living; for the transgression of my people was he stricken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.53.9'>And [men] appointed his grave with the wicked, but he was with the rich in his death, because he had done no violence, neither was there guile in his mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.53.10'>Yet it pleased Jehovah to bruise him; he hath subjected [him] to suffering. When thou shalt make his soul an offering for sin, he shall see a seed, he shall prolong [his] days, and the pleasure of Jehovah shall prosper in his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.53.11'>He shall see of [the fruit of] the travail of his soul, [and] shall be satisfied: by his knowledge shall my righteous servant instruct many in righteousness; and *he* shall bear their iniquities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.53.12'>Therefore will I assign him a portion with the great, and he shall divide the spoil with the strong: because he hath poured out his soul unto death, and was reckoned with the transgressors; and he bore the sin of many, and made intercession for the transgressors.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.54'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.1'>Exult, thou barren, that didst not bear; break forth into singing, and shout for joy, thou that didst not travail with child: for more are the children of the desolate than the children of the married wife, saith Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.2'>Enlarge the place of thy tent, and let them stretch forth the curtains of thy habitations: spare not, lengthen thy cords, and strengthen thy stakes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.3'>For thou shalt spread abroad on the right hand and on the left; and thy seed shall possess nations, and they shall make desolate cities to be inhabited.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.4'>Fear not, for thou shalt not be ashamed; neither be thou confounded, for thou shalt not be put to shame: for thou shalt forget the shame of thy youth, and shalt not remember the reproach of thy widowhood any more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.5'>For thy Maker is thy husband: Jehovah of hosts is his name, and thy Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel: the God of the whole earth shall he be called.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.6'>For Jehovah hath called thee as a woman forsaken and grieved in spirit, and as a wife of youth, that hath been refused, saith thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.7'>For a small moment have I forsaken thee; but with great mercies will I gather thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.8'>In the outpouring of wrath have I hid my face from thee for a moment; but with everlasting loving-kindness will I have mercy on thee, saith Jehovah, thy Redeemer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.9'>For this is [as] the waters of Noah unto me, since I have sworn that the waters of Noah should no more go over the earth: so have I sworn that I will no more be wroth with thee, nor rebuke thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.10'>For the mountains shall depart, and the hills be removed; but my loving-kindness shall not depart from thee, neither shall my covenant of peace be removed, saith Jehovah, that hath mercy on thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.11'>[Thou] afflicted, tossed with tempest, not comforted! Behold, I will set thy stones in antimony, and lay thy foundations with sapphires;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.12'>and I will make thy battlements of rubies, and thy gates of carbuncles, and all thy borders of precious stones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.13'>And all thy children [shall be] taught of Jehovah, and great shall be the peace of thy children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.14'>In righteousness shalt thou be established: thou shalt be far from oppression, for thou shalt not fear; and from terror, for it shall not come near thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.15'>Behold, they shall surely gather together, [but] not by me: whosoever gathereth together against thee shall fall because of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.16'>Behold, it is I who have created the smith that bloweth in the fire of coal, and that bringeth forth an instrument for his work; and I have created the destroyer to ravage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.54.17'>No weapon that is prepared against thee shall prosper; and every tongue that riseth against thee in judgment, thou shalt condemn. This is the inheritance of the servants of Jehovah; and their righteousness is of me, saith Jehovah.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.55'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.55.1'>Ho, every one that thirsteth, come ye to the waters; and he that hath no money, come ye, buy, and eat: yea, come, buy wine and milk without money and without price!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.55.2'>Wherefore do ye spend money for [that which is] not bread? and your labour for that which satisfieth not? Hearken diligently unto me, and eat ye [that which is] good, and let your soul delight itself in fatness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.55.3'>Incline your ear, and come unto me; hear, and your soul shall live; and I will make an everlasting covenant with you, the sure mercies of David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.55.4'>Behold, I have given him [for] a witness to the peoples, a prince and commander to the peoples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.55.5'>Behold, thou shalt call a nation thou knowest not, and a nation [that] knew not thee shall run unto thee, because of Jehovah thy God, and the Holy One of Israel; for he hath glorified thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.55.6'>Seek ye Jehovah while he may be found, call ye upon him while he is near.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.55.7'>Let the wicked forsake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts; and let him return unto Jehovah, and he will have mercy upon him; and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.55.8'>For my thoughts are not your thoughts, neither are your ways my ways, saith Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.55.9'>For [as] the heavens are higher than the earth, so are my ways higher than your ways, and my thoughts than your thoughts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.55.10'>For as the rain cometh down, and the snow from heaven, and returneth not thither, but watereth the earth, and maketh it bring forth and bud, that it may give seed to the sower, and bread to the eater:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.55.11'>so shall my word be that goeth forth out of my mouth: it shall not return unto me void, but it shall do that which I please, and it shall accomplish that for which I send it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.55.12'>For ye shall go out with joy, and be led forth with peace; the mountains and the hills shall break forth before you into singing, and all the trees of the field shall clap their hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.55.13'>Instead of the thorn shall come up the cypress, and instead of the nettle shall come up the myrtle; and it shall be to Jehovah for a name, for an everlasting sign [that] shall not be cut off.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.56'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.56.1'>Thus saith Jehovah: Keep ye judgment and do righteousness; for my salvation is near to come, and my righteousness to be revealed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.56.2'>Blessed is the man that doeth this, and the son of man that holdeth fast to it; that keepeth the sabbath from profaning it, and keepeth his hand from doing any evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.56.3'>And let not the son of the alien, that hath joined himself to Jehovah, speak saying, Jehovah hath entirely separated me from his people; neither let the eunuch say, Behold, I am a dry tree;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.56.4'>for thus saith Jehovah: Unto the eunuchs that keep my sabbaths, and choose the things that please me, and hold fast to my covenant,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.56.5'>even unto them will I give in my house and within my walls a place and a name better than of sons and daughters; I will give them an everlasting name, that shall not be cut off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.56.6'>Also the sons of the alien, that join themselves to Jehovah, to minister unto him and to love the name of Jehovah, to be his servants, every one that keepeth the sabbath from profaning it, and holdeth fast to my covenant;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.56.7'>even them will I bring to my holy mountain, and make them joyful in my house of prayer; their burnt-offerings and their sacrifices shall be accepted upon mine altar: for my house shall be called a house of prayer for all the peoples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.56.8'>The Lord Jehovah, who gathereth the outcasts of Israel, saith: Yet will I gather [others] to him, with those of his that are gathered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.56.9'>All ye beasts of the field, come to devour, all ye beasts in the forest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.56.10'>His watchmen are all of them blind, they are without knowledge; they are all dumb dogs that cannot bark, dreaming, lying down, loving to slumber:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.56.11'>and the dogs are greedy, they know not to be satisfied, and these are shepherds that know not how to discern: they all turn to their own way, every one for his gain, even to the last of them:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.56.12'>Come, [say they,] I will fetch wine, and we will fill ourselves with strong drink; and to-morrow shall be as this day, [and] much more abundant.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.57'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.1'>The righteous perisheth, and no man layeth it to heart; and merciful men are taken away, none considering that the righteous is taken away from before the evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.2'>He entereth into peace: they rest in their beds, [each one] that hath walked in his uprightness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.3'>But draw near hither, ye sons of the sorceress, the seed of the adulterer and the harlot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.4'>Against whom do ye sport yourselves? Against whom do ye make a wide mouth, [and] draw out the tongue? Are ye not children of transgression, a seed of falsehood,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.5'>inflaming yourselves with idols under every green tree, slaying the children in the valleys under the clefts of the rocks?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.6'>Among the smooth [stones] of the torrent is thy portion; they, they are thy lot: even to them hast thou poured out a drink-offering, thou hast offered an oblation. Shall I be comforted myself as to these things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.7'>Upon a lofty and high mountain hast thou set thy bed: even thither didst thou go up to offer sacrifice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.8'>Behind the doors also and the posts hast thou set up thy remembrance: for apart from me, thou hast uncovered thyself, and art gone up; thou hast enlarged thy bed, and hast made agreement with them; thou lovedst their bed, thou sawest their nakedness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.9'>And thou wentest to the king with ointment, and didst multiply thy perfumes, and didst send thy messengers afar off, and didst debase thyself unto Sheol.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.10'>Thou wast wearied by the multitude of thy ways; [but] thou saidst not, It is of no avail. Thou didst find a quickening of thy strength; therefore thou wast not sick [of it].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.11'>And of whom hast thou been afraid or feared, that thou hast lied, and hast not remembered me, nor taken it to heart? Have not I even of long time held my peace, and thou fearest me not?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.12'>I will declare thy righteousness, and thy works; and they shall not profit thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.13'>When thou criest, let them that are gathered by thee deliver thee! But a wind shall carry them all away, a breath shall take them; but he that putteth his trust in me shall inherit the land, and possess my holy mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.14'>And it shall be said, Cast up, cast up, prepare the way, take up the stumbling-blocks out of the way of my people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.15'>For thus saith the high and lofty One that inhabiteth eternity, and whose name is Holy: I dwell in the high and holy [place], and with him that is of a contrite and humble spirit, to revive the spirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.16'>For I will not contend for ever, neither will I be always wroth; for the spirit would fail before me, and the souls [which] I have made.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.17'>For the iniquity of his covetousness was I wroth, and smote him; I hid me, and was wroth, and he went on backslidingly in the way of his heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.18'>I have seen his ways, and will heal him; and I will lead him, and will restore comforts unto him and to those of his that mourn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.19'>I create the fruit of the lips: peace, peace to him [that is] afar off, and to him [that is] nigh, saith Jehovah; and I will heal him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.20'>But the wicked are like the troubled sea, which cannot rest, and whose waters cast up mire and dirt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.57.21'>There is no peace, saith my God, to the wicked.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.58'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.58.1'>Cry aloud, spare not, lift up thy voice like a trumpet, and declare unto my people their transgression, and to the house of Jacob their sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.58.2'>Yet they seek me daily, and delight to know my ways, as a nation that doeth righteousness, and hath not forsaken the ordinance of their God; they ask of me the ordinances of righteousness, they take delight in approaching to God:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.58.3'>Wherefore have we fasted, and thou seest not; have afflicted our soul, and thou takest no knowledge? Behold, in the day of your fast ye find what pleaseth [you], and exact all your labours.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.58.4'>Behold, ye have fasted for strife and debate, and to smite with the fist of wickedness; ye do not at present fast, to cause your voice to be heard on high.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.58.5'>Is such the fast that I have chosen, a day for a man to afflict his soul, that he should bow down his head as a bulrush, and spread sackcloth and ashes [under him]? Wilt thou call this a fast, and a day acceptable to Jehovah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.58.6'>Is not this the fast which I have chosen: to loose the bands of wickedness, to undo the thongs of the yoke, and to send forth free the crushed, and that ye break every yoke?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.58.7'>Is it not to deal thy bread to the hungry, and that thou bring to thy house the needy wanderers; when thou seest the naked, that thou cover him; and that thou hide not thyself from thine own flesh?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.58.8'>Then shall thy light break forth as the dawn, and thy health shall spring forth speedily; and thy righteousness shall go before thee, the glory of Jehovah shall be thy rearguard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.58.9'>Then shalt thou call, and Jehovah will answer; thou shalt cry, and he will say, Here I am. If thou take away from the midst of thee the yoke, the putting forth of the finger and the unjust speech,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.58.10'>and thou proffer thy soul to the hungry, and satisfy the afflicted soul: then shall thy light rise in the darkness, and thine obscurity be as midday;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.58.11'>and Jehovah will guide thee continually, and satisfy thy soul in drought, and strengthen thy bones; and thou shalt be like a watered garden, and like a water-spring, whose waters deceive not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.58.12'>And they [that come] of thee shall build the old waste places: thou shalt raise up the foundations [that have remained] from generation to generation; and thou shalt be called, Repairer of the breaches, restorer of frequented paths.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.58.13'>If thou turn back thy foot from the sabbath, [from] doing thy pleasure on my holy day, and call the sabbath a delight, the holy [day] of Jehovah, honourable; and thou honour him, not doing thine own ways, nor finding thine own pleasure, nor speaking [idle] words;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.58.14'>then shalt thou delight thyself in Jehovah, and I will cause thee to ride on the high places of the earth, and feed thee with the heritage of Jacob thy father: for the mouth of Jehovah hath spoken.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.59'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.1'>Behold, Jehovah's hand is not shortened that it cannot save, neither his ear heavy that it cannot hear;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.2'>but your iniquities have separated between you and your God, and your sins have hid [his] face from you, that he doth not hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.3'>For your hands are stained with blood, and your fingers with iniquity; your lips speak lies, your tongue muttereth unrighteousness:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.4'>none calleth for justice, none pleadeth in truthfulness. They trust in vanity, and speak falsehood; they conceive mischief, and bring forth iniquity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.5'>They hatch serpents' eggs, and weave the spider's web: he that eateth of their eggs dieth, and that which is crushed breaketh out into a viper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.6'>Their webs shall not become garments, neither shall they cover themselves with their works; their works are works of iniquity, and the act of violence is in their hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.7'>Their feet run to evil, and they make haste to shed innocent blood; their thoughts are thoughts of iniquity; wasting and destruction are in their paths;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.8'>the way of peace they know not, and there is no judgment in their goings; they have made their paths crooked: whoso goeth therein knoweth not peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.9'>Therefore is justice far from us, and righteousness overtaketh us not: we wait for light, and behold darkness; for brightness, [but] we walk in obscurity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.10'>We grope for the wall like the blind, and we grope as if we had no eyes: we stumble at midday as in the twilight; amongst the flourishing we are as the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.11'>We roar all like bears, and mourn grievously like doves: we look for judgment, and there is none; for salvation, [but] it is far from us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.12'>For our transgressions are multiplied before thee, and our sins testify against us; for our transgressions are with us; and our iniquities, we know them:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.13'>in transgressing and lying against Jehovah, and departing away from our God, speaking oppression and revolt, conceiving and uttering from the heart words of falsehood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.14'>And judgment is turned away backward, and righteousness standeth afar off; for truth stumbleth in the street, and uprightness cannot enter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.15'>And truth faileth; and he that departeth from evil maketh himself a prey. And Jehovah saw [it], and it was evil in his sight that there was no judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.16'>And he saw that there was no man, and he wondered that there was no intercessor; and his arm brought him salvation, and his righteousness, it sustained him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.17'>And he put on righteousness as a breastplate, and a helmet of salvation upon his head; and he put on garments of vengeance [for] clothing, and was clad with zeal as a cloak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.18'>According to deeds, so will he repay: fury to his adversaries, recompence to his enemies; to the islands he will repay recompence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.19'>And they shall fear the name of Jehovah from the west, and from the rising of the sun, his glory. When the adversary shall come in like a flood, the Spirit of Jehovah will lift up a banner against him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.20'>And the Redeemer will come to Zion, and unto them that turn from transgression in Jacob, saith Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.59.21'>And as for me, this is my covenant with them, saith Jehovah: My spirit that is upon thee, and my words which I have put in thy mouth, shall not depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy seed, nor out of the mouth of thy seed's seed, saith Jehovah, from henceforth and for ever.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.60'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.1'>Arise, shine! for thy light is come, and the glory of Jehovah is risen upon thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.2'>For behold, darkness shall cover the earth, and gross darkness the peoples; but Jehovah will arise upon thee, and his glory shall be seen on thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.3'>And the nations shall walk by thy light, and kings by the brightness of thy rising.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.4'>Lift up thine eyes round about, and see: all they gather themselves together, they come to thee: thy sons come from afar, and thy daughters are carried upon the side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.5'>Then thou shalt see, and shalt be brightened, and thy heart shall throb, and be enlarged; for the abundance of the sea shall be turned unto thee, the wealth of the nations shall come unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.6'>A multitude of camels shall cover thee, young camels of Midian and Ephah; all they from Sheba shall come: they shall bring gold and incense; and they shall publish the praises of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.7'>All the flocks of Kedar shall be gathered unto thee, the rams of Nebaioth shall serve thee: they shall come up with acceptance on mine altar, and I will beautify the house of my magnificence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.8'>Who are these that come flying as a cloud, and as doves to their dove-cotes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.9'>For the isles shall await me, and the ships of Tarshish first, to bring thy sons from afar, their silver and their gold with them, unto the name of Jehovah thy God, and to the Holy One of Israel, for he hath glorified thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.10'>And the sons of the alien shall build up thy walls, and their kings shall minister unto thee. For in my wrath I smote thee, but in my favour have I had mercy on thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.11'>And thy gates shall stand open continually: (they shall not be shut day nor night,) that the wealth of the nations may be brought unto thee, and that their kings may be led [to thee].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.12'>For the nation and the kingdom that will not serve thee shall perish; and those nations shall be utterly wasted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.13'>The glory of Lebanon shall come unto thee, the cypress, pine, and box-tree together, to beautify the place of my sanctuary; and I will make the place of my feet glorious.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.14'>And the children of them that afflicted thee shall come bending unto thee; and all they that despised thee shall bow themselves down at the soles of thy feet; and they shall call thee The city of Jehovah, the Zion of the Holy One of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.15'>Instead of thy being forsaken and hated, so that no one went through [thee], I will make thee an eternal excellency, a joy from generation to generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.16'>And thou shalt suck the milk of the nations, and shalt suck the breast of kings; and thou shalt know that I, Jehovah, [am] thy Saviour and thy Redeemer, the Mighty One of Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.17'>For bronze I will bring gold, and for iron I will bring silver, and for wood bronze, and for stones iron; and I will make thine officers peace, and thy rulers righteousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.18'>Violence shall no more be heard in thy land, wasting nor destruction within thy borders; but thou shalt call thy walls Salvation, and thy gates Praise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.19'>The sun shall be no more thy light by day, neither for brightness shall the moon give light unto thee; but Jehovah shall be thine everlasting light, and thy God thy glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.20'>Thy sun shall no more go down, neither shall thy moon withdraw itself; for Jehovah shall be thine everlasting light, and the days of thy mourning shall be ended.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.21'>Thy people also shall be all righteous: they shall possess the land for ever the branch of my planting, the work of my hands, that I may be glorified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.60.22'>The little one shall become a thousand, and the smallest a mighty nation: I, Jehovah, will hasten it in its time.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.61'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.61.1'>The Spirit of the Lord Jehovah is upon me, because Jehovah hath anointed me to announce glad tidings unto the meek; he hath sent me to bind up the broken-hearted, to proclaim liberty to the captives, and opening of the prison to them that are bound;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.61.2'>to proclaim the acceptable year of Jehovah, and the day of vengeance of our God; to comfort all that mourn;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.61.3'>to appoint unto them that mourn in Zion, that beauty should be given unto them instead of ashes, the oil of joy instead of mourning, the garment of praise instead of the spirit of heaviness: that they might be called terebinths of righteousness, the planting of Jehovah, that he may be glorified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.61.4'>And they shall build the old wastes, they shall raise up the former desolations, and they shall repair the waste cities, the places desolate from generation to generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.61.5'>And strangers shall stand and feed your flocks, and the sons of the alien shall be your ploughmen and your vinedressers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.61.6'>But as for you, ye shall be called priests of Jehovah; it shall be said of you: Ministers of our God. Ye shall eat the wealth of the nations, and into their glory shall ye enter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.61.7'>Instead of your shame [ye shall have] double; instead of confusion they shall celebrate with joy their portion: therefore in their land they shall possess the double; everlasting joy shall be unto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.61.8'>For I, Jehovah, love judgment, I hate robbery with wrong; and I will give their recompence in truth, and I will make an everlasting covenant with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.61.9'>And their seed shall be known among the nations, and their offspring among the peoples: all that see them shall acknowledge them, that they are a seed that Jehovah hath blessed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.61.10'>I will greatly rejoice in Jehovah, my soul shall be joyful in my God; for he hath clothed me with the garments of salvation, he hath covered me with the robe of righteousness, as a bridegroom decketh himself with the priestly turban, and as a bride adorneth herself with her jewels.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.61.11'>For as the earth bringeth forth her bud, and as a garden causeth the things that are sown in it to spring forth, so the Lord Jehovah will cause righteousness and praise to spring forth before all the nations.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.62'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.62.1'>For Zion's sake will I not hold my peace, and for Jerusalem's sake I will not be still, until her righteousness go forth as brightness, and her salvation as a torch that burneth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.62.2'>And the nations shall see thy righteousness, and all kings thy glory; and thou shalt be called by a new name, which the mouth of Jehovah will name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.62.3'>And thou shalt be a crown of beauty in the hand of Jehovah, and a royal diadem in the hand of thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.62.4'>Thou shalt no more be termed, Forsaken; neither shall thy land any more be termed, Desolate: but thou shalt be called, My delight is in her, and thy land, Married; for Jehovah delighteth in thee, and thy land shall be married.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.62.5'>For [as] a young man marrieth a virgin, shall thy sons marry thee; and with the joy of the bridegroom over the bride, shall thy God rejoice over thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.62.6'>I have set watchmen upon thy walls, Jerusalem; all the day and all the night they shall never hold their peace: ye that put Jehovah in remembrance, keep not silence,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.62.7'>and give him no rest, till he establish, and till he make Jerusalem a praise in the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.62.8'>Jehovah hath sworn by his right hand and by the arm of his strength, I will indeed no more give thy corn [to be] food for thine enemies; and the sons of the alien shall not drink thy new wine, for which thou hast laboured;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.62.9'>for they that have garnered it shall eat it, and praise Jehovah; and they that have gathered it shall drink it in the courts of my holiness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.62.10'>Go through, go through the gates; prepare the way of the people; cast up, cast up the highway; gather out the stones; lift up a banner for the peoples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.62.11'>Behold, Jehovah hath proclaimed unto the end of the earth, Say ye to the daughter of Zion, Behold, thy salvation cometh; behold, his reward is with him, and his recompence before him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.62.12'>And they shall call them, The holy people, The redeemed of Jehovah; and thou shalt be called, The sought out, The city not forsaken.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.63'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.1'>Who is this that cometh from Edom, with deep-red garments from Bozrah, this that is glorious in his apparel, travelling in the greatness of his strength? I that speak in righteousness, mighty to save.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.2'>Wherefore is redness in thine apparel, and thy garments like him that treadeth in the winevat?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.3'>I have trodden the winepress alone, and of the peoples not a man was with me; and I have trodden them in mine anger, and trampled them in my fury; and their blood is sprinkled upon my garments, and I have stained all mine apparel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.4'>For the day of vengeance was in my heart, and the year of my redeemed had come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.5'>And I looked, and there was none to help; and I wondered that there was none to uphold: and mine own arm brought salvation unto me; and my fury, it upheld me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.6'>And I have trodden down the peoples in mine anger, and made them drunk in my fury; and their blood have I brought down to the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.7'>I will record the loving-kindnesses of Jehovah, the praises of Jehovah, according to all that Jehovah hath bestowed upon us, and the great goodness toward the house of Israel which he hath bestowed upon them according to his mercies, and according to the multitude of his loving-kindnesses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.8'>And he said, They are indeed my people, children that will not lie; and he became their Saviour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.9'>In all their affliction he was afflicted, and the Angel of his presence saved them: in his love and in his pity he redeemed them; and he bore them and carried them all the days of old.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.10'>But they rebelled and grieved his holy Spirit: and he turned to be their enemy; himself, he fought against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.11'>But he remembered the days of old, Moses [and] his people: Where is he that brought them up out of the sea with the shepherds of his flock? Where is he that put his holy Spirit within him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.12'>his glorious arm leading them by the right hand of Moses, dividing the waters before them, to make himself an everlasting name,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.13'>who led them through the depths, like a horse in the wilderness, [and] they stumbled not?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.14'>As cattle go down into the valley, the Spirit of Jehovah gave them rest; so didst thou lead thy people, to make thyself a glorious name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.15'>Look down from the heavens, and behold from the habitation of thy holiness and of thy glory! Where is thy zeal and thy strength, the sounding of thy bowels and of thy tender mercies? Are they restrained toward me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.16'>For thou art our Father, though Abraham be ignorant of us, and Israel acknowledge us not: thou, Jehovah, art our Father; our Redeemer, from everlasting, is thy name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.17'>Why, O Jehovah, hast thou made us to err from thy ways, hast hardened our heart from thy fear? Return for thy servants' sake, the tribes of thine inheritance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.18'>Thy holy people have possessed [it] but a little while: our adversaries have trodden down thy sanctuary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.63.19'>We have become [like those] over whom thou never barest rule, those not called by thy name.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.64'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.64.1'>Oh, that thou wouldest rend the heavens, that thou wouldest come down, that the mountains might flow down at thy presence,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.64.2'>as fire kindleth brushwood, as the fire causeth water to boil, to make thy name known to thine adversaries, that the nations might tremble at thy presence!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.64.3'>When thou didst terrible things [which] we looked not for, thou camest down, and the mountains flowed down at thy presence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.64.4'>Never have [men] heard, nor perceived by the ear, nor hath eye seen a God beside thee, who acteth for him that waiteth for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.64.5'>Thou meetest him that rejoiceth to do righteousness, those that remember thee in thy ways: (behold, thou wast wroth, and we have sinned:) in those is perpetuity, and we shall be saved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.64.6'>And we are all become as an unclean [thing], and all our righteousnesses are as filthy rags; and we all fade as a leaf, and our iniquities, like the wind, have carried us away;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.64.7'>and there is none that calleth upon thy name, that stirreth up himself to take hold of thee; for thou hast hidden thy face from us, and hast caused us to melt away through our iniquities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.64.8'>And now, Jehovah, thou art our Father; we are the clay, and thou our potter; and we all are the work of thy hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.64.9'>Be not wroth very sore, O Jehovah, neither remember iniquity for ever. Behold, see, we beseech thee, we are all thy people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.64.10'>Thy holy cities are become a wilderness, Zion is a wilderness, Jerusalem a desolation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.64.11'>Our holy and our beautiful house, where our fathers praised thee, is burnt up with fire, and all our precious things are laid waste.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.64.12'>Wilt thou restrain thyself in presence of these things, Jehovah? Wilt thou hold thy peace, and afflict us very sore?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.65'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.1'>I am sought out of them that inquired not [for me], I am found of them that sought me not; I have said, Behold me, behold me, unto a nation that was not called by my name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.2'>I have stretched out my hands all the day unto a rebellious people, who walk in a way not good, after their own thoughts;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.3'>the people that provoke me to anger continually to my face, sacrificing in gardens and burning incense upon the bricks;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.4'>who sit down among the graves, and lodge in the secret places; who eat swine's flesh, and broth of abominable things [is in] their vessels;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.5'>who say, Stand by thyself, come not near to me; for I am holier than thou. These are a smoke in my nose, a fire that burneth all the day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.6'>Behold, it is written before me: I will not keep silence, but will recompense, even recompense into their bosom,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.7'>your iniquities, and the iniquities of your fathers together, saith Jehovah, who have burned incense upon the mountains, and outraged me upon the hills; and I will measure their former work into their bosom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.8'>Thus saith Jehovah: As the new wine is found in the cluster, and it is said, Destroy it not, for a blessing is in it; so will I do for my servants' sakes, that I may not destroy [them] all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.9'>And I will bring forth a seed out of Jacob, and out of Judah a possessor of my mountains; and mine elect shall possess it, and my servants shall dwell there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.10'>And the Sharon shall be a fold for flocks, and the valley of Achor a couching-place of the herds, for my people that have sought me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.11'>But ye who forsake Jehovah, who forget my holy mountain, who prepare a table for Gad, and fill up mixed wine unto Meni:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.12'>I will even assign you to the sword, and ye shall all bow down in the slaughter; because I called, and ye did not answer, I spoke, and ye did not hear; but ye did what was evil in mine eyes, and chose that wherein I delight not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.13'>Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, my servants shall eat, and *ye* shall be hungry; behold, my servants shall drink, and *ye* shall be thirsty; behold, my servants shall rejoice, and *ye* shall be ashamed;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.14'>behold, my servants shall sing aloud for gladness of heart, and *ye* shall cry out for sorrow of heart, and shall howl for vexation of spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.15'>And ye shall leave your name for a curse unto mine elect; for the Lord Jehovah will slay thee, and will call his servants by another name:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.16'>so that he who blesseth himself in the land shall bless himself by the God of truth; and he that sweareth in the land shall swear by the God of truth: because the former troubles shall be forgotten, and because they shall be hidden from mine eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.17'>For behold, I create new heavens and a new earth; and the former shall not be remembered, nor come into mind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.18'>But be glad and rejoice for ever in that which I create. For behold, I create Jerusalem a rejoicing, and her people a joy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.19'>And I will rejoice over Jerusalem, and will joy in my people; and the voice of weeping shall be no more heard in her, nor the voice of crying.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.20'>There shall be no more thenceforth an infant of days, nor an old man that hath not completed his days; for the youth shall die a hundred years old, and the sinner being a hundred years old shall be accursed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.21'>And they shall build houses, and inhabit them; and they shall plant vineyards, and eat the fruit thereof:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.22'>they shall not build, and another inhabit; they shall not plant, and another eat: for as the days of a tree shall be the days of my people, and mine elect shall long enjoy the work of their hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.23'>They shall not labour in vain, nor bring forth for terror; for they are the seed of the blessed of Jehovah, and their offspring with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.24'>And it shall come to pass, that before they call, I will answer; while they are yet speaking, I will hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.65.25'>The wolf and the lamb shall feed together, and the lion shall eat straw like the ox; and dust shall be the serpent's meat. They shall not hurt nor destroy in all my holy mountain, saith Jehovah.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Isa.66'>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.1'>Thus saith Jehovah: The heavens are my throne, and the earth is my footstool: what is the house that ye will build unto me? and what is the place of my rest?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.2'>Even all these things hath my hand made, and all these things have been, saith Jehovah. But to this man will I look: to the afflicted and contrite in spirit, and who trembleth at my word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.3'>He that slaughtereth an ox, smiteth a man; he that sacrificeth a lamb, breaketh a dog's neck; he that offereth an oblation, [it is as] swine's blood; he that presenteth a memorial of incense, [is as] he that blesseth an idol. As they have chosen their own ways, and their soul delighteth in their abominations,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.4'>I also will choose their calamities, and will bring their fears upon them; because I called, and none answered, I spoke, and they did not hear, but did that which was evil in mine eyes, and chose that wherein I delight not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.5'>Hear the word of Jehovah, ye that tremble at his word: Your brethren that hated you, that cast you out for my name's sake, said, Let Jehovah be glorified, and let us see your joy! but they shall be ashamed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.6'>A voice of tumult from the city, a voice from the temple, a voice of Jehovah that rendereth recompence to his enemies!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.7'>Before she travailed, she brought forth; before her pain came, she was delivered of a man-child.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.8'>Who hath heard such a thing? who hath seen such things? Can a land be made to bring forth in one day? shall a nation be born at once? For as soon as Zion travailed, she brought forth her sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.9'>Shall I bring to the birth, and not cause to bring forth? saith Jehovah; I who cause to bring forth, shall I shut [the womb]? saith thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.10'>Rejoice with Jerusalem, and be glad for her, all ye that love her; rejoice for joy with her, all ye that mourn over her:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.11'>because ye shall suck, and be satisfied with the breasts of her consolations; because ye shall drink out, and be delighted with the abundance of her glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.12'>For thus saith Jehovah: Behold, I will extend peace to her like a river, and the glory of the nations like an overflowing torrent; and ye shall suck, ye shall be carried upon the side, and be dandled upon the knees.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.13'>As one whom his mother comforteth, so will I comfort you; and ye shall be comforted in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.14'>And ye shall see [this], and your heart shall rejoice, and your bones shall flourish like the grass; and the hand of Jehovah shall be known toward his servants, and he will have indignation toward his enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.15'>For behold, Jehovah will come with fire, and his chariots like a whirlwind, to render his anger with fury, and his rebuke with flames of fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.16'>For by fire and by his sword will Jehovah enter into judgment with all flesh: and the slain of Jehovah shall be many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.17'>They that sanctify themselves, and purify themselves in the gardens behind one in the midst; that eat swine's flesh, and the abomination, and the mouse, shall perish together, saith Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.18'>And I, their works and their thoughts [are before me]. [The time] cometh for the gathering of all nations and tongues; and they shall come, and see my glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.19'>And I will set a sign among them, and I will send those that escape of them unto the nations, to Tarshish, Pul, and Lud, that draw the bow; to Tubal and Javan, to the isles afar off, that have not heard my fame, neither have seen my glory: and they shall declare my glory among the nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.20'>And they shall bring all your brethren out of all the nations as an oblation unto Jehovah, upon horses, and in chariots, and in covered waggons, and upon mules, and upon dromedaries, to my holy mountain, to Jerusalem, saith Jehovah, as the children of Israel bring an oblation in a clean vessel into the house of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.21'>And I will also take of them for priests [and] for Levites, saith Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.22'>For as the new heavens and the new earth which I will make shall remain before me, saith Jehovah, so shall your seed and your name remain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.23'>And it shall come to pass from new moon to new moon, and from sabbath to sabbath, all flesh shall come to worship before me, saith Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Isa.66.24'>And they shall go forth, and look upon the carcases of the men that have transgressed against me: for their worm shall not die, neither shall their fire be quenched; and they shall be an abhorrence unto all flesh.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>