<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='darby' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='darby'>
        <title>Darby Bible</title>
        <contributor>The Unbound Bible
Biola University:
13800 Biola Ave.
La Mirada, CA 90639
United States of America
562-903-4722 </contributor>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>The Holy Bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>First published in 1890 by John Nelson Darby, an Anglo-Irish bible teacher associated with the early years of the Plymouth Brethren. Darby also published translations of the Bible in French and German.</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>darby</identifier>
        <source>http://unbound.biola.edu/zips/index.cfm?lang=English</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the Bible to the nations of the world</coverage>
        <rights>We believe that this Bible is found in the Public Domain.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Zech'>
      <chapter osisID='Zech.1'>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.1'>In the eighth month, in the second year of Darius, came the word of Jehovah unto Zechariah the prophet, the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.2'>Jehovah hath been very wroth with your fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.3'>And thou shalt say unto them, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Return unto me, saith Jehovah of hosts, and I will return unto you, saith Jehovah of hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.4'>Be ye not as your fathers, unto whom the former prophets cried, saying, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Turn ye now from your evil ways, and from your evil doings; but they did not hearken nor attend unto me, saith Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.5'>Your fathers, where are they? and the prophets, do they live for ever?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.6'>But my words and my statutes, which I commanded my servants the prophets, did they not overtake your fathers? And they turned and said, Like as Jehovah of hosts thought to do unto us, according to our ways and according to our doings, so hath he dealt with us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.7'>Upon the four and twentieth day of the eleventh month, which is the month Shebat, in the second year of Darius, came the word of Jehovah unto Zechariah the prophet, the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.8'>I saw by night, and behold, a man riding upon a red horse, and he stood among the myrtle-trees that were in the low valley; and behind him were red, bay, and white horses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.9'>And I said, My lord, what are these? And the angel that talked with me said unto me, I will shew thee what these are.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.10'>And the man that stood among the myrtle-trees answered and said, These are they whom Jehovah hath sent to walk to and fro through the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.11'>And they answered the angel of Jehovah that stood among the myrtle-trees, and said, We have walked to and fro through the earth, and behold, all the earth sitteth still and is at rest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.12'>And the angel of Jehovah answered and said, Jehovah of hosts, how long wilt thou not have mercy on Jerusalem and on the cities of Judah, against which thou hast had indignation these seventy years?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.13'>And Jehovah answered the angel that talked with me good words, comforting words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.14'>And the angel that talked with me said unto me, Cry, saying, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: I am jealous for Jerusalem and for Zion with a great jealousy,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.15'>and I am wroth exceedingly with the nations that are at ease; for I was but a little wroth, and they helped forward the affliction.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.16'>Therefore thus saith Jehovah: I am returned to Jerusalem with mercies: my house shall be built in it, saith Jehovah of hosts, and the line shall be stretched forth upon Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.17'>Cry further, saying, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: My cities shall yet overflow with prosperity, and Jehovah shall yet comfort Zion, and shall yet choose Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.18'>And I lifted up mine eyes, and saw, and behold four horns.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.19'>And I said unto the angel that talked with me, What are these? And he said to me, These are the horns which have scattered Judah, Israel, and Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.20'>And Jehovah shewed me four craftsmen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.1.21'>And I said, What come these to do? And he spoke, saying, Those are the horns which scattered Judah, so that no man lifted up his head; but these are come to affright them, to cast out the horns of the nations, which lifted up the horn against the land of Judah to scatter it.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Zech.2'>
        <verse osisID='Zech.2.1'>And I lifted up mine eyes, and saw, and behold a man with a measuring line in his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.2.2'>And I said, Whither goest thou? And he said unto me, To measure Jerusalem, to see what is the breadth thereof, and what is the length thereof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.2.3'>And behold, the angel that talked with me went forth; and another angel went forth to meet him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.2.4'>and said unto him, Run, speak to this young man, saying, Jerusalem shall be inhabited as towns without walls for the multitude of men and cattle therein;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.2.5'>and I, saith Jehovah, I will be unto her a wall of fire round about, and will be the glory in the midst of her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.2.6'>Ho, ho! flee from the land of the north, saith Jehovah; for I have scattered you abroad as the four winds of the heavens, saith Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.2.7'>Ho! escape, Zion, that dwellest with the daughter of Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.2.8'>For thus saith Jehovah of hosts: After the glory, hath he sent me unto the nations that made you a spoil; for he that toucheth you toucheth the apple of his eye.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.2.9'>For behold, I will shake my hand upon them, and they shall become a spoil to those that served them: and ye shall know that Jehovah of hosts hath sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.2.10'>Sing aloud and rejoice, daughter of Zion; for behold, I come, and I will dwell in the midst of thee, saith Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.2.11'>And many nations shall join themselves to Jehovah in that day, and shall be unto me for a people; and I will dwell in the midst of thee, and thou shalt know that Jehovah of hosts hath sent me unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.2.12'>And Jehovah shall inherit Judah [as] his portion in the holy land, and shall yet choose Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.2.13'>Let all flesh be silent before Jehovah; for he is risen up out of his holy habitation.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Zech.3'>
        <verse osisID='Zech.3.1'>And he shewed me Joshua the high priest standing before the Angel of Jehovah, and Satan standing at his right hand to resist him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.3.2'>And Jehovah said unto Satan, Jehovah rebuke thee, O Satan! Yea, Jehovah that hath chosen Jerusalem rebuke thee! Is not this a brand plucked out of the fire?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.3.3'>And Joshua was clothed with filthy garments, and stood before the Angel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.3.4'>And he spoke and said unto those that stood before him, saying, Take away the filthy garments from off him. And unto him he said, See, I have caused thine iniquity to pass from thee, and I clothe thee with festival-robes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.3.5'>And I said, Let them set a pure turban upon his head. And they set the pure turban upon his head, and clothed him with garments; and the Angel of Jehovah stood by.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.3.6'>And the Angel of Jehovah protested unto Joshua, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.3.7'>Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: If thou wilt walk in my ways, and if thou wilt keep my charge, then thou shalt also judge my house, and shalt also keep my courts; and I will give thee a place to walk among these that stand by.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.3.8'>Hear now, Joshua the high priest, thou and thy fellows that sit before thee for they are men of portent for behold, I will bring forth my servant the Branch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.3.9'>For behold, the stone that I have laid before Joshua upon one stone are seven eyes; behold, I will engrave the graving thereof, saith Jehovah of hosts, and I will remove the iniquity of this land in one day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.3.10'>In that day, saith Jehovah of hosts, shall ye invite every man his neighbour under the vine and under the fig-tree.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Zech.4'>
        <verse osisID='Zech.4.1'>And the angel that talked with me came again, and waked me, as a man that is wakened out of his sleep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.4.2'>And he said unto me, What seest thou? And I said, I see, and behold, a lamp-stand all of gold, with a bowl upon the top of it, and its seven lamps thereon, seven [lamps] and seven pipes to the lamps, which are upon the top thereof;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.4.3'>and two olive-trees beside it, one on the right of the bowl, and the other on the left of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.4.4'>And I answered and spoke to the angel that talked with me, saying, What are these, my lord?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.4.5'>And the angel that talked with me answered and said unto me, Knowest thou not what these are? And I said, No, my lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.4.6'>And he answered and spoke unto me, saying, This is the word of Jehovah unto Zerubbabel, saying, Not by might, nor by power, but by my Spirit, saith Jehovah of hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.4.7'>Who art thou, O great mountain? before Zerubbabel [thou dost become] a plain; and he shall bring forth the head-stone with shoutings: Grace, grace unto it!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.4.8'>And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.4.9'>The hands of Zerubbabel have laid the foundation of this house; and his hands shall finish it: and thou shalt know that Jehovah of hosts hath sent me unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.4.10'>For who hath despised the day of small things? Yea, they shall rejoice [even] those seven and shall see the plummet in the hand of Zerubbabel: these are the eyes of Jehovah, which run to and fro in the whole earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.4.11'>And I answered and said unto him, What are these two olive-trees on the right of the lamp-stand and on its left?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.4.12'>And I answered the second time and said unto him, What are the two olive-branches which are beside the two golden tubes that empty the gold out of themselves?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.4.13'>And he spoke to me, saying, Knowest thou not what these are? And I said, No, my lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.4.14'>And he said, These are the two sons of oil, that stand before the Lord of the whole earth.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Zech.5'>
        <verse osisID='Zech.5.1'>And I lifted up mine eyes again, and saw, and behold, a flying roll.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.5.2'>And he said unto me, What seest thou? And I said, I see a flying roll: the length thereof is twenty cubits, and the breadth thereof ten cubits.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.5.3'>And he said unto me, This is the curse that goeth forth over the face of the whole land: for every one that stealeth shall be cut off according to it on this side; and every one that sweareth shall be cut off according to it on that side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.5.4'>I will cause it to go forth, saith Jehovah of hosts, and it shall enter into the house of the thief, and into the house of him that sweareth falsely by my name; and it shall lodge in the midst of his house, and shall consume it with the timber thereof and the stones thereof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.5.5'>And the angel that talked with me went forth, and said unto me, Lift up now thine eyes, and see what is this that goeth forth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.5.6'>And I said, What is it? And he said, This is the ephah that goeth forth. And he said, This is their resemblance in all the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.5.7'>And behold, there was lifted up a round plate of lead; and this is a woman that sitteth in the midst of the ephah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.5.8'>And he said, This is Wickedness: and he cast her into the midst of the ephah; and he cast the weight of lead upon the mouth thereof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.5.9'>And I lifted up mine eyes, and saw, and behold, there came out two women, and the wind was in their wings; and they had wings like the wings of a stork; and they lifted up the ephah between the earth and the heavens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.5.10'>And I said to the angel that talked with me, Whither do these carry the ephah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.5.11'>And he said unto me, To build it a house in the land of Shinar; and it shall be established, and set there upon its own base.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Zech.6'>
        <verse osisID='Zech.6.1'>And I lifted up mine eyes again, and saw, and behold, there came four chariots out from between two mountains; and the mountains were mountains of brass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.6.2'>In the first chariot were red horses; and in the second chariot black horses;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.6.3'>and in the third chariot white horses; and in the fourth chariot grisled, strong horses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.6.4'>And I spoke and said unto the angel that talked with me, What are these, my lord?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.6.5'>And the angel answered and said unto me, These are the four spirits of the heavens, which go forth from standing before the Lord of all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.6.6'>That in which are the black horses goeth forth into the north country; and the white go forth after them; and the grisled go forth towards the south country;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.6.7'>and the strong go forth, and seek to go that they may walk to and fro through the earth. And he said, Go, walk to and fro through the earth. And they walked to and fro through the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.6.8'>And he cried unto me, and spoke unto me, saying, See, these that go forth towards the north country have quieted my spirit in the north country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.6.9'>And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.6.10'>Take [gifts] of them of the captivity, of Heldai, of Tobijah, and of Jedaiah, and come thou the same day, and enter into the house of Josiah the son of Zephaniah, whither they are come from Babylon;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.6.11'>yea, take silver and gold, and make crowns, and set [them] upon the head of Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.6.12'>and speak unto him, saying, Thus speaketh Jehovah of hosts, saying, Behold a man whose name is [the] Branch; and he shall grow up from his own place, and he shall build the temple of Jehovah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.6.13'>even he shall build the temple of Jehovah; and he shall bear the glory, and shall sit and rule upon his throne; and he shall be a priest upon his throne; and the counsel of peace shall be between them both.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.6.14'>And the crowns shall be for Helem, and for Tobijah, and for Jedaiah, and for Hen the son of Zephaniah, for a memorial in the temple of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.6.15'>And they that are far off shall come and build at the temple of Jehovah: and ye shall know that Jehovah of hosts hath sent me unto you. And [this] shall come to pass, if ye will diligently hearken to the voice of Jehovah your God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Zech.7'>
        <verse osisID='Zech.7.1'>And it came to pass in the fourth year of king Darius, that the word of Jehovah came unto Zechariah on the fourth [day] of the ninth month, [even] in Chislev,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.7.2'>when Bethel had sent Sherezer and Regem-melech, and his men, to supplicate Jehovah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.7.3'>[and] to speak unto the priests that were in the house of Jehovah of hosts, and to the prophets, saying, Should I weep in the fifth month, separating myself, as I have done now so many years?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.7.4'>And the word of Jehovah of hosts came unto me, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.7.5'>Speak unto all the people of the land, and to the priests, saying, When ye fasted and mourned in the fifth and in the seventh [month], even those seventy years, did ye really fast unto me, [even] unto me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.7.6'>And when ye ate, and when ye drank, was it not you that were eating and drinking?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.7.7'>Are not these the words that Jehovah cried by the former prophets, when Jerusalem was inhabited and at peace, and her cities round about her, when the south and the lowland were inhabited?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.7.8'>And the word of Jehovah came unto Zechariah, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.7.9'>Thus speaketh Jehovah of hosts, saying, Execute true judgment, and shew loving-kindness and mercies one to another,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.7.10'>and oppress not the widow and the fatherless, the stranger and the afflicted; and let none of you imagine evil against his brother in your heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.7.11'>But they refused to hearken, and turned a rebellious shoulder, and made their ears heavy, that they should not hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.7.12'>And they made their heart [as] an adamant, that they should not hear the law, and the words that Jehovah of hosts sent by his Spirit by the hand of the former prophets: therefore was there great wrath from Jehovah of hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.7.13'>And it came to pass, like as he called, and they would not hear, so they called, and I would not hear, saith Jehovah of hosts;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.7.14'>and I scattered them with a whirlwind among all the nations whom they knew not, and the land was desolate after them, so that no one passed through nor returned; and they laid the pleasant land desolate.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Zech.8'>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.1'>And the word of Jehovah of hosts came [unto me], saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.2'>Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: I am jealous for Zion with great jealousy, and I am jealous for her with great fury.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.3'>Thus saith Jehovah: I am returned unto Zion, and will dwell in the midst of Jerusalem; and Jerusalem shall be called, The city of truth; and the mountain of Jehovah of hosts, The holy mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.4'>Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: There shall yet old men and old women sit in the streets of Jerusalem, each one with his staff in his hand for multitude of days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.5'>And the streets of the city shall be full of boys and girls playing in the streets thereof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.6'>Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: If it be wonderful in the eyes of the remnant of this people in those days, should it also be wonderful in mine eyes? saith Jehovah of hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.7'>Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Behold, I will save my people from the east country and from the west country;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.8'>and I will bring them, and they shall dwell in the midst of Jerusalem; and they shall be my people, and I will be their God, in truth and in righteousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.9'>Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Let your hands be strong, ye that hear in these days these words by the mouth of the prophets, that were in the day that the foundation of the house of Jehovah of hosts was laid, that the temple might be built.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.10'>For before those days there was no hire for man, nor any hire for beast; and there was no peace for him that went out or that came in, because of the distress: for I let loose all men, every one against his neighbour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.11'>But now I will not be unto the remnant of this people as in the former days, saith Jehovah of hosts;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.12'>for the seed shall be prosperous, the vine shall give its fruit, and the ground shall give its produce, and the heavens shall give their dew; and I will cause the remnant of this people to possess all these [things].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.13'>And it shall come to pass, like as ye were a curse among the nations, O house of Judah and house of Israel, so will I save you, and ye shall be a blessing: fear ye not, let your hands be strong.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.14'>For thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Like as I thought to do you evil when your fathers provoked me to wrath, saith Jehovah of hosts, and I repented not;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.15'>so again have I thought in these days to do good unto Jerusalem and to the house of Judah: fear ye not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.16'>These are the things that ye shall do: Speak truth every one with his neighbour; execute truth and the judgment of peace in your gates;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.17'>and let none of you imagine evil in your hearts against his neighbour; and love no false oath: for all these are [things] that I hate, saith Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.18'>And the word of Jehovah of hosts came unto me, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.19'>Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: The fast of the fourth [month] and the fast of the fifth, and the fast of the seventh, and the fast of the tenth, shall be to the house of Judah joy and gladness, and cheerful gatherings. Love ye then truth and peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.20'>Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Yet again shall there come peoples, and the inhabitants of many cities;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.21'>and the inhabitants of one city shall go to another, saying, Let us go speedily to supplicate Jehovah, and to seek Jehovah of hosts: I will go also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.22'>And many peoples and strong nations shall come to seek Jehovah of hosts in Jerusalem, and to supplicate Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.8.23'>Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: In those days shall ten men take hold, out of all languages of the nations, shall even take hold of the skirt of him that is a Jew, saying, We will go with you; for we have heard [that] God is with you.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Zech.9'>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.1'>The burden of the word of Jehovah, in the land of Hadrach, and [on] Damascus shall it rest; (for Jehovah hath an eye upon men, and upon all the tribes of Israel;)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.2'>and also [on] Hamath [which] bordereth thereon; on Tyre and Zidon, though she be very wise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.3'>And Tyre hath built herself a stronghold, and hath heaped up silver as the dust, and fine gold as the mire of the streets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.4'>Behold, the Lord will take possession of her, and he will smite her power in the sea; and she shall be devoured with fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.5'>Ashkelon shall see [it], and fear; Gazah also, and she shall be greatly pained; Ekron also, for her expectation shall be put to shame: and the king shall perish from Gazah, and Ashkelon shall not be inhabited.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.6'>And a bastard shall dwell in Ashdod, and I will cut off the pride of the Philistines;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.7'>and I will take away his blood out of his mouth, and his abominations from between his teeth; but he that remaineth, he also shall belong to our God, and shall be as a leader in Judah, and Ekron as a Jebusite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.8'>And I will encamp about my house because of the army, because of those that pass by and that return; and the exactor shall not pass through them any more: for now have I seen [it] with mine eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.9'>Rejoice greatly, daughter of Zion; shout, daughter of Jerusalem! Behold, thy King cometh to thee: he is just, and having salvation; lowly and rIding upon an ass, even upon a colt the foal of an ass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.10'>And I will cut off the chariot from Ephraim, and the horse from Jerusalem; and the battle-bow shall be cut off. And he shall speak peace unto the nations; and his dominion shall be from sea to sea, and from the river to the ends of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.11'>As for thee also, by the blood of thy covenant, I will send forth thy prisoners out of the pit wherein is no water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.12'>Turn again to the stronghold, prisoners of hope! even to-day do I declare I will render double unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.13'>For I have bent Judah for me, I have filled the bow with Ephraim; and I will raise up thy sons, O Zion, against thy sons, O Greece, and make thee like the sword of a mighty man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.14'>And Jehovah shall be seen over them, and his arrow shall go forth as the lightning; and the Lord Jehovah will blow the trumpet, and will march with whirlwinds of the south.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.15'>Jehovah of hosts will defend them; and they shall devour, and shall tread down the sling-stones; and they shall drink, [and] make a noise as from wine; and they shall be filled like a bowl, like the corners of the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.16'>And Jehovah their God shall save them in that day as the flock of his people; for [they shall be as] the stones of a crown, lifted up upon his land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.9.17'>For how great is his goodness, and how great is his beauty! Corn shall make the young men flourish, and new wine the maidens.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Zech.10'>
        <verse osisID='Zech.10.1'>Ask of Jehovah rain in the time of the latter rain; Jehovah will make lightnings, and he will give them showers of rain, to every one grass in the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.10.2'>For the teraphim have spoken vanity, and the diviners have seen a lie, and have told false dreams: they comfort in vain. Therefore they have gone away as a flock, they are in distress, because there is no shepherd.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.10.3'>Mine anger is kindled against the shepherds, and I will punish the he-goats; for Jehovah of hosts visiteth his flock, the house of Judah, and maketh them as his majestic horse in the battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.10.4'>From him shall come forth the corner-stone, from him the nail, from him the battle bow, from him every exactor together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.10.5'>And they shall be as mighty men, treading down the mire of the streets in the battle; and they shall fight, for Jehovah is with them, and the riders on horses shall be put to shame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.10.6'>And I will strengthen the house of Judah, and I will save the house of Joseph, and I will bring them back again; for I will have mercy upon them; and they shall be as though I had not cast them off: for I am Jehovah their God, and I will answer them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.10.7'>And [they of] Ephraim shall be like a mighty man, and their hearts shall rejoice as through wine; and their children shall see [it], and rejoice; their heart shall be joyful in Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.10.8'>I will hiss for them, and gather them; for I have redeemed them: and they shall multiply as they used to multiply.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.10.9'>And I will sow them among the peoples, and they shall remember me in far countries; and they shall live with their children and return.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.10.10'>And I will bring them again out of the land of Egypt, and gather them out of Assyria; and I will bring them into the land of Gilead and Lebanon; and [place] shall not be found for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.10.11'>And he shall pass through the sea of affliction, and shall smite the billows in the sea, and all the depths of the Nile shall dry up; and the pride of Assyria shall be brought down, and the sceptre of Egypt shall depart away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.10.12'>And I will strengthen them in Jehovah; and they shall walk in his name, saith Jehovah.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Zech.11'>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.1'>Open thy doors, O Lebanon, that the fire may devour thy cedars.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.2'>Howl, cypress, for the cedar is fallen; because the noble ones are spoiled. Howl, ye oaks of Bashan; for the strong forest is come down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.3'>A voice of howling of the shepherds; for their glory is spoiled: a voice of roaring of young lions; for the pride of Jordan is spoiled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.4'>Thus saith Jehovah my God: Feed the flock of slaughter,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.5'>whose possessors slay them without being held guilty; and they that sell them say, Blessed be Jehovah! for I am become rich; and their own shepherds pity them not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.6'>For I will no more pity the inhabitants of the land, saith Jehovah, and behold, I will deliver men, every one into his neighbour's hand, and into the hand of his king; and they shall smite the land, and I will not deliver out of their hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.7'>So I fed the flock of slaughter, truly the poor of the flock. And I took unto me two staves; the one I called Beauty, and the other I called Bands; and I fed the flock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.8'>And I destroyed three shepherds in one month; and my soul was vexed with them, and their soul also loathed me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.9'>And I said, I will not feed you: that which dieth, let it die; and that which perisheth let it perish; and let them which are left eat every one the flesh of another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.10'>And I took my staff, Beauty, and cut it asunder, that I might break my covenant which I had made with all the peoples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.11'>And it was broken in that day; and so the poor of the flock that gave heed to me knew that it was the word of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.12'>And I said unto them, If ye think good, give [me] my hire; and if not, forbear. And they weighed for my hire thirty silver-pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.13'>And Jehovah said unto me, Cast it unto the potter: a goodly price that I was prized at by them. And I took the thirty silver-pieces, and cast them to the potter in the house of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.14'>And I cut asunder mine other staff, Bands, to break the brotherhood between Judah and Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.15'>And Jehovah said unto me, Take unto thee yet the instruments of a foolish shepherd.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.16'>For behold, I will raise up a shepherd in the land, who shall not visit those that are about to perish, neither shall seek that which is strayed away, nor heal that which is wounded, nor feed that which is sound; but he will eat the flesh of the fat, and tear their hoofs in pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.11.17'>Woe to the worthless shepherd that leaveth the flock! The sword shall be upon his arm, and upon his right eye; his arm shall be clean dried up, and his right eye utterly darkened.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Zech.12'>
        <verse osisID='Zech.12.1'>The burden of the word of Jehovah concerning Israel. [Thus] saith Jehovah, who stretcheth out the heavens, and layeth the foundation of the earth, and formeth the spirit of man within him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.12.2'>Behold, I will make Jerusalem a cup of bewilderment unto all the peoples round about, and also against Judah shall it be in the siege against Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.12.3'>And it shall come to pass in that day [that] I will make Jerusalem a burdensome stone unto all peoples: all that burden themselves with it shall certainly be wounded, and all the nations of the earth shall be assembled together against it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.12.4'>In that day, saith Jehovah, I will smite every horse with astonishment, and his rider with madness; but I will open mine eyes upon the house of Judah, and will smite every horse of the peoples with blindness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.12.5'>And the leaders of Judah shall say in their heart, The inhabitants of Jerusalem shall be my strength through Jehovah of hosts their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.12.6'>In that day will I make the leaders of Judah like a hearth of fire among wood, and like a torch of fire in a sheaf; and they shall devour all the peoples round about, on the right hand and on the left; and Jerusalem shall dwell again in her own place, in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.12.7'>And Jehovah shall save the tents of Judah first, that the glory of the house of David and the glory of the inhabitants of Jerusalem be not magnified over Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.12.8'>In that day will Jehovah defend the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and he that stumbleth among them at that day shall be as David; and the house of David as God, as the Angel of Jehovah before them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.12.9'>And it shall come to pass in that day, [that] I will seek to destroy all the nations that come against Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.12.10'>And I will pour upon the house of David and upon the inhabitants of Jerusalem the spirit of grace and of supplications; and they shall look on me whom they pierced, and they shall mourn for him, as one mourneth for an only [son], and shall be in bitterness for him, as one that is in bitterness for [his] firstborn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.12.11'>In that day shall there be a great mourning in Jerusalem, as the mourning of Hadad-rimmon in the valley of Megiddon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.12.12'>And the land shall mourn, every family apart: the family of the house of David apart, and their wives apart; the family of the house of Nathan apart, and their wives apart;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.12.13'>the family of the house of Levi apart, and their wives apart; the family of Shimei apart, and their wives apart;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.12.14'>all the families that remain, every family apart, and their wives apart.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Zech.13'>
        <verse osisID='Zech.13.1'>In that day there shall be a fountain opened to the house of David and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem for sin and for uncleanness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.13.2'>And it shall come to pass in that day, saith Jehovah of hosts, [that] I will cut off the names of the idols out of the land, and they shall no more be remembered; and also I will cause the prophets and the unclean spirit to pass out of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.13.3'>And it shall come to pass, if any shall yet prophesy, that his father and his mother that begat him shall say unto him, Thou shalt not live; for thou speakest lies in the name of Jehovah; and his father and his mother that begat him shall thrust him through when he prophesieth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.13.4'>And it shall come to pass in that day, [that] the prophets shall be ashamed every one of his vision, when he prophesieth; neither shall they wear a hairy mantle to deceive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.13.5'>And he shall say, I am no prophet, I am a tiller of the ground; for man acquired me [as bondman] from my youth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.13.6'>And one shall say unto him, What are those wounds in thy hands? And he will say, Those with which I was wounded in the house of my friends.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.13.7'>Awake, O sword, against my shepherd, even against the man [that is] my fellow, saith Jehovah of hosts: smite the shepherd, and the sheep shall be scattered, and I will turn my hand upon the little ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.13.8'>And it shall come to pass in all the land, saith Jehovah, two parts therein shall be cut off [and] die; but the third shall be left therein.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.13.9'>And I will bring the third part into the fire, and will refine them as silver is refined, and will try them as gold is tried. They shall call on my name, and I will answer them: I will say, It is my people; and they shall say, Jehovah is my God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Zech.14'>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.1'>Behold, the day cometh for Jehovah, and thy spoil shall be divided in the midst of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.2'>And I will assemble all the nations against Jerusalem to battle; and the city shall be taken, and the houses rifled, and the women ravished; and half of the city shall go forth into captivity; and the rest of the people shall not be cut off from the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.3'>And Jehovah will go forth and fight with those nations, as when he fought in the day of battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.4'>And his feet shall stand in that day upon the mount of Olives, which is before Jerusalem toward the east, and the mount of Olives shall cleave in the midst thereof toward the east and toward the west, a very great valley; and half of the mountain shall remove toward the north, and half of it toward the south.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.5'>And ye shall flee [by] the valley of my mountains; for the valley of the mountains shall reach unto Azal: ye shall even flee, like as ye fled from before the earthquake in the days of Uzziah king of Judah. And Jehovah my God shall come, [and] all the holy ones with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.6'>And it shall come to pass in that day, [that] there shall not be light; the shining shall be obscured.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.7'>And it shall be one day which is known to Jehovah, not day, and not night; and it shall come to pass, at eventide it shall be light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.8'>And it shall come to pass in that day [that] living waters shall go out from Jerusalem; half of them toward the eastern sea, and half of them toward the hinder sea: in summer and in winter shall it be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.9'>And Jehovah shall be king over all the earth: in that day shall there be one Jehovah, and his name one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.10'>All the land from Geba to Rimmon south of Jerusalem shall be turned as the Arabah; and [Jerusalem] shall be lifted up, and shall dwell in her own place, from Benjamin's gate unto the place of the first gate, unto the corner-gate, and from the tower of Hananeel unto the king's winepresses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.11'>And [men] shall dwell in it, and there shall be no more utter destruction; and Jerusalem shall dwell safely.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.12'>And this shall be the plague wherewith Jehovah will smite all the peoples that have warred against Jerusalem: their flesh shall consume away while they stand upon their feet, and their eyes shall consume away in their holes, and their tongue shall consume away in their mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.13'>And it shall come to pass in that day [that] a great panic from Jehovah shall be among them; and they shall lay hold every one on the hand of his neighbour, and his hand shall rise up against the hand of his neighbour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.14'>And Judah also shall fight at Jerusalem; and the wealth of all the nations round about shall be gathered together gold, and silver, and garments, in great abundance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.15'>And so shall be the plague of the horse, of the mule, of the camel, and of the ass, and of all the beasts that shall be in those camps, as this plague.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.16'>And it shall come to pass, that all that are left of all the nations which came against Jerusalem shall go up from year to year to worship the King, Jehovah of hosts, and to celebrate the feast of tabernacles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.17'>And it shall be, that whoso goeth not up of the families of the earth unto Jerusalem to worship the King, Jehovah of hosts, upon them shall be no rain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.18'>And if the family of Egypt go not up, and come not, neither [shall it be] upon them; [there] shall be the plague, wherewith Jehovah will smite the nations that go not up to celebrate the feast of tabernacles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.19'>This shall be the punishment of Egypt, and the punishment of all the nations that go not up to celebrate the feast of tabernacles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.20'>In that day shall there be upon the bells of the horses, HOLINESS UNTO JEHOVAH; and the pots in Jehovah's house shall be like the bowls before the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Zech.14.21'>And every pot in Jerusalem and in Judah shall be holiness unto Jehovah of hosts; and all they that sacrifice shall come and take of them, and seethe therein. And in that day there shall be no more a Canaanite in the house of Jehovah of hosts.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>