<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='rsv' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='rsv'>
        <title>Revised Standard Version</title>
        <contributor>Sword Project</contributor>
        <creator>ColdHeart</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-22</date>
        <description>The Holy Bible, Revised Standard Version 1952 (RSV), the authorized revision of the American Standard Version of 1901, Copyright (c) 1946, 1952, 1973 by the Division of Christian Education of the National Council of Churches of Christ in the United States of America.</description>
        <publisher>DarkBibleORG</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>rsv</identifier>
        <source>http://www.crosswire.org/sword/servlet/SwordMod.Verify?modName=RSV</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide th bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Division of Christian Education of the National Council of the churches of Christ in the U.S.A. 1946, 1952, 1973 Rachel Riensche, Vice President, Corporate Affairs Augsburg Fortress Publishers, 100 South Fifth Street, Suite 700. Minneapolis, MN 55402, USA</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Exod'>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.1'>
        <title>When Jacob finished charging his sons, he drew up his feet into the bed, and breathed his last, and was gathered to his people.</title>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.1'>These are the names of the sons of Israel who came to Egypt with Jacob, each with his household:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.2'>Reuben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.3'>Is'sachar, Zeb'ulun, and Benjamin,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.4'>Dan and Naph'tali, Gad and Asher.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.5'>All the offspring of Jacob were seventy persons; Joseph was already in Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.6'>Then Joseph died, and all his brothers, and all that generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.7'>But the descendants of Israel were fruitful and increased greatly; they multiplied and grew exceedingly strong; so that the land was filled with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.8'>Now there arose a new king over Egypt, who did not know Joseph.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.9'>And he said to his people, "Behold, the people of Israel are too many and too mighty for us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.10'>Come, let us deal shrewdly with them, lest they multiply, and, if war befall us, they join our enemies and fight against us and escape from the land."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.11'>Therefore they set taskmasters over them to afflict them with heavy burdens; and they built for Pharaoh store-cities, Pithom and Ra-am'ses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.12'>But the more they were oppressed, the more they multiplied and the more they spread abroad. And the Egyptians were in dread of the people of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.13'>So they made the people of Israel serve with rigor,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.14'>and made their lives bitter with hard service, in mortar and brick, and in all kinds of work in the field; in all their work they made them serve with rigor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.15'>Then the king of Egypt said to the Hebrew midwives, one of whom was named Shiph'rah and the other Pu'ah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.16'>"When you serve as midwife to the Hebrew women, and see them upon the birthstool, if it is a son, you shall kill him; but if it is a daughter, she shall live."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.17'>But the midwives feared God, and did not do as the king of Egypt commanded them, but let the male children live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.18'>So the king of Egypt called the midwives, and said to them, "Why have you done this, and let the male children live?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.19'>The midwives said to Pharaoh, "Because the Hebrew women are not like the Egyptian women; for they are vigorous and are delivered before the midwife comes to them."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.20'>So God dealt well with the midwives; and the people multiplied and grew very strong.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.21'>And because the midwives feared God he gave them families.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.22'>Then Pharaoh commanded all his people, "Every son that is born to the Hebrews you shall cast into the Nile, but you shall let every daughter live."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.2'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.1'>Now a man from the house of Levi went and took to wife a daughter of Levi.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.2'>The woman conceived and bore a son; and when she saw that he was a goodly child, she hid him three months.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.3'>And when she could hide him no longer she took for him a basket made of bulrushes, and daubed it with bitumen and pitch; and she put the child in it and placed it among the reeds at the river's brink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.4'>And his sister stood at a distance, to know what would be done to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.5'>Now the daughter of Pharaoh came down to bathe at the river, and her maidens walked beside the river; she saw the basket among the reeds and sent her maid to fetch it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.6'>When she opened it she saw the child; and lo, the babe was crying. She took pity on him and said, "This is one of the Hebrews' children."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.7'>Then his sister said to Pharaoh's daughter, "Shall I go and call you a nurse from the Hebrew women to nurse the child for you?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.8'>And Pharaoh's daughter said to her, "Go." So the girl went and called the child's mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.9'>And Pharaoh's daughter said to her, "Take this child away, and nurse him for me, and I will give you your wages." So the woman took the child and nursed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.10'>And the child grew, and she brought him to Pharaoh's daughter, and he became her son; and she named him Moses, for she said, "Because I drew him out of the water."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.11'>One day, when Moses had grown up, he went out to his people and looked on their burdens; and he saw an Egyptian beating a Hebrew, one of his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.12'>He looked this way and that, and seeing no one he killed the Egyptian and hid him in the sand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.13'>When he went out the next day, behold, two Hebrews were struggling together; and he said to the man that did the wrong, "Why do you strike your fellow?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.14'>He answered, "Who made you a prince and a judge over us? Do you mean to kill me as you killed the Egyptian?" Then Moses was afraid, and thought, "Surely the thing is known."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.15'>When Pharaoh heard of it, he sought to kill Moses.  But Moses fled from Pharaoh, and stayed in the land of Mid'ian; and he sat down by a well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.16'>Now the priest of Mid'ian had seven daughters; and they came and drew water, and filled the troughs to water their father's flock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.17'>The shepherds came and drove them away; but Moses stood up and helped them, and watered their flock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.18'>When they came to their father Reu'el, he said, "How is it that you have come so soon today?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.19'>They said, "An Egyptian delivered us out of the hand of the shepherds, and even drew water for us and watered the flock."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.20'>He said to his daughters, "And where is he? Why have you left the man? Call him, that he may eat bread."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.21'>And Moses was content to dwell with the man, and he gave Moses his daughter Zippo'rah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.22'>She bore a son, and he called his name Gershom; for he said, "I have been a sojourner in a foreign land."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.23'>In the course of those many days the king of Egypt died. And the people of Israel groaned under their bondage, and cried out for help, and their cry under bondage came up to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.24'>And God heard their groaning, and God remembered his covenant with Abraham, with Isaac, and with Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.25'>And God saw the people of Israel, and God knew their condition.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.3'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.1'>Now Moses was keeping the flock of his father-in-law, Jethro, the priest of Mid'ian; and he led his flock to the west side of the wilderness, and came to Horeb, the mountain of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.2'>And the angel of the LORD appeared to him in a flame of fire out of the midst of a bush; and he looked, and lo, the bush was burning, yet it was not consumed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.3'>And Moses said, "I will turn aside and see this great sight, why the bush is not burnt."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.4'>When the LORD saw that he turned aside to see, God called to him out of the bush, "Moses, Moses!" And he said, "Here am I."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.5'>Then he said, "Do not come near; put off your shoes from your feet, for the place on which you are standing is holy ground."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.6'>And he said, "I am the God of your father, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob." And Moses hid his face, for he was afraid to look at God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.7'>Then the LORD said, "I have seen the affliction of my people who are in Egypt, and have heard their cry because of their taskmasters; I know their sufferings,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.8'>and I have come down to deliver them out of the hand of the Egyptians, and to bring them up out of that land to a good and broad land, a land flowing with milk and honey, to the place of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Amorites, the Per'izzites, the Hivites, and the Jeb'usites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.9'>And now, behold, the cry of the people of Israel has come to me, and I have seen the oppression with which the Egyptians oppress them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.10'>Come, I will send you to Pharaoh that you may bring forth my people, the sons of Israel, out of Egypt."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.11'>But Moses said to God, "Who am I that I should go to Pharaoh, and bring the sons of Israel out of Egypt?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.12'>He said, "But I will be with you; and this shall be the sign for you, that I have sent you: when you have brought forth the people out of Egypt, you shall serve God upon this mountain."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.13'>Then Moses said to God, "If I come to the people of Israel and say to them, `The God of your fathers has sent me to you,' and they ask me, `What is his name?' what shall I say to them?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.14'>God said to Moses, "I AM WHO I AM." And he said, "Say this to the people of Israel, `I AM has sent me to you.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.15'>God also said to Moses, "Say this to the people of Israel, `The LORD, the God of your fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has sent me to you': this is my name for ever, and thus I am to be remembered throughout all generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.16'>Go and gather the elders of Israel together, and say to them, `The LORD, the God of your fathers, the God of Abraham, of Isaac, and of Jacob, has appeared to me, saying, "I have observed you and what has been done to you in Egypt;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.17'>and I promise that I will bring you up out of the affliction of Egypt, to the land of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Amorites, the Per'izzites, the Hivites, and the Jeb'usites, a land flowing with milk and honey."'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.18'>And they will hearken to your voice; and you and the elders of Israel shall go to the king of Egypt and say to him, `The LORD, the God of the Hebrews, has met with us; and now, we pray you, let us go a three days' journey into the wilderness, that we may sacrifice to the LORD our God.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.19'>I know that the king of Egypt will not let you go unless compelled by a mighty hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.20'>So I will stretch out my hand and smite Egypt with all the wonders which I will do in it; after that he will let you go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.21'>And I will give this people favor in the sight of the Egyptians; and when you go, you shall not go empty,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.22'>but each woman shall ask of her neighbor, and of her who sojourns in her house, jewelry of silver and of gold, and clothing, and you shall put them on your sons and on your daughters; thus you shall despoil the Egyptians."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.4'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.1'>Then Moses answered, "But behold, they will not believe me or listen to my voice, for they will say, `The LORD did not appear to you.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.2'>The LORD said to him, "What is that in your hand?" He said, "A rod."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.3'>And he said, "Cast it on the ground." So he cast it on the ground, and it became a serpent; and Moses fled from it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.4'>But the LORD said to Moses, "Put out your hand, and take it by the tail"-- so he put out his hand and caught it, and it became a rod in his hand--</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.5'>"that they may believe that the LORD, the God of their fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has appeared to you."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.6'>Again, the LORD said to him, "Put your hand into your bosom." And he put his hand into his bosom; and when he took it out, behold, his hand was leprous, as white as snow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.7'>Then God said, "Put your hand back into your bosom." So he put his hand back into his bosom; and when he took it out, behold, it was restored like the rest of his flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.8'>"If they will not believe you," God said, "or heed the first sign, they may believe the latter sign.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.9'>If they will not believe even these two signs or heed your voice, you shall take some water from the Nile and pour it upon the dry ground; and the water which you shall take from the Nile will become blood upon the dry ground."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.10'>But Moses said to the LORD, "Oh, my Lord, I am not eloquent, either heretofore or since thou hast spoken to thy servant; but I am slow of speech and of tongue."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.11'>Then the LORD said to him, "Who has made man's mouth? Who makes him dumb, or deaf, or seeing, or blind? Is it not I, the LORD?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.12'>Now therefore go, and I will be with your mouth and teach you what you shall speak."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.13'>But he said, "Oh, my Lord, send, I pray, some other person."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.14'>Then the anger of the LORD was kindled against Moses and he said, "Is there not Aaron, your brother, the Levite? I know that he can speak well; and behold, he is coming out to meet you, and when he sees you he will be glad in his heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.15'>And you shall speak to him and put the words in his mouth; and I will be with your mouth and with his mouth, and will teach you what you shall do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.16'>He shall speak for you to the people; and he shall be a mouth for you, and you shall be to him as God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.17'>And you shall take in your hand this rod, with which you shall do the signs."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.18'>Moses went back to Jethro his father-in-law and said to him, "Let me go back, I pray, to my kinsmen in Egypt and see whether they are still alive." And Jethro said to Moses, "Go in peace."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.19'>And the LORD said to Moses in Mid'ian, "Go back to Egypt; for all the men who were seeking your life are dead."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.20'>So Moses took his wife and his sons and set them on an ass, and went back to the land of Egypt; and in his hand Moses took the rod of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.21'>And the LORD said to Moses, "When you go back to Egypt, see that you do before Pharaoh all the miracles which I have put in your power; but I will harden his heart, so that he will not let the people go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.22'>And you shall say to Pharaoh, `Thus says the LORD, Israel is my first-born son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.23'>and I say to you, "Let my son go that he may serve me"; if you refuse to let him go, behold, I will slay your first-born son.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.24'>At a lodging place on the way the LORD met him and sought to kill him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.25'>Then Zippo'rah took a flint and cut off her son's foreskin, and touched Moses' feet with it, and said, "Surely you are a bridegroom of blood to me!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.26'>So he let him alone. Then it was that she said, "You are a bridegroom of blood," because of the circumcision.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.27'>The LORD said to Aaron, "Go into the wilderness to meet Moses." So he went, and met him at the mountain of God and kissed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.28'>And Moses told Aaron all the words of the LORD with which he had sent him, and all the signs which he had charged him to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.29'>Then Moses and Aaron went and gathered together all the elders of the people of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.30'>And Aaron spoke all the words which the LORD had spoken to Moses, and did the signs in the sight of the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.31'>And the people believed; and when they heard that the LORD had visited the people of Israel and that he had seen their affliction, they bowed their heads and worshiped.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.5'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.1'>Afterward Moses and Aaron went to Pharaoh and said, "Thus says the LORD, the God of Israel, `Let my people go, that they may hold a feast to me in the wilderness.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.2'>But Pharaoh said, "Who is the LORD, that I should heed his voice and let Israel go? I do not know the LORD, and moreover I will not let Israel go."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.3'>Then they said, "The God of the Hebrews has met with us; let us go, we pray, a three days' journey into the wilderness, and sacrifice to the LORD our God, lest he fall upon us with pestilence or with the sword."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.4'>But the king of Egypt said to them, "Moses and Aaron, why do you take the people away from their work? Get to your burdens."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.5'>And Pharaoh said, "Behold, the people of the land are now many and you make them rest from their burdens!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.6'>The same day Pharaoh commanded the taskmasters of the people and their foremen,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.7'>"You shall no longer give the people straw to make bricks, as heretofore; let them go and gather straw for themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.8'>But the number of bricks which they made heretofore you shall lay upon them, you shall by no means lessen it; for they are idle; therefore they cry, `Let us go and offer sacrifice to our God.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.9'>Let heavier work be laid upon the men that they may labor at it and pay no regard to lying words."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.10'>So the taskmasters and the foremen of the people went out and said to the people, "Thus says Pharaoh, `I will not give you straw.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.11'>Go yourselves, get your straw wherever you can find it; but your work will not be lessened in the least.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.12'>So the people were scattered abroad throughout all the land of Egypt, to gather stubble for straw.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.13'>The taskmasters were urgent, saying, "Complete your work, your daily task, as when there was straw."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.14'>And the foremen of the people of Israel, whom Pharaoh's taskmasters had set over them, were beaten, and were asked, "Why have you not done all your task of making bricks today, as hitherto?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.15'>Then the foremen of the people of Israel came and cried to Pharaoh, "Why do you deal thus with your servants?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.16'>No straw is given to your servants, yet they say to us, `Make bricks!' And behold, your servants are beaten; but the fault is in your own people."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.17'>But he said, "You are idle, you are idle; therefore you say, `Let us go and sacrifice to the LORD.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.18'>Go now, and work; for no straw shall be given you, yet you shall deliver the same number of bricks."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.19'>The foremen of the people of Israel saw that they were in evil plight, when they said, "You shall by no means lessen your daily number of bricks."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.20'>They met Moses and Aaron, who were waiting for them, as they came forth from Pharaoh;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.21'>and they said to them, "The LORD look upon you and judge, because you have made us offensive in the sight of Pharaoh and his servants, and have put a sword in their hand to kill us."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.22'>Then Moses turned again to the LORD and said, "O LORD, why hast thou done evil to this people? Why didst thou ever send me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.23'>For since I came to Pharaoh to speak in thy name, he has done evil to this people, and thou hast not delivered thy people at all."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.6'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.1'>But the LORD said to Moses, "Now you shall see what I will do to Pharaoh; for with a strong hand he will send them out, yea, with a strong hand he will drive them out of his land."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.2'>And God said to Moses, "I am the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.3'>I appeared to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, as God Almighty, but by my name the LORD I did not make myself known to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.4'>I also established my covenant with them, to give them the land of Canaan, the land in which they dwelt as sojourners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.5'>Moreover I have heard the groaning of the people of Israel whom the Egyptians hold in bondage and I have remembered my covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.6'>Say therefore to the people of Israel, `I am the LORD, and I will bring you out from under the burdens of the Egyptians, and I will deliver you from their bondage, and I will redeem you with an outstretched arm and with great acts of judgment,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.7'>and I will take you for my people, and I will be your God; and you shall know that I am the LORD your God, who has brought you out from under the burdens of the Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.8'>And I will bring you into the land which I swore to give to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob; I will give it to you for a possession. I am the LORD.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.9'>Moses spoke thus to the people of Israel; but they did not listen to Moses, because of their broken spirit and their cruel bondage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.10'>And the LORD said to Moses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.11'>"Go in, tell Pharaoh king of Egypt to let the people of Israel go out of his land."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.12'>But Moses said to the LORD, "Behold, the people of Israel have not listened to me; how then shall Pharaoh listen to me, who am a man of uncircumcised lips?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.13'>But the LORD spoke to Moses and Aaron, and gave them a charge to the people of Israel and to Pharaoh king of Egypt to bring the people of Israel out of the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.14'>These are the heads of their fathers' houses: the sons of Reuben, the first-born of Israel: Hanoch, Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi; these are the families of Reuben.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.15'>The sons of Simeon: Jemu'el, Jamin, Ohad, Jachin, Zohar, and Shaul, the son of a Canaanite woman; these are the families of Simeon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.16'>These are the names of the sons of Levi according to their generations: Gershon, Kohath, and Merar'i, the years of the life of Levi being a hundred and thirty-seven years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.17'>The sons of Gershon: Libni and Shim'e-i, by their families.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.18'>The sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uz'ziel, the years of the life of Kohath being a hundred and thirty-three years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.19'>The sons of Merar'i: Mahli and Mushi. These are the families of the Levites according to their generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.20'>Amram took to wife Joch'ebed his father's sister and she bore him Aaron and Moses, the years of the life of Amram being one hundred and thirty-seven years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.21'>The sons of Izhar: Korah, Nepheg, and Zichri.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.22'>And the sons of Uz'ziel: Mi'sha-el, Elza'phan, and Sithri.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.23'>Aaron took to wife Eli'sheba, the daughter of Ammin'adab and the sister of Nahshon; and she bore him Nadab, Abi'hu, Elea'zar, and Ith'amar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.24'>The sons of Korah: Assir, Elka'nah, and Abi'asaph; these are the families of the Ko'rahites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.25'>Elea'zar, Aaron's son, took to wife one of the daughters of Pu'ti-el; and she bore him Phin'ehas. These are the heads of the fathers' houses of the Levites by their families.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.26'>These are the Aaron and Moses to whom the LORD said: "Bring out the people of Israel from the land of Egypt by their hosts."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.27'>It was they who spoke to Pharaoh king of Egypt about bringing out the people of Israel from Egypt, this Moses and this Aaron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.28'>On the day when the LORD spoke to Moses in the land of Egypt,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.29'>the LORD said to Moses, "I am the LORD; tell Pharaoh king of Egypt all that I say to you."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.30'>But Moses said to the LORD, "Behold, I am of uncircumcised lips; how then shall Pharaoh listen to me?"</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.7'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.1'>And the LORD said to Moses, "See, I make you as God to Pharaoh; and Aaron your brother shall be your prophet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.2'>You shall speak all that I command you; and Aaron your brother shall tell Pharaoh to let the people of Israel go out of his land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.3'>But I will harden Pharaoh's heart, and though I multiply my signs and wonders in the land of Egypt,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.4'>Pharaoh will not listen to you; then I will lay my hand upon Egypt and bring forth my hosts, my people the sons of Israel, out of the land of Egypt by great acts of judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.5'>And the Egyptians shall know that I am the LORD, when I stretch forth my hand upon Egypt and bring out the people of Israel from among them."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.6'>And Moses and Aaron did so; they did as the LORD commanded them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.7'>Now Moses was eighty years old, and Aaron eighty- three years old, when they spoke to Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.8'>And the LORD said to Moses and Aaron,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.9'>"When Pharaoh says to you, `Prove yourselves by working a miracle,' then you shall say to Aaron, `Take your rod and cast it down before Pharaoh, that it may become a serpent.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.10'>So Moses and Aaron went to Pharaoh and did as the LORD commanded; Aaron cast down his rod before Pharaoh and his servants, and it became a serpent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.11'>Then Pharaoh summoned the wise men and the sorcerers; and they also, the magicians of Egypt, did the same by their secret arts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.12'>For every man cast down his rod, and they became serpents. But Aaron's rod swallowed up their rods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.13'>Still Pharaoh's heart was hardened, and he would not listen to them; as the LORD had said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.14'>Then the LORD said to Moses, "Pharaoh's heart is hardened, he refuses to let the people go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.15'>Go to Pharaoh in the morning, as he is going out to the water; wait for him by the river's brink, and take in your hand the rod which was turned into a serpent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.16'>And you shall say to him, `The LORD, the God of the Hebrews, sent me to you, saying, "Let my people go, that they may serve me in the wilderness; and behold, you have not yet obeyed."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.17'>Thus says the LORD, "By this you shall know that I am the LORD: behold, I will strike the water that is in the Nile with the rod that is in my hand, and it shall be turned to blood,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.18'>and the fish in the Nile shall die, and the Nile shall become foul, and the Egyptians will loathe to drink water from the Nile."'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.19'>And the LORD said to Moses, "Say to Aaron, `Take your rod and stretch out your hand over the waters of Egypt, over their rivers, their canals, and their ponds, and all their pools of water, that they may become blood; and there shall be blood throughout all the land of Egypt, both in vessels of wood and in vessels of stone.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.20'>Moses and Aaron did as the LORD commanded; in the sight of Pharaoh and in the sight of his servants, he lifted up the rod and struck the water that was in the Nile, and all the water that was in the Nile turned to blood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.21'>And the fish in the Nile died; and the Nile became foul, so that the Egyptians could not drink water from the Nile; and there was blood throughout all the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.22'>But the magicians of Egypt did the same by their secret arts; so Pharaoh's heart remained hardened, and he would not listen to them; as the LORD had said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.23'>Pharaoh turned and went into his house, and he did not lay even this to heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.24'>And all the Egyptians dug round about the Nile for water to drink, for they could not drink the water of the Nile.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.25'>Seven days passed after the LORD had struck the Nile.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.8'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.1'>Then the LORD said to Moses, "Go in to Pharaoh and say to him, `Thus says the LORD, "Let my people go, that they may serve me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.2'>But if you refuse to let them go, behold, I will plague all your country with frogs;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.3'>the Nile shall swarm with frogs which shall come up into your house, and into your bedchamber and on your bed, and into the houses of your servants and of your people, and into your ovens and your kneading bowls;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.4'>the frogs shall come up on you and on your people and on all your servants."'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.5'>And the LORD said to Moses, "Say to Aaron, `Stretch out your hand with your rod over the rivers, over the canals, and over the pools, and cause frogs to come upon the land of Egypt!'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.6'>So Aaron stretched out his hand over the waters of Egypt; and the frogs came up and covered the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.7'>But the magicians did the same by their secret arts, and brought frogs upon the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.8'>Then Pharaoh called Moses and Aaron, and said, "Entreat the LORD to take away the frogs from me and from my people; and I will let the people go to sacrifice to the LORD."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.9'>Moses said to Pharaoh, "Be pleased to command me when I am to entreat, for you and for your servants and for your people, that the frogs be destroyed from you and your houses and be left only in the Nile."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.10'>And he said, "Tomorrow." Moses said, "Be it as you say, that you may know that there is no one like the LORD our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.11'>The frogs shall depart from you and your houses and your servants and your people; they shall be left only in the Nile."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.12'>So Moses and Aaron went out from Pharaoh; and Moses cried to the LORD concerning the frogs, as he had agreed with Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.13'>And the LORD did according to the word of Moses; the frogs died out of the houses and courtyards and out of the fields.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.14'>And they gathered them together in heaps, and the land stank.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.15'>But when Pharaoh saw that there was a respite, he hardened his heart, and would not listen to them; as the LORD had said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.16'>Then the LORD said to Moses, "Say to Aaron, `Stretch out your rod and strike the dust of the earth, that it may become gnats throughout all the land of Egypt.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.17'>And they did so; Aaron stretched out his hand with his rod, and struck the dust of the earth, and there came gnats on man and beast; all the dust of the earth became gnats throughout all the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.18'>The magicians tried by their secret arts to bring forth gnats, but they could not. So there were gnats on man and beast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.19'>And the magicians said to Pharaoh, "This is the finger of God." But Pharaoh's heart was hardened, and he would not listen to them; as the LORD had said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.20'>Then the LORD said to Moses, "Rise up early in the morning and wait for Pharaoh, as he goes out to the water, and say to him, `Thus says the LORD, "Let my people go, that they may serve me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.21'>Else, if you will not let my people go, behold, I will send swarms of flies on you and your servants and your people, and into your houses; and the houses of the Egyptians shall be filled with swarms of flies, and also the ground on which they stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.22'>But on that day I will set apart the land of Goshen, where my people dwell, so that no swarms of flies shall be there; that you may know that I am the LORD in the midst of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.23'>Thus I will put a division between my people and your people. By tomorrow shall this sign be."'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.24'>And the LORD did so; there came great swarms of flies into the house of Pharaoh and into his servants' houses, and in all the land of Egypt the land was ruined by reason of the flies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.25'>Then Pharaoh called Moses and Aaron, and said, "Go, sacrifice to your God within the land."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.26'>But Moses said, "It would not be right to do so; for we shall sacrifice to the LORD our God offerings abominable to the Egyptians. If we sacrifice offerings abominable to the Egyptians before their eyes, will they not stone us?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.27'>We must go three days' journey into the wilderness and sacrifice to the LORD our God as he will command us."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.28'>So Pharaoh said, "I will let you go, to sacrifice to the LORD your God in the wilderness; only you shall not go very far away. Make entreaty for me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.29'>Then Moses said, "Behold, I am going out from you and I will pray to the LORD that the swarms of flies may depart from Pharaoh, from his servants, and from his people, tomorrow; only let not Pharaoh deal falsely again by not letting the people go to sacrifice to the LORD."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.30'>So Moses went out from Pharaoh and prayed to the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.31'>And the LORD did as Moses asked, and removed the swarms of flies from Pharaoh, from his servants, and from his people; not one remained.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.32'>But Pharaoh hardened his heart this time also, and did not let the people go.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.9'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.1'>Then the LORD said to Moses, "Go in to Pharaoh, and say to him, `Thus says the LORD, the God of the Hebrews, "Let my people go, that they may serve me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.2'>For if you refuse to let them go and still hold them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.3'>behold, the hand of the LORD will fall with a very severe plague upon your cattle which are in the field, the horses, the asses, the camels, the herds, and the flocks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.4'>But the LORD will make a distinction between the cattle of Israel and the cattle of Egypt, so that nothing shall die of all that belongs to the people of Israel."'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.5'>And the LORD set a time, saying, "Tomorrow the LORD will do this thing in the land."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.6'>And on the morrow the LORD did this thing; all the cattle of the Egyptians died, but of the cattle of the people of Israel not one died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.7'>And Pharaoh sent, and behold, not one of the cattle of the Israelites was dead. But the heart of Pharaoh was hardened, and he did not let the people go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.8'>And the LORD said to Moses and Aaron, "Take handfuls of ashes from the kiln, and let Moses throw them toward heaven in the sight of Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.9'>And it shall become fine dust over all the land of Egypt, and become boils breaking out in sores on man and beast throughout all the land of Egypt."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.10'>So they took ashes from the kiln, and stood before Pharaoh, and Moses threw them toward heaven, and it became boils breaking out in sores on man and beast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.11'>And the magicians could not stand before Moses because of the boils, for the boils were upon the magicians and upon all the Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.12'>But the LORD hardened the heart of Pharaoh, and he did not listen to them; as the LORD had spoken to Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.13'>Then the LORD said to Moses, "Rise up early in the morning and stand before Pharaoh, and say to him, `Thus says the LORD, the God of the Hebrews, "Let my people go, that they may serve me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.14'>For this time I will send all my plagues upon your heart, and upon your servants and your people, that you may know that there is none like me in all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.15'>For by now I could have put forth my hand and struck you and your people with pestilence, and you would have been cut off from the earth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.16'>but for this purpose have I let you live, to show you my power, so that my name may be declared throughout all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.17'>You are still exalting yourself against my people, and will not let them go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.18'>Behold, tomorrow about this time I will cause very heavy hail to fall, such as never has been in Egypt from the day it was founded until now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.19'>Now therefore send, get your cattle and all that you have in the field into safe shelter; for the hail shall come down upon every man and beast that is in the field and is not brought home, and they shall die."'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.20'>Then he who feared the word of the LORD among the servants of Pharaoh made his slaves and his cattle flee into the houses;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.21'>but he who did not regard the word of the LORD left his slaves and his cattle in the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.22'>And the LORD said to Moses, "Stretch forth your hand toward heaven, that there may be hail in all the land of Egypt, upon man and beast and every plant of the field, throughout the land of Egypt."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.23'>Then Moses stretched forth his rod toward heaven; and the LORD sent thunder and hail, and fire ran down to the earth. And the LORD rained hail upon the land of Egypt;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.24'>there was hail, and fire flashing continually in the midst of the hail, very heavy hail, such as had never been in all the land of Egypt since it became a nation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.25'>The hail struck down everything that was in the field throughout all the land of Egypt, both man and beast; and the hail struck down every plant of the field, and shattered every tree of the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.26'>Only in the land of Goshen, where the people of Israel were, there was no hail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.27'>Then Pharaoh sent, and called Moses and Aaron, and said to them, "I have sinned this time; the LORD is in the right, and I and my people are in the wrong.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.28'>Entreat the LORD; for there has been enough of this thunder and hail; I will let you go, and you shall stay no longer."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.29'>Moses said to him, "As soon as I have gone out of the city, I will stretch out my hands to the LORD; the thunder will cease, and there will be no more hail, that you may know that the earth is the LORD's.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.30'>But as for you and your servants, I know that you do not yet fear the LORD God."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.31'>(The flax and the barley were ruined, for the barley was in the ear and the flax was in bud.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.32'>But the wheat and the spelt were not ruined, for they are late in coming up.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.33'>So Moses went out of the city from Pharaoh, and stretched out his hands to the LORD; and the thunder and the hail ceased, and the rain no longer poured upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.34'>But when Pharaoh saw that the rain and the hail and the thunder had ceased, he sinned yet again, and hardened his heart, he and his servants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.35'>So the heart of Pharaoh was hardened, and he did not let the people of Israel go; as the LORD had spoken through Moses.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.10'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.1'>Then the LORD said to Moses, "Go in to Pharaoh; for I have hardened his heart and the heart of his servants, that I may show these signs of mine among them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.2'>and that you may tell in the hearing of your son and of your son's son how I have made sport of the Egyptians and what signs I have done among them; that you may know that I am the LORD."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.3'>So Moses and Aaron went in to Pharaoh, and said to him, "Thus says the LORD, the God of the Hebrews, `How long will you refuse to humble yourself before me? Let my people go, that they may serve me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.4'>For if you refuse to let my people go, behold, tomorrow I will bring locusts into your country,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.5'>and they shall cover the face of the land, so that no one can see the land; and they shall eat what is left to you after the hail, and they shall eat every tree of yours which grows in the field,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.6'>and they shall fill your houses, and the houses of all your servants and of all the Egyptians; as neither your fathers nor your grandfathers have seen, from the day they came on earth to this day.'" Then he turned and went out from Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.7'>And Pharaoh's servants said to him, "How long shall this man be a snare to us? Let the men go, that they may serve the LORD their God; do you not yet understand that Egypt is ruined?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.8'>So Moses and Aaron were brought back to Pharaoh; and he said to them, "Go, serve the LORD your God; but who are to go?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.9'>And Moses said, "We will go with our young and our old; we will go with our sons and daughters and with our flocks and herds, for we must hold a feast to the LORD."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.10'>And he said to them, "The LORD be with you, if ever I let you and your little ones go! Look, you have some evil purpose in mind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.11'>No! Go, the men among you, and serve the LORD, for that is what you desire." And they were driven out from Pharaoh's presence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.12'>Then the LORD said to Moses, "Stretch out your hand over the land of Egypt for the locusts, that they may come upon the land of Egypt, and eat every plant in the land, all that the hail has left."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.13'>So Moses stretched forth his rod over the land of Egypt, and the LORD brought an east wind upon the land all that day and all that night; and when it was morning the east wind had brought the locusts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.14'>And the locusts came up over all the land of Egypt, and settled on the whole country of Egypt, such a dense swarm of locusts as had never been before, nor ever shall be again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.15'>For they covered the face of the whole land, so that the land was darkened, and they ate all the plants in the land and all the fruit of the trees which the hail had left; not a green thing remained, neither tree nor plant of the field, through all the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.16'>Then Pharaoh called Moses and Aaron in haste, and said, "I have sinned against the LORD your God, and against you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.17'>Now therefore, forgive my sin, I pray you, only this once, and entreat the LORD your God only to remove this death from me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.18'>So he went out from Pharaoh, and entreated the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.19'>And the LORD turned a very strong west wind, which lifted the locusts and drove them into the Red Sea; not a single locust was left in all the country of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.20'>But the LORD hardened Pharaoh's heart, and he did not let the children of Israel go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.21'>Then the LORD said to Moses, "Stretch out your hand toward heaven that there may be darkness over the land of Egypt, a darkness to be felt."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.22'>So Moses stretched out his hand toward heaven, and there was thick darkness in all the land of Egypt three days;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.23'>they did not see one another, nor did any rise from his place for three days; but all the people of Israel had light where they dwelt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.24'>Then Pharaoh called Moses, and said, "Go, serve the LORD; your children also may go with you; only let your flocks and your herds remain behind."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.25'>But Moses said, "You must also let us have sacrifices and burnt offerings, that we may sacrifice to the LORD our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.26'>Our cattle also must go with us; not a hoof shall be left behind, for we must take of them to serve the LORD our God, and we do not know with what we must serve the LORD until we arrive there."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.27'>But the LORD hardened Pharaoh's heart, and he would not let them go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.28'>Then Pharaoh said to him, "Get away from me; take heed to yourself; never see my face again; for in the day you see my face you shall die."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.29'>Moses said, "As you say! I will not see your face again."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.11'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.1'>The LORD said to Moses, "Yet one plague more I will bring upon Pharaoh and upon Egypt; afterwards he will let you go hence; when he lets you go, he will drive you away completely.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.2'>Speak now in the hearing of the people, that they ask, every man of his neighbor and every woman of her neighbor, jewelry of silver and of gold."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.3'>And the LORD gave the people favor in the sight of the Egyptians. Moreover, the man Moses was very great in the land of Egypt, in the sight of Pharaoh's servants and in the sight of the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.4'>And Moses said, "Thus says the LORD: About midnight I will go forth in the midst of Egypt;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.5'>and all the first-born in the land of Egypt shall die, from the first-born of Pharaoh who sits upon his throne, even to the first-born of the maidservant who is behind the mill; and all the first-born of the cattle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.6'>And there shall be a great cry throughout all the land of Egypt, such as there has never been, nor ever shall be again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.7'>But against any of the people of Israel, either man or beast, not a dog shall growl; that you may know that the LORD makes a distinction between the Egyptians and Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.8'>And all these your servants shall come down to me, and bow down to me, saying, `Get you out, and all the people who follow you.' And after that I will go out." And he went out from Pharaoh in hot anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.9'>Then the LORD said to Moses, "Pharaoh will not listen to you; that my wonders may be multiplied in the land of Egypt."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.10'>Moses and Aaron did all these wonders before Pharaoh; and the LORD hardened Pharaoh's heart, and he did not let the people of Israel go out of his land.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.12'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.1'>The LORD said to Moses and Aaron in the land of Egypt,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.2'>"This month shall be for you the beginning of months; it shall be the first month of the year for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.3'>Tell all the congregation of Israel that on the tenth day of this month they shall take every man a lamb according to their fathers' houses, a lamb for a household;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.4'>and if the household is too small for a lamb, then a man and his neighbor next to his house shall take according to the number of persons; according to what each can eat you shall make your count for the lamb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.5'>Your lamb shall be without blemish, a male a year old; you shall take it from the sheep or from the goats;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.6'>and you shall keep it until the fourteenth day of this month, when the whole assembly of the congregation of Israel shall kill their lambs in the evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.7'>Then they shall take some of the blood, and put it on the two doorposts and the lintel of the houses in which they eat them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.8'>They shall eat the flesh that night, roasted; with unleavened bread and bitter herbs they shall eat it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.9'>Do not eat any of it raw or boiled with water, but roasted, its head with its legs and its inner parts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.10'>And you shall let none of it remain until the morning, anything that remains until the morning you shall burn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.11'>In this manner you shall eat it: your loins girded, your sandals on your feet, and your staff in your hand; and you shall eat it in haste. It is the LORD's passover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.12'>For I will pass through the land of Egypt that night, and I will smite all the first-born in the land of Egypt, both man and beast; and on all the gods of Egypt I will execute judgments: I am the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.13'>The blood shall be a sign for you, upon the houses where you are; and when I see the blood, I will pass over you, and no plague shall fall upon you to destroy you, when I smite the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.14'>"This day shall be for you a memorial day, and you shall keep it as a feast to the LORD; throughout your generations you shall observe it as an ordinance for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.15'>Seven days you shall eat unleavened bread; on the first day you shall put away leaven out of your houses, for if any one eats what is leavened, from the first day until the seventh day, that person shall be cut off from Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.16'>On the first day you shall hold a holy assembly, and on the seventh day a holy assembly; no work shall be done on those days; but what every one must eat, that only may be prepared by you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.17'>And you shall observe the feast of unleavened bread, for on this very day I brought your hosts out of the land of Egypt: therefore you shall observe this day, throughout your generations, as an ordinance for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.18'>In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month at evening, you shall eat unleavened bread, and so until the twenty-first day of the month at evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.19'>For seven days no leaven shall be found in your houses; for if any one eats what is leavened, that person shall be cut off from the congregation of Israel, whether he is a sojourner or a native of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.20'>You shall eat nothing leavened; in all your dwellings you shall eat unleavened bread."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.21'>Then Moses called all the elders of Israel, and said to them, "Select lambs for yourselves according to your families, and kill the passover lamb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.22'>Take a bunch of hyssop and dip it in the blood which is in the basin, and touch the lintel and the two doorposts with the blood which is in the basin; and none of you shall go out of the door of his house until the morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.23'>For the LORD will pass through to slay the Egyptians; and when he sees the blood on the lintel and on the two doorposts, the LORD will pass over the door, and will not allow the destroyer to enter your houses to slay you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.24'>You shall observe this rite as an ordinance for you and for your sons for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.25'>And when you come to the land which the LORD will give you, as he has promised, you shall keep this service.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.26'>And when your children say to you, `What do you mean by this service?'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.27'>you shall say, `It is the sacrifice of the LORD's passover, for he passed over the houses of the people of Israel in Egypt, when he slew the Egyptians but spared our houses.'" And the people bowed their heads and worshiped.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.28'>Then the people of Israel went and did so; as the LORD had commanded Moses and Aaron, so they did.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.29'>At midnight the LORD smote all the first-born in the land of Egypt, from the first-born of Pharaoh who sat on his throne to the first-born of the captive who was in the dungeon, and all the first-born of the cattle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.30'>And Pharaoh rose up in the night, he, and all his servants, and all the Egyptians; and there was a great cry in Egypt, for there was not a house where one was not dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.31'>And he summoned Moses and Aaron by night, and said, "Rise up, go forth from among my people, both you and the people of Israel; and go, serve the LORD, as you have said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.32'>Take your flocks and your herds, as you have said, and be gone; and bless me also!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.33'>And the Egyptians were urgent with the people, to send them out of the land in haste; for they said, "We are all dead men."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.34'>So the people took their dough before it was leavened, their kneading bowls being bound up in their mantles on their shoulders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.35'>The people of Israel had also done as Moses told them, for they had asked of the Egyptians jewelry of silver and of gold, and clothing;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.36'>and the LORD had given the people favor in the sight of the Egyptians, so that they let them have what they asked. Thus they despoiled the Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.37'>And the people of Israel journeyed from Ram'eses to Succoth, about six hundred thousand men on foot, besides women and children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.38'>A mixed multitude also went up with them, and very many cattle, both flocks and herds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.39'>And they baked unleavened cakes of the dough which they had brought out of Egypt, for it was not leavened, because they were thrust out of Egypt and could not tarry, neither had they prepared for themselves any provisions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.40'>The time that the people of Israel dwelt in Egypt was four hundred and thirty years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.41'>And at the end of four hundred and thirty years, on that very day, all the hosts of the LORD went out from the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.42'>It was a night of watching by the LORD, to bring them out of the land of Egypt; so this same night is a night of watching kept to the LORD by all the people of Israel throughout their generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.43'>And the LORD said to Moses and Aaron, "This is the ordinance of the passover: no foreigner shall eat of it;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.44'>but every slave that is bought for money may eat of it after you have circumcised him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.45'>No sojourner or hired servant may eat of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.46'>In one house shall it be eaten; you shall not carry forth any of the flesh outside the house; and you shall not break a bone of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.47'>All the congregation of Israel shall keep it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.48'>And when a stranger shall sojourn with you and would keep the passover to the LORD, let all his males be circumcised, then he may come near and keep it; he shall be as a native of the land. But no uncircumcised person shall eat of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.49'>There shall be one law for the native and for the stranger who sojourns among you."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.50'>Thus did all the people of Israel; as the LORD commanded Moses and Aaron, so they did.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.51'>And on that very day the LORD brought the people of Israel out of the land of Egypt by their hosts.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.13'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.1'>The LORD said to Moses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.2'>"Consecrate to me all the first-born; whatever is the first to open the womb among the people of Israel, both of man and of beast, is mine."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.3'>And Moses said to the people, "Remember this day, in which you came out from Egypt, out of the house of bondage, for by strength of hand the LORD brought you out from this place; no leavened bread shall be eaten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.4'>This day you are to go forth, in the month of Abib.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.5'>And when the LORD brings you into the land of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Amorites, the Hivites, and the Jeb'usites, which he swore to your fathers to give you, a land flowing with milk and honey, you shall keep this service in this month.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.6'>Seven days you shall eat unleavened bread, and on the seventh day there shall be a feast to the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.7'>Unleavened bread shall be eaten for seven days; no leavened bread shall be seen with you, and no leaven shall be seen with you in all your territory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.8'>And you shall tell your son on that day, `It is because of what the LORD did for me when I came out of Egypt.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.9'>And it shall be to you as a sign on your hand and as a memorial between your eyes, that the law of the LORD may be in your mouth; for with a strong hand the LORD has brought you out of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.10'>You shall therefore keep this ordinance at its appointed time from year to year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.11'>"And when the LORD brings you into the land of the Canaanites, as he swore to you and your fathers, and shall give it to you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.12'>you shall set apart to the LORD all that first opens the womb. All the firstlings of your cattle that are males shall be the LORD's.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.13'>Every firstling of an ass you shall redeem with a lamb, or if you will not redeem it you shall break its neck. Every first-born of man among your sons you shall redeem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.14'>And when in time to come your son asks you, `What does this mean?' you shall say to him, `By strength of hand the LORD brought us out of Egypt, from the house of bondage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.15'>For when Pharaoh stubbornly refused to let us go, the LORD slew all the first-born in the land of Egypt, both the first-born of man and the first-born of cattle. Therefore I sacrifice to the LORD all the males that first open the womb; but all the first-born of my sons I redeem.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.16'>It shall be as a mark on your hand or frontlets between your eyes; for by a strong hand the LORD brought us out of Egypt."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.17'>When Pharaoh let the people go, God did not lead them by way of the land of the Philistines, although that was near; for God said, "Lest the people repent when they see war, and return to Egypt."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.18'>But God led the people round by the way of the wilderness toward the Red Sea. And the people of Israel went up out of the land of Egypt equipped for battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.19'>And Moses took the bones of Joseph with him; for Joseph had solemnly sworn the people of Israel, saying, "God will visit you; then you must carry my bones with you from here."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.20'>And they moved on from Succoth, and encamped at Etham, on the edge of the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.21'>And the LORD went before them by day in a pillar of cloud to lead them along the way, and by night in a pillar of fire to give them light, that they might travel by day and by night;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.22'>the pillar of cloud by day and the pillar of fire by night did not depart from before the people.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.14'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.1'>Then the LORD said to Moses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.2'>"Tell the people of Israel to turn back and encamp in front of Pi-ha-hi'roth, between Migdol and the sea, in front of Ba'al-ze'phon; you shall encamp over against it, by the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.3'>For Pharaoh will say of the people of Israel, `They are entangled in the land; the wilderness has shut them in.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.4'>And I will harden Pharaoh's heart, and he will pursue them and I will get glory over Pharaoh and all his host; and the Egyptians shall know that I am the LORD." And they did so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.5'>When the king of Egypt was told that the people had fled, the mind of Pharaoh and his servants was changed toward the people, and they said, "What is this we have done, that we have let Israel go from serving us?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.6'>So he made ready his chariot and took his army with him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.7'>and took six hundred picked chariots and all the other chariots of Egypt with officers over all of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.8'>And the LORD hardened the heart of Pharaoh king of Egypt and he pursued the people of Israel as they went forth defiantly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.9'>The Egyptians pursued them, all Pharaoh's horses and chariots and his horsemen and his army, and overtook them encamped at the sea, by Pi-ha-hi'roth, in front of Ba'al-ze'phon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.10'>When Pharaoh drew near, the people of Israel lifted up their eyes, and behold, the Egyptians were marching after them; and they were in great fear. And the people of Israel cried out to the LORD;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.11'>and they said to Moses, "Is it because there are no graves in Egypt that you have taken us away to die in the wilderness? What have you done to us, in bringing us out of Egypt?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.12'>Is not this what we said to you in Egypt, `Let us alone and let us serve the Egyptians'? For it would have been better for us to serve the Egyptians than to die in the wilderness."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.13'>And Moses said to the people, "Fear not, stand firm, and see the salvation of the LORD, which he will work for you today; for the Egyptians whom you see today, you shall never see again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.14'>The LORD will fight for you, and you have only to be still."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.15'>The LORD said to Moses, "Why do you cry to me? Tell the people of Israel to go forward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.16'>Lift up your rod, and stretch out your hand over the sea and divide it, that the people of Israel may go on dry ground through the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.17'>And I will harden the hearts of the Egyptians so that they shall go in after them, and I will get glory over Pharaoh and all his host, his chariots, and his horsemen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.18'>And the Egyptians shall know that I am the LORD, when I have gotten glory over Pharaoh, his chariots, and his horsemen."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.19'>Then the angel of God who went before the host of Israel moved and went behind them; and the pillar of cloud moved from before them and stood behind them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.20'>coming between the host of Egypt and the host of Israel. And there was the cloud and the darkness; and the night passed without one coming near the other all night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.21'>Then Moses stretched out his hand over the sea; and the LORD drove the sea back by a strong east wind all night, and made the sea dry land, and the waters were divided.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.22'>And the people of Israel went into the midst of the sea on dry ground, the waters being a wall to them on their right hand and on their left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.23'>The Egyptians pursued, and went in after them into the midst of the sea, all Pharaoh's horses, his chariots, and his horsemen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.24'>And in the morning watch the LORD in the pillar of fire and of cloud looked down upon the host of the Egyptians, and discomfited the host of the Egyptians,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.25'>clogging their chariot wheels so that they drove heavily; and the Egyptians said, "Let us flee from before Israel; for the LORD fights for them against the Egyptians."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.26'>Then the LORD said to Moses, "Stretch out your hand over the sea, that the water may come back upon the Egyptians, upon their chariots, and upon their horsemen."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.27'>So Moses stretched forth his hand over the sea, and the sea returned to its wonted flow when the morning appeared; and the Egyptians fled into it, and the LORD routed the Egyptians in the midst of the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.28'>The waters returned and covered the chariots and the horsemen and all the host of Pharaoh that had followed them into the sea; not so much as one of them remained.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.29'>But the people of Israel walked on dry ground through the sea, the waters being a wall to them on their right hand and on their left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.30'>Thus the LORD saved Israel that day from the hand of the Egyptians; and Israel saw the Egyptians dead upon the seashore.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.31'>And Israel saw the great work which the LORD did against the Egyptians, and the people feared the LORD; and they believed in the LORD and in his servant Moses.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.15'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.1'>Then Moses and the people of Israel sang this song to the LORD, saying, "I will sing to the LORD, for he has triumphed gloriously; the horse and his rider he has thrown into the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.2'>The LORD is my strength and my song, and he has become my salvation; this is my God, and I will praise him, my father's God, and I will exalt him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.3'>The LORD is a man of war; the LORD is his name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.4'>"Pharaoh's chariots and his host he cast into the sea; and his picked officers are sunk in the Red Sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.5'>The floods cover them; they went down into the depths like a stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.6'>Thy right hand, O LORD, glorious in power, thy right hand, O LORD, shatters the enemy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.7'>In the greatness of thy majesty thou overthrowest thy adversaries; thou sendest forth thy fury, it consumes them like stubble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.8'>At the blast of thy nostrils the waters piled up, the floods stood up in a heap; the deeps congealed in the heart of the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.9'>The enemy said, `I will pursue, I will overtake, I will divide the spoil, my desire shall have its fill of them. I will draw my sword, my hand shall destroy them.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.10'>Thou didst blow with thy wind, the sea covered them; they sank as lead in the mighty waters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.11'>"Who is like thee, O LORD, among the gods? Who is like thee, majestic in holiness, terrible in glorious deeds, doing wonders?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.12'>Thou didst stretch out thy right hand, the earth swallowed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.13'>"Thou hast led in thy steadfast love the people whom thou hast redeemed, thou hast guided them by thy strength to thy holy abode.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.14'>The peoples have heard, they tremble; pangs have seized on the inhabitants of Philistia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.15'>Now are the chiefs of Edom dismayed; the leaders of Moab, trembling seizes them; all the inhabitants of Canaan have melted away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.16'>Terror and dread fall upon them; because of the greatness of thy arm, they are as still as a stone, till thy people, O LORD, pass by, till the people pass by whom thou hast purchased.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.17'>Thou wilt bring them in, and plant them on thy own mountain, the place, O LORD, which thou hast made for thy abode, the sanctuary, O LORD, which thy hands have established.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.18'>The LORD will reign for ever and ever."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.19'>For when the horses of Pharaoh with his chariots and his horsemen went into the sea, the LORD brought back the waters of the sea upon them; but the people of Israel walked on dry ground in the midst of the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.20'>Then Miriam, the prophetess, the sister of Aaron, took a timbrel in her hand; and all the women went out after her with timbrels and dancing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.21'>And Miriam sang to them: "Sing to the LORD, for he has triumphed gloriously; the horse and his rider he has thrown into the sea."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.22'>Then Moses led Israel onward from the Red Sea, and they went into the wilderness of Shur; they went three days in the wilderness and found no water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.23'>When they came to Marah, they could not drink the water of Marah because it was bitter; therefore it was named Marah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.24'>And the people murmured against Moses, saying, "What shall we drink?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.25'>And he cried to the LORD; and the LORD showed him a tree, and he threw it into the water, and the water became sweet.  There the LORD made for them a statute and an ordinance and there he proved them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.26'>saying, "If you will diligently hearken to the voice of the LORD your God, and do that which is right in his eyes, and give heed to his commandments and keep all his statutes, I will put none of the diseases upon you which I put upon the Egyptians; for I am the LORD, your healer."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.27'>Then they came to Elim, where there were twelve springs of water and seventy palm trees; and they encamped there by the water.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.16'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.1'>They set out from Elim, and all the congregation of the people of Israel came to the wilderness of Sin, which is between Elim and Sinai, on the fifteenth day of the second month after they had departed from the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.2'>And the whole congregation of the people of Israel murmured against Moses and Aaron in the wilderness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.3'>and said to them, "Would that we had died by the hand of the LORD in the land of Egypt, when we sat by the fleshpots and ate bread to the full; for you have brought us out into this wilderness to kill this whole assembly with hunger."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.4'>Then the LORD said to Moses, "Behold, I will rain bread from heaven for you; and the people shall go out and gather a day's portion every day, that I may prove them, whether they will walk in my law or not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.5'>On the sixth day, when they prepare what they bring in, it will be twice as much as they gather daily."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.6'>So Moses and Aaron said to all the people of Israel, "At evening you shall know that it was the LORD who brought you out of the land of Egypt,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.7'>and in the morning you shall see the glory of the LORD, because he has heard your murmurings against the LORD. For what are we, that you murmur against us?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.8'>And Moses said, "When the LORD gives you in the evening flesh to eat and in the morning bread to the full, because the LORD has heard your murmurings which you murmur against him--what are we? Your murmurings are not against us but against the LORD."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.9'>And Moses said to Aaron, "Say to the whole congregation of the people of Israel, `Come near before the LORD, for he has heard your murmurings.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.10'>And as Aaron spoke to the whole congregation of the people of Israel, they looked toward the wilderness, and behold, the glory of the LORD appeared in the cloud.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.11'>And the LORD said to Moses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.12'>"I have heard the murmurings of the people of Israel; say to them, `At twilight you shall eat flesh, and in the morning you shall be filled with bread; then you shall know that I am the LORD your God.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.13'>In the evening quails came up and covered the camp; and in the morning dew lay round about the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.14'>And when the dew had gone up, there was on the face of the wilderness a fine, flake-like thing, fine as hoarfrost on the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.15'>When the people of Israel saw it, they said to one another, "What is it?" For they did not know what it was. And Moses said to them, "It is the bread which the LORD has given you to eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.16'>This is what the LORD has commanded: `Gather of it, every man of you, as much as he can eat; you shall take an omer apiece, according to the number of the persons whom each of you has in his tent.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.17'>And the people of Israel did so; they gathered, some more, some less.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.18'>But when they measured it with an omer, he that gathered much had nothing over, and he that gathered little had no lack; each gathered according to what he could eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.19'>And Moses said to them, "Let no man leave any of it till the morning."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.20'>But they did not listen to Moses; some left part of it till the morning, and it bred worms and became foul; and Moses was angry with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.21'>Morning by morning they gathered it, each as much as he could eat; but when the sun grew hot, it melted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.22'>On the sixth day they gathered twice as much bread, two omers apiece; and when all the leaders of the congregation came and told Moses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.23'>he said to them, "This is what the LORD has commanded: `Tomorrow is a day of solemn rest, a holy sabbath to the LORD; bake what you will bake and boil what you will boil, and all that is left over lay by to be kept till the morning.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.24'>So they laid it by till the morning, as Moses bade them; and it did not become foul, and there were no worms in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.25'>Moses said, "Eat it today, for today is a sabbath to the LORD; today you will not find it in the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.26'>Six days you shall gather it; but on the seventh day, which is a sabbath, there will be none."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.27'>On the seventh day some of the people went out to gather, and they found none.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.28'>And the LORD said to Moses, "How long do you refuse to keep my commandments and my laws?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.29'>See! The LORD has given you the sabbath, therefore on the sixth day he gives you bread for two days; remain every man of you in his place, let no man go out of his place on the seventh day."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.30'>So the people rested on the seventh day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.31'>Now the house of Israel called its name manna; it was like coriander seed, white, and the taste of it was like wafers made with honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.32'>And Moses said, "This is what the LORD has commanded: `Let an omer of it be kept throughout your generations, that they may see the bread with which I fed you in the wilderness, when I brought you out of the land of Egypt.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.33'>And Moses said to Aaron, "Take a jar, and put an omer of manna in it, and place it before the LORD, to be kept throughout your generations."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.34'>As the LORD commanded Moses, so Aaron placed it before the testimony, to be kept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.35'>And the people of Israel ate the manna forty years, till they came to a habitable land; they ate the manna, till they came to the border of the land of Canaan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.36'>(An omer is the tenth part of an ephah.)</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.17'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.1'>All the congregation of the people of Israel moved on from the wilderness of Sin by stages, according to the commandment of the LORD, and camped at Reph'idim; but there was no water for the people to drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.2'>Therefore the people found fault with Moses, and said, "Give us water to drink." And Moses said to them, "Why do you find fault with me? Why do you put the LORD to the proof?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.3'>But the people thirsted there for water, and the people murmured against Moses, and said, "Why did you bring us up out of Egypt, to kill us and our children and our cattle with thirst?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.4'>So Moses cried to the LORD, "What shall I do with this people? They are almost ready to stone me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.5'>And the LORD said to Moses, "Pass on before the people, taking with you some of the elders of Israel; and take in your hand the rod with which you struck the Nile, and go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.6'>Behold, I will stand before you there on the rock at Horeb; and you shall strike the rock, and water shall come out of it, that the people may drink." And Moses did so, in the sight of the elders of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.7'>And he called the name of the place Massah and Mer'ibah, because of the faultfinding of the children of Israel, and because they put the LORD to the proof by saying, "Is the LORD among us or not?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.8'>Then came Am'alek and fought with Israel at Reph'idim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.9'>And Moses said to Joshua, "Choose for us men, and go out, fight with Am'alek; tomorrow I will stand on the top of the hill with the rod of God in my hand."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.10'>So Joshua did as Moses told him, and fought with Am'alek; and Moses, Aaron, and Hur went up to the top of the hill.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.11'>Whenever Moses held up his hand, Israel prevailed; and whenever he lowered his hand, Am'alek prevailed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.12'>But Moses' hands grew weary; so they took a stone and put it under him, and he sat upon it, and Aaron and Hur held up his hands, one on one side, and the other on the other side; so his hands were steady until the going down of the sun.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.13'>And Joshua mowed down Am'alek and his people with the edge of the sword.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.14'>And the LORD said to Moses, "Write this as a memorial in a book and recite it in the ears of Joshua, that I will utterly blot out the remembrance of Am'alek from under heaven."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.15'>And Moses built an altar and called the name of it, The LORD is my banner,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.16'>saying, "A hand upon the banner of the LORD! The LORD will have war with Am'alek from generation to generation."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.18'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.1'>Jethro, the priest of Mid'ian, Moses' father-in-law, heard of all that God had done for Moses and for Israel his people, how the LORD had brought Israel out of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.2'>Now Jethro, Moses' father-in-law, had taken Zippo'rah, Moses' wife, after he had sent her away,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.3'>and her two sons, of whom the name of the one was Gershom (for he said, "I have been a sojourner in a foreign land"),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.4'>and the name of the other, Elie'zer (for he said, "The God of my father was my help, and delivered me from the sword of Pharaoh").</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.5'>And Jethro, Moses' father-in-law, came with his sons and his wife to Moses in the wilderness where he was encamped at the mountain of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.6'>And when one told Moses, "Lo, your father-in-law Jethro is coming to you with your wife and her two sons with her,"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.7'>Moses went out to meet his father-in-law, and did obeisance and kissed him; and they asked each other of their welfare, and went into the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.8'>Then Moses told his father-in-law all that the LORD had done to Pharaoh and to the Egyptians for Israel's sake, all the hardship that had come upon them in the way, and how the LORD had delivered them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.9'>And Jethro rejoiced for all the good which the LORD had done to Israel, in that he had delivered them out of the hand of the Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.10'>And Jethro said, "Blessed be the LORD, who has delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians and out of the hand of Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.11'>Now I know that the LORD is greater than all gods, because he delivered the people from under the hand of the Egyptians, when they dealt arrogantly with them."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.12'>And Jethro, Moses' father-in-law, offered a burnt offering and sacrifices to God; and Aaron came with all the elders of Israel to eat bread with Moses' father-in-law before God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.13'>On the morrow Moses sat to judge the people, and the people stood about Moses from morning till evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.14'>When Moses' father-in-law saw all that he was doing for the people, he said, "What is this that you are doing for the people? Why do you sit alone, and all the people stand about you from morning till evening?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.15'>And Moses said to his father-in-law, "Because the people come to me to inquire of God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.16'>when they have a dispute, they come to me and I decide between a man and his neighbor, and I make them know the statutes of God and his decisions."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.17'>Moses' father-in-law said to him, "What you are doing is not good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.18'>You and the people with you will wear yourselves out, for the thing is too heavy for you; you are not able to perform it alone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.19'>Listen now to my voice; I will give you counsel, and God be with you! You shall represent the people before God, and bring their cases to God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.20'>and you shall teach them the statutes and the decisions, and make them know the way in which they must walk and what they must do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.21'>Moreover choose able men from all the people, such as fear God, men who are trustworthy and who hate a bribe; and place such men over the people as rulers of thousands, of hundreds, of fifties, and of tens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.22'>And let them judge the people at all times; every great matter they shall bring to you, but any small matter they shall decide themselves; so it will be easier for you, and they will bear the burden with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.23'>If you do this, and God so commands you, then you will be able to endure, and all this people also will go to their place in peace."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.24'>So Moses gave heed to the voice of his father-in-law and did all that he had said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.25'>Moses chose able men out of all Israel, and made them heads over the people, rulers of thousands, of hundreds, of fifties, and of tens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.26'>And they judged the people at all times; hard cases they brought to Moses, but any small matter they decided themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.27'>Then Moses let his father-in-law depart, and he went his way to his own country.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.19'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.1'>On the third new moon after the people of Israel had gone forth out of the land of Egypt, on that day they came into the wilderness of Sinai.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.2'>And when they set out from Reph'idim and came into the wilderness of Sinai, they encamped in the wilderness; and there Israel encamped before the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.3'>And Moses went up to God, and the LORD called to him out of the mountain, saying, "Thus you shall say to the house of Jacob, and tell the people of Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.4'>You have seen what I did to the Egyptians, and how I bore you on eagles' wings and brought you to myself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.5'>Now therefore, if you will obey my voice and keep my covenant, you shall be my own possession among all peoples; for all the earth is mine,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.6'>and you shall be to me a kingdom of priests and a holy nation. These are the words which you shall speak to the children of Israel."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.7'>So Moses came and called the elders of the people, and set before them all these words which the LORD had commanded him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.8'>And all the people answered together and said, "All that the LORD has spoken we will do." And Moses reported the words of the people to the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.9'>And the LORD said to Moses, "Lo, I am coming to you in a thick cloud, that the people may hear when I speak with you, and may also believe you for ever."  Then Moses told the words of the people to the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.10'>And the LORD said to Moses, "Go to the people and consecrate them today and tomorrow, and let them wash their garments,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.11'>and be ready by the third day; for on the third day the LORD will come down upon Mount Sinai in the sight of all the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.12'>And you shall set bounds for the people round about, saying, `Take heed that you do not go up into the mountain or touch the border of it; whoever touches the mountain shall be put to death;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.13'>no hand shall touch him, but he shall be stoned or shot; whether beast or man, he shall not live.' When the trumpet sounds a long blast, they shall come up to the mountain."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.14'>So Moses went down from the mountain to the people, and consecrated the people; and they washed their garments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.15'>And he said to the people, "Be ready by the third day; do not go near a woman."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.16'>On the morning of the third day there were thunders and lightnings, and a thick cloud upon the mountain, and a very loud trumpet blast, so that all the people who were in the camp trembled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.17'>Then Moses brought the people out of the camp to meet God; and they took their stand at the foot of the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.18'>And Mount Sinai was wrapped in smoke, because the LORD descended upon it in fire; and the smoke of it went up like the smoke of a kiln, and the whole mountain quaked greatly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.19'>And as the sound of the trumpet grew louder and louder, Moses spoke, and God answered him in thunder.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.20'>And the LORD came down upon Mount Sinai, to the top of the mountain; and the LORD called Moses to the top of the mountain, and Moses went up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.21'>And the LORD said to Moses, "Go down and warn the people, lest they break through to the LORD to gaze and many of them perish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.22'>And also let the priests who come near to the LORD consecrate themselves, lest the LORD break out upon them."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.23'>And Moses said to the LORD, "The people cannot come up to Mount Sinai; for thou thyself didst charge us, saying, `Set bounds about the mountain, and consecrate it.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.24'>And the LORD said to him, "Go down, and come up bringing Aaron with you; but do not let the priests and the people break through to come up to the LORD, lest he break out against them."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.25'>So Moses went down to the people and told them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.20'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.1'>And God spoke all these words, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.2'>"I am the LORD your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.3'>"You shall have no other gods before me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.4'>"You shall not make for yourself a graven image, or any likeness of anything that is in heaven above, or that is in the earth beneath, or that is in the water under the earth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.5'>you shall not bow down to them or serve them; for I the LORD your God am a jealous God, visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children to the third and the fourth generation of those who hate me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.6'>but showing steadfast love to thousands of those who love me and keep my commandments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.7'>"You shall not take the name of the LORD your God in vain; for the LORD will not hold him guiltless who takes his name in vain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.8'>"Remember the sabbath day, to keep it holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.9'>Six days you shall labor, and do all your work;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.10'>but the seventh day is a sabbath to the LORD your God; in it you shall not do any work, you, or your son, or your daughter, your manservant, or your maidservant, or your cattle, or the sojourner who is within your gates;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.11'>for in six days the LORD made heaven and earth, the sea, and all that is in them, and rested the seventh day; therefore the LORD blessed the sabbath day and hallowed it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.12'>"Honor your father and your mother, that your days may be long in the land which the LORD your God gives you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.13'>"You shall not kill.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.14'>"You shall not commit adultery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.15'>"You shall not steal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.16'>"You shall not bear false witness against your neighbor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.17'>"You shall not covet your neighbor's house; you shall not covet your neighbor's wife, or his manservant, or his maidservant, or his ox, or his ass, or anything that is your neighbor's."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.18'>Now when all the people perceived the thunderings and the lightnings and the sound of the trumpet and the mountain smoking, the people were afraid and trembled; and they stood afar off,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.19'>and said to Moses, "You speak to us, and we will hear; but let not God speak to us, lest we die."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.20'>And Moses said to the people, "Do not fear; for God has come to prove you, and that the fear of him may be before your eyes, that you may not sin."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.21'>And the people stood afar off, while Moses drew near to the thick darkness where God was.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.22'>And the LORD said to Moses, "Thus you shall say to the people of Israel: `You have seen for yourselves that I have talked with you from heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.23'>You shall not make gods of silver to be with me, nor shall you make for yourselves gods of gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.24'>An altar of earth you shall make for me and sacrifice on it your burnt offerings and your peace offerings, your sheep and your oxen; in every place where I cause my name to be remembered I will come to you and bless you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.25'>And if you make me an altar of stone, you shall not build it of hewn stones; for if you wield your tool upon it you profane it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.26'>And you shall not go up by steps to my altar, that your nakedness be not exposed on it.'</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.21'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.1'>"Now these are the ordinances which you shall set before them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.2'>When you buy a Hebrew slave, he shall serve six years, and in the seventh he shall go out free, for nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.3'>If he comes in single, he shall go out single; if he comes in married, then his wife shall go out with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.4'>If his master gives him a wife and she bears him sons or daughters, the wife and her children shall be her master's and he shall go out alone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.5'>But if the slave plainly says, `I love my master, my wife, and my children; I will not go out free,'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.6'>then his master shall bring him to God, and he shall bring him to the door or the doorpost; and his master shall bore his ear through with an awl; and he shall serve him for life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.7'>"When a man sells his daughter as a slave, she shall not go out as the male slaves do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.8'>If she does not please her master, who has designated her for himself, then he shall let her be redeemed; he shall have no right to sell her to a foreign people, since he has dealt faithlessly with her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.9'>If he designates her for his son, he shall deal with her as with a daughter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.10'>If he takes another wife to himself, he shall not diminish her food, her clothing, or her marital rights.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.11'>And if he does not do these three things for her, she shall go out for nothing, without payment of money.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.12'>"Whoever strikes a man so that he dies shall be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.13'>But if he did not lie in wait for him, but God let him fall into his hand, then I will appoint for you a place to which he may flee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.14'>But if a man willfully attacks another to kill him treacherously, you shall take him from my altar, that he may die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.15'>"Whoever strikes his father or his mother shall be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.16'>"Whoever steals a man, whether he sells him or is found in possession of him, shall be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.17'>"Whoever curses his father or his mother shall be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.18'>"When men quarrel and one strikes the other with a stone or with his fist and the man does not die but keeps his bed,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.19'>then if the man rises again and walks abroad with his staff, he that struck him shall be clear; only he shall pay for the loss of his time, and shall have him thoroughly healed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.20'>"When a man strikes his slave, male or female, with a rod and the slave dies under his hand, he shall be punished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.21'>But if the slave survives a day or two, he is not to be punished; for the slave is his money.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.22'>"When men strive together, and hurt a woman with child, so that there is a miscarriage, and yet no harm follows, the one who hurt her shall be fined, according as the woman's husband shall lay upon him; and he shall pay as the judges determine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.23'>If any harm follows, then you shall give life for life,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.24'>eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.25'>burn for burn, wound for wound, stripe for stripe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.26'>"When a man strikes the eye of his slave, male or female, and destroys it, he shall let the slave go free for the eye's sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.27'>If he knocks out the tooth of his slave, male or female, he shall let the slave go free for the tooth's sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.28'>"When an ox gores a man or a woman to death, the ox shall be stoned, and its flesh shall not be eaten; but the owner of the ox shall be clear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.29'>But if the ox has been accustomed to gore in the past, and its owner has been warned but has not kept it in, and it kills a man or a woman, the ox shall be stoned, and its owner also shall be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.30'>If a ransom is laid on him, then he shall give for the redemption of his life whatever is laid upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.31'>If it gores a man's son or daughter, he shall be dealt with according to this same rule.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.32'>If the ox gores a slave, male or female, the owner shall give to their master thirty shekels of silver, and the ox shall be stoned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.33'>"When a man leaves a pit open, or when a man digs a pit and does not cover it, and an ox or an ass falls into it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.34'>the owner of the pit shall make it good; he shall give money to its owner, and the dead beast shall be his.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.35'>"When one man's ox hurts another's, so that it dies, then they shall sell the live ox and divide the price of it; and the dead beast also they shall divide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.36'>Or if it is known that the ox has been accustomed to gore in the past, and its owner has not kept it in, he shall pay ox for ox, and the dead beast shall be his.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.22'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.1'>"If a man steals an ox or a sheep, and kills it or sells it, he shall pay five oxen for an ox, and four sheep for a sheep. He shall make restitution; if he has nothing, then he shall If the stolen beast is found alive in his possession, whether it is an ox or an ass or a sheep, "If a thief is found breaking in, and is struck so that he dies, there shall be no bloodguilt for him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.2'>but if the sun has risen upon him, there shall be "When a man causes a field or vineyard to be grazed over, or lets his beast loose and it feeds in another man's field, he shall make restitution from the best in his own field and in his own vineyard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.3'>"When fire breaks out and catches in thorns so that the stacked grain or the standing grain or the field is consumed, he that kindled the fire shall make full restitution.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.4'>"If a man delivers to his neighbor money or goods to keep, and it is stolen out of the man's house, then, if the thief is found, he shall pay double.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.5'>If the thief is not found, the owner of the house shall come near to God, to show whether or not he has put his hand to his neighbor's goods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.6'>"For every breach of trust, whether it is for ox, for ass, for sheep, for clothing, or for any kind of lost thing, of which one says, `This is it,' the case of both parties shall come before God; he whom God shall condemn shall pay double to his neighbor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.7'>"If a man delivers to his neighbor an ass or an ox or a sheep or any beast to keep, and it dies or is hurt or is driven away, without any one seeing it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.8'>an oath by the LORD shall be between them both to see whether he has not put his hand to his neighbor's property; and the owner shall accept the oath, and he shall not make restitution.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.9'>But if it is stolen from him, he shall make restitution to its owner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.10'>If it is torn by beasts, let him bring it as evidence; he shall not make restitution for what has been torn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.11'>"If a man borrows anything of his neighbor, and it is hurt or dies, the owner not being with it, he shall make full restitution.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.12'>If the owner was with it, he shall not make restitution; if it was hired, it came for its hire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.13'>"If a man seduces a virgin who is not betrothed, and lies with her, he shall give the marriage present for her, and make her his wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.14'>If her father utterly refuses to give her to him, he shall pay money equivalent to the marriage present for virgins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.15'>"You shall not permit a sorceress to live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.16'>"Whoever lies with a beast shall be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.17'>"Whoever sacrifices to any god, save to the LORD only, shall be utterly destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.18'>"You shall not wrong a stranger or oppress him, for you were strangers in the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.19'>You shall not afflict any widow or orphan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.20'>If you do afflict them, and they cry out to me, I will surely hear their cry;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.21'>and my wrath will burn, and I will kill you with the sword, and your wives shall become widows and your children fatherless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.22'>"If you lend money to any of my people with you who is poor, you shall not be to him as a creditor, and you shall not exact interest from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.23'>If ever you take your neighbor's garment in pledge, you shall restore it to him before the sun goes down;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.24'>for that is his only covering, it is his mantle for his body; in what else shall he sleep? And if he cries to me, I will hear, for I am compassionate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.25'>"You shall not revile God, nor curse a ruler of your people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.26'>"You shall not delay to offer from the fulness of your harvest and from the outflow of your presses.  "The first-born of your sons you shall give to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.27'>You shall do likewise with your oxen and with your sheep: seven days it shall be with its dam; on the eighth day you shall give it to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.28'>"You shall be men consecrated to me; therefore you shall not eat any flesh that is torn by beasts in the field; you shall cast it to the dogs.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.23'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.1'>"You shall not utter a false report. You shall not join hands with a wicked man, to be a malicious witness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.2'>You shall not follow a multitude to do evil; nor shall you bear witness in a suit, turning aside after a multitude, so as to pervert justice;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.3'>nor shall you be partial to a poor man in his suit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.4'>"If you meet your enemy's ox or his ass going astray, you shall bring it back to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.5'>If you see the ass of one who hates you lying under its burden, you shall refrain from leaving him with it, you shall help him to lift it up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.6'>"You shall not pervert the justice due to your poor in his suit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.7'>Keep far from a false charge, and do not slay the innocent and righteous, for I will not acquit the wicked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.8'>And you shall take no bribe, for a bribe blinds the officials, and subverts the cause of those who are in the right.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.9'>"You shall not oppress a stranger; you know the heart of a stranger, for you were strangers in the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.10'>"For six years you shall sow your land and gather in its yield;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.11'>but the seventh year you shall let it rest and lie fallow, that the poor of your people may eat; and what they leave the wild beasts may eat. You shall do likewise with your vineyard, and with your olive orchard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.12'>"Six days you shall do your work, but on the seventh day you shall rest; that your ox and your ass may have rest, and the son of your bondmaid, and the alien, may be refreshed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.13'>Take heed to all that I have said to you; and make no mention of the names of other gods, nor let such be heard out of your mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.14'>"Three times in the year you shall keep a feast to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.15'>You shall keep the feast of unleavened bread; as I commanded you, you shall eat unleavened bread for seven days at the appointed time in the month of Abib, for in it you came out of Egypt. None shall appear before me empty-handed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.16'>You shall keep the feast of harvest, of the first fruits of your labor, of what you sow in the field. You shall keep the feast of ingathering at the end of the year, when you gather in from the field the fruit of your labor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.17'>Three times in the year shall all your males appear before the Lord GOD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.18'>"You shall not offer the blood of my sacrifice with leavened bread, or let the fat of my feast remain until the morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.19'>"The first of the first fruits of your ground you shall bring into the house of the LORD your God.  "You shall not boil a kid in its mother's milk.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.20'>"Behold, I send an angel before you, to guard you on the way and to bring you to the place which I have prepared.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.21'>Give heed to him and hearken to his voice, do not rebel against him, for he will not pardon your transgression; for my name is in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.22'>"But if you hearken attentively to his voice and do all that I say, then I will be an enemy to your enemies and an adversary to your adversaries.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.23'>"When my angel goes before you, and brings you in to the Amorites, and the Hittites, and the Per'izzites, and the Canaanites, the Hivites, and the Jeb'usites, and I blot them out,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.24'>you shall not bow down to their gods, nor serve them, nor do according to their works, but you shall utterly overthrow them and break their pillars in pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.25'>You shall serve the LORD your God, and I will bless your bread and your water; and I will take sickness away from the midst of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.26'>None shall cast her young or be barren in your land; I will fulfil the number of your days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.27'>I will send my terror before you, and will throw into confusion all the people against whom you shall come, and I will make all your enemies turn their backs to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.28'>And I will send hornets before you, which shall drive out Hivite, Canaanite, and Hittite from before you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.29'>I will not drive them out from before you in one year, lest the land become desolate and the wild beasts multiply against you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.30'>Little by little I will drive them out from before you, until you are increased and possess the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.31'>And I will set your bounds from the Red Sea to the sea of the Philistines, and from the wilderness to the Euphra'tes; for I will deliver the inhabitants of the land into your hand, and you shall drive them out before you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.32'>You shall make no covenant with them or with their gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.33'>They shall not dwell in your land, lest they make you sin against me; for if you serve their gods, it will surely be a snare to you."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.24'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.1'>And he said to Moses, "Come up to the LORD, you and Aaron, Nadab, and Abi'hu, and seventy of the elders of Israel, and worship afar off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.2'>Moses alone shall come near to the LORD; but the others shall not come near, and the people shall not come up with him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.3'>Moses came and told the people all the words of the LORD and all the ordinances; and all the people answered with one voice, and said, "All the words which the LORD has spoken we will do."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.4'>And Moses wrote all the words of the LORD. And he rose early in the morning, and built an altar at the foot of the mountain, and twelve pillars, according to the twelve tribes of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.5'>And he sent young men of the people of Israel, who offered burnt offerings and sacrificed peace offerings of oxen to the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.6'>And Moses took half of the blood and put it in basins, and half of the blood he threw against the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.7'>Then he took the book of the covenant, and read it in the hearing of the people; and they said, "All that the LORD has spoken we will do, and we will be obedient."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.8'>And Moses took the blood and threw it upon the people, and said, "Behold the blood of the covenant which the LORD has made with you in accordance with all these words."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.9'>Then Moses and Aaron, Nadab, and Abi'hu, and seventy of the elders of Israel went up,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.10'>and they saw the God of Israel; and there was under his feet as it were a pavement of sapphire stone, like the very heaven for clearness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.11'>And he did not lay his hand on the chief men of the people of Israel; they beheld God, and ate and drank.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.12'>The LORD said to Moses, "Come up to me on the mountain, and wait there; and I will give you the tables of stone, with the law and the commandment, which I have written for their instruction."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.13'>So Moses rose with his servant Joshua, and Moses went up into the mountain of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.14'>And he said to the elders, "Tarry here for us, until we come to you again; and, behold, Aaron and Hur are with you; whoever has a cause, let him go to them."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.15'>Then Moses went up on the mountain, and the cloud covered the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.16'>The glory of the LORD settled on Mount Sinai, and the cloud covered it six days; and on the seventh day he called to Moses out of the midst of the cloud.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.17'>Now the appearance of the glory of the LORD was like a devouring fire on the top of the mountain in the sight of the people of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.18'>And Moses entered the cloud, and went up on the mountain. And Moses was on the mountain forty days and forty nights.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.25'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.1'>The LORD said to Moses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.2'>"Speak to the people of Israel, that they take for me an offering; from every man whose heart makes him willing you shall receive the offering for me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.3'>And this is the offering which you shall receive from them: gold, silver, and bronze,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.4'>blue and purple and scarlet stuff and fine twined linen, goats' hair,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.5'>tanned rams' skins, goatskins, acacia wood,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.6'>oil for the lamps, spices for the anointing oil and for the fragrant incense,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.7'>onyx stones, and stones for setting, for the ephod and for the breastpiece.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.8'>And let them make me a sanctuary, that I may dwell in their midst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.9'>According to all that I show you concerning the pattern of the tabernacle, and of all its furniture, so you shall make it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.10'>"They shall make an ark of acacia wood; two cubits and a half shall be its length, a cubit and a half its breadth, and a cubit and a half its height.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.11'>And you shall overlay it with pure gold, within and without shall you overlay it, and you shall make upon it a molding of gold round about.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.12'>And you shall cast four rings of gold for it and put them on its four feet, two rings on the one side of it, and two rings on the other side of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.13'>You shall make poles of acacia wood, and overlay them with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.14'>And you shall put the poles into the rings on the sides of the ark, to carry the ark by them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.15'>The poles shall remain in the rings of the ark; they shall not be taken from it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.16'>And you shall put into the ark the testimony which I shall give you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.17'>Then you shall make a mercy seat of pure gold; two cubits and a half shall be its length, and a cubit and a half its breadth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.18'>And you shall make two cherubim of gold; of hammered work shall you make them, on the two ends of the mercy seat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.19'>Make one cherub on the one end, and one cherub on the other end; of one piece with the mercy seat shall you make the cherubim on its two ends.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.20'>The cherubim shall spread out their wings above, overshadowing the mercy seat with their wings, their faces one to another; toward the mercy seat shall the faces of the cherubim be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.21'>And you shall put the mercy seat on the top of the ark; and in the ark you shall put the testimony that I shall give you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.22'>There I will meet with you, and from above the mercy seat, from between the two cherubim that are upon the ark of the testimony, I will speak with you of all that I will give you in commandment for the people of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.23'>"And you shall make a table of acacia wood; two cubits shall be its length, a cubit its breadth, and a cubit and a half its height.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.24'>You shall overlay it with pure gold, and make a molding of gold around it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.25'>And you shall make around it a frame a handbreadth wide, and a molding of gold around the frame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.26'>And you shall make for it four rings of gold, and fasten the rings to the four corners at its four legs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.27'>Close to the frame the rings shall lie, as holders for the poles to carry the table.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.28'>You shall make the poles of acacia wood, and overlay them with gold, and the table shall be carried with these.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.29'>And you shall make its plates and dishes for incense, and its flagons and bowls with which to pour libations; of pure gold you shall make them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.30'>And you shall set the bread of the Presence on the table before me always.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.31'>"And you shall make a lampstand of pure gold. The base and the shaft of the lampstand shall be made of hammered work; its cups, its capitals, and its flowers shall be of one piece with it;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.32'>and there shall be six branches going out of its sides, three branches of the lampstand out of one side of it and three branches of the lampstand out of the other side of it;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.33'>three cups made like almonds, each with capital and flower, on one branch, and three cups made like almonds, each with capital and flower, on the other branch--so for the six branches going out of the lampstand;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.34'>and on the lampstand itself four cups made like almonds, with their capitals and flowers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.35'>and a capital of one piece with it under each pair of the six branches going out from the lampstand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.36'>Their capitals and their branches shall be of one piece with it, the whole of it one piece of hammered work of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.37'>And you shall make the seven lamps for it; and the lamps shall be set up so as to give light upon the space in front of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.38'>Its snuffers and their trays shall be of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.39'>Of a talent of pure gold shall it be made, with all these utensils.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.40'>And see that you make them after the pattern for them, which is being shown you on the mountain.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.26'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.1'>"Moreover you shall make the tabernacle with ten curtains of fine twined linen and blue and purple and scarlet stuff; with cherubim skilfully worked shall you make them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.2'>The length of each curtain shall be twenty-eight cubits, and the breadth of each curtain four cubits; all the curtains shall have one measure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.3'>Five curtains shall be coupled to one another; and the other five curtains shall be coupled to one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.4'>And you shall make loops of blue on the edge of the outmost curtain in the first set; and likewise you shall make loops on the edge of the outmost curtain in the second set.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.5'>Fifty loops you shall make on the one curtain, and fifty loops you shall make on the edge of the curtain that is in the second set; the loops shall be opposite one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.6'>And you shall make fifty clasps of gold, and couple the curtains one to the other with the clasps, that the tabernacle may be one whole.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.7'>"You shall also make curtains of goats' hair for a tent over the tabernacle; eleven curtains shall you make.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.8'>The length of each curtain shall be thirty cubits, and the breadth of each curtain four cubits; the eleven curtains shall have the same measure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.9'>And you shall couple five curtains by themselves, and six curtains by themselves, and the sixth curtain you shall double over at the front of the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.10'>And you shall make fifty loops on the edge of the curtain that is outmost in one set, and fifty loops on the edge of the curtain which is outmost in the second set.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.11'>"And you shall make fifty clasps of bronze, and put the clasps into the loops, and couple the tent together that it may be one whole.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.12'>And the part that remains of the curtains of the tent, the half curtain that remains, shall hang over the back of the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.13'>And the cubit on the one side, and the cubit on the other side, of what remains in the length of the curtains of the tent shall hang over the sides of the tabernacle, on this side and that side, to cover it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.14'>And you shall make for the tent a covering of tanned rams' skins and goatskins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.15'>"And you shall make upright frames for the tabernacle of acacia wood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.16'>Ten cubits shall be the length of a frame, and a cubit and a half the breadth of each frame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.17'>There shall be two tenons in each frame, for fitting together; so shall you do for all the frames of the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.18'>You shall make the frames for the tabernacle: twenty frames for the south side;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.19'>and forty bases of silver you shall make under the twenty frames, two bases under one frame for its two tenons, and two bases under another frame for its two tenons;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.20'>and for the second side of the tabernacle, on the north side twenty frames,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.21'>and their forty bases of silver, two bases under one frame, and two bases under another frame;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.22'>and for the rear of the tabernacle westward you shall make six frames.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.23'>And you shall make two frames for corners of the tabernacle in the rear;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.24'>they shall be separate beneath, but joined at the top, at the first ring; thus shall it be with both of them; they shall form the two corners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.25'>And there shall be eight frames, with their bases of silver, sixteen bases; two bases under one frame, and two bases under another frame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.26'>"And you shall make bars of acacia wood, five for the frames of the one side of the tabernacle,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.27'>and five bars for the frames of the other side of the tabernacle, and five bars for the frames of the side of the tabernacle at the rear westward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.28'>The middle bar, halfway up the frames, shall pass through from end to end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.29'>You shall overlay the frames with gold, and shall make their rings of gold for holders for the bars; and you shall overlay the bars with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.30'>And you shall erect the tabernacle according to the plan for it which has been shown you on the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.31'>"And you shall make a veil of blue and purple and scarlet stuff and fine twined linen; in skilled work shall it be made, with cherubim;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.32'>and you shall hang it upon four pillars of acacia overlaid with gold, with hooks of gold, upon four bases of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.33'>And you shall hang the veil from the clasps, and bring the ark of the testimony in thither within the veil; and the veil shall separate for you the holy place from the most holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.34'>You shall put the mercy seat upon the ark of the testimony in the most holy place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.35'>And you shall set the table outside the veil, and the lampstand on the south side of the tabernacle opposite the table; and you shall put the table on the north side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.36'>"And you shall make a screen for the door of the tent, of blue and purple and scarlet stuff and fine twined linen, embroidered with needlework.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.37'>And you shall make for the screen five pillars of acacia, and overlay them with gold; their hooks shall be of gold, and you shall cast five bases of bronze for them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.27'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.1'>"You shall make the altar of acacia wood, five cubits long and five cubits broad; the altar shall be square, and its height shall be three cubits.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.2'>And you shall make horns for it on its four corners; its horns shall be of one piece with it, and you shall overlay it with bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.3'>You shall make pots for it to receive its ashes, and shovels and basins and forks and firepans; all its utensils you shall make of bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.4'>You shall also make for it a grating, a network of bronze; and upon the net you shall make four bronze rings at its four corners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.5'>And you shall set it under the ledge of the altar so that the net shall extend halfway down the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.6'>And you shall make poles for the altar, poles of acacia wood, and overlay them with bronze;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.7'>and the poles shall be put through the rings, so that the poles shall be upon the two sides of the altar, when it is carried.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.8'>You shall make it hollow, with boards; as it has been shown you on the mountain, so shall it be made.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.9'>"You shall make the court of the tabernacle. On the south side the court shall have hangings of fine twined linen a hundred cubits long for one side;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.10'>their pillars shall be twenty and their bases twenty, of bronze, but the hooks of the pillars and their fillets shall be of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.11'>And likewise for its length on the north side there shall be hangings a hundred cubits long, their pillars twenty and their bases twenty, of bronze, but the hooks of the pillars and their fillets shall be of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.12'>And for the breadth of the court on the west side there shall be hangings for fifty cubits, with ten pillars and ten bases.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.13'>The breadth of the court on the front to the east shall be fifty cubits.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.14'>The hangings for the one side of the gate shall be fifteen cubits, with three pillars and three bases.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.15'>On the other side the hangings shall be fifteen cubits, with three pillars and three bases.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.16'>For the gate of the court there shall be a screen twenty cubits long, of blue and purple and scarlet stuff and fine twined linen, embroidered with needlework; it shall have four pillars and with them four bases.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.17'>All the pillars around the court shall be filleted with silver; their hooks shall be of silver, and their bases of bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.18'>The length of the court shall be a hundred cubits, the breadth fifty, and the height five cubits, with hangings of fine twined linen and bases of bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.19'>All the utensils of the tabernacle for every use, and all its pegs and all the pegs of the court, shall be of bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.20'>"And you shall command the people of Israel that they bring to you pure beaten olive oil for the light, that a lamp may be set up to burn continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.21'>In the tent of meeting, outside the veil which is before the testimony, Aaron and his sons shall tend it from evening to morning before the LORD. It shall be a statute for ever to be observed throughout their generations by the people of Israel.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.28'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.1'>"Then bring near to you Aaron your brother, and his sons with him, from among the people of Israel, to serve me as priests--Aaron and Aaron's sons, Nadab and Abi'hu, Elea'zar and Ith'amar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.2'>And you shall make holy garments for Aaron your brother, for glory and for beauty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.3'>And you shall speak to all who have ability, whom I have endowed with an able mind, that they make Aaron's garments to consecrate him for my priesthood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.4'>These are the garments which they shall make: a breastpiece, an ephod, a robe, a coat of checker work, a turban, and a girdle; they shall make holy garments for Aaron your brother and his sons to serve me as priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.5'>"They shall receive gold, blue and purple and scarlet stuff, and fine twined linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.6'>And they shall make the ephod of gold, of blue and purple and scarlet stuff, and of fine twined linen, skilfully worked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.7'>It shall have two shoulder-pieces attached to its two edges, that it may be joined together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.8'>And the skilfully woven band upon it, to gird it on, shall be of the same workmanship and materials, of gold, blue and purple and scarlet stuff, and fine twined linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.9'>And you shall take two onyx stones, and engrave on them the names of the sons of Israel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.10'>six of their names on the one stone, and the names of the remaining six on the other stone, in the order of their birth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.11'>As a jeweler engraves signets, so shall you engrave the two stones with the names of the sons of Israel; you shall enclose them in settings of gold filigree.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.12'>And you shall set the two stones upon the shoulder-pieces of the ephod, as stones of remembrance for the sons of Israel; and Aaron shall bear their names before the LORD upon his two shoulders for remembrance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.13'>And you shall make settings of gold filigree,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.14'>and two chains of pure gold, twisted like cords; and you shall attach the corded chains to the settings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.15'>"And you shall make a breastpiece of judgment, in skilled work; like the work of the ephod you shall make it; of gold, blue and purple and scarlet stuff, and fine twined linen shall you make it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.16'>It shall be square and double, a span its length and a span its breadth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.17'>And you shall set in it four rows of stones. A row of sardius, topaz, and carbuncle shall be the first row;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.18'>and the second row an emerald, a sapphire, and a diamond;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.19'>and the third row a jacinth, an agate, and an amethyst;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.20'>and the fourth row a beryl, an onyx, and a jasper; they shall be set in gold filigree.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.21'>There shall be twelve stones with their names according to the names of the sons of Israel; they shall be like signets, each engraved with its name, for the twelve tribes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.22'>And you shall make for the breastpiece twisted chains like cords, of pure gold;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.23'>and you shall make for the breastpiece two rings of gold, and put the two rings on the two edges of the breastpiece.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.24'>And you shall put the two cords of gold in the two rings at the edges of the breastpiece;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.25'>the two ends of the two cords you shall attach to the two settings of filigree, and so attach it in front to the shoulder-pieces of the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.26'>And you shall make two rings of gold, and put them at the two ends of the breastpiece, on its inside edge next to the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.27'>And you shall make two rings of gold, and attach them in front to the lower part of the two shoulder-pieces of the ephod, at its joining above the skilfully woven band of the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.28'>And they shall bind the breastpiece by its rings to the rings of the ephod with a lace of blue, that it may lie upon the skilfully woven band of the ephod, and that the breastpiece shall not come loose from the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.29'>So Aaron shall bear the names of the sons of Israel in the breastpiece of judgment upon his heart, when he goes into the holy place, to bring them to continual remembrance before the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.30'>And in the breastpiece of judgment you shall put the Urim and the Thummim, and they shall be upon Aaron's heart, when he goes in before the LORD; thus Aaron shall bear the judgment of the people of Israel upon his heart before the LORD continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.31'>"And you shall make the robe of the ephod all of blue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.32'>It shall have in it an opening for the head, with a woven binding around the opening, like the opening in a garment, that it may not be torn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.33'>On its skirts you shall make pomegranates of blue and purple and scarlet stuff, around its skirts, with bells of gold between them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.34'>a golden bell and a pomegranate, a golden bell and a pomegranate, round about on the skirts of the robe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.35'>And it shall be upon Aaron when he ministers, and its sound shall be heard when he goes into the holy place before the LORD, and when he comes out, lest he die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.36'>"And you shall make a plate of pure gold, and engrave on it, like the engraving of a signet, `Holy to the LORD.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.37'>And you shall fasten it on the turban by a lace of blue; it shall be on the front of the turban.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.38'>It shall be upon Aaron's forehead, and Aaron shall take upon himself any guilt incurred in the holy offering which the people of Israel hallow as their holy gifts; it shall always be upon his forehead, that they may be accepted before the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.39'>"And you shall weave the coat in checker work of fine linen, and you shall make a turban of fine linen, and you shall make a girdle embroidered with needlework.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.40'>"And for Aaron's sons you shall make coats and girdles and caps; you shall make them for glory and beauty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.41'>And you shall put them upon Aaron your brother, and upon his sons with him, and shall anoint them and ordain them and consecrate them, that they may serve me as priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.42'>And you shall make for them linen breeches to cover their naked flesh; from the loins to the thighs they shall reach;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.43'>and they shall be upon Aaron, and upon his sons, when they go into the tent of meeting, or when they come near the altar to minister in the holy place; lest they bring guilt upon themselves and die. This shall be a perpetual statute for him and for his descendants after him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.29'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.1'>"Now this is what you shall do to them to consecrate them, that they may serve me as priests. Take one young bull and two rams without blemish,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.2'>and unleavened bread, unleavened cakes mixed with oil, and unleavened wafers spread with oil. You shall make them of fine wheat flour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.3'>And you shall put them in one basket and bring them in the basket, and bring the bull and the two rams.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.4'>You shall bring Aaron and his sons to the door of the tent of meeting, and wash them with water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.5'>And you shall take the garments, and put on Aaron the coat and the robe of the ephod, and the ephod, and the breastpiece, and gird him with the skilfully woven band of the ephod;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.6'>and you shall set the turban on his head, and put the holy crown upon the turban.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.7'>And you shall take the anointing oil, and pour it on his head and anoint him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.8'>Then you shall bring his sons, and put coats on them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.9'>and you shall gird them with girdles and bind caps on them; and the priesthood shall be theirs by a perpetual statute. Thus you shall ordain Aaron and his sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.10'>"Then you shall bring the bull before the tent of meeting. Aaron and his sons shall lay their hands upon the head of the bull,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.11'>and you shall kill the bull before the LORD, at the door of the tent of meeting,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.12'>and shall take part of the blood of the bull and put it upon the horns of the altar with your finger, and the rest of the blood you shall pour out at the base of the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.13'>And you shall take all the fat that covers the entrails, and the appendage of the liver, and the two kidneys with the fat that is on them, and burn them upon the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.14'>But the flesh of the bull, and its skin, and its dung, you shall burn with fire outside the camp; it is a sin offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.15'>"Then you shall take one of the rams, and Aaron and his sons shall lay their hands upon the head of the ram,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.16'>and you shall slaughter the ram, and shall take its blood and throw it against the altar round about.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.17'>Then you shall cut the ram into pieces, and wash its entrails and its legs, and put them with its pieces and its head,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.18'>and burn the whole ram upon the altar; it is a burnt offering to the LORD; it is a pleasing odor, an offering by fire to the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.19'>"You shall take the other ram; and Aaron and his sons shall lay their hands upon the head of the ram,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.20'>and you shall kill the ram, and take part of its blood and put it upon the tip of the right ear of Aaron and upon the tips of the right ears of his sons, and upon the thumbs of their right hands, and upon the great toes of their right feet, and throw the rest of the blood against the altar round about.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.21'>Then you shall take part of the blood that is on the altar, and of the anointing oil, and sprinkle it upon Aaron and his garments, and upon his sons and his sons' garments with him; and he and his garments shall be holy, and his sons and his sons' garments with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.22'>"You shall also take the fat of the ram, and the fat tail, and the fat that covers the entrails, and the appendage of the liver, and the two kidneys with the fat that is on them, and the right thigh (for it is a ram of ordination),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.23'>and one loaf of bread, and one cake of bread with oil, and one wafer, out of the basket of unleavened bread that is before the LORD;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.24'>and you shall put all these in the hands of Aaron and in the hands of his sons, and wave them for a wave offering before the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.25'>Then you shall take them from their hands, and burn them on the altar in addition to the burnt offering, as a pleasing odor before the LORD; it is an offering by fire to the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.26'>"And you shall take the breast of the ram of Aaron's ordination and wave it for a wave offering before the LORD; and it shall be your portion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.27'>And you shall consecrate the breast of the wave offering, and the thigh of the priests' portion, which is waved, and which is offered from the ram of ordination, since it is for Aaron and for his sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.28'>It shall be for Aaron and his sons as a perpetual due from the people of Israel, for it is the priests' portion to be offered by the people of Israel from their peace offerings; it is their offering to the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.29'>"The holy garments of Aaron shall be for his sons after him, to be anointed in them and ordained in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.30'>The son who is priest in his place shall wear them seven days, when he comes into the tent of meeting to minister in the holy place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.31'>"You shall take the ram of ordination, and boil its flesh in a holy place;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.32'>and Aaron and his sons shall eat the flesh of the ram and the bread that is in the basket, at the door of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.33'>They shall eat those things with which atonement was made, to ordain and consecrate them, but an outsider shall not eat of them, because they are holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.34'>And if any of the flesh for the ordination, or of the bread, remain until the morning, then you shall burn the remainder with fire; it shall not be eaten, because it is holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.35'>"Thus you shall do to Aaron and to his sons, according to all that I have commanded you; through seven days shall you ordain them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.36'>and every day you shall offer a bull as a sin offering for atonement. Also you shall offer a sin offering for the altar, when you make atonement for it, and shall anoint it, to consecrate it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.37'>Seven days you shall make atonement for the altar, and consecrate it, and the altar shall be most holy; whatever touches the altar shall become holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.38'>"Now this is what you shall offer upon the altar: two lambs a year old day by day continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.39'>One lamb you shall offer in the morning, and the other lamb you shall offer in the evening;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.40'>and with the first lamb a tenth measure of fine flour mingled with a fourth of a hin of beaten oil, and a fourth of a hin of wine for a libation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.41'>And the other lamb you shall offer in the evening, and shall offer with it a cereal offering and its libation, as in the morning, for a pleasing odor, an offering by fire to the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.42'>It shall be a continual burnt offering throughout your generations at the door of the tent of meeting before the LORD, where I will meet with you, to speak there to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.43'>There I will meet with the people of Israel, and it shall be sanctified by my glory;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.44'>I will consecrate the tent of meeting and the altar; Aaron also and his sons I will consecrate, to serve me as priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.45'>And I will dwell among the people of Israel, and will be their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.46'>And they shall know that I am the LORD their God, who brought them forth out of the land of Egypt that I might dwell among them; I am the LORD their God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.30'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.1'>"You shall make an altar to burn incense upon; of acacia wood shall you make it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.2'>A cubit shall be its length, and a cubit its breadth; it shall be square, and two cubits shall be its height; its horns shall be of one piece with it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.3'>And you shall overlay it with pure gold, its top and its sides round about and its horns; and you shall make for it a molding of gold round about.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.4'>And two golden rings shall you make for it; under its molding on two opposite sides of it shall you make them, and they shall be holders for poles with which to carry it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.5'>You shall make the poles of acacia wood, and overlay them with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.6'>And you shall put it before the veil that is by the ark of the testimony, before the mercy seat that is over the testimony, where I will meet with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.7'>And Aaron shall burn fragrant incense on it; every morning when he dresses the lamps he shall burn it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.8'>and when Aaron sets up the lamps in the evening, he shall burn it, a perpetual incense before the LORD throughout your generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.9'>You shall offer no unholy incense thereon, nor burnt offering, nor cereal offering; and you shall pour no libation thereon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.10'>Aaron shall make atonement upon its horns once a year; with the blood of the sin offering of atonement he shall make atonement for it once in the year throughout your generations; it is most holy to the LORD."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.11'>The LORD said to Moses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.12'>"When you take the census of the people of Israel, then each shall give a ransom for himself to the LORD when you number them, that there be no plague among them when you number them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.13'>Each who is numbered in the census shall give this: half a shekel according to the shekel of the sanctuary (the shekel is twenty gerahs), half a shekel as an offering to the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.14'>Every one who is numbered in the census, from twenty years old and upward, shall give the LORD's offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.15'>The rich shall not give more, and the poor shall not give less, than the half shekel, when you give the LORD's offering to make atonement for yourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.16'>And you shall take the atonement money from the people of Israel, and shall appoint it for the service of the tent of meeting; that it may bring the people of Israel to remembrance before the LORD, so as to make atonement for yourselves."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.17'>The LORD said to Moses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.18'>"You shall also make a laver of bronze, with its base of bronze, for washing. And you shall put it between the tent of meeting and the altar, and you shall put water in it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.19'>with which Aaron and his sons shall wash their hands and their feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.20'>When they go into the tent of meeting, or when they come near the altar to minister, to burn an offering by fire to the LORD, they shall wash with water, lest they die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.21'>They shall wash their hands and their feet, lest they die: it shall be a statute for ever to them, even to him and to his descendants throughout their generations."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.22'>Moreover, the LORD said to Moses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.23'>"Take the finest spices: of liquid myrrh five hundred shekels, and of sweet-smelling cinnamon half as much, that is, two hundred and fifty, and of aromatic cane two hundred and fifty,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.24'>and of cassia five hundred, according to the shekel of the sanctuary, and of olive oil a hin;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.25'>and you shall make of these a sacred anointing oil blended as by the perfumer; a holy anointing oil it shall be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.26'>And you shall anoint with it the tent of meeting and the ark of the testimony,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.27'>and the table and all its utensils, and the lampstand and its utensils, and the altar of incense,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.28'>and the altar of burnt offering with all its utensils and the laver and its base;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.29'>you shall consecrate them, that they may be most holy; whatever touches them will become holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.30'>And you shall anoint Aaron and his sons, and consecrate them, that they may serve me as priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.31'>And you shall say to the people of Israel, `This shall be my holy anointing oil throughout your generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.32'>It shall not be poured upon the bodies of ordinary men, and you shall make no other like it in composition; it is holy, and it shall be holy to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.33'>Whoever compounds any like it or whoever puts any of it on an outsider shall be cut off from his people.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.34'>And the LORD said to Moses, "Take sweet spices, stacte, and onycha, and galbanum, sweet spices with pure frankincense (of each shall there be an equal part),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.35'>and make an incense blended as by the perfumer, seasoned with salt, pure and holy;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.36'>and you shall beat some of it very small, and put part of it before the testimony in the tent of meeting where I shall meet with you; it shall be for you most holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.37'>And the incense which you shall make according to its composition, you shall not make for yourselves; it shall be for you holy to the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.38'>Whoever makes any like it to use as perfume shall be cut off from his people."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.31'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.1'>The LORD said to Moses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.2'>"See, I have called by name Bez'alel the son of Uri, son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.3'>and I have filled him with the Spirit of God, with ability and intelligence, with knowledge and all craftsmanship,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.4'>to devise artistic designs, to work in gold, silver, and bronze,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.5'>in cutting stones for setting, and in carving wood, for work in every craft.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.6'>And behold, I have appointed with him Oho'liab, the son of Ahis'amach, of the tribe of Dan; and I have given to all able men ability, that they may make all that I have commanded you:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.7'>the tent of meeting, and the ark of the testimony, and the mercy seat that is thereon, and all the furnishings of the tent,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.8'>the table and its utensils, and the pure lampstand with all its utensils, and the altar of incense,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.9'>and the altar of burnt offering with all its utensils, and the laver and its base,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.10'>and the finely worked garments, the holy garments for Aaron the priest and the garments of his sons, for their service as priests,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.11'>and the anointing oil and the fragrant incense for the holy place. According to all that I have commanded you they shall do."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.12'>And the LORD said to Moses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.13'>"Say to the people of Israel, `You shall keep my sabbaths, for this is a sign between me and you throughout your generations, that you may know that I, the LORD, sanctify you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.14'>You shall keep the sabbath, because it is holy for you; every one who profanes it shall be put to death; whoever does any work on it, that soul shall be cut off from among his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.15'>Six days shall work be done, but the seventh day is a sabbath of solemn rest, holy to the LORD; whoever does any work on the sabbath day shall be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.16'>Therefore the people of Israel shall keep the sabbath, observing the sabbath throughout their generations, as a perpetual covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.17'>It is a sign for ever between me and the people of Israel that in six days the LORD made heaven and earth, and on the seventh day he rested, and was refreshed.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.18'>And he gave to Moses, when he had made an end of speaking with him upon Mount Sinai, the two tables of the testimony, tables of stone, written with the finger of God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.32'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.1'>When the people saw that Moses delayed to come down from the mountain, the people gathered themselves together to Aaron, and said to him, "Up, make us gods, who shall go before us; as for this Moses, the man who brought us up out of the land of Egypt, we do not know what has become of him."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.2'>And Aaron said to them, "Take off the rings of gold which are in the ears of your wives, your sons, and your daughters, and bring them to me."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.3'>So all the people took off the rings of gold which were in their ears, and brought them to Aaron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.4'>And he received the gold at their hand, and fashioned it with a graving tool, and made a molten calf; and they said, "These are your gods, O Israel, who brought you up out of the land of Egypt!"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.5'>When Aaron saw this, he built an altar before it; and Aaron made proclamation and said, "Tomorrow shall be a feast to the LORD."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.6'>And they rose up early on the morrow, and offered burnt offerings and brought peace offerings; and the people sat down to eat and drink, and rose up to play.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.7'>And the LORD said to Moses, "Go down; for your people, whom you brought up out of the land of Egypt, have corrupted themselves;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.8'>they have turned aside quickly out of the way which I commanded them; they have made for themselves a molten calf, and have worshiped it and sacrificed to it, and said, `These are your gods, O Israel, who brought you up out of the land of Egypt!'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.9'>And the LORD said to Moses, "I have seen this people, and behold, it is a stiff-necked people;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.10'>now therefore let me alone, that my wrath may burn hot against them and I may consume them; but of you I will make a great nation."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.11'>But Moses besought the LORD his God, and said, "O LORD, why does thy wrath burn hot against thy people, whom thou hast brought forth out of the land of Egypt with great power and with a mighty hand?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.12'>Why should the Egyptians say, `With evil intent did he bring them forth, to slay them in the mountains, and to consume them from the face of the earth'? Turn from thy fierce wrath, and repent of this evil against thy people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.13'>Remember Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, thy servants, to whom thou didst swear by thine own self, and didst say to them, `I will multiply your descendants as the stars of heaven, and all this land that I have promised I will give to your descendants, and they shall inherit it for ever.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.14'>And the LORD repented of the evil which he thought to do to his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.15'>And Moses turned, and went down from the mountain with the two tables of the testimony in his hands, tables that were written on both sides; on the one side and on the other were they written.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.16'>And the tables were the work of God, and the writing was the writing of God, graven upon the tables.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.17'>When Joshua heard the noise of the people as they shouted, he said to Moses, "There is a noise of war in the camp."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.18'>But he said, "It is not the sound of shouting for victory, or the sound of the cry of defeat, but the sound of singing that I hear."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.19'>And as soon as he came near the camp and saw the calf and the dancing, Moses' anger burned hot, and he threw the tables out of his hands and broke them at the foot of the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.20'>And he took the calf which they had made, and burnt it with fire, and ground it to powder, and scattered it upon the water, and made the people of Israel drink it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.21'>And Moses said to Aaron, "What did this people do to you that you have brought a great sin upon them?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.22'>And Aaron said, "Let not the anger of my lord burn hot; you know the people, that they are set on evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.23'>For they said to me, `Make us gods, who shall go before us; as for this Moses, the man who brought us up out of the land of Egypt, we do not know what has become of him.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.24'>And I said to them, `Let any who have gold take it off'; so they gave it to me, and I threw it into the fire, and there came out this calf."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.25'>And when Moses saw that the people had broken loose (for Aaron had let them break loose, to their shame among their enemies),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.26'>then Moses stood in the gate of the camp, and said, "Who is on the LORD's side? Come to me." And all the sons of Levi gathered themselves together to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.27'>And he said to them, "Thus says the LORD God of Israel, `Put every man his sword on his side, and go to and fro from gate to gate throughout the camp, and slay every man his brother, and every man his companion, and every man his neighbor.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.28'>And the sons of Levi did according to the word of Moses; and there fell of the people that day about three thousand men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.29'>And Moses said, "Today you have ordained yourselves for the service of the LORD, each one at the cost of his son and of his brother, that he may bestow a blessing upon you this day."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.30'>On the morrow Moses said to the people, "You have sinned a great sin. And now I will go up to the LORD; perhaps I can make atonement for your sin."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.31'>So Moses returned to the LORD and said, "Alas, this people have sinned a great sin; they have made for themselves gods of gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.32'>But now, if thou wilt forgive their sin--and if not, blot me, I pray thee, out of thy book which thou hast written."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.33'>But the LORD said to Moses, "Whoever has sinned against me, him will I blot out of my book.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.34'>But now go, lead the people to the place of which I have spoken to you; behold, my angel shall go before you. Nevertheless, in the day when I visit, I will visit their sin upon them."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.35'>And the LORD sent a plague upon the people, because they made the calf which Aaron made.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.33'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.1'>The LORD said to Moses, "Depart, go up hence, you and the people whom you have brought up out of the land of Egypt, to the land of which I swore to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, saying, `To your descendants I will give it.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.2'>And I will send an angel before you, and I will drive out the Canaanites, the Amorites, the Hittites, the Per'izzites, the Hivites, and the Jeb'usites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.3'>Go up to a land flowing with milk and honey; but I will not go up among you, lest I consume you in the way, for you are a stiff-necked people."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.4'>When the people heard these evil tidings, they mourned; and no man put on his ornaments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.5'>For the LORD had said to Moses, "Say to the people of Israel, `You are a stiff-necked people; if for a single moment I should go up among you, I would consume you. So now put off your ornaments from you, that I may know what to do with you.'"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.6'>Therefore the people of Israel stripped themselves of their ornaments, from Mount Horeb onward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.7'>Now Moses used to take the tent and pitch it outside the camp, far off from the camp; and he called it the tent of meeting. And every one who sought the LORD would go out to the tent of meeting, which was outside the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.8'>Whenever Moses went out to the tent, all the people rose up, and every man stood at his tent door, and looked after Moses, until he had gone into the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.9'>When Moses entered the tent, the pillar of cloud would descend and stand at the door of the tent, and the LORD would speak with Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.10'>And when all the people saw the pillar of cloud standing at the door of the tent, all the people would rise up and worship, every man at his tent door.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.11'>Thus the LORD used to speak to Moses face to face, as a man speaks to his friend. When Moses turned again into the camp, his servant Joshua the son of Nun, a young man, did not depart from the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.12'>Moses said to the LORD, "See, thou sayest to me, `Bring up this people'; but thou hast not let me know whom thou wilt send with me. Yet thou hast said, `I know you by name, and you have also found favor in my sight.'</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.13'>Now therefore, I pray thee, if I have found favor in thy sight, show me now thy ways, that I may know thee and find favor in thy sight. Consider too that this nation is thy people."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.14'>And he said, "My presence will go with you, and I will give you rest."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.15'>And he said to him, "If thy presence will not go with me, do not carry us up from here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.16'>For how shall it be known that I have found favor in thy sight, I and thy people? Is it not in thy going with us, so that we are distinct, I and thy people, from all other people that are upon the face of the earth?"</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.17'>And the LORD said to Moses, "This very thing that you have spoken I will do; for you have found favor in my sight, and I know you by name."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.18'>Moses said, "I pray thee, show me thy glory."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.19'>And he said, "I will make all my goodness pass before you, and will proclaim before you my name `The LORD'; and I will be gracious to whom I will be gracious, and will show mercy on whom I will show mercy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.20'>But," he said, "you cannot see my face; for man shall not see me and live."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.21'>And the LORD said, "Behold, there is a place by me where you shall stand upon the rock;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.22'>and while my glory passes by I will put you in a cleft of the rock, and I will cover you with my hand until I have passed by;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.23'>then I will take away my hand, and you shall see my back; but my face shall not be seen."</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.34'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.1'>The LORD said to Moses, "Cut two tables of stone like the first; and I will write upon the tables the words that were on the first tables, which you broke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.2'>Be ready in the morning, and come up in the morning to Mount Sinai, and present yourself there to me on the top of the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.3'>No man shall come up with you, and let no man be seen throughout all the mountain; let no flocks or herds feed before that mountain."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.4'>So Moses cut two tables of stone like the first; and he rose early in the morning and went up on Mount Sinai, as the LORD had commanded him, and took in his hand two tables of stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.5'>And the LORD descended in the cloud and stood with him there, and proclaimed the name of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.6'>The LORD passed before him, and proclaimed, "The LORD, the LORD, a God merciful and gracious, slow to anger, and abounding in steadfast love and faithfulness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.7'>keeping steadfast love for thousands, forgiving iniquity and transgression and sin, but who will by no means clear the guilty, visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children and the children's children, to the third and the fourth generation."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.8'>And Moses made haste to bow his head toward the earth, and worshiped.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.9'>And he said, "If now I have found favor in thy sight, O Lord, let the Lord, I pray thee, go in the midst of us, although it is a stiff-necked people; and pardon our iniquity and our sin, and take us for thy inheritance."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.10'>And he said, "Behold, I make a covenant. Before all your people I will do marvels, such as have not been wrought in all the earth or in any nation; and all the people among whom you are shall see the work of the LORD; for it is a terrible thing that I will do with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.11'>"Observe what I command you this day. Behold, I will drive out before you the Amorites, the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Per'izzites, the Hivites, and the Jeb'usites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.12'>Take heed to yourself, lest you make a covenant with the inhabitants of the land whither you go, lest it become a snare in the midst of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.13'>You shall tear down their altars, and break their pillars, and cut down their Ashe'rim</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.14'>(for you shall worship no other god, for the LORD, whose name is Jealous, is a jealous God),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.15'>lest you make a covenant with the inhabitants of the land, and when they play the harlot after their gods and sacrifice to their gods and one invites you, you eat of his sacrifice,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.16'>and you take of their daughters for your sons, and their daughters play the harlot after their gods and make your sons play the harlot after their gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.17'>"You shall make for yourself no molten gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.18'>"The feast of unleavened bread you shall keep. Seven days you shall eat unleavened bread, as I commanded you, at the time appointed in the month Abib; for in the month Abib you came out from Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.19'>All that opens the womb is mine, all your male cattle, the firstlings of cow and sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.20'>The firstling of an ass you shall redeem with a lamb, or if you will not redeem it you shall break its neck. All the first-born of your sons you shall redeem. And none shall appear before me empty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.21'>"Six days you shall work, but on the seventh day you shall rest; in plowing time and in harvest you shall rest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.22'>And you shall observe the feast of weeks, the first fruits of wheat harvest, and the feast of ingathering at the year's end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.23'>Three times in the year shall all your males appear before the LORD God, the God of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.24'>For I will cast out nations before you, and enlarge your borders; neither shall any man desire your land, when you go up to appear before the LORD your God three times in the year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.25'>"You shall not offer the blood of my sacrifice with leaven; neither shall the sacrifice of the feast of the passover be left until the morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.26'>The first of the first fruits of your ground you shall bring to the house of the LORD your God. You shall not boil a kid in its mother's milk."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.27'>And the LORD said to Moses, "Write these words; in accordance with these words I have made a covenant with you and with Israel."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.28'>And he was there with the LORD forty days and forty nights; he neither ate bread nor drank water. And he wrote upon the tables the words of the covenant, the ten commandments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.29'>When Moses came down from Mount Sinai, with the two tables of the testimony in his hand as he came down from the mountain, Moses did not know that the skin of his face shone because he had been talking with God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.30'>And when Aaron and all the people of Israel saw Moses, behold, the skin of his face shone, and they were afraid to come near him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.31'>But Moses called to them; and Aaron and all the leaders of the congregation returned to him, and Moses talked with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.32'>And afterward all the people of Israel came near, and he gave them in commandment all that the LORD had spoken with him in Mount Sinai.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.33'>And when Moses had finished speaking with them, he put a veil on his face;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.34'>but whenever Moses went in before the LORD to speak with him, he took the veil off, until he came out; and when he came out, and told the people of Israel what he was commanded,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.35'>the people of Israel saw the face of Moses, that the skin of Moses' face shone; and Moses would put the veil upon his face again, until he went in to speak with him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.35'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.1'>Moses assembled all the congregation of the people of Israel, and said to them, "These are the things which the LORD has commanded you to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.2'>Six days shall work be done, but on the seventh day you shall have a holy sabbath of solemn rest to the LORD; whoever does any work on it shall be put to death;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.3'>you shall kindle no fire in all your habitations on the sabbath day."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.4'>Moses said to all the congregation of the people of Israel, "This is the thing which the LORD has commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.5'>Take from among you an offering to the LORD; whoever is of a generous heart, let him bring the LORD's offering: gold, silver, and bronze;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.6'>blue and purple and scarlet stuff and fine twined linen; goats' hair,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.7'>tanned rams' skins, and goatskins; acacia wood,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.8'>oil for the light, spices for the anointing oil and for the fragrant incense,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.9'>and onyx stones and stones for setting, for the ephod and for the breastpiece.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.10'>"And let every able man among you come and make all that the LORD has commanded: the tabernacle,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.11'>its tent and its covering, its hooks and its frames, its bars, its pillars, and its bases;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.12'>the ark with its poles, the mercy seat, and the veil of the screen;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.13'>the table with its poles and all its utensils, and the bread of the Presence;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.14'>the lampstand also for the light, with its utensils and its lamps, and the oil for the light;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.15'>and the altar of incense, with its poles, and the anointing oil and the fragrant incense, and the screen for the door, at the door of the tabernacle;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.16'>the altar of burnt offering, with its grating of bronze, its poles, and all its utensils, the laver and its base;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.17'>the hangings of the court, its pillars and its bases, and the screen for the gate of the court;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.18'>the pegs of the tabernacle and the pegs of the court, and their cords;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.19'>the finely wrought garments for ministering in the holy place, the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and the garments of his sons, for their service as priests."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.20'>Then all the congregation of the people of Israel departed from the presence of Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.21'>And they came, every one whose heart stirred him, and every one whose spirit moved him, and brought the LORD's offering to be used for the tent of meeting, and for all its service, and for the holy garments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.22'>So they came, both men and women; all who were of a willing heart brought brooches and earrings and signet rings and armlets, all sorts of gold objects, every man dedicating an offering of gold to the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.23'>And every man with whom was found blue or purple or scarlet stuff or fine linen or goats' hair or tanned rams' skins or goatskins, brought them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.24'>Every one who could make an offering of silver or bronze brought it as the LORD's offering; and every man with whom was found acacia wood of any use in the work, brought it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.25'>And all women who had ability spun with their hands, and brought what they had spun in blue and purple and scarlet stuff and fine twined linen;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.26'>all the women whose hearts were moved with ability spun the goats' hair.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.27'>And the leaders brought onyx stones and stones to be set, for the ephod and for the breastpiece,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.28'>and spices and oil for the light, and for the anointing oil, and for the fragrant incense.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.29'>All the men and women, the people of Israel, whose heart moved them to bring anything for the work which the LORD had commanded by Moses to be done, brought it as their freewill offering to the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.30'>And Moses said to the people of Israel, "See, the LORD has called by name Bez'alel the son of Uri, son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.31'>and he has filled him with the Spirit of God, with ability, with intelligence, with knowledge, and with all craftsmanship,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.32'>to devise artistic designs, to work in gold and silver and bronze,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.33'>in cutting stones for setting, and in carving wood, for work in every skilled craft.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.34'>And he has inspired him to teach, both him and Oho'liab the son of Ahis'amach of the tribe of Dan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.35'>He has filled them with ability to do every sort of work done by a craftsman or by a designer or by an embroiderer in blue and purple and scarlet stuff and fine twined linen, or by a weaver--by any sort of workman or skilled designer.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.36'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.1'>Bez'alel and Oho'liab and every able man in whom the LORD has put ability and intelligence to know how to do any work in the construction of the sanctuary shall work in accordance with all that the LORD has commanded."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.2'>And Moses called Bez'alel and Oho'liab and every able man in whose mind the LORD had put ability, every one whose heart stirred him up to come to do the work;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.3'>and they received from Moses all the freewill offering which the people of Israel had brought for doing the work on the sanctuary. They still kept bringing him freewill offerings every morning,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.4'>so that all the able men who were doing every sort of task on the sanctuary came, each from the task that he was doing,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.5'>and said to Moses, "The people bring much more than enough for doing the work which the LORD has commanded us to do."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.6'>So Moses gave command, and word was proclaimed throughout the camp, "Let neither man nor woman do anything more for the offering for the sanctuary." So the people were restrained from bringing;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.7'>for the stuff they had was sufficient to do all the work, and more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.8'>And all the able men among the workmen made the tabernacle with ten curtains; they were made of fine twined linen and blue and purple and scarlet stuff, with cherubim skilfully worked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.9'>The length of each curtain was twenty-eight cubits, and the breadth of each curtain four cubits; all the curtains had the same measure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.10'>And he coupled five curtains to one another, and the other five curtains he coupled to one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.11'>And he made loops of blue on the edge of the outmost curtain of the first set; likewise he made them on the edge of the outmost curtain of the second set;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.12'>he made fifty loops on the one curtain, and he made fifty loops on the edge of the curtain that was in the second set; the loops were opposite one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.13'>And he made fifty clasps of gold, and coupled the curtains one to the other with clasps; so the tabernacle was one whole.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.14'>He also made curtains of goats' hair for a tent over the tabernacle; he made eleven curtains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.15'>The length of each curtain was thirty cubits, and the breadth of each curtain four cubits; the eleven curtains had the same measure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.16'>He coupled five curtains by themselves, and six curtains by themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.17'>And he made fifty loops on the edge of the outmost curtain of the one set, and fifty loops on the edge of the other connecting curtain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.18'>And he made fifty clasps of bronze to couple the tent together that it might be one whole.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.19'>And he made for the tent a covering of tanned rams' skins and goatskins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.20'>Then he made the upright frames for the tabernacle of acacia wood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.21'>Ten cubits was the length of a frame, and a cubit and a half the breadth of each frame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.22'>Each frame had two tenons, for fitting together; he did this for all the frames of the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.23'>The frames for the tabernacle he made thus: twenty frames for the south side;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.24'>and he made forty bases of silver under the twenty frames, two bases under one frame for its two tenons, and two bases under another frame for its two tenons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.25'>And for the second side of the tabernacle, on the north side, he made twenty frames</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.26'>and their forty bases of silver, two bases under one frame and two bases under another frame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.27'>And for the rear of the tabernacle westward he made six frames.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.28'>And he made two frames for corners of the tabernacle in the rear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.29'>And they were separate beneath, but joined at the top, at the first ring; he made two of them thus, for the two corners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.30'>There were eight frames with their bases of silver: sixteen bases, under every frame two bases.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.31'>And he made bars of acacia wood, five for the frames of the one side of the tabernacle,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.32'>and five bars for the frames of the other side of the tabernacle, and five bars for the frames of the tabernacle at the rear westward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.33'>And he made the middle bar to pass through from end to end halfway up the frames.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.34'>And he overlaid the frames with gold, and made their rings of gold for holders for the bars, and overlaid the bars with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.35'>And he made the veil of blue and purple and scarlet stuff and fine twined linen; with cherubim skilfully worked he made it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.36'>And for it he made four pillars of acacia, and overlaid them with gold; their hooks were of gold, and he cast for them four bases of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.37'>He also made a screen for the door of the tent, of blue and purple and scarlet stuff and fine twined linen, embroidered with needlework;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.38'>and its five pillars with their hooks. He overlaid their capitals, and their fillets were of gold, but their five bases were of bronze.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.37'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.1'>Bez'alel made the ark of acacia wood; two cubits and a half was its length, a cubit and a half its breadth, and a cubit and a half its height.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.2'>And he overlaid it with pure gold within and without, and made a molding of gold around it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.3'>And he cast for it four rings of gold for its four corners, two rings on its one side and two rings on its other side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.4'>And he made poles of acacia wood, and overlaid them with gold,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.5'>and put the poles into the rings on the sides of the ark, to carry the ark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.6'>And he made a mercy seat of pure gold; two cubits and a half was its length, and a cubit and a half its breadth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.7'>And he made two cherubim of hammered gold; on the two ends of the mercy seat he made them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.8'>one cherub on the one end, and one cherub on the other end; of one piece with the mercy seat he made the cherubim on its two ends.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.9'>The cherubim spread out their wings above, overshadowing the mercy seat with their wings, with their faces one to another; toward the mercy seat were the faces of the cherubim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.10'>He also made the table of acacia wood; two cubits was its length, a cubit its breadth, and a cubit and a half its height;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.11'>and he overlaid it with pure gold, and made a molding of gold around it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.12'>And he made around it a frame a handbreadth wide, and made a molding of gold around the frame.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.13'>He cast for it four rings of gold, and fastened the rings to the four corners at its four legs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.14'>Close to the frame were the rings, as holders for the poles to carry the table.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.15'>He made the poles of acacia wood to carry the table, and overlaid them with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.16'>And he made the vessels of pure gold which were to be upon the table, its plates and dishes for incense, and its bowls and flagons with which to pour libations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.17'>He also made the lampstand of pure gold. The base and the shaft of the lampstand were made of hammered work; its cups, its capitals, and its flowers were of one piece with it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.18'>And there were six branches going out of its sides, three branches of the lampstand out of one side of it and three branches of the lampstand out of the other side of it;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.19'>three cups made like almonds, each with capital and flower, on one branch, and three cups made like almonds, each with capital and flower, on the other branch --so for the six branches going out of the lampstand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.20'>And on the lampstand itself were four cups made like almonds, with their capitals and flowers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.21'>and a capital of one piece with it under each pair of the six branches going out of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.22'>Their capitals and their branches were of one piece with it; the whole of it was one piece of hammered work of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.23'>And he made its seven lamps and its snuffers and its trays of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.24'>He made it and all its utensils of a talent of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.25'>He made the altar of incense of acacia wood; its length was a cubit, and its breadth was a cubit; it was square, and two cubits was its height; its horns were of one piece with it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.26'>He overlaid it with pure gold, its top, and its sides round about, and its horns; and he made a molding of gold round about it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.27'>and made two rings of gold on it under its molding, on two opposite sides of it, as holders for the poles with which to carry it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.28'>And he made the poles of acacia wood, and overlaid them with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.29'>He made the holy anointing oil also, and the pure fragrant incense, blended as by the perfumer.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.38'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.1'>He made the altar of burnt offering also of acacia wood; five cubits was its length, and five cubits its breadth; it was square, and three cubits was its height.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.2'>He made horns for it on its four corners; its horns were of one piece with it, and he overlaid it with bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.3'>And he made all the utensils of the altar, the pots, the shovels, the basins, the forks, and the firepans: all its utensils he made of bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.4'>And he made for the altar a grating, a network of bronze, under its ledge, extending halfway down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.5'>He cast four rings on the four corners of the bronze grating as holders for the poles;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.6'>he made the poles of acacia wood, and overlaid them with bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.7'>And he put the poles through the rings on the sides of the altar, to carry it with them; he made it hollow, with boards.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.8'>And he made the laver of bronze and its base of bronze, from the mirrors of the ministering women who ministered at the door of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.9'>And he made the court; for the south side the hangings of the court were of fine twined linen, a hundred cubits;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.10'>their pillars were twenty and their bases twenty, of bronze, but the hooks of the pillars and their fillets were of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.11'>And for the north side a hundred cubits, their pillars twenty, their bases twenty, of bronze, but the hooks of the pillars and their fillets were of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.12'>And for the west side were hangings of fifty cubits, their pillars ten, and their sockets ten; the hooks of the pillars and their fillets were of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.13'>And for the front to the east, fifty cubits.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.14'>The hangings for one side of the gate were fifteen cubits, with three pillars and three bases.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.15'>And so for the other side; on this hand and that hand by the gate of the court were hangings of fifteen cubits, with three pillars and three bases.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.16'>All the hangings round about the court were of fine twined linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.17'>And the bases for the pillars were of bronze, but the hooks of the pillars and their fillets were of silver; the overlaying of their capitals was also of silver, and all the pillars of the court were filleted with silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.18'>And the screen for the gate of the court was embroidered with needlework in blue and purple and scarlet stuff and fine twined linen; it was twenty cubits long and five cubits high in its breadth, corresponding to the hangings of the court.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.19'>And their pillars were four; their four bases were of bronze, their hooks of silver, and the overlaying of their capitals and their fillets of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.20'>And all the pegs for the tabernacle and for the court round about were of bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.21'>This is the sum of the things for the tabernacle, the tabernacle of the testimony, as they were counted at the commandment of Moses, for the work of the Levites under the direction of Ith'amar the son of Aaron the priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.22'>Bez'alel the son of Uri, son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah, made all that the LORD commanded Moses;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.23'>and with him was Oho'liab the son of Ahis'amach, of the tribe of Dan, a craftsman and designer and embroiderer in blue and purple and scarlet stuff and fine twined linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.24'>All the gold that was used for the work, in all the construction of the sanctuary, the gold from the offering, was twenty-nine talents and seven hundred and thirty shekels, by the shekel of the sanctuary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.25'>And the silver from those of the congregation who were numbered was a hundred talents and a thousand seven hundred and seventy-five shekels, by the shekel of the sanctuary:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.26'>a beka a head (that is, half a shekel, by the shekel of the sanctuary), for every one who was numbered in the census, from twenty years old and upward, for six hundred and three thousand, five hundred and fifty men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.27'>The hundred talents of silver were for casting the bases of the sanctuary, and the bases of the veil; a hundred bases for the hundred talents, a talent for a base.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.28'>And of the thousand seven hundred and seventy-five shekels he made hooks for the pillars, and overlaid their capitals and made fillets for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.29'>And the bronze that was contributed was seventy talents, and two thousand and four hundred shekels;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.30'>with it he made the bases for the door of the tent of meeting, the bronze altar and the bronze grating for it and all the utensils of the altar,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.31'>the bases round about the court, and the bases of the gate of the court, all the pegs of the tabernacle, and all the pegs round about the court.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.39'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.1'>And of the blue and purple and scarlet stuff they made finely wrought garments, for ministering in the holy place; they made the holy garments for Aaron; as the LORD had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.2'>And he made the ephod of gold, blue and purple and scarlet stuff, and fine twined linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.3'>And gold leaf was hammered out and cut into threads to work into the blue and purple and the scarlet stuff, and into the fine twined linen, in skilled design.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.4'>They made for the ephod shoulder-pieces, joined to it at its two edges.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.5'>And the skilfully woven band upon it, to gird it on, was of the same materials and workmanship, of gold, blue and purple and scarlet stuff, and fine twined linen; as the LORD had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.6'>The onyx stones were prepared, enclosed in settings of gold filigree and engraved like the engravings of a signet, according to the names of the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.7'>And he set them on the shoulder-pieces of the ephod, to be stones of remembrance for the sons of Israel; as the LORD had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.8'>He made the breastpiece, in skilled work, like the work of the ephod, of gold, blue and purple and scarlet stuff, and fine twined linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.9'>It was square; the breastpiece was made double, a span its length and a span its breadth when doubled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.10'>And they set in it four rows of stones. A row of sardius, topaz, and carbuncle was the first row;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.11'>and the second row, an emerald, a sapphire, and a diamond;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.12'>and the third row, a jacinth, an agate, and an amethyst;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.13'>and the fourth row, a beryl, an onyx, and a jasper; they were enclosed in settings of gold filigree.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.14'>There were twelve stones with their names according to the names of the sons of Israel; they were like signets, each engraved with its name, for the twelve tribes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.15'>And they made on the breastpiece twisted chains like cords, of pure gold;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.16'>and they made two settings of gold filigree and two gold rings, and put the two rings on the two edges of the breastpiece;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.17'>and they put the two cords of gold in the two rings at the edges of the breastpiece.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.18'>Two ends of the two cords they had attached to the two settings of filigree; thus they attached it in front to the shoulder-pieces of the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.19'>Then they made two rings of gold, and put them at the two ends of the breastpiece, on its inside edge next to the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.20'>And they made two rings of gold, and attached them in front to the lower part of the two shoulder-pieces of the ephod, at its joining above the skilfully woven band of the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.21'>And they bound the breastpiece by its rings to the rings of the ephod with a lace of blue, so that it should lie upon the skilfully woven band of the ephod, and that the breastpiece should not come loose from the ephod; as the LORD had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.22'>He also made the robe of the ephod woven all of blue;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.23'>and the opening of the robe in it was like the opening in a garment, with a binding around the opening, that it might not be torn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.24'>On the skirts of the robe they made pomegranates of blue and purple and scarlet stuff and fine twined linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.25'>They also made bells of pure gold, and put the bells between the pomegranates upon the skirts of the robe round about, between the pomegranates;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.26'>a bell and a pomegranate, a bell and a pomegranate round about upon the skirts of the robe for ministering; as the LORD had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.27'>They also made the coats, woven of fine linen, for Aaron and his sons,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.28'>and the turban of fine linen, and the caps of fine linen, and the linen breeches of fine twined linen,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.29'>and the girdle of fine twined linen and of blue and purple and scarlet stuff, embroidered with needlework; as the LORD had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.30'>And they made the plate of the holy crown of pure gold, and wrote upon it an inscription, like the engraving of a signet, "Holy to the LORD."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.31'>And they tied to it a lace of blue, to fasten it on the turban above; as the LORD had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.32'>Thus all the work of the tabernacle of the tent of meeting was finished; and the people of Israel had done according to all that the LORD had commanded Moses; so had they done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.33'>And they brought the tabernacle to Moses, the tent and all its utensils, its hooks, its frames, its bars, its pillars, and its bases;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.34'>the covering of tanned rams' skins and goatskins, and the veil of the screen;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.35'>the ark of the testimony with its poles and the mercy seat;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.36'>the table with all its utensils, and the bread of the Presence;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.37'>the lampstand of pure gold and its lamps with the lamps set and all its utensils, and the oil for the light;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.38'>the golden altar, the anointing oil and the fragrant incense, and the screen for the door of the tent;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.39'>the bronze altar, and its grating of bronze, its poles, and all its utensils; the laver and its base;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.40'>the hangings of the court, its pillars, and its bases, and the screen for the gate of the court, its cords, and its pegs; and all the utensils for the service of the tabernacle, for the tent of meeting;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.41'>the finely worked garments for ministering in the holy place, the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and the garments of his sons to serve as priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.42'>According to all that the LORD had commanded Moses, so the people of Israel had done all the work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.43'>And Moses saw all the work, and behold, they had done it; as the LORD had commanded, so had they done it. And Moses blessed them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.40'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.1'>The LORD said to Moses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.2'>"On the first day of the first month you shall erect the tabernacle of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.3'>And you shall put in it the ark of the testimony, and you shall screen the ark with the veil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.4'>And you shall bring in the table, and set its arrangements in order; and you shall bring in the lampstand, and set up its lamps.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.5'>And you shall put the golden altar for incense before the ark of the testimony, and set up the screen for the door of the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.6'>You shall set the altar of burnt offering before the door of the tabernacle of the tent of meeting,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.7'>and place the laver between the tent of meeting and the altar, and put water in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.8'>And you shall set up the court round about, and hang up the screen for the gate of the court.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.9'>Then you shall take the anointing oil, and anoint the tabernacle and all that is in it, and consecrate it and all its furniture; and it shall become holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.10'>You shall also anoint the altar of burnt offering and all its utensils, and consecrate the altar; and the altar shall be most holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.11'>You shall also anoint the laver and its base, and consecrate it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.12'>Then you shall bring Aaron and his sons to the door of the tent of meeting, and shall wash them with water,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.13'>and put upon Aaron the holy garments, and you shall anoint him and consecrate him, that he may serve me as priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.14'>You shall bring his sons also and put coats on them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.15'>and anoint them, as you anointed their father, that they may serve me as priests: and their anointing shall admit them to a perpetual priesthood throughout their generations."</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.16'>Thus did Moses; according to all that the LORD commanded him, so he did.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.17'>And in the first month in the second year, on the first day of the month, the tabernacle was erected.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.18'>Moses erected the tabernacle; he laid its bases, and set up its frames, and put in its poles, and raised up its pillars;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.19'>and he spread the tent over the tabernacle, and put the covering of the tent over it, as the LORD had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.20'>And he took the testimony and put it into the ark, and put the poles on the ark, and set the mercy seat above on the ark;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.21'>and he brought the ark into the tabernacle, and set up the veil of the screen, and screened the ark of the testimony; as the LORD had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.22'>And he put the table in the tent of meeting, on the north side of the tabernacle, outside the veil,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.23'>and set the bread in order on it before the LORD; as the LORD had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.24'>And he put the lampstand in the tent of meeting, opposite the table on the south side of the tabernacle,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.25'>and set up the lamps before the LORD; as the LORD had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.26'>And he put the golden altar in the tent of meeting before the veil,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.27'>and burnt fragrant incense upon it; as the LORD had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.28'>And he put in place the screen for the door of the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.29'>And he set the altar of burnt offering at the door of the tabernacle of the tent of meeting, and offered upon it the burnt offering and the cereal offering; as the LORD had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.30'>And he set the laver between the tent of meeting and the altar, and put water in it for washing,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.31'>with which Moses and Aaron and his sons washed their hands and their feet;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.32'>when they went into the tent of meeting, and when they approached the altar, they washed; as the LORD commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.33'>And he erected the court round the tabernacle and the altar, and set up the screen of the gate of the court. So Moses finished the work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.34'>Then the cloud covered the tent of meeting, and the glory of the LORD filled the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.35'>And Moses was not able to enter the tent of meeting, because the cloud abode upon it, and the glory of the LORD filled the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.36'>Throughout all their journeys, whenever the cloud was taken up from over the tabernacle, the people of Israel would go onward;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.37'>but if the cloud was not taken up, then they did not go onward till the day that it was taken up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.38'>For throughout all their journeys the cloud of the LORD was upon the tabernacle by day, and fire was in it by night, in the sight of all the house of Israel.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>