<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='rsv' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='rsv'>
        <title>Revised Standard Version</title>
        <contributor>Sword Project</contributor>
        <creator>ColdHeart</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-22</date>
        <description>The Holy Bible, Revised Standard Version 1952 (RSV), the authorized revision of the American Standard Version of 1901, Copyright (c) 1946, 1952, 1973 by the Division of Christian Education of the National Council of Churches of Christ in the United States of America.</description>
        <publisher>DarkBibleORG</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>rsv</identifier>
        <source>http://www.crosswire.org/sword/servlet/SwordMod.Verify?modName=RSV</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide th bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Division of Christian Education of the National Council of the churches of Christ in the U.S.A. 1946, 1952, 1973 Rachel Riensche, Vice President, Corporate Affairs Augsburg Fortress Publishers, 100 South Fifth Street, Suite 700. Minneapolis, MN 55402, USA</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Phlm'>
      <chapter osisID='Phlm.1'>
        <title>Declare these things; exhort and reprove with all authority. Let no one disregard you.</title>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.1'>Paul, a prisoner for Christ Jesus, and Timothy our brother,  To Phile'mon our beloved fellow worker</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.2'>and Ap'phia our sister and Archip'pus our fellow soldier, and the church in your house:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.3'>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.4'>I thank my God always when I remember you in my prayers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.5'>because I hear of your love and of the faith which you have toward the Lord Jesus and all the saints,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.6'>and I pray that the sharing of your faith may promote the knowledge of all the good that is ours in Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.7'>For I have derived much joy and comfort from your love, my brother, because the hearts of the saints have been refreshed through you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.8'>Accordingly, though I am bold enough in Christ to command you to do what is required,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.9'>yet for love's sake I prefer to appeal to you--I, Paul, an ambassador and now a prisoner also for Christ Jesus--</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.10'>I appeal to you for my child, Ones'imus, whose father I have become in my imprisonment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.11'>(Formerly he was useless to you, but now he is indeed useful to you and to me.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.12'>I am sending him back to you, sending my very heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.13'>I would have been glad to keep him with me, in order that he might serve me on your behalf during my imprisonment for the gospel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.14'>but I preferred to do nothing without your consent in order that your goodness might not be by compulsion but of your own free will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.15'>Perhaps this is why he was parted from you for a while, that you might have him back for ever,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.16'>no longer as a slave but more than a slave, as a beloved brother, especially to me but how much more to you, both in the flesh and in the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.17'>So if you consider me your partner, receive him as you would receive me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.18'>If he has wronged you at all, or owes you anything, charge that to my account.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.19'>I, Paul, write this with my own hand, I will repay it--to say nothing of your owing me even your own self.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.20'>Yes, brother, I want some benefit from you in the Lord. Refresh my heart in Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.21'>Confident of your obedience, I write to you, knowing that you will do even more than I say.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.22'>At the same time, prepare a guest room for me, for I am hoping through your prayers to be granted to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.23'>Ep'aphras, my fellow prisoner in Christ Jesus, sends greetings to you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.24'>and so do Mark, Aristar'chus, Demas, and Luke, my fellow workers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Phlm.1.25'>The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>