<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='Diaglot' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='Diaglot'>
        <title>Diaglot NT - 1865</title>
        <contributor>Watch Tower Bible and Tract Society</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>
    
The Emphatic Diaglott

About=From the title page we read as follows: "The Emphatic Diaglott, containing the
original Greek text of what is commonly styled the New Testament (according to the
recension of Dr. J. J. Griesbach) with an interlineary translation, on the renderings
of eminent critics, and on the various readings of The Vatican Manuscript, No. 1209, in
the Vatican Library, together with illustrative and explanatory foot notes, and a
copious selection of references, ..., by Benjamin Wilson."

Although the translator does not claim this version to be superior to any other, he
feels that this work presents certain valuable features not found elsewhere. These are
listed in the Preface.

Careful fidelity in giving true rendering of the original text into English has been
maintained throughout. No regard whatever has been given to prevailing doctrines or
prejudices of sects, or the peculiar tenets of theologians.

Help in this work was derived from works of great and learned men. The sources include
the following: lexicons, grammars, ancient and modern versions, commentaries (critical
and explanatory), cyclopedias, and dictionaries (Bible and others). It is not presumed
that this work is free from faults and errors.

Watch Tower Bible and Tract Society (1942)

Text from http://www.biblestudentslibrary.org/ used by permission.

</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>Diaglot</identifier>
        <source>http://users.eggconnect.net/noddy3/diaglott.pdf</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='1Tim'>
      <chapter osisID='1Tim.1'>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.1'>Paul, an apostle of Jesus Anointed, according to an appointment of God, a saviour of us, and Anointed Jesus, of the hope of us,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.2'>to Timothy a genuine child in faith; favor, mercy, peace from God a Father of us, and Anointed Jesus the Lord of us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.3'>As I entreated thee to remain in Ephesus, departing for Macedonia, that thou mayest charge some not other to teach,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.4'>nor to hold to fables and genealogies endless, which disputes occasion rather than an administration of God that by faith;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.5'>(the now end of the commandment is love out of a pure heart and conscience good and faith unfeigned;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.6'>which some having missed, turned aside to foolish talking,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.7'>wishing to be lawteachers, not understanding neither the things they say, nor concerning certain things they positively affirm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.8'>We know but, that good the law, if one it lawfully may use,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.9'>knowing this, that for a just one a law not is laid down, for lawless ones but and for unruly ones, for ungodly ones and sinners, for impious ones and for profane ones, for smiters of fathers and for smiters of mothers, for mankillers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.10'>for fornicators, for sodomites, for manstealers, for liars, for oathbreakers, and if anything other to the sound teaching is opposed,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.11'>according to the glad tidings of the glory of the blessed God, which was entrusted with I;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.12'>and give thanks I to the one having empowered me Anointed Jesus the Lord of us, because faithful me he regarded, placing into service,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.13'>him formerly being a defamer and a persecutor and a violent person; but I received mercy, because being ignorant I acted in unbelief,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.14'>superabounded but the favor of the Lord of us with faith and love of that in Anointed Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.15'>True the word, and of all reception worthy, that Anointed Jesus came into the world sinners to save, of whom first am I;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.16'>but through this I received mercy, that in me first might show forth Jesus Anointed the all forbearance, for an example of those being about to believe on him for life agelasting;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.17'>to the now King of the ages, incorruptible, invisible, only God, honor and glory for the ages of the ages; so be it.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.18'>This the charge I commit to thee, child O Timothy, according to the preceding in respect to thee prophecies that thou mayest war by them the good warfare,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.19'>holding faith and good a conscience, which some having thrust away, concerning the faith were shipwreck;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.1.20'>of whom is Hymenius and Alexander, whom I delivered up to the adversary, so that they might be taught not to revile.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Tim.2'>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.1'>I exhort therefore first of all to make supplications, prayers, intercessions, thanksgivings in behalf of all men;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.2'>in behalf of kings, and of all of those in high station being; so that a tranquil and quiet life we may lead in all piety and seriousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.3'>This for good and acceptable in presence of the preserver of us God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.4'>who all men wishes to be saved, and into in exact knowledge of truth to come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.5'>One for God, one and mediator of God and of men, a man Anointed Jesus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.6'>he having given himself a ransom in behalf of all; the testimony for seasons own,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.7'>for which was placed I a herald and an apostle, (truth I speak, not I speak falsely,) a teacher of nations in faith and in truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.8'>I direct therefore to pray the men in every place, lifting up holy hands without wrath and disputing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.9'>In the same way and the women in apparel becoming, with modesty and soundness of mind, to adorn themselves, not with wreaths, of gold, or pearls or garment expensive,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.10'>but, (which in becoming for women undertaking worship of God,) by means of works good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.11'>A woman in quietness let learn with all submission.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.12'>A women but to teach not I permit, nor to assume authority over a man, but to be in silence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.13'>Adam for first was formed, then Eve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.14'>And Adam not was deceived; the but woman having been deceived, in transgression became;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.2.15'>she will be preserved but through the childbearing, if they abide in faith and love and holiness with sobriety of mind.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Tim.3'>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.1'>True the word: If any one an oversight long after, excellent a work he desires.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.2'>It behooves then the overseer unblamable to be, of one wife a husband, vigilant, sedate, orderly, hospitable, fit to teach;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.3'>not a wine drinker, not a striker, but gentle, not quarrelsome, not a lover of money;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.4'>of the own house well presiding, children having in subjection with all dignity;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.5'>(if but any one of the own house to preside not knows, how a congregation of God will he take care off?)</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.6'>not a new convert, so that not being puffed up into a judgment he may fall of the accuser;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.7'>it behooves but him also a testimony good to have from those outside, so that not into reproach he may fall and a snare of the accuser.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.8'>Servants in like manner dignified, not twoworded, not to wine much being addicted, not eager for base gain,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.9'>holding the secret of the faith in a pure conscience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.10'>Also these but let be proved first, then let serve, unblamable being.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.11'>Women in like manner serious, not accusers, vigilant, faithful in all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.12'>Servants let be of one wife a husband, children well presiding over and of the own houses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.13'>Those for well having served, a standing for themselves honorable they acquire, and much confidence in faith in that in Anointed Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.14'>These things to thee I write, hoping to come to thee very soon;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.15'>if but I should delay, that thou mayest know, know it behooves in a house of God to conduct thyself, which is a congregation of God living.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.3.16'>A pillar and basis of the truth and confessedly great is the of the piety secret. Who was manifested in flesh, was justified in spirit, was seen by messengers, was proclaimed among nations, was believed among a world, was taken up in glory.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Tim.4'>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.1'>The but spirit expressly says, that in subsequent seasons will fall away some from the faith, adhering to spirits wandering and to teachings of demons,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.2'>by hypocrisy of falsespeakers, having been cauterized the own conscience,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.3'>forbidding to marry, to abstain from foods, which the God created for a partaking of with thanksgiving by the faithful ones and they have known the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.4'>Because every creature of God good, and nothing cast away, with thanksgiving being received;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.5'>it is sanctified for through a word of God and of prayer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.6'>These things setting forth to the brethren, good thou wilt be a servant of Jesus Anointed, being nourished with the words of the faith and of the good teachings, which thou hast closely followed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.7'>The but profane and old women fables do thou avoid; discipline but thyself for piety.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.8'>The for bodily discipline for a little it is profitable; the but piety for all things profitable it is, a promise having of life of the now and of that about coming.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.9'>True the word and of all acceptance worthy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.10'>In order of this and we toil and are reproached, because we have hoped in God living, who is a preserver of all men, especially of believers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.11'>Do thou enjoin these things and do thou teach.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.12'>No one thee the youth let despise, but a pattern become thou of the believers in word, in conduct, in love, in faith, in purity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.13'>Till I come, attend thou to the reading, to the exhorting, to the teaching.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.14'>Not be thou neglectful of the in thee endowment, which was given to thee through prophecy, with laying on the hands of the eldership.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.15'>These things do thou care for, in these things be thou; so that of thee the progress manifest may be in all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.4.16'>Attend thou to thyself, and to the teaching; continue thou in them; this for doing, both thyself thou wilt save and those hearing thee.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Tim.5'>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.1'>An elderly man not thou mayest chide, but exhort as a father; younger men, as brothers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.2'>elderly women, as mothers; younger women, as sisters, in all purity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.3'>Widows honor, those really widows.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.4'>If but any widow children or grandchildren has, let them be taught first the own house to be dutiful, and a recompense to render to the progenitors; this for is acceptable in presence of the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.5'>She but really a widow and having been left alone she hoped in the God, and continues in the supplications and in the prayers night and day;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.6'>she but luxuriously, living has died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.7'>And these things enjoin, so that unblamable ones they may be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.8'>If but any one for those of own, and especially of the household, not provides, the faith has denied, and is an unbeliever worse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.9'>A widow let be enrolled not less of years sixty, having become, of one husband a wife,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.10'>by works good being attested; if she reared a family, if she received strangers, if of holy ones feet she washed, if afflicted ones she relieved, if every work good she closely followed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.11'>Younger but widows reject; when for they may be wanton towards the Anointed, to marry they wish;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.12'>having condemnation, because the first fidelity they violated;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.13'>at the same time and also idle ones they learn to go about the houses; not only but idle ones, but also praters and busy bodies, speaking the things not proper.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.14'>I wish therefore younger ones to marry, to bear children, to keep house, no opportunity to give to the opponent of reproach on account.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.15'>Already for some turned aside after the adversary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.16'>If any believing man or believing woman has widows, let such support them, and not let burden the congregation, so that those really widows may be relieved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.17'>The well presiding elders double honor let be esteemed worthy; especially those toiling in word and teaching.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.18'>Says for the writing: An ox trending not thou shalt muzzle; and, worthy the laborer of the hire of himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.19'>Against an elder an accusation not do thou receive, without if not by two or three witnesses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.20'>The sinning ones, in presence of all reprove thou, so that also the remainder fear may have.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.21'>I solemnly enjoin in presence of the God and Lord Jesus Anointed and of the chosen messengers, that these things thou mayst keep without prejudice nothing doing by partiality.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.22'>Hands hastily to no one do thou put and not do thou share in sins with others. Thyself pure do thou keep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.23'>No longer be thou a water drinker, but wine a little do thou use on account of the stomach of thee and the frequent of thee weaknesses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.24'>Of some men the sins previously manifest are, before leading to judgment; in some but indeed they fellow after.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.5.25'>In like manner also the good works previously manifest are; and the things otherwise being, to be hidden not are able.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Tim.6'>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.1'>As many as are under a yoke slaves, the own masters of all honor worthy let them esteem, that not the name of the God and the teaching may be reviled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.2'>Those and believing having masters, not let them disregard, because brethren they are; but rather let them serve, because believing ones they are and beloved ones who of the welldoing are recipients. These thing do thou teach, and do thou exhort.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.3'>If any one teach differently, and not assents to being sound in words in those of the Lord of us Jesus Anointed, and so that according to piety teaching;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.4'>he is puffed up, nothing being versed in, but being sick about questions and strifes of words, out of which arises envy, strife, evilspeakings, suspicions wicked,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.5'>wrangling having been corrupted of men the mind, and having been devoid of the truth, supposing gain to be the piety. withdraw thyself from of the such ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.6'>It is but gain great the piety with a competency.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.7'>Nothing for we brought into the world; evident, that neither to carry out any thing are we able.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.8'>Having and foods and coverings, with these things we shall be satisfied.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.9'>Those but wishing to be rich, fall into a temptation and a snare, and desires many foolish and hurtful, which sink deep the men into destruction and ruin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.10'>A root for of all of the evils is the love of money; which some longing after wandered from the faith, and themselves pierced around with sorrows many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.11'>Thou but, O man of the God, these things flee; pursue thou and righteousness, piety, faith, love, patience, meekness;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.12'>contest thou the good contest of the faith, do thou lay hold of the agelasting life, for which thou wast called out, and thou didst confess the good confession in presence of many witnesses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.13'>I charge thee in presence of the God, of that making alive the things all, and Anointed Jesus, of that one testifying before Pontius Pilate the good confession,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.14'>to keep thee the commandment spotless, blameless, till the appearance of the Lord of us Jesus Anointed,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.15'>which in seasons own he will show the blessed and only Potentate, the King of those being kings and Lord of those being lords,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.16'>the only one having deathlessness, light dwelling in inaccessible, whom saw no one of men, nor to see is able; to whom honor and might agelasting; so be it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.17'>To those rich ones in the present age do thou charge not to be highmined, nor to have confidence in wealth uncertain, but in the God the living, in that offering to us all things richly for enjoyment;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.18'>to work good, to be rich in works good, liberal ones to be, communicative ones,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.19'>treasuring up for themselves a foundation good for the future, so that they may lay hold of that really life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Tim.6.20'>O Timothy, the trust guard thou, avoiding the profane empty sounds and oppositions of the falselynamed knowledge; which some having professed, concerning the faith missed the mark. The favor with thee.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>