<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='Diaglot' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='Diaglot'>
        <title>Diaglot NT - 1865</title>
        <contributor>Watch Tower Bible and Tract Society</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>
    
The Emphatic Diaglott

About=From the title page we read as follows: "The Emphatic Diaglott, containing the
original Greek text of what is commonly styled the New Testament (according to the
recension of Dr. J. J. Griesbach) with an interlineary translation, on the renderings
of eminent critics, and on the various readings of The Vatican Manuscript, No. 1209, in
the Vatican Library, together with illustrative and explanatory foot notes, and a
copious selection of references, ..., by Benjamin Wilson."

Although the translator does not claim this version to be superior to any other, he
feels that this work presents certain valuable features not found elsewhere. These are
listed in the Preface.

Careful fidelity in giving true rendering of the original text into English has been
maintained throughout. No regard whatever has been given to prevailing doctrines or
prejudices of sects, or the peculiar tenets of theologians.

Help in this work was derived from works of great and learned men. The sources include
the following: lexicons, grammars, ancient and modern versions, commentaries (critical
and explanatory), cyclopedias, and dictionaries (Bible and others). It is not presumed
that this work is free from faults and errors.

Watch Tower Bible and Tract Society (1942)

Text from http://www.biblestudentslibrary.org/ used by permission.

</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>Diaglot</identifier>
        <source>http://users.eggconnect.net/noddy3/diaglott.pdf</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='3John'>
      <chapter osisID='3John.1'>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.1'>The elder to Gaius the beloved one, whom I love in truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.2'>O beloved one, concerning all things I wish thee to prosper and to be in health, even as prospers thee the life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.3'>I rejoiced for greatly, coming brethren and testifying of the in the truth, even as thou in truth walkest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.4'>Greater of these not I have joy, that I hear the my children in truth walking.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.5'>O beloved one, faithfully thou doest whatever thou mayest work for the brethren and in the strangers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.6'>these bore testimony of thee to the love in presence of congregation; whom well thou wilt do having sent forward worthily of the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.7'>On behalf for of the name they went forth, nothing receiving from the Gentiles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.8'>We therefore ought to receive the such like ones, that coworkers we may become in the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.9'>I wrote to the congregation; but the one loving to be first of them Diotrephes not receives us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.10'>On account of this, if I come, I will remember of him the works which he does, with words evil prating against us; and not being satisfied in these things, not even he receives the brethren, and those wishing he forbids, and out of the congregation he casts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.11'>O beloved one, not do thou imitate the evil thing, but the good thing. The one doing good, of the God is; the one doing evil, not has seen the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.12'>Demetrius has been testified to by all, and by herself the truth; also we and testify, and you know, that the testimony of us true is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.13'>Many things I had to write, but not I wish by means of ink and pen to thee to write;</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.14'>I hop but immediately to see thee, and mouth to mouth we will speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='3John.1.15'>Peace to thee. Salute thee the friends; do thou salute the friends by name.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>