<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='Diaglot' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='Diaglot'>
        <title>Diaglot NT - 1865</title>
        <contributor>Watch Tower Bible and Tract Society</contributor>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>
    
The Emphatic Diaglott

About=From the title page we read as follows: "The Emphatic Diaglott, containing the
original Greek text of what is commonly styled the New Testament (according to the
recension of Dr. J. J. Griesbach) with an interlineary translation, on the renderings
of eminent critics, and on the various readings of The Vatican Manuscript, No. 1209, in
the Vatican Library, together with illustrative and explanatory foot notes, and a
copious selection of references, ..., by Benjamin Wilson."

Although the translator does not claim this version to be superior to any other, he
feels that this work presents certain valuable features not found elsewhere. These are
listed in the Preface.

Careful fidelity in giving true rendering of the original text into English has been
maintained throughout. No regard whatever has been given to prevailing doctrines or
prejudices of sects, or the peculiar tenets of theologians.

Help in this work was derived from works of great and learned men. The sources include
the following: lexicons, grammars, ancient and modern versions, commentaries (critical
and explanatory), cyclopedias, and dictionaries (Bible and others). It is not presumed
that this work is free from faults and errors.

Watch Tower Bible and Tract Society (1942)

Text from http://www.biblestudentslibrary.org/ used by permission.

</description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>Diaglot</identifier>
        <source>http://users.eggconnect.net/noddy3/diaglott.pdf</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='John'>
      <chapter osisID='John.1'>
        <verse osisID='John.1.1'>In a beginning was the Word, and the Word was with the God, and a god was the Word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.2'>This was in a beginning with the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.3'>All through it was done; and without it was done not even one, that has been done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.4'>In it life was, and the life was the light of the men;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.5'>and the light in the darkness shines, and the darkness it not apprehended.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.6'>Was a man having been sent from God, a name to him John;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.7'>this came for a witness, that he might testify about the light, that all might believe through him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.8'>Not was he the light, but that he might testify about the light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.9'>Was the light the true, which enlightens every man coming into the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.10'>In the world he was, and the world through him was, and the world him not knew.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.11'>Into the own he came, and the own him not received.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.12'>As many as but received him, he gave to them authority children of God to become, to those believing into the name of him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.13'>who not from bloods, nor from a will of flesh, nor from a will of a man, but from God were begotten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.14'>And the Word flesh became, and tabernacled among us, (and we beheld the glory of him, a glory as of an onlybegotten from a father,) full of favor and truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.15'>John testifies concerning him, and cried saying: This was, of whom I said; He after me coming, before me has become; for first of me he was.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.16'>Because out of the fulness of him we all received, and favor upon favor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.17'>For the law through Moses was given; the favor and the truth through Jesus Anointed came.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.18'>God no one has seen ever; the onlybegotten son, that being in the bosom of the Father, he has made known.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.19'>And this is the testimony of the John, when sent the Jews from Jerusalem priests and levites, that they might ask him: Thou who art?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.20'>And he confessed and not denied; and confessed: That not am I the Anointed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.21'>And they asked him: What thou? Elias art thou? And he says: Not I am. The prophet art thou? And he answered: No.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.22'>They said then to him: Who art thou? that an answer we may give to those having sent us; what sayest thou about thyself?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.23'>He said: I: A voice crying in the desert; Make you straight the way of a lord, as said Esaias the prophet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.24'>And those having been sent were of the Pharisees;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.25'>and they asked him, and said to him: Why then dippest thou, if thou not art the Anointed, nor Elias, nor a prophet?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.26'>Answered then the John, saying: I dip in water; midst but of you stands, whom you not know,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.27'>he after me coming, of whom I not am worthy, that I may loose of him the strap of the sandal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.28'>These in Bethany were done beyond the Jordan, where was John dipping.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.29'>In the morrow he beholds the Jesus coming to him, and he says: Behold the lamb of the God, he taking away the sin of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.30'>This is he, about whom I said: After me comes a man, who before me has become; because first of me he was.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.31'>And I not knew him; but that he might be manifested to the Israel, because of this am come I in the water dipping.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.32'>And bore testimony John, saying: That I saw the spirit coming down like a dove out of heaven, and it abode on him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.33'>And I not knew him; but he having sent me to dip in water, he to me said: On whom thou mayest see the spirit coming down, and abiding on him, this is he dipping in spirit holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.34'>And I have seen, and have testified, that this is the son of the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.35'>The morrow again was standing the John, and of the disciples of him two.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.36'>And having looked on the Jesus walking, he says: Behold the lamb of the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.37'>And heard him the two disciples speaking, and they followed the Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.38'>Having turned and the Jesus, and seeing them following, he says to them: What seek you? They and said to him: Rabbi, (which means being interpreted, O teacher,) were dwellest thou?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.39'>He says to them: Come you and see you. They came and saw, where he dwells; and with him abode the day that. Hour it was about tenth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.40'>Was Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter, one of the two of those having heard from John, and having followed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.41'>Finds he first the brother that own Simon, and he says to him: We have found the Messiah (which is being interpreted, Anointed.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.42'>And he brought him to the Jesus. Having looked to him the Jesus said: Thou art Simon, the son of Jona; thou shalt be called Cephas; which means Peter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.43'>The morrow he desired to go forth into the Galilee; and he finds Philip, and says to him: Follow me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.44'>Was and the Philip from Bethsaida of the city of Andrew and Peter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.45'>Finds Philip the Nathanael, and says to him: Whom wrote Moses in the law, and the prophets, we have found, Jesus the son of the Joseph, that from Nazareth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.46'>And said to him Nathanael: Out of Nazareth is able any good to be? Says to him Philip: Come and see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.47'>Saw the Jesus the Nathanael coming to him, and he says concerning him: Behold indeed an Israelite, in whom guile not is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.48'>Says to him Nathanael: Whence me knowest thou? Answered Jesus and said to him: Before the thee Philip to have called, being under the figtree, I saw thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.49'>Answered Nathanael and says to him: Rabbi, thou art the son of the God, thou art the king of the Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.50'>Answered Jesus and said to him: Because I said to thee; I saw thee underneath the figtree, believest thou? greater of these thou shalt see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.1.51'>And he says to him: Indeed indeed I say to you, from now you shall see the heaven having been opened, and the messengers of the God ascending and descending on the son of the man.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.2'>
        <verse osisID='John.2.1'>And in the day the third a marriagefeast occurred in Cana of the Galilee; and was the mother of the Jesus there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.2'>Was invited and also the Jesus and the disciples of him to the marriagefeast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.3'>And having fallen short of wine, says the mother of the Jesus to him: Wine not they have.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.4'>Says to her the Jesus: What to me and to thee, O woman? Not yet has come the hour of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.5'>Says the mother of him to the servants; whatever he may say to you, do you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.6'>Were and there waterpots of stone six being placed according to the mode of cleansing of the Jews, holding each measures two or three.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.7'>Says to them the Jesus: Fill you the waterpots of water. And they filled them to top.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.8'>And he says to them: Draw you now, and carry to the ruler of the feast. And they carried.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.9'>When and tasted the ruler of the feast the water wine having become; (and not he knew whence it is; the but servants knew, those having drawn the water;) calls the bridegroom the ruler of the feast,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.10'>and says to him: Every man first the good wine places, and when they may have drunk freely, then the worse; thou has kept the good wine till now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.11'>This did the beginning of the signs the Jesus in Cana of the Galilee, and manifested the glory of himself; and believed into him the disciples of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.12'>After this he went down into Capernaum, he and the mother of him, and the brothers of him, and the disciples of him, and there remained not many days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.13'>And nigh was the passover of the Jews, and went up to Jerusalem the Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.14'>And he found in the temple those selling oxen and sheep and doves, and the moneychangers sitting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.15'>And having made a whip out of rushes, all he drove out of the temple, the and sheep and the oxen; and of the moneychangers he poured out the coin, and the tables overturned;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.16'>and to those the doves selling he said: Take these hence; not make you the house of the Father of me a house of merchandise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.17'>Remembered and the disciples of him, that having been written it is: The zeal of the house of thee will consume me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.18'>Answered then the Jews and said to him: What sign showest thou to us, that thee thou doest?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.19'>Answered the Jesus and said to them: Destroy the temple this, and in three days I will raise it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.20'>Said then the Jews: Forty and six years was being built the temple this; and thou in three days will raise it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.21'>He but spoke concerning the temple of the body of himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.22'>When therefore he was raised out of dead ones, remembered the disciples of him, that this he spoke; and they believed the writing, and the word which said the Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.23'>When and was in the Jerusalem at the passover at the feast, many believed into the name of him, beholding of him the signs which he did.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.24'>He but the Jesus not committed himself to them, because the him to know all;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.2.25'>and because not need he had, that any one should testify concerning the man; he for knew, what was in the man.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.3'>
        <verse osisID='John.3.1'>Was and a man of the Pharisees, Nicodemus a name to him, a ruler of the Jews;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.2'>this came to him by night, and said to him: Rabbi, we know that from God thou hast come a teacher; no one for these the signs is able to do, which thou doest, except may be the God with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.3'>Answered the Jesus and said to him: Indeed indeed I say to thee, if not any one may be born from above, not is able to see the kingdom of the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.4'>Says to him the Nicodemus: How is able a man to be born old being? not is able into the womb of the mother of himself a second time to enter, and to be born?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.5'>Answered Jesus: Indeed indeed I say to thee, if not any one may be born out of water and spirit, not is able to enter into the kingdom of the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.6'>That having been born out of the flesh, flesh is; and that having been born out of the spirit, a spirit is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.7'>Not thou mayest wonder, that I said to thee: Must you to be born from above.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.8'>The spirit where it wills breathes; and the sound of it thou hearest, but not thou knowest, whence it comes, and where it goes; thus is every one the having been born out of of the spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.9'>Answered Nicodemus and said to him: How is able these to be?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.10'>Answered Jesus and said to him: Thou art the teacher of the Israel, and these not thou knowest?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.11'>Indeed indeed I say to thee, that which we know we speak, and what we have seen we testify; and the testimony of us not you receive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.12'>If the things earthly I told you, and not you believed; how, I tell you the things heavenly, will you believe?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.13'>And no one has ascended into the heaven, except he out of the heaven having descended, the son of the man, the being in the heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.14'>And even as Moses raised aloft the serpent in the desert, thus to be raised it behooves the son of the man;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.15'>that every one who believing into him, not may be destroyed, but may have life agelasting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.16'>Thus for loved the God the world, so that the son of himself the onlybegotten he gave, that every one who believing into him, not may be destroyed, but may have life agelasting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.17'>Not for sent the God the son of himself into the world, that he might judge the world, but that might be saved the world through him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.18'>He believing into him, not is judged; he but not believing, already is judged, became not he has believed into the name of the onlybegotten son of the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.19'>This and is the judgment, that the light has come into the world, and loved the man rather the darkness, than the light; was for evil of them the works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.20'>Every one for the vile things doing, hates the light, and not comes to the light, that not may be detected the works of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.21'>He but doing the truth comes to the light, so that may be made manifest of him the works, that in God it is having been done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.22'>After these came the Jesus and the disciples of him into the Judean land; and there remained with them, and was dipping.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.23'>Was and also John dipping in Enon, near the Salim, because waters many was there; and they were coming, and were being dipped.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.24'>Not yet for was having been cast into the prison the John.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.25'>Occurred then a disciple of the disciples of John with a Jew about cleansing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.26'>And they came to the John, and said to him: Rabbi, who was with thee beyond the Jordan, to whom thou has testified, behold, he dips, and all come to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.27'>Answered John and said: Not is able a man to receive nothing, except it may be having been given to him from the heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.28'>Yourselves you to me bear testimony, that I said: Not am I the Anointed, but that having been sent I am in presence of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.29'>He having the bride, a bridegroom is; the but friend of the bridegroom, that standing and hearing him, with joy rejoices through the voices of the bridegroom. This therefore the joy that of me has been completed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.30'>Him it behooves to increase, me but to increase.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.31'>He from above coming, over all is. He being from the earth, from the earth is, and from the earth speaks; he from the heaven coming, over all is,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.32'>and what he has seen and heard, this he testifies; and the testimony of him no one receives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.33'>He receiving of him the testimony, has set his seal, that the God true is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.34'>Whom for has sent the God, the words of the God speaks; not for by measure gives the God the spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.35'>The Father loves the son, and all has been given in the hand of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.3.36'>He believing into the son, has life agelasting; he but disobeying the son, not shall see life, but the anger of the God abides on him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.4'>
        <verse osisID='John.4.1'>When therefore knew the Lord that heard the Pharisees, that Jesus more disciples made and dipped, than John;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.2'>(though indeed Jesus himself not dipped, but the disciples of him;)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.3'>he left the Judea, and went again into the Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.4'>It behooved and him to pass through the Samaria.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.5'>He comes therefore into a city of the Samaritans, being called Sychar, near by the field, of which gave Jacob Joseph to the son of himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.6'>Was and there a spring of the Jacob. The then Jesus having become weary from the journey, sat down thus over the spring; hour was about six.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.7'>Comes a woman of the Samaria, to draw water. Say to her the Jesus: Give to me a drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.8'>(The for disciples of him had gone into the city, that provisions they might buy.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.9'>Says then to him the woman that Samaritan: How thou, a Jew being, from me to drink askest, being a woman a Samaritan? (Not for associate with Jews Samaritans.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.10'>Answered Jesus and said to her: If thou hast known the gift of the God, and who is be saying to thee: Give to me to drink; thou wouldst ask him, and he would give thee water living.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.11'>Says to him the woman: O lord, nothing to draw with thou hast, and the well is deep; whence then hast thou the water the living?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.12'>Not thou greater art the father of us, Jacob? who gave to us the well, and he of it drank, and the sons of him, and the cattle of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.13'>Answered Jesus and said to her: All the drinking of the water this, will thirst again;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.14'>who but ever may drink of the water, of which I shall give to him, not not may thirst to the age; but the water, which I shall give him, shall be in him a well of water springing into life agelasting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.15'>Says to him the woman: O lord, give to me this the water, that not I may thirst, nor may come in this place to draw.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.16'>Says to her the Jesus: Go, call the husband of thee, and come here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.17'>Answered the woman and said: Not I have a husband. Says to her the Jesus: Rightly thou didst say: That a husband not I have.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.18'>Five for husbands thou hast had; and now whom thou hast not is of thee a husband; this truly thou hast said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.19'>Says to him the woman: O lord, I see, that a prophet art thou.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.20'>The fathers of us in the mountain this worshipped; and you say, that in Jerusalem is the place, where it is necessary to worship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.21'>Says to her the Jesus: O woman, believe thou me, that comes an hour, when neither in the mountain this, nor in Jerusalem you shall worship the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.22'>You worship what not you know; we worship what we know; because the salvation from the Jews is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.23'>But comes an hour, and now is, when the true worshippers shall worship the Father in spirit and truth; and for the Father such like seeks those worshipping him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.24'>A spirit the God; and those worshipping him, in spirit and truth it behooves to worship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.25'>Says to him the woman: I know, that Messiah comes; (the being called Anointed;) when may come he, he will relate to us all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.26'>Says to her the Jesus: I am, he talking to thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.27'>And on this came the disciples of him, and wondered, that with a woman he talked. No one nevertheless said: What seekest thou? or, why talkest thou with her?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.28'>Left therefore the bucket of herself the woman, and went into the city, and says to the men:</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.29'>Come you, see a man, who told me all what I did; not this is the Anointed?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.30'>They went out of the city, and were coming to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.31'>In and the meantime were asking him the disciples saying: Rabbi, eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.32'>He but said to them: I food have to eat, which you not know.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.33'>Said then the disciples to each other: Not any one brought to him food?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.34'>Says to them the Jesus: My food is, that I may do the will of the sending me, and may finish of him the work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.35'>Not you say, that yet four months it is, and the harvest comes? Lo, I say to you, lift up the eyes of you, and see you the fields, that white they are to harvest already.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.36'>He reaping a reward receives, and gathers fruit for life agelasting; so that both he sowing together may rejoice, and he reaping.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.37'>In for this the word is the true, that one is the sowing, and another the reaping.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.38'>I sent you to reap what you have labored; others labored, and you into the labor of them are entered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.39'>Out of and the city that many believed into him of the Samaritans, through the word of the woman, testifying: That he told me all what I did.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.40'>When therefore came to him the Samaritans, asking him to abide with them; and he abode there two days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.41'>And many more believed through the word of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.42'>To the and woman they said: That no longer through the they saying we believe; ourselves for we have heard, and we know, that this is truly the savior of the world the Anointed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.43'>After and the two days he went out thence, and went out into the Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.44'>Himself for Jesus testified, that a prophet in the own country honor not has.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.45'>When therefore he came into the Galilee, received him the Galileans, all having seen what he did in Jerusalem at the feast; also themselves for came to the feast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.46'>He came then again into the Cana of the Galilee, where he made the water wine. And was certain courtier, of whom the son was sick, in Capernaum.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.47'>This hearing that Jesus was come out of the Judea into the Galilee, went to him, and was asking him, that he would come down, and heal of him the son; he was about for to die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.48'>Said therefore the Jesus to him: If not signs and prodigies you may see, not not you may believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.49'>Says to him the courtier: O sir, come down, before to die the child of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.50'>Says to him the Jesus: Go; the son of thee lives. And believed the man the word which said to him Jesus, and went.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.51'>Already and of him was going down, the slaves of him met him, and reported, saying: That the child of thee lives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.52'>He inquired then of them the hour, in which better he was. And they said to him: That yesterday hour seventh left the fever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.53'>Knew then the father, that in that the hour, in which said to him the Jesus: That the son of thee lives. And he believed himself, and the house of him all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.4.54'>This again a second sign did the Jesus, having come out of the Judea into the Galilee.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.5'>
        <verse osisID='John.5.1'>After these things was a feast of the Jews, and went up the Jesus to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.2'>Is now in the Jerusalem, by the sheepgate, a swimming bath, that being called in Hebrew Bethesda, five porches having.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.3'>In these were lying a multitude great of those sick, blind, blame, withered waiting the of the water moving.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.4'>A messenger for at a season went down in the swimmingbath, and agitated the water; he then first stepping in after the agitation of the water, sound became, who indeed was held by disease.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.5'>Was and a certain man there, thirty and eight years being in the feeble health.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.6'>This seeing the Jesus lying, and knowing that long already time he had been, he says to him: Do thou wish sound to become?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.7'>Answered him he sick being: O sir, a man not I have, that when may be agitated the water, he may put me into the swimmingbath; in which but am coming I, another before me goes down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.8'>Says to him the Jesus: Rise, take up the bed of thee, and walk.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.9'>And immediately became sound the man, and took up the bed of himself, and walked. It was and a sabbath in that the day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.10'>Said then the Jews to the having been healed: A sabbath it is; not it is lawful for thee to carry the bed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.11'>He answered them: He having made a sound, he to me said: Take up the bed of thee, and walk.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.12'>They asked then him: Who is the man, he saying to thee: Take up the bed of thee, and walk?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.13'>He but having been cured not knew who it is; the for Jesus slipped out, a crowd being in the place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.14'>After these finds him the Jesus in the temple, and said to him: See, sound thou hast become; no longer do thou sin, that so worse to thee anything may happen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.15'>Went away the man, and told to the Jews, that Jesus it is, he having made him sound.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.16'>And through this persecuted the Jesus the Jews, because these he did in a sabbath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.17'>The and Jesus answered them: The father of me till now works, and I work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.18'>Through this therefore more sought him the Jews to kill, because not only he was breaking the sabbath, but also a Father his own said the God, equal himself making to the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.19'>Answered then the Jesus and said to them: Indeed indeed I say to you, not is able the son to do of himself nothing, if not anything he may see the Father doing; what for ever he may do, these also the son in like manner does.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.20'>The for Father loves the son, and all shows to him, what he does; and greater of these shows to him works, so that you may wonder.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.21'>As for the Father raises the dead ones and makes alive; thus also the son, whom he will, makes alive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.22'>Not even for the Father judges any one; but the judgment all has given to the son;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.23'>so that all may honor the son, even as they honor the Father. He not honoring the son, not honors the Father, that having sent him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.24'>Indeed indeed I say to you, that he the word of me hearing, and believing, the having sent me has life agelasting, and into judgment not comes, but has passed out of the death into the life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.25'>Indeed indeed I say to you, that comes an hour, and now is, when the dead ones shall hear the voice of the son of the God; and those having heard will live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.26'>As for the Father has life in himself; so he gave also the son life to have in himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.27'>And authority he gave to him also judgment to execute, because a son of man he is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.28'>Not wonder you this; because comes an hour, in which all those in the tombs, shall hear the voice of him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.29'>and shall come forth, those the good things having done, to a resurrection of life; those and the evil things having done, to a resurrection of judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.30'>Not am able I to do of myself nothing. Even as I hear, I judge, and the judgment the mine just is; that not I seek the will the mine, but the will of the sending me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.31'>If I testify concerning myself, the testimony of me out not is true.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.32'>Another is he testifying concerning me; and I know, that rue is the testimony, which he testifies concerning me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.33'>You have sent to John, and he has testified to the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.34'>I but not from a man the testimony receive; but these things I say, that you may be saved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.35'>He was the lamp the burning and shinning; you and were willing to rejoice for an hour in the light of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.36'>I but have the testimony greater of the John; the for works, which gave to me the Father, that I might finish them, these the works, which I do, testifies concerning me, because the Father me has sent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.37'>And he having sent me Father himself has testified concerning me. Neither a voice of him have you heard at any time, nor form of him have you seen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.38'>And the word of him not you have abiding in you; because whom sent he, this you not believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.39'>You search the writings, because you think in them life agelasting to have; and they are those testifying concerning me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.40'>and not you are willing to come to me, so that life you may have.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.41'>Glory from men not I receive;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.42'>but I have known you, that the love of the God not you have in yourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.43'>I have come in the name of the Father of me, and not you receive me; if another should come in the name the own, him you will receive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.44'>How are able you to believe, glory from one another receiving, and the glory that from the only God not you seek?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.45'>Not think you, that I will accuse you to the Father; is he accusing you, Moses, into whom you have hoped.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.46'>If for you believe Moses, you would believe me; concerning for me he wrote.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.5.47'>If but the of him writings not you believe, how the my words will you believe.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.6'>
        <verse osisID='John.6.1'>After these things went the Jesus over the sea that of Galilee, of the Tiberias.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.2'>And was following him a crowd great, because they saw the signs, which he was doing on those being sick.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.3'>Went and into the mountain the Jesus, and there he was sitting with the disciples of himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.4'>Was and near the passover, the feast of the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.5'>Lifted up then the Jesus the eyes, and seeing that great a crowd was coming to him, says to the Philip: Whence shall we buy loaves, that may eat these?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.6'>(This but he said trying him; he for knew, what he was about to do.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.7'>Answered him Philip: Two hundred denarii of loaves not are enough for them, so that each of them a little may take.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.8'>Says to him one of the disciples of him, Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter:</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.9'>Is little boy one here, who has five loaves barley, and two small fishes; but these what are for so many?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.10'>Said and the Jesus: Make you the men to recline. Was and grass much in the place. Reclined therefore the men the number about five thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.11'>Took and the loaves the Jesus, and having thanks distributed to the disciples, the and disciples to those reclining; in like manner also of the fishes what they wished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.12'>When and they were filled, he says to the disciples of himself: Collect the remaining fragments, so that not any may be lost.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.13'>They collected therefore, and filled twelve baskets of fragments, out of the five loaves of the barley, which remained to those having eaten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.14'>The therefore men seeing what did a sign the Jesus, said: That this is truly the prophet, he coming into the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.15'>Jesus therefore knowing that they were about to come, and to seize him, that they might make him a king, retired again into the mountain himself alone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.16'>As and evening it became, went down the disciples of him on the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.17'>And stepping into the ship, they were going over the sea to Capernaum. And dark now it had become, and not had come to them the Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.18'>The and sea, a wind great blowing was becoming agitated.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.19'>Having driven therefore about furlongs twentyfive or thirty, they see the Jesus walking on the sea, and near the ship was coming; and they were afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.20'>He but says to them: I am, not fear you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.21'>They were willing therefore to receive him into the ship; and immediately the ship was at the land, to which they were going.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.22'>The next day the crowd, that standing over the sea, seeing, that boat other not was there, if not one, and that not went with the disciples of himself the Jesus into the boat, but alone the disciples of him went away;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.23'>(other but came boats from Tiberias near the place, where they ate the bread, having given thanks the Lord;)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.24'>when therefore saw the crowd, that Jesus not is there, nor the disciples of him, they entered themselves into the boats, and came to Capernaum, seeking the Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.25'>And finding him beyond the sea, they said to him: Rabbi, when here didst thou come?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.26'>Answered them the Jesus and said: Indeed indeed I say to you: You seek me, not because you saw signs, but because you ate of the loaves, and were filled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.27'>Work you not the food that perishing, but the food that abiding into life agelasting, which the son of the man to you will give; him for the Father sealed the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.28'>Said therefore to him: What shall we do, that we may work the works of the God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.29'>Answered the Jesus and said to them: This is the work of the God, that you may believe into whom sent he.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.30'>They said therefore to him: What then doest thou sign, that we may see and we may believe thee? what doest thou work?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.31'>The fathers of us the manna ate in the desert, as it is having been written: Bread from the heaven gave them to eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.32'>Said therefore to them the Jesus: Indeed indeed I say to you, not Moses has given to you the bread from the heaven; but the Father of me gives to you the bread from the heaven the true.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.33'>The for bread of the God is he coming down from the heaven, and life is giving to the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.34'>They said then to him: O sir, always give to us the bread this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.35'>Said but to them the Jesus: I am the bread of the life; he coming to me, not not may hunger; and he believing into me, not not may thirst ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.36'>But I said to you, that even you have seen me, and not you believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.37'>All what gives to me the Father, to me will come; and the coming to me, not not I will cast out;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.38'>because I have come down from heaven, not that I may do the will the mine, but the will of having sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.39'>This and is the will of the having sent me, that every which he has given to me, not I may lose out of it, but raise up it in the last day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.40'>This for is the will of the having sent me, that all who seeing the son, and believing into him, may have life agelasting; and will raise him I in the last day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.41'>Were murmuring then the Jews about him, because he said: I am the bread that having come down from the heaven;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.42'>and they said: Not this is Jesus the son of Joseph, of whom we know the father and the mother? How then he says this: That from the heaven I have come down?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.43'>Answered the Jesus and said to them: Not murmur you with one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.44'>No one is able to come to me, if not the Father, that having sent me, may draw him, and I will raise up him in the last day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.45'>It is having been written in the prophets: And they shall be all taught of God. Every one who having heard from the Father and having learned, comes to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.46'>Not that the Father any one has seen, if not he being from the God; this has seen the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.47'>Indeed indeed I say to you, he believing into me, has life agelasting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.48'>I am the bread of the life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.49'>The fathers of you ate the manna in the desert, and died:</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.50'>This is is the bread, that from the heaven coming down, so that any one of it may eat, and not may die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.51'>I am the bread that living, that from the heaven having come down; if any one may eat of this the bread, he shall live into the age. And the bread also, which I will give, the flesh of me is, which I will give in behalf of the world life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.52'>Were contending therefore with one another the Jews, saying: How is able this to us to give the flesh to eat?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.53'>Said them to them the Jesus: Indeed indeed I say to you, if not you may eat the flesh of the son of the man, and you may drink of him the blood, not have life in yourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.54'>He eating of me the flesh, and drinking of me the blood, has life agelasting; and I will raise up him in the last day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.55'>The for flesh of me truly is food, and the blood of me truly is drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.56'>He eating of me the flesh, and drinking of me the blood, in me abides, and I in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.57'>As sent me the living Father, and I live through the Father; also he eating me, even he shall live through me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.58'>This is the bread, that from the heaven having come down; not as ate the fathers of you, and died; he eating this the bread, shall live into the age.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.59'>These things he said in a synagogue teaching in Capernaum.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.60'>Many therefore having heard of the disciples of him, said: Hard is this the saying; who is able it to hear?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.61'>Knowing but the Jesus in himself, that were murmuring about this the disciples of himself, he said to them: This you offends?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.62'>If then you should see the son of the man ascending, where he was the first?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.63'>The spirit is that making alive; the flesh not profits nothing. The words, which I speak to you, spirit is and life is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.64'>But are of you some, who not believe; knew for from beginning the Jesus, some are who not believing, and who is he about betraying him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.65'>And he said: Through this I have said to you that no one is able to come to me, if not may be having been given to him from the Father of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.66'>From this many went the disciples of him into the things behind; and no longer with him were walking.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.67'>Said therefore the Jesus to the twelve: Not and you wish to go?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.68'>Answered him Simon Peter: O lord, to whom shall we go? words of life agelasting thou hast;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.69'>and we have believed and have known, that thou art the holy one of the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.70'>Answered them the Jesus: Not I you the twelve choose? and of you one an accuser is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.6.71'>He spoke now the Judas of Simon Iscariot; this for was about him to deliver up, one being of the twelve.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.7'>
        <verse osisID='John.7.1'>And was walking the Jesus after these things in the Galilee; not for he wished in the Judea to walk, because were seeking him the Jews to kill.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.2'>Was and near the feast of the Jews, the feast of tabernacles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.3'>Said therefore to him the brothers of him: Depart hence, and go into the Judea, so that also the disciples of thee may see the works of thee, which thou doest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.4'>No one for in secret anything does, and he seeks himself in public to be. If these things thou doest, manifest thyself to the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.5'>Not even for the brothers of him believed into him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.6'>Says then to them the Jesus: The season the mine not yet is present; the but season the yours always is ready.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.7'>Not is able the world to hate you; me but it hates, because I testify concerning it, that the works of it evil is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.8'>You go up to the feast this; I not go up to the feast this, because the season the mine not yet has fully come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.9'>These things saying to them, he remained in the Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.10'>When but had gone up the brothers of him, then also he went up to the feast, not openly, but as in secret.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.11'>The then Jews sought him in the feast, and said: Where is he?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.12'>And murmuring much about him was among the crowds. The some said: That good he is; other said: No; but he deceives the crowd.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.13'>No one however with freedom spoke about him, because of the fear of the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.14'>Now and of the feast being half out, went up the Jesus into the temple, and taught.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.15'>And wondered the Jews, saying: How this letters knows, not having learned?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.16'>Answered them the Jesus and said: The my teaching not is mine, but of the sending me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.17'>If any one may wish the will of him to do, he shall know concerning the teaching, whether from the God it is, or I from myself speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.18'>He from himself speaking, the glory the own seeks; he but seeking the glory of the sending him, this true is, and unrighteousness in him not is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.19'>Not Moses has given to you the law? and no one of you does the law; why me do you seek to kill?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.20'>Answered the crowd and said: A demon thou hast; who thee seeks to kill?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.21'>Answered the Jesus and said to them: One work I did, and all you wonder because of this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.22'>Moses has given to you the circumcision; (not that of the Moses it is, but of the fathers,) and in a sabbath you circumcise a man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.23'>If circumcision receives a man in a sabbath, that not may be loosed the law of Moses, with me are you angry, because whole a man sound I made in a sabbath?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.24'>Not judge you according to appearance, but the righteous judgment judge you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.25'>Said then some of the Jerusalemites: Not this is he, whom they seek to kill?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.26'>and lo, boldly he is talking, and nothing to him they say; not truly did know the rulers, that this is the Anointed?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.27'>But this we know, whence he is; the but Anointed when he comes, no one knows, whence he is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.28'>Cried then in the temple teaching the Jesus, and saying: And me you know, and you know whence I am; and of myself not I have come, but is true he having sent me, whom you not know.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.29'>I know him, because from him I am, and he me sent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.30'>They sought therefore him to seize; and no one put on him the hands, because not yet had come the hour of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.31'>Many and out of the crowd believed into him, and said: That the Anointed when he may come, not more signs of these will do, which he did?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.32'>Heard the Pharisees of the crowd murmuring about him these things; and sent the Pharisees and the highpriests officers, that they might seize him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.33'>Said then the Jesus: Yet a little time with you I am, and I go to the sending me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.34'>You will seek me, and not will find; and where I am I you not are able to come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.35'>Said therefore the Jews to themselves: Where this he is about to go, that we not shall find him? not into the dispersion of the Greeks is about to go, and to teach the Greeks?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.36'>What is this the word, which he said: You will seek me, and not you will find; and whence am I you not are able to come?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.37'>In and the last day the great of the feast stood the Jesus, and cried, saying: If any one may thirst, let him come to me, and let him drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.38'>He believing into me, as said the scripture, rivers out of the belly of him shall flow of water living.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.39'>This but said concerning the spirit, of which was about to receive the believing into him; not yet for was spirit holy, because the Jesus not yet was glorified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.40'>Many therefore out of the crowd having heard the word, said: This is truly the prophet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.41'>Others said: This is the Anointed. Others but said: Not for out of the Galilee the Anointed comes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.42'>Not the writing said, that of the seed of David, and from Bethlehem the village, where was David, the Anointed comes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.43'>And division then in the crowd occurred through him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.44'>Some and wished of them to seize him; but no one put on him the hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.45'>Came therefore the officers to the highpriests and Pharisees. And said to them these: Why not did you bring him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.46'>Answered the officers: Never thus spoke a man, as this the man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.47'>Answered then them the Pharisees: Not also you have been deceived?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.48'>not any one of the rulers believed into him, or of the Pharisees?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.49'>but the crowd this the not knowing the law; accursed are.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.50'>Says Nicodemus to them, he coming of night to him, one being of them:</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.51'>Not the law of us judges the man, if not it may hear from him first, and may know what he does?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.52'>They answered and said to him: Not also thou of the Galilee art? search and see, that a prophet out of the Galilee not has been raised.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.7.53'>And went every one into the house of himself.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.8'>
        <verse osisID='John.8.1'>Jesus but went into the mountain of the olivetrees;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.2'>early morn and again he came into the temple, and all the people came to him; and having sat down he taught them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.3'>Bring and the scribes and the Pharisees to him a woman in adultery having been taken, and placing her in middle,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.4'>they say to him: O teacher, this the woman was taken in the very act committing adultery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.5'>In now the law Moses to us commanded the such like to be stoned? thou therefore what sayest thou?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.6'>This but they said tempting him, that they might have to accuse him. The but Jesus down stooping, with the finger wrote on the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.7'>When but they continued asking him, having raised up he said to them: He without sin of you, first the stone on her let him cast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.8'>And again down stooping, wrote on the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.9'>They and having heard, and by the conscience being convinced, went out one by one, beginning from the elders even to the last ones; and left alone the Jesus, and the woman in middle standing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.10'>Having raised up and the Jesus, and no one seeing but the woman, said to her: The woman, where are those the accusers of thee? no one thee condemned?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.11'>She and said: No one, O lord. Said and to her the Jesus: Neither I thee condemn; go, and no longer do thou sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.12'>Again therefore the Jesus to them spoke, saying: I am the light of the world; he following me, not not shall walk in the darkness, but shall have the light of the life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.13'>Said therefore to him the Pharisees: Thou concerning thyself dost testify; the testimony of thee not is true.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.14'>Answered Jesus and said to them: Even if I testify concerning myself, true is the testimony of me; because I know, whence I came, and where I go; you but not know, whence I came, or where I go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.15'>You according to the flesh judge, I not judge no one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.16'>Even if judge but I, the judgment the my true is; because alone not I am, but I and the having sent me Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.17'>Also in the law and the your it has been written: That two of men the testimony true is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.18'>I am he testifying concerning myself, and testifies concerning me the having sent me Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.19'>They said then to him: Where is the father of thee? Answered Jesus: Neither me you know, nor the Father of me. If me you knew, also the Father of me you would know.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.20'>These the words he spoke in the treasury, teaching in the temple; and no one seized him, because not yet had come the hour of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.21'>Said therefore again to them the Jesus: I go away, and you will seek me, and in the sin of you you will die; where I go, you not are able to come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.22'>Said then the Jews: Not will he kill himself, because he says: Where I go, you not are able to come?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.23'>And he said to them: You from the beneath are, I from the above am; you from the world this are, I not am from the world this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.24'>I said therefore to you, that you will die in the sins of you; if for not you may believe, that I am, you will die in the sins of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.25'>They said therefore to him: Thou who art? And said to them the Jesus: The beginning what, what even I say to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.26'>Many things I have about you to say, and to judge; but he having sent me true is; and I what I heard from him, these things I say to the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.27'>Not they knew, that the Father to them he spoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.28'>Said then to them the Jesus: When you may left up the son of the man, then you will know that I am; and from myself I do nothing, but as taught me the Father of me these things I say;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.29'>and he having sent me, with me is; not left me alone the Father, because I the things pleasing to him do always.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.30'>These of him speaking, many believed into him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.31'>Said then the Jesus to those having believed him Jews: If you may abide in the word the my, truly disciples of me you are,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.32'>and you shall know the truth, and the truth shall make free you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.33'>They answered him: Seed of Abraham we are, and to no one have we been slaves at any time; how thou sayest: That free you shall become?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.34'>Answered them the Jesus: Indeed indeed I say to you, that every one who is doing the sin, a slave is of the sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.35'>The but slave not abides in the house to the age; the son abides to the age.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.36'>If then the son you may make free, really free you shall be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.37'>I know, that seed of Abraham you are; but you seek me to kill, because the word the mine not has place in you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.38'>I what have seen from the Father of me, I speak; and you therefore what you have seen from the father of you, do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.39'>They answered and said to him: The father of us Abraham is. Says to them the Jesus: If children of the Abraham you are, the works of the Abraham you would do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.40'>Now but you seek me to kill, a man, who the truth to you has spoken, which I have heard from the God; this Abraham not did. You do the works of the father of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.41'>They said then to him: We from fornication not have been born; one father we have, the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.42'>Said to them the Jesus: If the God a father of you was, you would love me; I for from the God came out and am come; not even for of myself I have come, but he me sent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.43'>Why the speech the mine not know you? Because not you are able to hear the word the mine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.44'>You from the father the accuser are, and the lusts of the father of you you wish to do. He a manslayer was from a beginning, and in the truth not has stood; because not is truth in him. When may speak the falsehood, from the own he speaks; because a liar is, also the father of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.45'>I but because the truth I speak, not you believe me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.46'>Who of you convicts me concerning sin? If truth I speak, why you not believe me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.47'>He being from the God, the words of the God hears; through this you not hear, because from the God not you are.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.48'>Answered the Jews and said to him: Not well say we, that a Samaritan art thou, and a demon thou hast?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.49'>Answered Jesus: I a demon not have, but I honor the Father of me, and you dishonor me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.50'>I but not seek the glory of me; it is he seeking and judging.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.51'>Indeed indeed I say to you, if any one the word the mine may keep, death not not he may see to the age.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.52'>Said then to him the Jews: Now we know, that a demon thou hast; Abraham died and the prophets, and thou sayest: If any one the word of me may keep, not not may taste of death to the age.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.53'>Not thou greater art of the father of us Abraham, who died? and the prophets died; whom thyself makest thou?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.54'>Answered Jesus: If I glorify myself, the glory of me nothing is. He is the Father of me he glorifying me, whom you say, that a God of you he is,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.55'>and not you know him; I but know him. And if I say, that not I know him, I shall be like you, a liar. But I know him, and the word of him I keep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.56'>Abraham the father of you ardently desired, that he might see the day the my; and he saw, and was glad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.57'>Said then the Jews to him: Fifty years not yet thou art, and Abraham hast thou seen?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.58'>Said to them the Jesus: Indeed indeed I say to you, before Abraham to have been born, I am.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.8.59'>They took up therefore stones, that they might cast on him; Jesus but hid himself, and went out of the temple.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.9'>
        <verse osisID='John.9.1'>And passing by, he saw a man blind from birth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.2'>And asked him the disciples of him, saying: Rabbi, who sinned? this, or the parents of him, that blind he should be born?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.3'>Answered Jesus: Neither this sinned, nor the parents of him; but that may be manifested the works of the God in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.4'>Me it behooves to work the works of the sending me, while day it is; comes night, when no one is able to work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.5'>While in the world I may be, light I am of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.6'>These things saying, he spit on the ground, and made clay of the spittle, and rubbed the clay on the eyes of the blind,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.7'>and said to him: Go, wash thyself in the pool of the Siloam; (which is interpreted, having been sent.) He went away therefore, and washed himself, and came seeing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.8'>The then neighbors, and those seeing him the before, because a beggar he was, said: Not this is he sitting and begging?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.9'>Others said: That this is. Others but: That like him it is. He said: That I am.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.10'>They said then to him: How were opened of thee the eyes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.11'>Answered he and said: A man, being named Jesus, clay made, and rubbed of me the eyes, and said to me: Go into the Siloam, and wash thyself. Going and and washing myself, I obtained sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.12'>They said then to him: Where is he? He says: Not I know.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.13'>They bring him to the Pharisees, that once blind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.14'>It was and a sabbath, when the clay made the Jesus, and opened of him the eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.15'>Again therefore asked him also the Pharisees, how he obtained sight. He and said to them: Clay he put of me on the eyes, and I washed myself, and see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.16'>Said therefore of the Pharisees some: This the man not is from the God, because the sabbath not he keeps. Others said: How is able a man a sinner such signs to do? And a division was among them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.17'>They say to the blind again: Thou what sayest concerning him, seeing that he opened of thee the eyes? He and said: That a prophet he is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.18'>Not believed therefore the Jews concerning him, that blind he was, and obtained sight, till when they called the parents of him the having obtained sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.19'>And they asked them, saying: This is the son of you, whom you say, that blind he was born? how then now he sees?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.20'>Answered them the parents of him and said: We know, that this is the son of us, and that blind he was born;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.21'>how but now he sees, not we know; or who opened of him the eyes, we not know, he full age has, him ask you; he concerning himself shall speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.22'>These things said the parents of him, because they feared the Jews. Already for had agreed the Jews, that if any one him should confess Anointed, from a synagogue should be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.23'>Through this the parents of him said: That full age he has, him ask you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.24'>They called therefore a second time the man, who was blind, and said to him: Give glory to the God; we know, that the man this a sinner is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.25'>Answered then he and said: If a sinner he is, not I know; one I know, that blind being, now I see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.26'>They said and to him again: What did he to thee? how opened of thee the eyes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.27'>He answered them: I said to you already, and not you did hear; why again do you wish to hear? not also you wish of him disciples to be?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.28'>They reviled him, and said: Thou art a disciple of him; we but of the Moses are disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.29'>We know, that to Moses has spoken the God; this but not we know whence is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.30'>Answered the man and said to them: In for this a wonder is, that you not know whence he is, and he has opened of me the eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.31'>We know but, that sinners the God not hears; but if any one a worshipper of God may be, and the will him may do, this he hears.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.32'>From the age not it was heard, that opened any one eyes of blind having been born.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.33'>If not was this from God, not were able to do nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.34'>They answered and said to him: In sins thou wast born wholly; and thou teachest us? And they cast him out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.35'>Heard the Jesus, that they cast him out; and having found him, said to him: Thou believest into the son of the God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.36'>Answered he and said: And who is he, O sir, that I may believe into him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.37'>Said and to him the Jesus: Even thou hast seen him, and he talking with thee, he is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.38'>He and said: I believe, O sir; and he prostrated to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.39'>And said the Jesus: For judgment I into the world this came, that those not seeing might see, and those seeing blind might become.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.40'>And heard of the Pharisees these things those being with him, and said to him: Not also we blind are?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.9.41'>Said to them the Jesus: If blind you were, not you would have sin; now but you say: That we see; the therefore sin of you remains.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.10'>
        <verse osisID='John.10.1'>Indeed indeed I say to you, he not entering through the door into the fold of the sheep, but going up another way, he a thief is and a robber;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.2'>he but entering through the door, a shepherd is of the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.3'>To him the doorkeeper opens; and the sheep the voice of him hears; and the own sheep he calls by name, and he leads out them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.4'>And when the own sheep he puts forth, before them he goes; and the sheep him follows, because they know the voice of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.5'>A stranger but not not they may follow, but will flee from him; because not they know of the strangers the voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.6'>This the parable said to them the Jesus; they but not knew, what was, which he spoke to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.7'>Said then again to them the Jesus: Indeed indeed I say to you, that I am the door of the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.8'>All as many as came before me, thieves are and robbers; but not heard them the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.9'>I am the door; through me if any one may come in, he shall be saved, and shall come in and go out, and pasture shall find.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.10'>The thief not come, if not that he may steal and may kill, and may destroy; I come, that life they may have, and abundance may have.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.11'>I am the shepherd the good; the shepherd the good the life of himself lays down in behalf of the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.12'>The hireling but, and not being a shepherd, of whom not are the sheep own, see the wolf coming, and leaves the sheep, and flees; and the wolf seizes them, and scatters the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.13'>The but hireling flees, because an hireling he is, and not it concerns him about the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.14'>I am the shepherd the good; and know the mine, and am known by the mine,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.15'>as knows me the Father, and I know the Father; and the life of me I lay down in behalf of the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.16'>And other sheep I have, which not is of the fold this; also them me it behooves to lead; and the voice of me they will hear, and there will be one flock, one shepherd.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.17'>Through this the Father me loves, because I lay down the life of me, that again I may receive her;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.18'>no one takes her from me, but I lay down her of myself; authority I have to lay down her, and authority I have again to receive her; this the command I received from the Father of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.19'>A division then again occurred among the Jews through the words these.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.20'>Said and many of them: A demon he has, and is mad; why him hear you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.21'>Others said: These the words not are of one being demonized; not a demon is able blind eyes to open?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.22'>Occurred now the feast of dedication in the Jerusalem, and winter it was;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.23'>and was walking the Jesus in the temple, in the porch of Solomon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.24'>Surrounded therefore him the Jews, and said to him: Till when the life of us dost thou take? If thou art the Anointed, tell us plainly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.25'>Answered them the Jesus: I told you, and not you believe. The works, which I do in the name of the Father of me these testify concerning me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.26'>But you not believe; not for you are of the sheep the mine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.27'>As I said to you, the sheep the mine the voice of me hears, and I know them, and they follow me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.28'>and I life agelasting give to them, and not not they will perish into the age, and not will wrest any one them out of the hand of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.29'>The father of me, who has given to me, greater of all is; and no one is able to wrest out of the hand of the Father of me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.30'>I and the Father one are.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.31'>Took up then again stones the Jews, that they might stone him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.32'>Answered them the Jesus: Many good works I showed you from the Father of me; because of which of them work do you stone me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.33'>Answered him the Jews saying: Concerning a good work not we stone thee, but concerning blasphemy, and that thou, a man being, makest thyself a god.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.34'>Answered them the Jesus: Not is it having been written in the law of you: I said, gods you are?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.35'>If them he called gods, to whom the word of the God came, and not is able to be broken the writing;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.36'>whom the Father set apart, and sent into the world, you say: That thou blasphemest, because I said, A son of the God I am?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.37'>If not I do the works of the Father of me, not you believe me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.38'>If but I do, and if me not you believe, the works believe you; that you may know and you may believe, that in me the Father, and I in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.39'>They sought therefore again him to seize; and he went forth out of the hand of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.40'>And he went again beyond the Jordan, to the place where was John the first dipping; and abode there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.41'>And many came to him, and said: That John indeed a sign did not one; all but what things said John concerning this, true was.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.10.42'>And believed many there into him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.11'>
        <verse osisID='John.11.1'>Was and certain sick one, Lazarus, from Bethany, out of the village of Mary and Martha the sister of her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.2'>(Was and Mary the having anointed the Lord with balsam, and wiped the feet of him with the hairs of herself; of whom the brother Lazarus was stick.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.3'>Sent therefore the sisters to him, saying: O lord, lo, whom thou lovest is sick.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.4'>Having heard and the Jesus said: This the sickness not is to death, but on account of the glory of the God, that may be glorified the son of the God through her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.5'>Loved now the Jesus the Martha, and the sister of her, and the Lazarus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.6'>When then he heard, that he was sick, then indeed he abode in which he was place two days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.7'>Then after this he says to the disciples: Let us go into the Judea again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.8'>Say to him the disciples: Rabbi, now sought thee to stone the Jews, and again goest thou there?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.9'>Answered Jesus: Not twelve are hours of the day? If any one may walk in the day, not he stumbles, because the light of the world this he sees.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.10'>If but any one may walk in the night, he stumbles, because the light not is in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.11'>These things he said; and after this he says to them: Lazarus the friend of us is fallen asleep; but I go, that I may awake him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.12'>Said then the disciples of him: O lord, if he is fallen asleep, he shall be saved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.13'>Had spoken but the Jesus about the death of him; they but thought, that concerning the repose of the sleep he speaks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.14'>Then therefore said to them the Jesus plainly: Lazarus died;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.15'>and I rejoice because of you, that you may believe, that not I was there; but we may go to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.16'>Said then Thomas, that being called a twin, to the fellowdisciples: May go also we, that we may die with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.17'>Coming therefore the Jesus found him four days already been in the tomb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.18'>Was now the Bethany near the Jerusalem, about from furlongs fifteen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.19'>And many of the Jews had come to those about Martha and Mary, that they might comfort them concerning the brother of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.20'>The then Martha when she heard, that Jesus was coming, met him; Mary but in the house was sitting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.21'>Said then the Martha to the Jesus: O lord, if thou hadst been here, the brother of me not would have died;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.22'>but and now I know, that whatever things thou mayest ask the God, will give to thee the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.23'>Says of her the Jesus: Will rise again the brother of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.24'>Says to him Martha: I know, that he will rise again, in the resurrection in the last day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.25'>Said to her the Jesus: I am the resurrection and the life; he believing into me, even if he may die, he shall live;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.26'>and all the living and believing into me, not not may die into the age. Believest thou this?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.27'>She says to him: Yes, O lord, I have believed, that thou art the Anointed, the son of the God, he into the world coming.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.28'>And these things saying, she went, and called Mary the sister of her privately, saying: The teacher is present, and calls thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.29'>She when she heard, rises up quickly, and comes to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.30'>(Not yet now had come the Jesus into the village; but was in the place, where met him the Martha.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.31'>The therefore Jews, those being with her in the house and were comforting her, seeing the Mary, that quickly she rose up and went out, followed her, saying: That she goes into the tomb, that she may weep there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.32'>The therefore Mary when came where was the Jesus, seeing him, she fell of him to the feet, saying to him: O lord, if thou hadst been there, not would have died of me the brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.33'>Jesus therefore when he saw her weeping, and those having come with her Jews weeping, he was agitated in the spirit, and troubled himself,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.34'>and said: Where have you laid him? They say to him: O lord, come, and see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.35'>Wept the Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.36'>Said then the Jews: See, how he loved him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.37'>Some but of them said: Not was able this, he having opened the eyes of the blind to have caused, that even this not should die?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.38'>Jesus therefore again being agitated in himself, comes to the tomb. It was now a cave, and a stone was lying on it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.39'>Says the Jesus: Take away the stone. Says to him the sister of the having died, Martha: O lord, now he smelling; fourth day for it is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.40'>Says to her the Jesus: Not I said to thee, that if thou wouldst believe, thou shalt see the glory of the God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.41'>They took away then the stone. The but Jesus lifted up the eyes above, and said: O Father, I give thanks to thee, that thou didst hear me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.42'>I and knew, that always me thou hearest; but on account of the crowd that standing I spoke, so that they may believe, that thou me has sent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.43'>And these things saying, with a voice loud he cried out: O Lazarus, come out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.44'>Came out he having been dead, having been bound the feet and the hands with bandages, and the face of him with a napkin bound about. Says to them the Jesus: Loose you him, and allow to go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.45'>Many therefore of the Jews, those having come to the Mary, and having gazed upon what he did, believed into him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.46'>Some but of them went to the Pharisees, and told them what did the Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.47'>Assembled then the highpriests and the Pharisees a high council, and said: What are we doing? because this the man many signs does.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.48'>If we allow him thus, all will believe into him; and will come the Romans, and will take away of us both the place and the nation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.49'>One and a certain of them, Caiaphas, highpriest being of the year that, said to them: You not know nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.50'>Neither do you consider, that it is better for us, that one man should die in behalf of the people, and not whole the nation should perish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.51'>This but from himself not he said; but highpriest being of the year that, he prophesied, that was about Jesus to die in behalf of the nation;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.52'>and not in behalf of the nation alone, but that also the children of the God those having been scattered he should gather into one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.53'>From that therefore the day they took counsel together, that they might kill him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.54'>Jesus therefore no longer publicly walked among the Jews, but went away thence into the country near the desert, into Ephraim being called a city; and there remained with the disciples of himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.55'>Was and near the passover the Jews; and went up many into Jerusalem out of the country before the passover, that they might purify themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.56'>They sought then the Jesus, and said with each other in the temple standing: What think you? that not not he may come to the feast?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.11.57'>Had given now both the highpriests and the Pharisees a commandment, that if any one should know where he is, he should show, how they might seize him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.12'>
        <verse osisID='John.12.1'>The therefore Jesus before six days the passover came into Bethany, where was Lazarus he having been dead, whom he raised out of dead ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.2'>They made therefore him a supper there, and the Martha served; the but Lazarus one was of those reclining with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.3'>The then Mary having taken a pound of balsam of spikenard genuine of great price, anointed the feet of the Jesus, and wiped with the hairs of herself the feet of him; the and house was filled with the odor of the balsam.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.4'>Says therefore one of the disciples of him, Judas of Simon Iscariot, he being about him to deliver up:</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.5'>Why this the balsam not sold three hundred denarii, and given to poor ones?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.6'>He said now this, not because about the poor it concerned him, but because a thief he was, and the box he had, and the things being put in he carried off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.7'>Said therefore the Jesus: Let alone her; for the day of the embalming of me she has kept it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.8'>The poor for always you have with yourselves, me but not always you have.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.9'>Knew therefore a crowd great of the Jews, that there he is; and they came not on account of the Jesus alone; but that also the Lazarus they might see, whom he raised out of dead ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.10'>Took counsel but the highpriests, that also the Lazarus they might kill;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.11'>because many on account of him went away of the Jews, and believed into the Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.12'>On the morrow a crowd great, who having come to the feast, having heard, that was coming Jesus into Jerusalem,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.13'>they took the branches of the palmtrees, and went out to a meeting with him, and cried out: Hosanna, worthy of blessing he coming in name of Lord, the king of the Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.14'>Finding and the Jesus a young ass, he sat on it, as it is having been written:</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.15'>Not fear, O daughter of Sion; lo, the king of thee comes sitting on a foal of an ass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.16'>These things now not knew the disciples of him the first; but when was glorified the Jesus, then they remembered, that these things was about him having been written, and these things they did to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.17'>Testified then the crowd, that being with him, that the Lazarus he called out of the tomb, and raised him out of dead ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.18'>On account of this also met him the crowd, because they heard this him to have done the sign.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.19'>The then Pharisees said to themselves: You see that not you gain nothing; see, the world after him is going away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.20'>Were and some Greeks of those going up, that they might worship in the feast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.21'>These therefore came to Philip, that from Bethsaida of the Galilee, and were asking him, saying: O sir, we wish the Jesus to see.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.22'>Come Philip, and says to the Andrew; and again Andrew and Philip say to the Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.23'>The but Jesus answered them, saying: Has come the hour, that may be glorified the son of the man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.24'>Indeed indeed I say to you, if not the grain of the wheat falling into the ground should die, he alone abides; if but it may die, much fruit it bears.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.25'>He loving the life of himself, shall lose her; and he hating the life of himself in the world this, into life agelasting shall keep her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.26'>If me may serve any one, me let him follow; and where am I, there also the servant the mine shall be; if any one me may serve, will honor him the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.27'>Now the soul of me is troubled; and what shall I say? O Father, save me from the hour this? But on account of this I came to the hour this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.28'>O Father, glorify of thee the name. Came then a voice out of the heaven: Both I glorified, and again will glorify.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.29'>The therefore crowd that standing and hearing, said thunder to have been. Others said: A messenger to him has spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.30'>Answered the Jesus and said: Not on account of me this the voice had come, but on account of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.31'>Now a judgment is the world this; now the ruler of the world this, will be cast out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.32'>And if I should be lifted up from the earth, all will draw to myself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.33'>This but he said, signifying by what death he was about to die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.34'>Answered him the crowd: We heard out of the law, that the Anointed abides into the age; and how thou sayest, that it behooves to be lifted up the son of the man? who is this the son of the man?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.35'>Said then to them the Jesus: Yet a little time the light among you is. Walk you, while the light you have, that not darkness you may overtake; and he walking in the darkness not knows where he goes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.36'>While the light you have, believe into the light, that sons of light you may become. These things spoke the Jesus, and going away he was hid from them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.37'>So many but of him signs having been done in presence of them not they did believe into him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.38'>that the word of Esaias the prophet might be fulfilled, which he said: O lord, who believed the report of us? and the arm of Lord to whom was it revealed?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.39'>On account of this not they were able to believe; because again said Esaias:</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.40'>He has blinded of them the eyes, and has hardened of them the heart; so that not they might see with the eyes, and understand with the heart, and should turn back, and I should heal them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.41'>These things said Esaias, because he saw the glory of him, and spoke concerning him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.42'>Nevertheless truly and of the rulers many believed into him; but on account of the Pharisees not did confess, so that not from synagogues they might be;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.43'>they loved for the glory of the men more, than the glory of the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.44'>Jesus and cried and said: He believing into me, not believe into me, but into him having sent me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.45'>and he seeing me, see him having sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.46'>I a light into the world have come, that all the believing into me, in the darkness not may abide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.47'>And if any one of me may hear the words, and not may believe, I not judge him; (not for I came, that I might judge the world, but that I might save the world);</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.48'>he rejecting me, and not receiving the words of me has that judging him; the word which I spoke, that shall judge him in the last day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.49'>Because I from myself not spoke; but the having sent me Father he me a commandment gave, what I should say and what I should I speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.12.50'>And I know, that the commandment of him life agelasting is. What therefore say I, as has spoken to me the Father, so I speak.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.13'>
        <verse osisID='John.13.1'>Before and the feast of the passover, knowing the Jesus, that was come of himself the hour, that he should depart out of the world this to the world, to an end he loved them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.2'>And supper being done, (the accuser already having put into the heart Judas of Simon Iscariot, that him he might betray,)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.3'>knowing the Jesus, that all things had given him the Father into the hands, and that from God he came out and to the God he goes;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.4'>rises from the supper, and puts off the mantles, and having taken a towel, girded himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.5'>Afterward he puts water into the washbasin, and began to wash the feet of the disciples, and to wipe with the towel with which he was having been girded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.6'>He comes then to Simon Peter; and says to him he: O lord, thou of me washest the feet?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.7'>Answered Jesus and said to him: What I do, thou not knowest now, thou shalt know but after these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.8'>Says to him Peter: Not not thou mayest wash the feet of me into the age. Answered him the Jesus: If not I may wash thee, thou hast a part of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.9'>Says to him Simon Peter: O lord, not the feet of me alone, but also the hands, and the head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.10'>Says to him the Jesus: He having been bathed not need has than the feet to wash, but is clean wholly; and you clean are, but not all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.11'>He knew for the betraying him; on account of this he said: Not all clean you are.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.12'>When therefore he had washed the feet of them, and taken the mantles of himself, falling down again, he said to them: Know you what I have done to you:</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.13'>You call me: The teacher and the lord; and well you say; I am for.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.14'>If then I washed of you the feet, the lord and the teacher, also you are bound of one another to wash the feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.15'>An example for I gave to you, that as I did to you, also you should do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.16'>Indeed indeed I say to you, not is a slave greater of the lord of himself, nor a messenger greater of the sending him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.17'>If these things you know, blessed are you, if you should do them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.18'>Not about all of you I speak; I know whom I chose; but, that the writing may be fulfilled: He eating with me the loaf, lifted up against me the heel of himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.19'>From now I say to you, before the to happen, that when it may happen, you may believe, that I am.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.20'>Indeed indeed I say to you: He receiving if any one I may send, me receives; he and me receiving, receives him having sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.21'>These things saying the Jesus was troubled in the spirit, and testified, and said: Indeed indeed I say to you, that one of you will betray me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.22'>Looked then to each other the disciples, doubting about whom he was speaking.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.23'>Was now reclining one of the disciples of him in the bosom of the Jesus, whom loved the Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.24'>Nods then to him Simon Peter, to ask who it might be concerning of whom he speaks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.25'>Falling and he on the breast of the Jesus, he says to him: O lord, who is it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.26'>Answers the Jesus: He it is, to whom I have dipped the little piece shall give. And having dipped the little piece, he gives to Judas of Simon Iscariot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.27'>And after the little piece, then answered into him the adversary. Says then to him the Jesus: What thou doest, do thou quickly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.28'>This now no one knew of those reclining with why he said to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.29'>Some for thought, seeing that the box had the Judas, that says to him the Jesus: Buy what things need we have for the feast; or to the poor that something he should give.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.30'>Having taken then the little piece he immediately went out; it was and night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.31'>When he went out, says the Jesus: Just now was glorified the son of the man, and the God was glorified in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.32'>If the God was glorified in him, also the God will glorify him in himself, and immediately will glorify him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.33'>O little children, yet a little with you I am. You will seek me; and as I said to the Jews: That where I go, you not are able to come; even to you I say now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.34'>A commandment new I give to you, that you may love each other; as I loved you, that also you might love each other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.35'>By this will know all that to me disciples you are, if love you have in each other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.36'>Says to him Simon Peter: O lord, where goest thou? Answered him the Jesus: Where I go, not thou art able me now to follow; afterwards but thou shalt follow me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.37'>Says to him Peter: O lord, why not I am able thee to follow now? the life of me in behalf of thee I will lay down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.13.38'>Answered him the Jesus: The life of thee in behalf of me wilt thou lay down? Indeed indeed I say to thee not not a cock will crow, till not thou wilt deny me thrice.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.14'>
        <verse osisID='John.14.1'>Not let be troubled of you the heart; believe you into the God, and into me believe you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.2'>In the house of the Father of me dwellings many are; if but not, I would have told you. I am going to prepare a place for you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.3'>and if I should go, and should prepare for you a place, again I am coming, and will receive you to myself; so that where am I, also you may be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.4'>And where I am going you know, and the way you know.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.5'>Says to him Thomas: O lord, not we know where thou art going? and how are we able the way to know?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.6'>Says to him the Jesus: I am the way, and the truth, and the life; no one comes to the Father, if not through me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.7'>If you had known me, also the Father of me you would have known; and from now you know him, and have seen him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.8'>Says to him Philip: O lord, show to us the Father, and it is enough for us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.9'>Says to him the Jesus: So long a time with you am I, and not knowest thou me, O Philip? He having seen me, has seen the Father; and how thou sayest: Show to us the Father?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.10'>Not believest thou, that I in the Father, and the Father in me is? The words which I speak to you, from myself not I speak; the but Father, he in me abiding, he does the works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.11'>You believe me, because I in the Father, and the Father in me, if but not, on account of the works themselves believe me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.12'>Indeed indeed I speak to you, he believing into me, the works which I do, also he shall do, and greater of these shall he do; because I to the Father of me am going,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.13'>and what any thing you may ask in the name of me, this I will do; that may be glorified the Father in the son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.14'>If any thing you may ask in the name of me, I will do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.15'>If you love me, the commandments the mine keep you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.16'>and I will ask the Father, and another helper he will give to you, that he may abide with you into the age;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.17'>the spirit of the truth, which the world not is able to receive, because not it beholds it, nor knows it; you but know it, because with you it abides, and in you it will be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.18'>Not I will leave you orphans; I am coming to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.19'>Yet a little, and the world me no more beholds; you but behold me; because I live, also you shall live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.20'>In that the day shall know you, because I in the Father of me, and you in me, and I in you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.21'>He having the commandments of me, and keeping them, that is he loving me; he and loving me, shall be loved by the Father of me; and I will love him, and will manifest to him myself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.22'>Says to him Judas (not the Iscariot): O lord, and how has it happened, that to us thou art about to manifest thyself, and not to the world?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.23'>Answered Jesus and said to him: If any one love me, the word of me he will keep; and the Father of me will love him; to him we will come, and a dwelling with him we will make.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.24'>He not loving me, the words of me not will keep; and the word which you hear, not is mine, but of the sending me Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.25'>These things I have spoken to you, with you abiding;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.26'>but the helper, the spirit the holy, which will send the Father in the name of me, that you will teach all things, and will remind you all things which I told you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.27'>Peace I leave to you, peace the mine I give to you; not as the world gives, I give to you. Not let be troubled of you the heart nor let it be afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.28'>You heard, that I said to you: I am going away, and I am coming to you. If you loved me, you would rejoice, that I am going to the Father; because the Father of me greater of me is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.29'>And now I have told you before it happens, so that when it happens, you may believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.30'>No more much I will speak with you. Is coming for he of the world ruling, and in me not has nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.14.31'>But that may know the world, that I love the Father, and as commanded me the Father, so I do. Arise you, let us go from this place.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.15'>
        <verse osisID='John.15.1'>I am the vine the true, and the Father of me the vinedresser is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.2'>Every branch in me, not bearing fruit, he takes away it; and every one the fruit bearing, he cleanses it, that more fruit it may bear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.3'>Already you clean are, through the word, which I have spoken to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.4'>Abide you in me, and I in you. As the branch not is able fruit to bear of itself, if not it may abide in the vine; so neither you, if not in me you abide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.5'>I am the vine, you the branches. He abiding in me, and I am in him, this bears fruit much; because apart from me not you are able to do nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.6'>If not any one may abide in me, he is cast out, like the branch, and is withered; and they gather them, and into a fire they cast, and it is burned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.7'>If you abide in me and the words of me in you may abide, whatever you may wish you shall ask, and it shall be for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.8'>In this was glorified the Father of me, that fruit much you might bear, and you shall be to me disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.9'>As loved me the Father, and I loved you; abide you in the love the mine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.10'>If the commandments of me you may keep, you will abide in the love of me; as I the commandments of the Father of me have kept, and abide of him in the love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.11'>These things I have spoken to you, that the joy the mine in you may abide, and the joy of you may be fulfilled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.12'>This is the commandment the mine, that you love each other, as I loved you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.13'>Greater of this love no one has, that any one the life of himself may lay down in behalf of the friends of himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.14'>You friends of me are, if you may do what things I command you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.15'>No more you I call slaves; because the slaves not knows what does of him the lord; you but I have called friends, because all things which I heard from the Father of me, I made known to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.16'>Not you me did choose, but I chose you, and appointed you, that you might go and fruit might bear, and the fruit of you might abide; so that whatever you may ask the Father in the name of me, he may give to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.17'>These things I command you, that you may love each other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.18'>If the world you hates, you know, that me before you it has hated.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.19'>If of the world you were, the world would the own kiss, because but of the world not you are, but I chose you out of the world, on account of this hates you the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.20'>Remember you the world, of which I said to you. Not is a slave greater of the lord of himself. If me they persecuted, also you they will persecute; if the word of me they kept, also the yours they will keep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.21'>But these things all they will do to you on account of the name of me, because not they know him sending me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.22'>If not I had come and spoken to them, sin not they had; now but an excuse not they have about the sin of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.23'>He me hating, also the Father of me hates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.24'>If the works, not I had done among them, which no one other has done, sin not they had; now but even they have seen, and have hated both me and that Father of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.25'>But, that may be fulfilled the word of having been written in the law of them: That they hated me without cause.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.26'>When but may come the helper, whom I will send to you from the Father, (the spirit of the truth, which from the Father shall come out,) that will testify concerning me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.15.27'>Also you and shall testify, because from a beginning with me you are.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.16'>
        <verse osisID='John.16.1'>These things I have spoken to you, that not you may be ensnared.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.2'>From synagogues they will put you; but comes an hour, that every one the killing you, may think a service to offer to the God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.3'>And these things they will do, because not they know the Father, nor me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.4'>But these things I have spoken to you, that when may come the hour, you may remember them, that I said to you. These things but to you from a beginning not I said, because with you I was.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.5'>Now but I go to him having sent me, and no one of you asks me: Where goest thou?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.6'>But because these things I have spoken to you, the sorrow has filled of you the heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.7'>But I the truth say to you; it is better for you, that I should go away. If for not I should go away, the helper not will come to you; if but I go, I will send him to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.8'>And having come he will convict the world concerning sin, and concerning righteousness, and concerning judgment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.9'>Concerning sin indeed, because not they believe into me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.10'>concerning righteousness but, because to the Father of me I go away, and no more you behold me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.11'>concerning and judgment, because the ruling of the world this has been judged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.12'>Yet many things I have to say to you, but not you are able to bear now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.13'>When but many may come he the spirit of the truth, he will lead you into all the truth. Not for he will speak from himself, but whatever he may hear, he will speak, and the things coming he will declare to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.14'>He me will glorify, because out of the mine will take, and will declare to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.15'>All things what was the Father, mine is. On account of this I said, that out of the mine he takes, and declares to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.16'>A little while, and not you see me; and again a little while, and you shall see me, because I am going to the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.17'>Said then of the disciples of him to each other: What is this which he says to us: A little while, and not you see me; and again a little while and you shall see me; and: Because I am going to the Father?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.18'>They said therefore: This what is which he says, the little while? Not we know what he says.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.19'>Knew the Jesus, that they wish him to ask, and said to them: Concerning this inquire you with each other, because I said: A little while, and not you see me; and again a little while, and you shall see me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.20'>Indeed indeed I say to you, that will weep and will lament you, the but world will rejoice; you and will be sorrowful, but the sorrow of you into joy shall become.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.21'>The woman when she may bear, sorrow has, because has come the hour of her; when but she may have borne the child, no more she remembers of the distress, on account of the joy, that was born a man into the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.22'>And you therefore sorrow indeed now have; again but I will see you, and will be rejoiced of you the heart, and the joy of you no one takes from you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.23'>and in that the day me not you will ask nothing; Indeed indeed I say to you, that whatever you may ask the Father in the name of me, he will give to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.24'>Till now not you asked nothing in the name of me; ask you, and you shall receive, so that the joy of you may be completed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.25'>These things in figures I have spoken to you; comes an hour, when no more in figures I will speak to you, but plainly concerning the Father i will tell you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.26'>In that the day in the name of me you will ask; and not I say to you, that I will entreat the Father concerning you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.27'>himself for the Father loves you, because you me have loved and have believed, that I from the God came out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.28'>I came out from the Father, and have come into the world; again I leave the world; and am going to the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.29'>Say to him the disciples of him: Lo, now plainly thou speakest, and a figure not one thou sayest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.30'>Now we know, that thou knowest all things, and no need has, that any one thee should ask; in this we believe, that from God thou didst come out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.31'>Answered them the Jesus: Now do you believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.32'>Lo, comes an hour, and now is come, that you will be scattered every one to the own, and me alone you may leave; and not I am alone, because the Father with me is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.16.33'>These things I have spoken to you, that in me peace you may have. In the world affliction you have; but be you of good courage, I have overcome the world.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.17'>
        <verse osisID='John.17.1'>These things spoke the Jesus, and lifted up the eyes of him to the heaven, and said: O Father, is come the hour; glorify of thee the son, that also the son of thee may glorify thee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.2'>as thou gavest to him authority over all flesh, so that all which thou hast given to him, he may give to them life agelasting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.3'>This and is the agelasting life, that they might know thee the only true God, and whom thou hast sent Jesus Anointed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.4'>I thee glorified on the earth; the work I finished, which thou hast given me, that I might do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.5'>And now glorify me, thou O Father, with thyself, with the glory, which I had, before of the the world to be, with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.6'>I manifested of thee the name to the men, whom thou hast given to me out of the world; thine they were, and to me them thou hast given; and the word of thee they have kept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.7'>Now they know, that all things whatever thou hast given me, from thee is;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.8'>because the words which thou hast given me, I have given to them; and they received, and knew truly, that thou thee I came out, and believed, that thou me didst send.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.9'>I concerning them ask; not concerning the world I ask, but concerning whom thou hast given me, because thine they are;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.10'>and the mine all thine is, and the thine mine, and I have been glorified in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.11'>And no more I am in the world, and these in the world are, and I to thee am coming. O Father holy, keep them in the name of thee, by which thou hast given to me; that they may be one, as we.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.12'>When I was with them in the world, I kept them in the name of thee; whom thou hast given to me I guarded, and no one of them was destroyed, if not the son of the destruction, that the writings may be fulfilled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.13'>Now and to thee I am coming, and these things I say in the world, that they may have the joy the mine fulfilled in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.14'>I have given to them the word of thee; and the world hated them, because not they are of the world, as I not am of the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.15'>Not I ask, that thou wouldst take them out of the world, but that thou wouldst keep them from the evil one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.16'>Of the world not they are, as I of the world not am.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.17'>Sanctify them in the truth of thee; the word the thine truth is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.18'>As me thou didst send into the world, also I sent them into the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.19'>And in behalf of them I sanctify myself, so that also they may be sanctified in truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.20'>Not concerning these and I ask alone, but also concerning those believing through the word of them into me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.21'>That all one may be; as thou, Father, in me, and I in thee, that also they in us one may be; that the world may believe, that thou me didst send.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.22'>And I the glory which thou hast given to me, have given to them; that they may be one, as we one are;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.23'>(I in them, and thou in me); that they may be perfected into one, and that may know the world, that thou me didst send, and thou didst love them, as me thou didst love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.24'>O Father, whom thou given to me, I wish, that where am I, also they may be with me; that they may behold the glory the mine, which thou didst give to me, because thou didst love me before a laying down of a world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.25'>O Father righteous, and the world thee not knew; I but thee knew, and these knew that thou me didst send.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.17.26'>And I made known to them the name of thee, and will make known; that the love which thou didst love me, in them may be, and I in them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.18'>
        <verse osisID='John.18.1'>These things saying the Jesus went out with the disciples of himself beyond the brook of the Kedron, where was a garden, into which entered himself and the disciples of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.2'>Knew and also Judas, he delivering up him, the place; because often met the Jesus there with the disciples of himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.3'>The then Judas having taken then band, and from the highpriests and Pharisees officers, comes there with torches and lamps and weapons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.4'>Jesus therefore knowing all the things coming on him, going out said to them: Whom seek you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.5'>They answered him: Jesus the Nazarene. Says to them the Jesus: I am. (Was standing and also Judas, the delivering up him, with them.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.6'>When therefore he said to them: That I am; they went into the behind, and fell on the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.7'>Again then them he asked: Whom seek you? They and said: Jesus the Nazarene.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.8'>Answered Jesus: I said to you, that I am; if therefore me you seek, suffer these to go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.9'>So that might be fulfilled the word, which he said: That whom thou hast given to me, not I lost of them no one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.10'>Simon then Peter having a sword, drew her, and struck the of the highpriest slave, and cut off of him the ear the right. Was now a name to the slave Malchus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.11'>Said therefore the Jesus to the Peter: Put up the sword into the sheath; the cup which has given to me the Father, not not should I drink it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.12'>The then band and the commander and the officers of the Jews apprehend the Jesus, and bound him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.13'>and led him to Annas first; he was for fatherinlaw of the Caiaphas, who was highpriest of the year that.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.14'>Was now Caiaphas he having advised the Jews, that it is better one man to be destroyed in behalf of the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.15'>Followed and the Jesus Simon Peter, and the other disciples. The and disciples that was known to the highpriest, and went in with the Jesus into the palace of the highpriest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.16'>The but Peter stood at the door without. Went out therefore the disciples the other, who was known to the highpriest, and spoke to the doorkeeper, and brought in the Peter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.17'>Says then the femaleservant the doorkeeper to the Peter: Not also thou of the disciples art the man this? Says he: Not I am.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.18'>Stood and the slaves and the officers a coal fire having made, because cold it was, and warmed themselves; was and with them the Peter standing and warming himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.19'>The therefore highpriest asked the Jesus concerning the disciples of him, and concerning the teaching of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.20'>Answered him the Jesus: I publicly spoke to the world; I always taught in a synagogue and in the temple, where all the Jews come together, and in secret I said nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.21'>Why me dost thou ask? ask those having heard, what I said to them; lo, they know what things said I.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.22'>These things and of him having said, one of the officers having stood by gave a blow to the Jesus, saying: Thus dost thou answer the highpriest?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.23'>Answered him the Jesus: If evil I spoke, testify concerning the evil; if but well, why me dost thou beat?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.24'>Sent him the Annas having been bound to Caiaphas the highpriest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.25'>Was and Simon Peter standing and warming himself. They said therefore to him: Not also thou of the disciples of him thou art? Denied he, and said: Not I am.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.26'>Says one of the slaves of the highpriest, a relative being of whom cut off Peter the ear: Not I thee saw in the garden with him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.27'>Again therefore denied the Peter; and immediately cock crew.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.28'>They led then the Jesus from of the Caiaphas into the Jerusalem hall; it was and morning. And they not went into the judgment hall, that not they might be defiled, but that they might eat the passover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.29'>Went out therefore the Pilate to them, and said: What accusation bring you against the man this?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.30'>They answered and said to him: If not was this an evildoer, not would to thee we delivered up him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.31'>Said then to them the Pilate: Take him you, and according to the law of you judge him. Said therefore to him the Jews: To us not it is lawful to kill no one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.32'>So that the word of the Jesus might be fulfilled, which he said, pointing out by what death he was about to die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.33'>Went then into the judgment hall again the Pilate, and called the Jesus, and said to him: Thou art the king of the Jews?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.34'>Answered him the Jesus: From thyself thou this sayest, or others to thee told concerning me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.35'>Answered the Pilate: Not I a Jew am? the nation the thine and highpriests delivered up thee to me; what didst thou do?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.36'>Answered Jesus: The kingdom the mine not is of the world this; if of the world this was the kingdom the mine, the officers would those for me contend, that not I might be delivered up to the Jews, now but the kingdom the mine not is from this place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.37'>Said then to him the Pilate: Not then a king art thou? Answered the Jesus: Thou sayest; that a king am I. I for this have been born, and for this I have come into the world, that I may testify to the truth. Every one who being of the truth, hears of me the voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.38'>Says to him the Pilate: What is truth? And this saying, again he went out to the Jews, and says to them: I not one fault find in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.39'>It is but a custom for you, that one to you I release in the passover; are you willing therefore, to you I release the king of the Jews?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.18.40'>They cried out then again all saying: Not this, but the Barabbas. Was now the Barabbas a robber.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.19'>
        <verse osisID='John.19.1'>Then therefore took the Pilate the Jesus, and scourged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.2'>And the soldiers braiding a crown of thorns, placed of him the head, and a mantle purple threw about him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.3'>and said: Hail the king of the Jews; and they gave him blows.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.4'>Went again out the Pilate, and says to them: Lo, I bring to you him out, that you may know, that in him not one fault I find.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.5'>(Came then the Jesus out, wearing the thorny crown, and the purple mantle.) And he says to them: See the man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.6'>When therefore saw him the highpriests and officers, they cried out saying: Crucify, crucify him. Says to them the Pilate: Take him you, and crucify; I for not find in him a fault.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.7'>Answered him the Jews: We a law have, and according to the law of us he ought to die, because himself, a son of God he made.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.8'>When therefore heard the Pilate this the word, more he was afraid;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.9'>and went into the judgment hall again, and says to the Jesus: Whence art thou? The but Jesus an answer not gave to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.10'>Says then to him the Pilate: To me not thou doest speak? not knowest thou, that authority I have to crucify thee; and authority I have to release thee?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.11'>Answered Jesus: Not thou couldst have authority not any against me, if not it was to thee having been given from above; on account of this he delivering up me to thee, greater sin has.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.12'>From this seeks the Pilate to release him. The but Jews cried out, saying: If this thou release, not thou art a friend of the Caesar; every one the king himself making, speaks against the Caesar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.13'>The therefore Pilate having heard this the word, brought out the Jesus, and sat down on the tribunal into a place being called Pavement, in Hebrew but Gabbatha;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.14'>(it was and a preparation of the passover, hour and about sixth;) and he says to the Jews: See the king of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.15'>They but cried out: Away, away; crucify him. Says to them the Pilate: The king of you shall I crucify? Answered the highpriests: Not we have a king, if not Caesar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.16'>Then therefore he delivered up him to them, that he might be crucified. They took and the Jesus and led.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.17'>And carrying the cross of himself, he went out into the being called of a skull a place, which is called in Hebrew Golgotha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.18'>Where him they crucified, and with him others two, hence and hence, in middle and the Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.19'>Wrote and also a title the Pilate, and placed upon the cross. It was and having been written: Jesus the Nazarene, the king of the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.20'>This therefore the title many read of the Jews, because near was the place of the city, where was crucified the Jesus; and it was having been written in Hebrew, in Greek, in Latin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.21'>Said therefore to the Pilate the highpriests of the Jews: Not write thou: The king of the Jews; but that he said: A king I am of the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.22'>Answered the Pilate: What I have written, I have written.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.23'>The then soldiers, when they crucified the Jesus, took the mantles of him, (and made four parts, to each soldier a part,) and the coat. Was but the coat without seam, from the top woven throughout whole;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.24'>they said then to each other: Not let us tear him, but we may cast lots about him, of whom it shall be. That the writing might be fulfilled that saying: They divided the mantles of me for themselves, and on the raiment of me they cast a lot. The indeed therefore soldiers these things did.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.25'>Stood now by the cross of the Jesus the mother of him, and the sister of the mother of him, Mary that of the Klopas, and Mary the Magdalene.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.26'>Jesus therefore seeing the mother, and the disciples standing by, whom he loved, he says to the mother of himself: O woman, lo, the son of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.27'>Then he says to the disciples: Lo, the mother of thee. And from that the hour took the disciple her into the own.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.28'>After this knowing the Jesus, that all things already had been finished that might be finished the writing, says: I thirst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.29'>A vessel therefore stood of vinegar full; they and filling a sponge of vinegar, and to a hyssopstalk putting round, brought of him to the mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.30'>When therefore took the vinegar the Jesus said: It has been finished; and having inclined the head, he gave up the spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.31'>The then Jews (that not might remain on the cross the bodies in the sabbath; since a preparation it was; was for great the day that of the sabbath) asked the Pilate, that might be broken of them the legs, and they might be taken away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.32'>Came therefore the soldiers, and of the indeed first, they brake the legs, and of the other that having been crucified with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.33'>To but the Jesus having come, when they saw him already having died, not they broke of him the legs;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.34'>but one of the soldiers with a spear of him the side pierced, and immediately came out blood and water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.35'>And he having seen has testified, and true of him is the testimony; and he knows, that rue things he says, so that also you may believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.36'>Occurred for these things, that the writing might be fulfilled: A bone not shall be broken of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.37'>And again another writing says: They shall look into whom they pierced.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.38'>After and these things, asked the Pilate the Joseph that from Arimathea, (being a disciple of the Jesus, having been hid but through the fear of the Jews,) that he might take away the body of the Jesus, and permitted the Pilate. He came therefore and took away the body of the Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.39'>Came and also Nicodemus, (the having come to the Jesus by night the first,) bringing a mixture of myrrh and aloes about pounds a hundred.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.40'>They took therefore the body of the Jesus, and bound it with linen cloths with the spices, as customary it is with the Jews to embalm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.41'>Was and in the place, where he was crucified, a garden, and in the garden a tomb new, in which not yet no one was laid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.19.42'>There therefore on account of the preparation of the Jews, because near was the tomb, they laid the Jesus.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.20'>
        <verse osisID='John.20.1'>The and first of the week Mary the Magdalene comes early, dark yet being, into the tomb; and sees the stone having been taken away out of the tomb,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.2'>she runs therefore and comes to Simon Peter, and to the other disciple, whom loved the Jesus, and says to them: They took away the Lord out of the tomb, and not we know, where they laid him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.3'>Went out then the Peter and the other disciples, and they came into the tomb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.4'>Ran and they two together; and the other disciple ran before more quickly of the Peter, and came first into the tomb;</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.5'>and stooping down he sees lying the linen cloths; not however he went in.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.6'>Comes then Simon Peter following him, and entered into the tomb, and sees the linen cloths lying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.7'>and the napkin which was on the head of him, not with the linen cloths lying, but apart having been folded up into one place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.8'>Then therefore went in also the other disciple, he coming first into the tomb, and saw, and believed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.9'>Not yet for they knew the writing, that it behooved him out of dead ones to have been raised.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.10'>Went then again to themselves the disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.11'>Mary but stands by the tomb weeping outside. As therefore she wept, she stopped down into the tomb,</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.12'>and sees two messengers in white sitting, one at the head, and one at the feet, where was laid the body of the Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.13'>And say to her they: O woman, why weepest thou? She says to them: Because they took away the Lord of me, and not I know where they laid him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.14'>These things having said, she turned into the behind, and sees the Jesus standing; and not knew, that Jesus it is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.15'>Says to her the Jesus: O woman, why weepest thou? whom seekest thou? She, supposing that the gardener it is, says to him: O sir, if thou didst carry off him, tell me where thou didst lay him, and I him will take away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.16'>Says to her the Jesus: Mary. Turning round she says to him: Rabboni, which means, O teacher.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.17'>Says to her the Jesus: Not me touch; not yet for I have gone up to the Father of me; go but to the brethren of me, and say to them: I go up to the Father of me and Father of you, even God of me and God of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.18'>Comes Mary the Magdalene telling the disciples, that she had seen the Lord, and these things he said to her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.19'>Being then evening in the day that the first of the week, and the doors having been shut, where were the disciples having been assembled, through the fear of the Jews, came the Jesus, and stood into the midst, and says to them: Peace to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.20'>And this having said, he showed to them the hands and the side of himself. Were glad therefore the disciples, seeing the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.21'>Said then to them the Jesus again: Peace to you; as sent me the Father, also I send you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.22'>And this having said, he breathed on, and says to them: Receive you a spirit holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.23'>If of whom you may forgive the sins, they are forgiven them; if of whom you may retain, they have been retained.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.24'>Thomas but, one of the twelve, he being called a twin, not was with them when came the Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.25'>Said then to him the other disciples: We have seen the Lord. He but said to them: If not I may see in the hands of him the mark of the nails, and may put the finger of me into the mark of the nails, and may put the hand of me into the side of him, not not I will believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.26'>And after days eight again were within the disciples of him, and Thomas with them. Comes the Jesus, the doors having been shut, and stood into the midst, and said: Peace to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.27'>Afterwards he says to the Thomas: Bring the finger of thee here, and see the hands of me, and bring the hand of thee, and put into the side of me; and not be thou unbelieving, but believing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.28'>Answered Thomas and said to him: The Lord of me and the God of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.29'>Says to him the Jesus: Because thou hast seen me, thou hast believed; blessed they not having seen, and having believed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.30'>Many indeed then and other signs did the Jesus in presence of the disciples of him, which not it is having been written in the book this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.20.31'>These things but have been written, that you may believe, that Jesus is the Anointed, the son of the God, and that believing life you may have in the name of him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='John.21'>
        <verse osisID='John.21.1'>After these things manifested himself again the Jesus to the disciples on the sea of the Tiberias. He manifested and thus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.2'>Were together Simon Peter, and Thomas he being called a twin, and Nathanael he from Cana of the Galilee, and they of the Zebedee, and others of the disciples of him two.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.3'>Says to them Simon Peter: I am going to fish. They say to him: Are going also we with thee. They went out, and entered into the ship immediately, and in that the night they caught nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.4'>Morning but now being come, stood the Jesus on the shore; not however knew the disciples, that Jesus it is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.5'>Says therefore to them the Jesus: Children, not any food have you? They answered him: No.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.6'>He and said to them: Cast you into the right parts of the ship the net, and you will find. They cast then, and no longer it to draw were able from the multitude of the fishes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.7'>Says therefore the disciple that whom loved the Jesus, to the Peter: The Lord it is; Simon then Peter, having heard that the Lord it is, the upper garment he girded; he was for naked; and threw himself into the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.8'>The but other disciples by the little ship came (not for they were far from the land, but about from cubits two hundred), dragging the net of the fishes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.9'>When therefore they went up to the land, they see a fire of coals lying, and a fish lying on, and bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.10'>Says to them the Jesus: Bring you from the fishes, which you caught just now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.11'>Went up Simon Peter, and drew the net to the land, full of fishes, great a hundred fiftythree; and so many being, not was torn the net.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.12'>Says to them the Jesus: Come, breakfast you. No one but presumed of the disciples to ask him: Thou who art? knowing, that the Lord it is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.13'>Comes the Jesus, and takes the bread, and gives to them, and the fish in like manner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.14'>This already third was manifested the Jesus to the disciples of himself, having been raised out of the dead ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.15'>When therefore they had breakfasted, says to the Simon Peter the Jesus: Simon of Jona, lovest thou me more of these? He says to him: Yes, O lord, thou knowest, that I dearly love thee. He says to him: Feed the lambs of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.16'>He says to him again a second time: Simon of Jona, lovest thou me? He says to him: Yes, O lord, thou knowest, that I dearly love thee. He says to him: Tend thou the sheep of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.17'>He says to him the third: Simon of Jona, dearly lovest thou me? Was grieved the Peter, because he said to him the third, Dearly lovest me thou? and he said to him: O lord, thou all things knowest; thou knowest, that i dearly love thee. Says to him the Jesus: Feed the sheep of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.18'>Indeed indeed I say to thee, when thou wast younger, thou didst gird thyself, and didst walk where thou didst wish; when but thou art old, thou wilt stretch out the hands of thee, and another thee will gird, and will carry where not thou wishest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.19'>This now he said, signifying, by what death he will glorify the God. And this having said, he says to him: Follow me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.20'>Having turned about and the Peter sees the disciples, whom loved the Jesus, following (who also reclined at the supper on the breast of him, and said: O lord, who is he betraying thee?)</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.21'>Him seeing the Peter says to the Jesus: O lord, this and what?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.22'>Says to him the Jesus: If him I wish to abide till I come, what to thee? thou follow me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.23'>Went out therefore the word this among the brethren, that the disciple that not dies. And not said to him the Jesus, that not he dies; but: If him I wish to abide till I come, what to thee?</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.24'>This is the disciple, he testifying concerning these things, and having written these things; and we know, that true is the testimony of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='John.21.25'>Is and also other many things did the Jesus, which if they should be written every one, not even him I suppose the world to contain the being written books.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>