<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='TCE' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='TCE'>
        <title>The Common Edition: New Testament</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>
                      ---------------------------------
                      The Common Edition: New Testament
                             --------------------
                             All rights reserved.
                      ----------------------------------
                      Copyright © Timothy E. Clontz 1999


The Common Edition: New Testament
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~

  The Common Edition is the result of a decade long study of the New Testament
  and numerous English translations in the modern church. The goals for this
  edition are:

        1.  To be accurate to the Greek Scriptures and yet highly readable, 

        2.  To balance traditional wording with modern English, and

        3.  To reflect the standard Christian understanding and wording of the
            New Testament.

  The purpose of these goals is to create a standardized New Testament for the
  modern English reader.

  There are two ways to create a standardized text. [The first way] is to
  create a text of such surpassing scholarship and expression that it
  practically eliminates the use of other editions for decades or perhaps
  centuries. [The second way] is to isolate what the most widely used
  editions have in common, eliminate what they do not have in common, and
  place the results in a single text.

  
  The King James Version succeeded in both of these two ways.

  Over the past hundred years there have been numerous attempts to create a
  new English standard Bible. Each of these attempts has sought to produce a
  standardized edition in the first way I have described. The Common Edition
  New Testament follows the second method.

  A standardized edition of any work seeks a balance between extremes. The
  most literally accurate version may not be the easiest to read. The most
  traditionally worded may not be very modern.

  It cannot have a target audience; what is best for preachers and theologians
  may not be best for the daily devotional reader.

  Finally, a standardized edition cannot be innovative. One reviewer gave me
  the highest compliment I could receive when he said, "there's nothing new
  about it!"

  I hope that readers will find in these pages exactly what they would expect
  from a standardized edition, and that no matter what versions they have used
  in the past, they will find something familiar here.

   
  This initial release into the public domain is intended for free
  distribution. The text itself is copyrighted, with the following provisions:

        1.  The Common Edition: New Testament may be copied and distributed in
            electronic or printed form for free.

        2.  It may be bound or downloaded for personal use or for a gift.

        3.  It may not be sold by anyone other than the editor. 

        4.  The text may not be altered.

        5.  No more than 10,000 words may be included in a document published
            for sale without the express written permission of the editor.

        6.  No more than 20% of a document published for sale may be quoted
            from this edition without the express written permission of the
            editor. 

        7.  All distributions of the Common Edition, and all documents which
            quote the Common Edition, must contain the following copyright
            notice: Common Edition New Testament, Copyright © Timothy E.
            Clontz 1999. All rights reserved.

  If you find a phrase or word which is unclear, or which you believe needs
  review, please email the editor at {teclontz@aol.com}.

   
  Although it is not appropriate to dedicate a New Testament to any
  individual, the editor would like to give his gratitude to the many people
  who have labored to preserve this text. Those who penned the autographs
  often faced ridicule or death. Nameless monks sleep in the dust, who
  faithfully copied one manuscript to another down through the centuries. By
  the time of the Reformation, William Tyndale had one wish: to make the
  Christian Bible available in English to the poorest farmhand in England. For
  this crime he was strangled and burned at the stake.

  And then there are those who have simply loved these words enough to live by
  their highest ideals. Without the goodness of their lives no one would
  believe there to be anything Holy about a Bible. One such godly man was M.
  D. Barefield, who learned to read as an adult just so that he could make
  this word his own. My grandfather, Bill Clontz, who will always be an
  example for my family, gradually bought larger and larger print Bibles and
  finally began using the Bible on tape - just to keep the Word fresh in his
  heart. Such people always stay fresh in the hearts of those who have known
  them, and their love for God is contagious.


  Timothy Clontz
  March 14, 1999
  
  </description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>TCE</identifier>
        <source>http://www.ccel.org/olb/tolbss/zipfiles/translations/twenty.exe
            http://www.ccel.org/olb/tolbss/zipfiles/translations/comed10d.zip</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='1Thess'>
      <chapter osisID='1Thess.1'>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.1.1'>Paul, Silvanus and Timothy, to the church of the Thessalonians in God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ: grace and peace to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.1.2'>We give thanks to God always for all of you, mentioning you in our prayers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.1.3'>remembering before our God and Father your work of faith and labor of love and steadfastness of hope in our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.1.4'>For we know, brethren beloved by God, that he has chosen you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.1.5'>for our gospel came to you not only in word, but also in power and in the Holy Spirit and with full conviction. You know what kind of men we proved to be among you for your sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.1.6'>You became imitators of us and of the Lord, for you received the word in much affliction, with the joy of the Holy Spirit;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.1.7'>so that you became an example to all the believers in Macedonia and in Achaia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.1.8'>For not only has the word of the Lord sounded forth from you in Macedonia and Achaia, but your faith in God has gone forth everywhere, so that we have no need to say anything.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.1.9'>For they themselves report about us what kind of a reception we had with you, and how you turned to God from idols to serve a living and true God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.1.10'>and to wait for his Son from heaven, whom he raised from the deadJesus, who rescues us from the wrath to come.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Thess.2'>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.1'>For you yourselves know, brethren, that our visit to you was not in vain;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.2'>but after we had already suffered and been shamefully treated in Philippi, as you know, we had the boldness in our God to speak to you the gospel of God in the face of great opposition.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.3'>For our appeal does not spring from error or impurity, nor is it made with deceit;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.4'>but just as we have been approved by God to be entrusted with the gospel, so we speak, not to please men, but to please God who tests our hearts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.5'>For, as you know, we never used flattery nor a pretext for greedGod is witness</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.6'>nor did we seek glory from men, either from you or from others, though we might have made demands as apostles of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.7'>But we were gentle among you, like a mother nursing her little children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.8'>Having so fond an affection for you, we were ready to share with you not only the gospel of God but also our own lives, because you had become very dear to us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.9'>For you remember our labor and toil, brethren; we worked night and day, that we might not be a burden to any of you, while we preached to you the gospel of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.10'>You are witnesses, and God also, how holy and righteous and blameless we behaved toward you believers;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.11'>for you know how, as a father with his own children, we exhorted each one of you and encouraged you and charged you</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.12'>to live a life worthy of God, who calls you into his own kingdom and glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.13'>And we also thank God constantly for this, that when you received the word of God which you heard from us, you accepted it not as the word of men but as what it really is, the word of God, which is at work in you who believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.14'>For you, brethren, became imitators of the churches of God in Christ Jesus which are in Judea, for you suffered the same things from your own countrymen as they did from the Jews,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.15'>who both killed the Lord Jesus and the prophets, and also drove us out. They displease God and are hostile to all men,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.16'>hindering us from speaking to the Gentiles so that they may be saved; with the result that they always fill up the measure of their sins. But wrath has come upon them at last.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.17'>But since we were taken away from you, brethren, for a short time, in person not in heart, we endeavored the more eagerly and with great desire to see you face to face.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.18'>For we wanted to come to youI, Paul, again and againbut Satan hindered us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.19'>For who is our hope or joy or crown of exultation? Is it not even you, in the presence of our Lord Jesus at his coming?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.2.20'>For you are our glory and joy.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Thess.3'>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.3.1'>Therefore when we could endure it no longer, we thought it best to be left behind at Athens alone,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.3.2'>and we sent Timothy, our brother and God's fellow worker in the gospel of Christ, to strengthen and encourage you in your faith,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.3.3'>so that no one would be unsettled by these afflictions. You yourselves know that we have been destined for this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.3.4'>For indeed when we were with you, we kept telling you in advance that we were going to suffer affliction; and so it came to pass, as you know.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.3.5'>For this reason, when I could endure it no longer, I also sent to find out about your faith, for fear that the tempter might have tempted you, and our labor would be in vain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.3.6'>But now that Timothy has come to us from you, and has brought us the good news of your faith and love and reported that you always remember us kindly and long to see us, just as we long to see you</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.3.7'>for this reason, brethren, in all our distress and affliction we were comforted about you through your faith;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.3.8'>for now we really live, if you stand firm in the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.3.9'>For what thanksgiving can we render to God for you in return for all the joy which we feel for your sake before our God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.3.10'>as we night and day keep praying most earnestly that we may see you face to face and supply what is lacking in your faith?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.3.11'>Now may our God and Father himself, and our Lord Jesus, direct our way to you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.3.12'>and may the Lord make you increase and abound in love for one another and for all, just as we do for you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.3.13'>so that he may establish your hearts without blame in holiness before our God and Father, at the coming of our Lord Jesus with all his saints.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Thess.4'>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.1'>Finally, brethren, we request and exhort you in the Lord Jesus, that as you learned from us how you ought to live and to please God, just as you are doing, you do so more and more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.2'>For you know what instructions we gave you by the authority of the Lord Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.3'>For this is the will of God, your sanctification: that is, that you should abstain from sexual immorality;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.4'>that each one of you know how to take his own spouse for himself in holiness and honor,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.5'>not in the passion of lust like the heathen, who do not know God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.6'>and that no man transgress and wrong his brother in this matter because the Lord is the avenger in all these things, just as we also told you before and solemnly warned you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.7'>For God has not called us to impurity, but to holiness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.8'>Therefore, he who rejects this instruction does not reject man but God, who gives you his Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.9'>Now concerning love of the brethren you have no need to have any one write to you, for you yourselves have been taught by God to love one another;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.10'>and indeed you do love all the brethren throughout Macedonia. But we urge you, brethren, to do so more and more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.11'>Make it your ambition to lead a quiet life, to mind your own business and to work with your hands, just as we told you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.12'>so that your daily life may win the respect of outsiders and so that you will not be dependent on anyone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.13'>But we do not want you to be ignorant, brethren, about those who are asleep, so that you will not grieve as do the rest who have no hope.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.14'>For if we believe that Jesus died and rose again, even so God will bring with him those who have fallen asleep in Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.15'>For this we declare to you by the word of the Lord, that we who are alive, who are left until the coming of the Lord, will not precede those who have fallen asleep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.16'>For the Lord himself will descend from heaven, with a loud command, with the voice of the archangel and with the trumpet call of God, and the dead in Christ will rise first.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.17'>Then we who are alive and are left will be caught up together with them in the clouds to meet the Lord in the air, and so we shall always be with the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.4.18'>Therefore comfort one another with these words.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Thess.5'>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.1'>Now as to the times and the seasons, brethren, you have no need to have anything written to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.2'>For you yourselves know well that the day of the Lord will come like a thief in the night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.3'>While people are saying, »Peace and safety,« then destruction will come upon them suddenly as labor pains upon a woman with child, and they will not escape.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.4'>But you, brethren, are not in darkness so that this day should surprise you like a thief.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.5'>For you are all sons of light and sons of the day; we are not of the night or of darkness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.6'>So then let us not sleep, as others do, but let us be alert and sober.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.7'>For those who sleep, sleep at night; and those who get drunk, get drunk at night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.8'>But, since we belong to the day, let us be sober, and put on the breastplate of faith and love, and as a helmet the hope of salvation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.9'>For God has not destined us to wrath, but to obtain salvation through our Lord Jesus Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.10'>who died for us, so that whether we are awake or asleep, we will live together with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.11'>Therefore encourage one another and build up one another, just as you also are doing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.12'>But we ask you, brethren, to respect those who labor among you and are over you in the Lord and admonish you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.13'>and that you esteem them very highly in love because of their work. Live in peace with one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.14'>And we urge you, brethren, admonish the idlers, encourage the fainthearted, help the weak, be patient with everyone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.15'>See that none of you repays evil for evil, but always seek to do good to one another and to all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.16'>Rejoice always,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.17'>pray without ceasing,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.18'>give thanks in all circumstances; for this is God's will for you in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.19'>Do not quench the Spirit;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.20'>do not despise prophecies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.21'>But test everything; hold fast to what is good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.22'>Abstain from every form of evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.23'>Now may the God of peace himself sanctify you entirely; and may your whole spirit and soul and body be kept blameless at the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.24'>He who calls you is faithful, and he will do it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.25'>Brethren, pray for us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.26'>Greet all the brethren with a holy kiss.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.27'>I charge you by the Lord to have this letter read to all the brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Thess.5.28'>The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>