<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='TCE' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='TCE'>
        <title>The Common Edition: New Testament</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>
                      ---------------------------------
                      The Common Edition: New Testament
                             --------------------
                             All rights reserved.
                      ----------------------------------
                      Copyright © Timothy E. Clontz 1999


The Common Edition: New Testament
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~

  The Common Edition is the result of a decade long study of the New Testament
  and numerous English translations in the modern church. The goals for this
  edition are:

        1.  To be accurate to the Greek Scriptures and yet highly readable, 

        2.  To balance traditional wording with modern English, and

        3.  To reflect the standard Christian understanding and wording of the
            New Testament.

  The purpose of these goals is to create a standardized New Testament for the
  modern English reader.

  There are two ways to create a standardized text. [The first way] is to
  create a text of such surpassing scholarship and expression that it
  practically eliminates the use of other editions for decades or perhaps
  centuries. [The second way] is to isolate what the most widely used
  editions have in common, eliminate what they do not have in common, and
  place the results in a single text.

  
  The King James Version succeeded in both of these two ways.

  Over the past hundred years there have been numerous attempts to create a
  new English standard Bible. Each of these attempts has sought to produce a
  standardized edition in the first way I have described. The Common Edition
  New Testament follows the second method.

  A standardized edition of any work seeks a balance between extremes. The
  most literally accurate version may not be the easiest to read. The most
  traditionally worded may not be very modern.

  It cannot have a target audience; what is best for preachers and theologians
  may not be best for the daily devotional reader.

  Finally, a standardized edition cannot be innovative. One reviewer gave me
  the highest compliment I could receive when he said, "there's nothing new
  about it!"

  I hope that readers will find in these pages exactly what they would expect
  from a standardized edition, and that no matter what versions they have used
  in the past, they will find something familiar here.

   
  This initial release into the public domain is intended for free
  distribution. The text itself is copyrighted, with the following provisions:

        1.  The Common Edition: New Testament may be copied and distributed in
            electronic or printed form for free.

        2.  It may be bound or downloaded for personal use or for a gift.

        3.  It may not be sold by anyone other than the editor. 

        4.  The text may not be altered.

        5.  No more than 10,000 words may be included in a document published
            for sale without the express written permission of the editor.

        6.  No more than 20% of a document published for sale may be quoted
            from this edition without the express written permission of the
            editor. 

        7.  All distributions of the Common Edition, and all documents which
            quote the Common Edition, must contain the following copyright
            notice: Common Edition New Testament, Copyright © Timothy E.
            Clontz 1999. All rights reserved.

  If you find a phrase or word which is unclear, or which you believe needs
  review, please email the editor at {teclontz@aol.com}.

   
  Although it is not appropriate to dedicate a New Testament to any
  individual, the editor would like to give his gratitude to the many people
  who have labored to preserve this text. Those who penned the autographs
  often faced ridicule or death. Nameless monks sleep in the dust, who
  faithfully copied one manuscript to another down through the centuries. By
  the time of the Reformation, William Tyndale had one wish: to make the
  Christian Bible available in English to the poorest farmhand in England. For
  this crime he was strangled and burned at the stake.

  And then there are those who have simply loved these words enough to live by
  their highest ideals. Without the goodness of their lives no one would
  believe there to be anything Holy about a Bible. One such godly man was M.
  D. Barefield, who learned to read as an adult just so that he could make
  this word his own. My grandfather, Bill Clontz, who will always be an
  example for my family, gradually bought larger and larger print Bibles and
  finally began using the Bible on tape - just to keep the Word fresh in his
  heart. Such people always stay fresh in the hearts of those who have known
  them, and their love for God is contagious.


  Timothy Clontz
  March 14, 1999
  
  </description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>TCE</identifier>
        <source>http://www.ccel.org/olb/tolbss/zipfiles/translations/twenty.exe
            http://www.ccel.org/olb/tolbss/zipfiles/translations/comed10d.zip</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='2Tim'>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.1'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.1'>Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by the will of God, according to the promise of life that is in Christ Jesus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.2'>to Timothy, my beloved son: grace, mercy and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.3'>I thank God, whom I serve with a clear conscience the way my forefathers did, as I constantly remember you in my prayers night and day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.4'>As I recall your tears, I long to see you, so that I may be filled with joy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.5'>For I am reminded of your sincere faith, which first dwelt in your grandmother Lois, and your mother Eunice, and I am sure is in you as well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.6'>For this reason I remind you to fan into flame the gift of God which is in you through the laying on of my hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.7'>For God did not give us a spirit of timidity, but a spirit of power and love and self-discipline.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.8'>So do not be ashamed to testify of our Lord or of me his prisoner, but join with me in suffering for the gospel according to the power of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.9'>who has saved us and called us with a holy calling, not according to our works, but according to his own purpose and the grace which was granted us in Christ Jesus from all eternity,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.10'>but has now been revealed through the appearing of our Savior Jesus Christ, who has abolished death and brought life and immortality to light through the gospel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.11'>For this gospel I was appointed a preacher and an apostle and a teacher.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.12'>For this reason I also suffer as I do. But I am not ashamed, for I know whom I have believed and I am convinced that he is able to guard what I have entrusted to him until that day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.13'>Follow the pattern of sound words which you have heard from me, in the faith and love which are in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.14'>Guard, through the Holy Spirit who dwells in us, the treasure that has been entrusted to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.15'>You are aware of the fact that all who are in Asia turned away from me, among whom are Phygelus and Hermogenes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.16'>May the Lord grant mercy to the household of Onesiphorus, for he often refreshed me and was not ashamed of my chains;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.17'>but when he was in Rome, he eagerly searched for me and found me</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.1.18'>may the Lord grant him to find mercy from the Lord on that Dayand you know very well all the service he rendered at Ephesus.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.2'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.1'>You then, my son, be strong in the grace that is in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.2'>And the things you have heard from me in the presence of many witnesses, entrust to faithful men who will be able to teach others also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.3'>Share in hardship as a good soldier of Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.4'>No soldier in active service gets entangled in civilian affairs, since his aim is to please the one who enlisted him as a soldier.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.5'>Also if anyone competes as an athlete, he does not win the prize unless he competes according to the rules.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.6'>The hard-working farmer ought to be the first to receive his share of the crops.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.7'>Consider what I say, for the Lord will give you understanding in everything.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.8'>Remember Jesus Christ, risen from the dead, descended from David according to my gospel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.9'>for which I am suffering even to the point of wearing chains like a criminal. But the word of God is not chained.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.10'>Therefore I endure everything for the sake of the elect, that they too may obtain the salvation that is in Christ Jesus, with eternal glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.11'>Here is a trustworthy saying: if we died with him, we will also live with him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.12'>if we endure, we will also reign with him;if we deny him, he also will deny us;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.13'>if we are faithless, he remains faithful,for he cannot deny himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.14'>Remind them of these things, and charge them in the presence of God to avoid disputing about words, which does no good, but only ruins the hearers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.15'>Do your best to present yourself to God as one approved, a workman who does not need to be ashamed, rightly handling the word of truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.16'>Avoid godless chatter, for it will lead people into more and more ungodliness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.17'>and their talk will spread like gangrene. Among them are Hymenaeus and Philetus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.18'>who have gone astray from the truth. They say that the resurrection has already taken place, and upset the faith of some.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.19'>Nevertheless, God's firm foundation stands, having this seal: »The Lord knows those who are his,« and, »Everyone who names the name of the Lord must turn away from wickedness.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.20'>In a large house there are not only vessels of gold and silver but also of wood and earthenware, and some for noble use, some for ignoble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.21'>If anyone cleanses himself from what is ignoble, he will be a vessel for noble purposes, made holy, useful to the Master and prepared to do any good work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.22'>Now flee from youthful lusts, and pursue righteousness, faith, love and peace, along with those who call on the Lord from a pure heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.23'>Don't have anything to do with foolish and stupid arguments, because you know that they produce quarrels.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.24'>And the Lord's servant must not be quarrelsome, but he must be kind to everyone, able to teach, patient when wronged,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.25'>with gentleness correcting those who are in opposition, if perhaps God will grant them repentance leading to the knowledge of the truth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.2.26'>and they may come to their senses and escape from the snare of the devil, having been held captive by him to do his will.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.3'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.1'>But understand this, that in the last days there will come times of stress.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.2'>For men will be lovers of self, lovers of money, boastful, arrogant, abusive, disobedient to their parents, ungrateful, unholy,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.3'>unloving, unforgiving, slanderous, without self-control, brutal, haters of good,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.4'>treacherous, reckless, conceited, lovers of pleasure rather than lovers of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.5'>holding a form of godliness but denying its power. Avoid such people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.6'>For among them are those who make their way into households and capture weak women, weighed down with sins and swayed by various impulses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.7'>always learning and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.8'>Just as Jannes and Jambres opposed Moses, so these men also oppose the truth, men of depraved mind, rejected in regard to the faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.9'>But they will not get very far, for their folly will be plain to all, as was that of those two men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.10'>You, however, know all about my teaching, my conduct, my purpose, faith, patience, love, endurance,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.11'>persecutions, and sufferings, such as happened to me at Antioch, at Iconium and at Lystra; what persecutions I endured, yet the Lord rescued me from them all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.12'>Indeed all who desire to live a godly life in Christ Jesus will be persecuted,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.13'>while evil men and impostors will go from bad to worse, deceiving and being deceived.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.14'>But as for you, continue in what you have learned and have become convinced of, knowing from whom you learned it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.15'>and how from childhood you have known the sacred writings which are able to make you wise for salvation through faith in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.16'>All scripture is inspired by God and profitable for teaching, for reproof, for correction, and for training in righteousness;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.3.17'>so that the man of God may be complete, equipped for every good work.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='2Tim.4'>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.1'>I solemnly charge you in the presence of God and of Christ Jesus, who is to judge the living and the dead, and by his appearing and his kingdom:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.2'>preach the word; be ready in season and out of season; correct, rebuke, and exhort, with great patience and instruction.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.3'>For the time will come when they will not endure sound doctrine; but having itching ears, they will accumulate for themselves teachers to suit their own desires,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.4'>and will turn their ears away from the truth and turn aside to myths.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.5'>But you, be sober in all things, endure hardship, do the work of an evangelist, fulfill your ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.6'>For I am already being poured out as a drink offering, and the time of my departure has come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.7'>I have fought the good fight, I have finished the race, I have kept the faith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.8'>In the future there is laid up for me the crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous Judge, will award to me on that day; and not only to me, but also to all who have loved his appearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.9'>Do your best to come to me soon;</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.10'>for Demas, having loved this present world, has deserted me and gone to Thessalonica. Crescens has gone to Galatia, and Titus to Dalmatia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.11'>Only Luke is with me. Get Mark and bring him with you, for he is useful to me in my ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.12'>But Tychicus I have sent to Ephesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.13'>When you come, bring the cloak that I left with Carpus at Troas, and the books, especially the parchments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.14'>Alexander the coppersmith did me great harm; the Lord will repay him for his deeds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.15'>Be on guard against him yourself, for he strongly opposed our message.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.16'>At my first defense no one came to my support, but all deserted me; may it not be counted against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.17'>But the Lord stood at my side and gave me strength, so that through me the message might be fully proclaimed and all the Gentiles might hear it. And I was rescued from the lion's mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.18'>The Lord will rescue me from every evil attack and will bring me safely to his heavenly kingdom. To him be the glory for ever and ever. Amen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.19'>Greet Prisca and Aquila, and the household of Onesiphorus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.20'>Erastus remained at Corinth, but Trophimus I left sick at Miletus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.21'>Do your best to come before winter. Eubulus greets you, and so do Pudens and Linus and Claudia and all the brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2Tim.4.22'>The Lord be with your spirit. Grace be with you.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>