<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='TCE' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='TCE'>
        <title>The Common Edition: New Testament</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>
                      ---------------------------------
                      The Common Edition: New Testament
                             --------------------
                             All rights reserved.
                      ----------------------------------
                      Copyright © Timothy E. Clontz 1999


The Common Edition: New Testament
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~

  The Common Edition is the result of a decade long study of the New Testament
  and numerous English translations in the modern church. The goals for this
  edition are:

        1.  To be accurate to the Greek Scriptures and yet highly readable, 

        2.  To balance traditional wording with modern English, and

        3.  To reflect the standard Christian understanding and wording of the
            New Testament.

  The purpose of these goals is to create a standardized New Testament for the
  modern English reader.

  There are two ways to create a standardized text. [The first way] is to
  create a text of such surpassing scholarship and expression that it
  practically eliminates the use of other editions for decades or perhaps
  centuries. [The second way] is to isolate what the most widely used
  editions have in common, eliminate what they do not have in common, and
  place the results in a single text.

  
  The King James Version succeeded in both of these two ways.

  Over the past hundred years there have been numerous attempts to create a
  new English standard Bible. Each of these attempts has sought to produce a
  standardized edition in the first way I have described. The Common Edition
  New Testament follows the second method.

  A standardized edition of any work seeks a balance between extremes. The
  most literally accurate version may not be the easiest to read. The most
  traditionally worded may not be very modern.

  It cannot have a target audience; what is best for preachers and theologians
  may not be best for the daily devotional reader.

  Finally, a standardized edition cannot be innovative. One reviewer gave me
  the highest compliment I could receive when he said, "there's nothing new
  about it!"

  I hope that readers will find in these pages exactly what they would expect
  from a standardized edition, and that no matter what versions they have used
  in the past, they will find something familiar here.

   
  This initial release into the public domain is intended for free
  distribution. The text itself is copyrighted, with the following provisions:

        1.  The Common Edition: New Testament may be copied and distributed in
            electronic or printed form for free.

        2.  It may be bound or downloaded for personal use or for a gift.

        3.  It may not be sold by anyone other than the editor. 

        4.  The text may not be altered.

        5.  No more than 10,000 words may be included in a document published
            for sale without the express written permission of the editor.

        6.  No more than 20% of a document published for sale may be quoted
            from this edition without the express written permission of the
            editor. 

        7.  All distributions of the Common Edition, and all documents which
            quote the Common Edition, must contain the following copyright
            notice: Common Edition New Testament, Copyright © Timothy E.
            Clontz 1999. All rights reserved.

  If you find a phrase or word which is unclear, or which you believe needs
  review, please email the editor at {teclontz@aol.com}.

   
  Although it is not appropriate to dedicate a New Testament to any
  individual, the editor would like to give his gratitude to the many people
  who have labored to preserve this text. Those who penned the autographs
  often faced ridicule or death. Nameless monks sleep in the dust, who
  faithfully copied one manuscript to another down through the centuries. By
  the time of the Reformation, William Tyndale had one wish: to make the
  Christian Bible available in English to the poorest farmhand in England. For
  this crime he was strangled and burned at the stake.

  And then there are those who have simply loved these words enough to live by
  their highest ideals. Without the goodness of their lives no one would
  believe there to be anything Holy about a Bible. One such godly man was M.
  D. Barefield, who learned to read as an adult just so that he could make
  this word his own. My grandfather, Bill Clontz, who will always be an
  example for my family, gradually bought larger and larger print Bibles and
  finally began using the Bible on tape - just to keep the Word fresh in his
  heart. Such people always stay fresh in the hearts of those who have known
  them, and their love for God is contagious.


  Timothy Clontz
  March 14, 1999
  
  </description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>TCE</identifier>
        <source>http://www.ccel.org/olb/tolbss/zipfiles/translations/twenty.exe
            http://www.ccel.org/olb/tolbss/zipfiles/translations/comed10d.zip</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Eph'>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.1'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.1'>Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, to the saints who are in Ephesus and faithful in Christ Jesus:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.2'>grace and peace to you from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.3'>Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who has blessed us with every spiritual blessing in the heavenly places in Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.4'>just as he chose us in him before the foundation of the world, that we would be holy and blameless before him. In love</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.5'>he predestined us to be adopted as his sons through Jesus Christ, according to the good pleasure of his will,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.6'>to the praise of his glorious grace, which he freely bestowed on us in the Beloved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.7'>In him we have redemption through his blood, the forgiveness of our trespasses, according to the riches of his grace</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.8'>which he lavished on us. In all wisdom and insight</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.9'>he made known to us the mystery of his will according to his good pleasure, which he purposed in Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.10'>as a plan for the fullness of the times, to unite all things in Christ, things in heaven and things on earth. In him</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.11'>also we have obtained an inheritance, having been predestined according to the purpose of him who works all things after the counsel of his will,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.12'>in order that we, who were the first to hope in Christ, would be for the praise of his glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.13'>In him, you also have heard the word of truth, the gospel of your salvation. Having also believed, you were sealed in him with the promised Holy Spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.14'>who is a deposit guaranteeing our inheritance, until the redemption of those who are God's possessionto the praise of his glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.15'>For this reason, ever since I heard of your faith in the Lord Jesus and your love for all the saints,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.16'>I do not cease giving thanks for you, remembering you in my prayers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.17'>that the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of glory, may give to you a spirit of wisdom and of revelation in the knowledge of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.18'>I pray also that the eyes of your heart may be enlightened, so that you may know what is the hope to which he has called you, what are the riches of his glorious inheritance in the saints,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.19'>and what is the immeasurable greatness of his power in us who believe. These are in accordance with the working of the strength of his might</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.20'>which he worked in Christ when he raised him from the dead and seated him at his right hand in the heavenly places,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.21'>far above all rule and authority and power and dominion, and above every name that is named, not only in this age but also in the one to come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.22'>And he put all things under his feet and gave him to be the head over all things for the church,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.1.23'>which is his body, the fullness of him who fills all in all.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.2'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.1'>And you were dead in your trespasses and sins,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.2'>in which you formerly walked according to the course of this world, according to the prince of the power of the air, the spirit that is now at work in the sons of disobedience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.3'>Among them we all once lived in the lusts of our flesh, following the desires of flesh and mind, and so we were by nature children of wrath, like the rest of mankind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.4'>But God, who is rich in mercy, because of his great love with which he loved us,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.5'>even when we were dead in our transgressions, made us alive together with Christ (by grace you have been saved),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.6'>and raised us up with him, and seated us with him in the heavenly places in Christ Jesus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.7'>so that in the coming ages he might show the surpassing riches of his grace in kindness toward us in Christ Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.8'>For by grace you have been saved through faith; and this is not of yourselves, it is the gift of God</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.9'>not as a result of works, so that no one may boast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.10'>For we are his workmanship, created in Christ Jesus for good works, which God prepared beforehand, that we would walk in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.11'>Therefore remember that formerly you, the Gentiles in the flesh, who are called »Uncircumcision« by the so-called »Circumcision,« which is performed in the flesh by human hands</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.12'>remember that you were at that time separate from Christ, excluded from the commonwealth of Israel, and strangers to the covenants of promise, having no hope and without God in the world.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.13'>But now in Christ Jesus you who once were far off have been brought near in the blood of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.14'>For he himself is our peace, who has made us both one and has broken down the barrier, the dividing wall of hostility,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.15'>by abolishing in his flesh the hostility, which is the Law of commandments and ordinances, so that he might create in himself one new man out of the two, thus making peace,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.16'>and might reconcile them both to God in one body through the cross, by which he put to death the hostility.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.17'>And he came and preached peace to you who were far away, and peace to those who were near;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.18'>for through him we both have our access in one Spirit to the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.19'>So then you are no longer strangers and aliens, but you are fellow citizens with the saints, and are members of God's household,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.20'>having been built on the foundation of the apostles and prophets, Christ Jesus himself being the cornerstone,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.21'>in whom the whole building is joined together and rises to become a holy temple in the Lord;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.2.22'>in whom you also are being built together into a dwelling of God in the Spirit.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.3'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.1'>For this reason I, Paul, am the prisoner of Christ Jesus for the sake of you Gentiles</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.2'>assuming that you have heard of the stewardship of God's grace that was given to me for you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.3'>that is, the mystery made known to me by revelation, as I have already written briefly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.4'>When you read this, you can understand my insight into the mystery of Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.5'>which was not made known to the sons of men in other generations as it has now been revealed to his holy apostles and prophets by the Spirit;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.6'>that is, how the Gentiles are fellow heirs and members of the same body, and partakers of the promise in Christ Jesus through the gospel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.7'>Of this gospel I was made a minister according to the gift of God's grace which was given me by the working of his power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.8'>To me, though I am the very least of all the saints, this grace was given, to preach to the Gentiles the unsearchable riches of Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.9'>and to make plain to everyone the administration of the mystery which for ages has been hidden in God who created all things;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.10'>so that the manifold wisdom of God might now be made known through the church to the rulers and authorities in the heavenly places.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.11'>This was according to the eternal purpose which he carried out in Christ Jesus our Lord,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.12'>in whom we have boldness and confidence of access through our faith in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.13'>Therefore I ask you not to lose heart at my tribulations for you, which are your glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.14'>For this reason I bow my knees before the Father,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.15'>from whom every family in heaven and on earth derives its name,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.16'>that according to the riches of his glory he may grant you to be strengthened with power through his Spirit in the inner man,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.17'>so that Christ may dwell in your hearts through faith; and that you, being rooted and grounded in love,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.18'>may have power to comprehend with all the saints what is the breadth and length and height and depth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.19'>and to know the love of Christ which surpasses knowledge, that you may be filled with all the fullness of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.20'>Now to him who is able to do far more abundantly than all that we ask or think, according to the power that works within us,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.3.21'>to him be glory in the church and in Christ Jesus to all generations, for ever and ever. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.4'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.1'>I therefore, a prisoner for the Lord, beg you to lead a life worthy of the calling to which you have been called,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.2'>with all humility and gentleness, with patience, showing tolerance for one another in love,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.3'>being diligent to preserve the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.4'>There is one body and one Spirit, just as you were called to the one hope that belongs to your call,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.5'>one Lord, one faith, one baptism,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.6'>one God and Father of all, who is over all and through all and in all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.7'>But to each one of us grace was given according to the measure of Christ's gift.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.8'>Therefore it says, »When he ascended on high, he led a host of captives,and he gave gifts to men.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.9'>(In saying, »He ascended,« what does it mean except that he had also descended into the lower parts of the earth?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.10'>He who descended is also he who ascended far above all the heavens, so that he might fill all things.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.11'>And he gave some to be apostles, some prophets, some evangelists, some pastors and teachers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.12'>to equip the saints for the work of service, for the building up of the body of Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.13'>until we all attain to the unity of the faith and of the knowledge of the Son of God, to become mature, to the measure of the stature of the fullness of Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.14'>As a result, we are no longer to be children, tossed here and there by waves and carried about by every wind of doctrine, by the cunning of men, by their craftiness in deceitful scheming.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.15'>But speaking the truth in love, we are to grow up in all aspects into him, who is the head, into Christ,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.16'>from whom the whole body, being joined and held together by what every joint supplies, according to the proper working of each part, causes the growth of the body and builds itself up in love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.17'>Now this I affirm and testify in the Lord, that you must no longer live as the Gentiles do, in the futility of their minds,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.18'>they are darkened in their understanding, alienated from the life of God because of the ignorance that is in them, due to the hardness of their heart;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.19'>and they, having become callous, have given themselves over to sensuality, greedy for the practice of every kind of impurity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.20'>But you did not learn Christ in this way,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.21'>assuming that you have heard about him and were taught in him, as the truth is in Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.22'>You were taught, with regard to your former manner of life, to put off your old self, which is being corrupted by its deceitful lusts;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.23'>and be renewed in the spirit of your minds,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.24'>and put on the new nature, created after the likeness of God in true righteousness and holiness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.25'>Therefore, laying aside falsehood, each one of you must speak truth with his neighbor, for we are members of one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.26'>Be angry, and yet do not sin; do not let the sun go down on your anger,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.27'>and do not give the devil an opportunity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.28'>He who has been stealing must steal no longer, but rather must labor, doing useful work with his own hands, so that he may have something to share with those in need.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.29'>Let no unwholesome talk come out of your mouths, but only such as is good for building others up according to the need of the moment, that it may impart grace to those who hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.30'>And do not grieve the Holy Spirit of God, in whom you were sealed for the day of redemption.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.31'>Let all bitterness and wrath and anger and clamor and slander be put away from you, along with all malice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.4.32'>Be kind and tenderhearted to one another, forgiving each other, just as in Christ God forgave you.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.5'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.1'>Therefore be imitators of God, as beloved children;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.2'>and walk in love, just as Christ loved us and gave himself up for us as a fragrant offering and sacrifice to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.3'>But immorality or any impurity or greed must not even be named among you, as is proper among saints.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.4'>And there must be no filthiness and silly talk, or coarse jesting, which are not fitting, but rather let there be thanksgiving.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.5'>For of this you can be sure, that no immoral, impure, or covetous personsuch a man is an idolaterhas any inheritance in the kingdom of Christ and of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.6'>Let no one deceive you with empty words, for because of these things the wrath of God comes upon the sons of disobedience.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.7'>Therefore do not be partners with them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.8'>for once you were darkness, but now you are light in the Lord; walk as children of light</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.9'>(for the fruit of the light consists in all goodness and righteousness and truth),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.10'>and try to learn what is pleasing to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.11'>Do not participate in the unfruitful deeds of darkness, but instead expose them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.12'>For it is a shame even to speak of the things that they do in secret.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.13'>But all things become visible when they are exposed by the light, for everything that becomes visible is light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.14'>For this reason it is said, »Awake, O sleeper,and arise from the dead,and Christ will shine on you.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.15'>Be careful, then, how you walk, not as unwise men, but as wise,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.16'>making the most of your time, because the days are evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.17'>Therefore do not be foolish, but understand what the will of the Lord is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.18'>And do not get drunk with wine, for that is debauchery; but be filled with the Spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.19'>speaking to one another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing and making melody with your heart to the Lord,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.20'>always giving thanks to God the Father for everything, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.21'>Be subject to one another out of reverence for Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.22'>Wives, be subject to your husbands, as to the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.23'>For the husband is the head of the wife as Christ is the head of the church, his body, of which he is himself the Savior.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.24'>As the church is subject to Christ, so let wives also be subject to their husbands in everything.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.25'>Husbands, love your wives, just as Christ loved the church and gave himself up for her,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.26'>that he might sanctify her, having cleansed her by the washing of water with the word,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.27'>that he might present the church to himself in all her glory, without spot or wrinkle or any such thing, that she might be holy and blameless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.28'>So husbands ought also to love their wives as their own bodies. He who loves his wife loves himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.29'>For no one ever hated his own flesh, but nourishes and cherishes it, just as Christ also does the church,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.30'>because we are members of his body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.31'>»For this reason a man shall leave his father and mother and be joined to his wife, and the two shall become one flesh.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.32'>This is a profound mystery; but I am saying that it refers to Christ and the church.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.5.33'>However, each one of you must also love his wife as himself, and the wife must see that she respects her husband.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Eph.6'>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.1'>Children, obey your parents in the Lord, for this is right.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.2'>»Honor your father and mother« (which is the first commandment with a promise),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.3'>»that it may be well with you and that you may live long on the earth.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.4'>Fathers, do not provoke your children to anger, but bring them up in the discipline and instruction of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.5'>Slaves, be obedient to those who are your masters according to the flesh, with fear and trembling, in sincerity of heart, as to Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.6'>not in the way of eye-service, as men-pleasers, but as slaves of Christ, doing the will of God from the heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.7'>Render service with good will, as to the Lord, and not to men,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.8'>knowing that whatever good thing each one does, this he will receive back from the Lord, whether he is a slave or free.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.9'>Masters, do the same to them, and give up threatening, knowing that he who is both their Master and yours is in heaven, and that there is no partiality with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.10'>Finally, be strong in the Lord and in the strength of his might.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.11'>Put on the full armor of God, so that you may be able to stand against the schemes of the devil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.12'>For our struggle is not against flesh and blood, but against the rulers, against the powers, against the world forces of this darkness, against the spiritual forces of wickedness in the heavenly places.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.13'>Therefore, take up the full armor of God, so that you may be able to resist in the evil day, and having done everything, to stand firm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.14'>Stand firm therefore, having girded your loins with truth, and having put on the breastplate of righteousness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.15'>and having shod your feet with the preparation of the gospel of peace;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.16'>in addition to all this, taking up the shield of faith, with which you can extinguish all the flaming arrows of the evil one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.17'>And take the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the spirit, which is the word of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.18'>Pray at all times in the Spirit, with all prayer and petition. And with this in view, keep alert with all perseverance and petition for all the saints,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.19'>and also pray for me, that in the opening of my mouth, utterance may be given me so that I will fearlessly make known the mystery of the gospel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.20'>for which I am an ambassador in chains; that I may declare it boldly, as I ought to speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.21'>Tychicus, the beloved brother and faithful minister in the Lord, will tell you everything, so that you also may know how I am and what I am doing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.22'>I have sent him to you for this very purpose, that you may know how we are, and that he may encourage your hearts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.23'>Peace be to the brethren, and love with faith, from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Eph.6.24'>Grace be with all who love our Lord Jesus Christ with an undying love.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>