<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='TCE' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='TCE'>
        <title>The Common Edition: New Testament</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>
                      ---------------------------------
                      The Common Edition: New Testament
                             --------------------
                             All rights reserved.
                      ----------------------------------
                      Copyright © Timothy E. Clontz 1999


The Common Edition: New Testament
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~

  The Common Edition is the result of a decade long study of the New Testament
  and numerous English translations in the modern church. The goals for this
  edition are:

        1.  To be accurate to the Greek Scriptures and yet highly readable, 

        2.  To balance traditional wording with modern English, and

        3.  To reflect the standard Christian understanding and wording of the
            New Testament.

  The purpose of these goals is to create a standardized New Testament for the
  modern English reader.

  There are two ways to create a standardized text. [The first way] is to
  create a text of such surpassing scholarship and expression that it
  practically eliminates the use of other editions for decades or perhaps
  centuries. [The second way] is to isolate what the most widely used
  editions have in common, eliminate what they do not have in common, and
  place the results in a single text.

  
  The King James Version succeeded in both of these two ways.

  Over the past hundred years there have been numerous attempts to create a
  new English standard Bible. Each of these attempts has sought to produce a
  standardized edition in the first way I have described. The Common Edition
  New Testament follows the second method.

  A standardized edition of any work seeks a balance between extremes. The
  most literally accurate version may not be the easiest to read. The most
  traditionally worded may not be very modern.

  It cannot have a target audience; what is best for preachers and theologians
  may not be best for the daily devotional reader.

  Finally, a standardized edition cannot be innovative. One reviewer gave me
  the highest compliment I could receive when he said, "there's nothing new
  about it!"

  I hope that readers will find in these pages exactly what they would expect
  from a standardized edition, and that no matter what versions they have used
  in the past, they will find something familiar here.

   
  This initial release into the public domain is intended for free
  distribution. The text itself is copyrighted, with the following provisions:

        1.  The Common Edition: New Testament may be copied and distributed in
            electronic or printed form for free.

        2.  It may be bound or downloaded for personal use or for a gift.

        3.  It may not be sold by anyone other than the editor. 

        4.  The text may not be altered.

        5.  No more than 10,000 words may be included in a document published
            for sale without the express written permission of the editor.

        6.  No more than 20% of a document published for sale may be quoted
            from this edition without the express written permission of the
            editor. 

        7.  All distributions of the Common Edition, and all documents which
            quote the Common Edition, must contain the following copyright
            notice: Common Edition New Testament, Copyright © Timothy E.
            Clontz 1999. All rights reserved.

  If you find a phrase or word which is unclear, or which you believe needs
  review, please email the editor at {teclontz@aol.com}.

   
  Although it is not appropriate to dedicate a New Testament to any
  individual, the editor would like to give his gratitude to the many people
  who have labored to preserve this text. Those who penned the autographs
  often faced ridicule or death. Nameless monks sleep in the dust, who
  faithfully copied one manuscript to another down through the centuries. By
  the time of the Reformation, William Tyndale had one wish: to make the
  Christian Bible available in English to the poorest farmhand in England. For
  this crime he was strangled and burned at the stake.

  And then there are those who have simply loved these words enough to live by
  their highest ideals. Without the goodness of their lives no one would
  believe there to be anything Holy about a Bible. One such godly man was M.
  D. Barefield, who learned to read as an adult just so that he could make
  this word his own. My grandfather, Bill Clontz, who will always be an
  example for my family, gradually bought larger and larger print Bibles and
  finally began using the Bible on tape - just to keep the Word fresh in his
  heart. Such people always stay fresh in the hearts of those who have known
  them, and their love for God is contagious.


  Timothy Clontz
  March 14, 1999
  
  </description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>TCE</identifier>
        <source>http://www.ccel.org/olb/tolbss/zipfiles/translations/twenty.exe
            http://www.ccel.org/olb/tolbss/zipfiles/translations/comed10d.zip</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Jude'>
      <chapter osisID='Jude.1'>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.1'>Jude, a servant of Jesus Christ and brother of James, to those who are called, beloved in God the Father and kept for Jesus Christ:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.2'>may mercy, peace, and love be multiplied to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.3'>Beloved, although I was very eager to write you about our common salvation, I felt the necessity to write to you appealing that you contend for the faith which was once for all delivered to the saints.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.4'>For certain persons have crept in secretly, those who were long ago marked out for this condemnation, ungodly persons who turn the grace of our God into licentiousness and deny our only Master and Lord, Jesus Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.5'>Now I desire to remind you, though you were once for all fully informed, that the Lord who saved a people out of the land of Egypt, afterward destroyed those who did not believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.6'>And the angels who did not keep their own domain, but abandoned their proper abode, he has kept in eternal chains under darkness for the judgment of the great day,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.7'>just as Sodom and Gomorrah and the surrounding cities, which likewise acted immorally and indulged in strange flesh, serve as an example by undergoing a punishment of eternal fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.8'>Yet in the same way these men in their dreamings defile the flesh, reject authority, and revile the glorious ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.9'>But Michael the archangel, when he disputed with the devil and argued about the body of Moses, did not dare pronounce against him a reviling judgment, but said, »The Lord rebuke you!«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.10'>But these men revile whatever they do not understand; and the things that they know by instinct, like unreasoning animals do, by these things they are destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.11'>Woe to them! For they have gone the way of Cain, and for the sake of gain they have rushed headlong into the Balaam's error, and perished in Korah's rebellion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.12'>These are the men who are blemishes in your love feasts when they feast with you without fear, caring for themselves; clouds without water, carried along by winds; autumn trees without fruit, twice dead, uprooted;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.13'>wild waves of the sea, casting up their own shame like foam; wandering stars, for whom the blackest darkness has been reserved forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.14'>It was also about these men that Enoch, in the seventh generation from Adam, prophesied, saying, »Behold, the Lord came with many thousands of his holy ones,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.15'>to execute judgment on all, and to convict all the ungodly of all their ungodly deeds which they have done in an ungodly way, and of all the harsh things which ungodly sinners have spoken against him.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.16'>These are grumblers, finding fault, following after their own lusts; they speak arrogantly, flattering people for their own advantage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.17'>But you must remember, beloved, the predictions of the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.18'>they said to you, »In the last time there will be scoffers, following their own ungodly lusts.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.19'>These are the ones who cause divisions, worldly-minded, devoid of the Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.20'>But you, beloved, build yourselves up on your most holy faith; pray in the Holy Spirit;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.21'>keep yourselves in the love of God; wait anxiously for the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ to eternal life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.22'>And have mercy on some, who doubt;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.23'>save others, snatching them out of the fire; and on some have mercy with fear, hating even the garment polluted by the flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.24'>Now to him who is able to keep you from falling and to present you without blemish before the presence of his glory with great joy,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Jude.1.25'>to the only God our Savior, through Jesus Christ our Lord, be glory, majesty, dominion, and authority, before all time and now and forever. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>