<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='TCE' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='TCE'>
        <title>The Common Edition: New Testament</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>Jens Grabner</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>
                      ---------------------------------
                      The Common Edition: New Testament
                             --------------------
                             All rights reserved.
                      ----------------------------------
                      Copyright © Timothy E. Clontz 1999


The Common Edition: New Testament
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~

  The Common Edition is the result of a decade long study of the New Testament
  and numerous English translations in the modern church. The goals for this
  edition are:

        1.  To be accurate to the Greek Scriptures and yet highly readable, 

        2.  To balance traditional wording with modern English, and

        3.  To reflect the standard Christian understanding and wording of the
            New Testament.

  The purpose of these goals is to create a standardized New Testament for the
  modern English reader.

  There are two ways to create a standardized text. [The first way] is to
  create a text of such surpassing scholarship and expression that it
  practically eliminates the use of other editions for decades or perhaps
  centuries. [The second way] is to isolate what the most widely used
  editions have in common, eliminate what they do not have in common, and
  place the results in a single text.

  
  The King James Version succeeded in both of these two ways.

  Over the past hundred years there have been numerous attempts to create a
  new English standard Bible. Each of these attempts has sought to produce a
  standardized edition in the first way I have described. The Common Edition
  New Testament follows the second method.

  A standardized edition of any work seeks a balance between extremes. The
  most literally accurate version may not be the easiest to read. The most
  traditionally worded may not be very modern.

  It cannot have a target audience; what is best for preachers and theologians
  may not be best for the daily devotional reader.

  Finally, a standardized edition cannot be innovative. One reviewer gave me
  the highest compliment I could receive when he said, "there's nothing new
  about it!"

  I hope that readers will find in these pages exactly what they would expect
  from a standardized edition, and that no matter what versions they have used
  in the past, they will find something familiar here.

   
  This initial release into the public domain is intended for free
  distribution. The text itself is copyrighted, with the following provisions:

        1.  The Common Edition: New Testament may be copied and distributed in
            electronic or printed form for free.

        2.  It may be bound or downloaded for personal use or for a gift.

        3.  It may not be sold by anyone other than the editor. 

        4.  The text may not be altered.

        5.  No more than 10,000 words may be included in a document published
            for sale without the express written permission of the editor.

        6.  No more than 20% of a document published for sale may be quoted
            from this edition without the express written permission of the
            editor. 

        7.  All distributions of the Common Edition, and all documents which
            quote the Common Edition, must contain the following copyright
            notice: Common Edition New Testament, Copyright © Timothy E.
            Clontz 1999. All rights reserved.

  If you find a phrase or word which is unclear, or which you believe needs
  review, please email the editor at {teclontz@aol.com}.

   
  Although it is not appropriate to dedicate a New Testament to any
  individual, the editor would like to give his gratitude to the many people
  who have labored to preserve this text. Those who penned the autographs
  often faced ridicule or death. Nameless monks sleep in the dust, who
  faithfully copied one manuscript to another down through the centuries. By
  the time of the Reformation, William Tyndale had one wish: to make the
  Christian Bible available in English to the poorest farmhand in England. For
  this crime he was strangled and burned at the stake.

  And then there are those who have simply loved these words enough to live by
  their highest ideals. Without the goodness of their lives no one would
  believe there to be anything Holy about a Bible. One such godly man was M.
  D. Barefield, who learned to read as an adult just so that he could make
  this word his own. My grandfather, Bill Clontz, who will always be an
  example for my family, gradually bought larger and larger print Bibles and
  finally began using the Bible on tape - just to keep the Word fresh in his
  heart. Such people always stay fresh in the hearts of those who have known
  them, and their love for God is contagious.


  Timothy Clontz
  March 14, 1999
  
  </description>
        <publisher>FREE BIBLE SOFTWARE GROUP</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>TCE</identifier>
        <source>http://www.ccel.org/olb/tolbss/zipfiles/translations/twenty.exe
            http://www.ccel.org/olb/tolbss/zipfiles/translations/comed10d.zip</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Titus'>
      <chapter osisID='Titus.1'>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.1'>Paul, a servant of God and an apostle of Jesus Christ, for the faith of God's elect and the knowledge of the truth which leads to godliness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.2'>in the hope of eternal life, which God, who cannot lie, promised long ages ago,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.3'>and at the proper time manifested in his word through the preaching with which I have been entrusted by the command of God our Savior,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.4'>to Titus, my true child in a common faith: grace and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Savior.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.5'>For this reason I left you in Crete, that you might straighten out what was left unfinished, and appoint elders in every town as I directed you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.6'>namely, if any man is blameless, the husband of one wife, and his children believe and are not open to the charge of being wild or rebellious.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.7'>For the overseer must be blameless as God's steward, not self-willed, not quick-tempered, not addicted to wine, not violent, not fond of sordid gain,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.8'>but hospitable, a lover of what is good, master of himself, upright, holy, and self-controlled;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.9'>he must hold firm to the sure word as taught, so that he may be able to give instruction in sound doctrine and also to refute those who contradict it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.10'>For there are many rebellious men, empty talkers and deceivers, especially those of the circumcision.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.11'>They must be silenced, because they are upsetting whole families by teaching things they ought not to teach for the sake of sordid gain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.12'>One of themselves, a prophet of their own, said, »Cretans are always liars, evil beasts, lazy gluttons.«</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.13'>This testimony is true. Therefore, rebuke them sharply, so that they may be sound in the faith</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.14'>and will pay no attention to Jewish myths or to the commands of men who reject the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.15'>To the pure, all things are pure; but to those who are corrupted and unbelieving, nothing is pure, but both their minds and consciences are corrupted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.1.16'>They profess to know God, but they deny him by their deeds; they are detestable and disobedient, unfit for any good deed.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Titus.2'>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.1'>But as for you, teach what befits sound doctrine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.2'>The older men are to be temperate, serious, sensible, sound in faith, in love, and in endurance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.3'>The older women likewise are to be reverent in behavior, not to be slanderers or slaves to much wine, but they are to teach what is good,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.4'>so they can train the young women to love their husbands and children,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.5'>to be sensible, pure, workers at home, kind, being subject to their own husbands, so that the word of God will not be dishonored.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.6'>Likewise urge the young men to be sensible.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.7'>Show yourself in all respects an example of good deeds, and in your teaching show integrity, seriousness,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.8'>and sound speech that cannot be condemned, so that an opponent may be put to shame, having nothing bad to say about us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.9'>Teach slaves to be subject to their masters in everything, to be well-pleasing, not to talk back to them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.10'>and not to steal, but to show that they can be fully trusted, so that in everything they will adorn the doctrine of God our Savior.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.11'>For the grace of God that brings salvation has appeared to all men,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.12'>training us to renounce ungodliness and worldly passions, and to live sober, upright, and godly lives in this present age,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.13'>looking for the blessed hope and the appearing of the glory of our great God and Savior, Christ Jesus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.14'>who gave himself for us to redeem us from all wickedness and to purify for himself a people that are his very own, zealous for good deeds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.2.15'>Speak these things; exhort and reprove with all authority. Let no one disregard you.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Titus.3'>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.1'>Remind them to be subject to rulers and authorities, to be obedient, to be ready for every good deed,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.2'>to speak evil of no one, to be peaceable and gentle, and to show true humility toward all men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.3'>For we ourselves were once foolish, disobedient, deceived, enslaved to various passions and pleasures, passing our days in malice and envy, hated by men and hating one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.4'>But when the kindness and love of God our Savior appeared,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.5'>he saved us, not on the basis of deeds which we have done in righteousness, but because of his own mercy, by the washing of regeneration and renewal in the Holy Spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.6'>whom he poured out upon us richly through Jesus Christ our Savior,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.7'>so that we might be justified by his grace and become heirs according to the hope of eternal life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.8'>This is a trustworthy saying; and concerning these things I want you to speak confidently, so that those who have believed God may be careful to devote themselves to good deeds. These things are excellent and profitable for men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.9'>But avoid foolish controversies and genealogies and strife and quarrels about the Law, for they are unprofitable and useless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.10'>Warn a man who is factious once, and then warn him a second time. After that, have nothing to do with him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.11'>knowing that such a man is perverted and sinful; he is self-condemned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.12'>When I send Artemas or Tychicus to you, do your best to come to me at Nicopolis, for I have decided to spend the winter there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.13'>Do your best to help Zenas the lawyer and Apollos on their way; see that they lack nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.14'>Our people must also learn to devote themselves to good deeds, so that they may help cases of urgent need, and not be unfruitful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Titus.3.15'>All who are with me send you greetings. Greet those who love us in the faith. Grace be with you all.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>