<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText xml:lang='en' osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='jubl2000'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='jubl2000'>
        <title>English Jubilee 2000 Bible</title>
        <contributor>Sword Project</contributor>
        <creator>ColdHeart</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>Translated from the Original Texts in Hebrew and Greek into Spanish by Casiodoro de Reina (1569) and compared with the revision of Cipriano de Valera (1602). Based on the New Testament of Francisco de Enzinas (1543) and on the New Testament (1556) with the Psalms (1557) of Juan Perez de Pineda.\par This material was translated from Spanish into English by Russell M. Stendal and compared with the Old English Translation of William Tyndale (Pentateuch of 1530, Ploughboy Edition New Testament of 1534, Joshua to 2 Chronicles of 1537, and Jonah). It was also compared word for word with the Authorized Version (by King James) of 1611.
</description>
        <publisher>DarkBibleORG</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>jubl2000</identifier>
        <source>http://www.crosswire.org/sword/servlet/SwordMod.Verify?modName=Jubilee2000</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide th bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Copyright 2000, 2001 Russell Martin Stendal May be quoted in other works.  May be used freely in all non-profit, non-commercial Bible distribution endeavors provided the content is not altered. For all commercial reproduction express written permission from the publisher is required.
       Ransom Press Internacional 10160 Main Dr. Bonita Springs, FL  34135 </rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='1Chr'>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.1'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.1'>Adam, Seth, Enosh,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.2'>Kenan, Mahalaleel, Jered,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.3'>Enoch, Methuselah, Lamech,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.4'>Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japheth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.5'>The sons of Japheth: Gomer, Magog, Madai, Javan, Tubal, Meshech, and Tiras.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.6'>And the sons of Gomer: Ashchenaz, Riphath, and Togarmah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.7'>And the sons of Javan: Elishah, Tarshish, Kittim, and Dodanim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.8'>The sons of Ham: Cush, Mizraim, Put, and Canaan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.9'>And the sons of Cush: Seba, Havilah, Sabta, Raamah, and Sabtecha. And the sons of Raamah: Sheba and Dedan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.10'>And Cush begat Nimrod; he began to be mighty upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.11'>And Mizraim begat Ludim, Anamim, Lehabim, Naphtuhim,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.12'>Pathrusim and Casluhim of whom came the Philistines and the Caphthorims.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.13'>And Canaan begat Zidon his firstborn and the Hitite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.14'>the Jebusite, the Amorite, the Girgashite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.15'>the Hivite, the Arkite, the Sinite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.16'>the Arvadite, the Zemarite, and the Hamathite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.17'>The sons of Shem: Elam, Asshur, Arphaxad, Lud, Aram, Uz, Hul, Gether, and Meshech.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.18'>And Arphaxad begat Shelah, and Shelah begat Eber.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.19'>And unto Eber were born two sons; the name of the one [was] Peleg because in his days the earth was divided, and his brother's name [was] Joktan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.20'>And Joktan begat Almodad, Sheleph, Hazarmaveth, Jerah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.21'>Hadoram, Uzal, Diklah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.22'>Ebal, Abimael, Sheba,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.23'>Ophir, Havilah, and Jobab. All these [were] the sons of Joktan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.24'>Shem, Arphaxad, Shelah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.25'>Eber, Peleg, Reu,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.26'>Serug, Nahor, Terah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.27'>and Abram, who [is] Abraham.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.28'>The sons of Abraham: Isaac and Ishmael.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.29'>These [are] their generations: The firstborn of Ishmael, Nebaioth, then Kedar, Adbeel, Mibsam,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.30'>Mishma, Dumah, Massa, Hadad, Tema,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.31'>Jetur, Naphish, and Kedemah. These are the sons of Ishmael.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.32'>Now the sons of Keturah, Abraham's concubine: she gave birth to Zimran, Jokshan, Medan, Midian, Ishbak, and Shuah. The sons of Jokshan: Sheba and Dedan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.33'>The sons of Midian: Ephah, Epher, Enoch, Abida, and Eldaah. All these [are] the sons of Keturah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.34'>And Abraham begat Isaac. The sons of Isaac: Esau and Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.35'>The sons of Esau: Eliphaz, Reuel, Jeush, Jaalam, and Korah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.36'>The sons of Eliphaz: Teman, Omar, Zephi, Gatam, Kenaz, Timna, and Amalek.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.37'>The sons of Reuel: Nahath, Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.38'>The sons of Seir: Lotan, Shobal, Zibeon, Anah, Dishon, Ezer, and Dishan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.39'>The sons of Lotan: Hori and Homam, and Timna [was] Lotan's sister.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.40'>The sons of Shobal: Alian, Manahath, Ebal, Shephi, and Onam. And the sons of Zibeon: Aiah and Anah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.41'>Dishon was the son of Anah. The sons of Dishon: Amram, Eshban, Ithran, and Cheran.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.42'>The sons of Ezer: Bilhan, Zavan, and Jakan. The sons of Dishan: Uz and Aran.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.43'>Now these [are] the kings that reigned in the land of Edom before [any] king reigned over the sons of Israel. Bela, the son of Beor, and the name of his city [was] Dinhabah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.44'>And when Bela was dead, Jobab, the son of Zerah of Bozrah, reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.45'>And when Jobab was dead, Husham of the land of the Temanites reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.46'>And when Husham was dead, Hadad, the son of Bedad, who smote Midian in the field of Moab, reigned in his stead; and the name of his city [was] Avith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.47'>And when Hadad was dead, Samlah of Masrekah reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.48'>And when Samlah was dead, Saul of Rehoboth by the river reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.49'>And when Saul was dead, Baalhanan, the son of Achbor, reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.50'>And when Baalhanan was dead, Hadad reigned in his stead. The name of his city [was] Pai, and his wife's name [was] Mehetabel, the daughter of Matred, the daughter of Mezahab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.51'>When Hadad was dead, the dukes came forth in Edom: Duke Timnah, Duke Aliah, Duke Jetheth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.52'>Duke Aholibamah, Duke Elah, Duke Pinon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.53'>Duke Kenaz, Duke Teman, Duke Mibzar,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.1.54'>Duke Magdiel, Duke Iram. These [were] the dukes of Edom.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.2'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.1'>These [are] the sons of Israel: Reuben, Simeon, Levi, Judah, Issachar, Zebulun,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.2'>Dan, Joseph, Benjamin, Naphtali, Gad, and Asher.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.3'>The sons of Judah: Er, Onan, and Shelah. These three were born unto him of the daughter of Shua, the Canaanitess. And Er, the firstborn of Judah, was evil in the sight of the LORD, and he slew him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.4'>And Tamar, his daughter-in-law, gave birth unto him Pharez and Zerah. All the sons of Judah [were] five.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.5'>The sons of Pharez: Hezron and Hamul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.6'>And the sons of Zerah: Zimri, Ethan, Heman, Calcol, and Dara, five of them in all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.7'>And the sons of Carmi: Achar, the troubler of Israel, who transgressed in the anathema.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.8'>Azariah was the son of Ethan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.9'>The sons that were born unto Hezron: Jerahmeel, Ram, and Chelubai.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.10'>And Ram begat Amminadab, and Amminadab begat Nahshon, prince of the sons of Judah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.11'>And Nahshon begat Salma, and Salma begat Boaz,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.12'>And Boaz begat Obed, and Obed begat Jesse,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.13'>And Jesse begat his firstborn Eliab, and Abinadab the second and Shimma the third,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.14'>Nethaneel the fourth, Raddai the fifth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.15'>Ozem the sixth, David the seventh,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.16'>whose sisters [were] Zeruiah, and Abigail. The sons of Zeruiah [were] three: Abishai, Joab, and Asahel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.17'>And Abigail gave birth to Amasa, whose father was Jether the Ishmeelite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.18'>And Caleb, the son of Hezron, begat Jerioth of Azubah, [his] wife. And her sons were Jesher, Shobab, and Ardon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.19'>And when Azubah was dead, Caleb took Ephrath as wife, who gave birth to Hur unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.20'>And Hur begat Uri, and Uri begat Bezaleel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.21'>And afterward Hezron went in to the daughter of Machir, the father of Gilead, whom he married when he [was] sixty years old, and she gave birth to Segum unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.22'>And Segub begat Jair, who had twenty-three cities in the land of Gilead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.23'>And Geshur and Aram took the cities of Jair from them, with Kenath and its towns, [even] sixty cities. All these [were] of the sons of Machir, the father of Gilead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.24'>And after Hezron was dead in Calebephratah, then Abiah, Hezron's wife, gave birth to Ashur unto him, the father of Tekoa.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.25'>And the sons of Jerahmeel, the firstborn of Hezron, were Ram, the firstborn, Bunah, Oren, Ozem, [and] Ahijah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.26'>Jerahmeel had also another wife, whose name [was] Atarah; she [was] the mother of Onam.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.27'>And the sons of Ram, the firstborn of Jerahmeel, were Maaz, Jamin, and Eker.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.28'>And the sons of Onam were Shammai and Jada. The sons of Shammai, Nadab, and Abishur.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.29'>And the name of the wife of Abishur [was] Abihail, and she gave birth to Ahban and Molid unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.30'>And the sons of Nadab: Seled and Appaim. But Seled died without children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.31'>And Ishi was the son of Appaim. And Sheshan, the son of Ishi; and the son of Sheshan, Ahlai.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.32'>And the sons of Jada, the brother of Shammai: Jether and Jonathan; and Jether died without children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.33'>And the sons of Jonathan: Peleth and Zaza. These were the sons of Jerahmeel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.34'>Now Sheshan had no sons, but daughters. And Sheshan had a servant, an Egyptian, whose name [was] Jarha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.35'>And Sheshan gave his daughter to Jarha, his servant, to wife; and she bore him Attai.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.36'>And Attai begat Nathan, and Nathan begat Zabad,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.37'>and Zabad begat Ephlal, and Ephlal begat Obed,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.38'>and Obed begat Jehu, and Jehu begat Azariah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.39'>and Azariah begat Helez, and Helez begat Eleasah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.40'>and Eleasah begat Sisamai, and Sisamai begat Shallum,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.41'>and Shallum begat Jekamiah, and Jekamiah begat Elishama.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.42'>Now the sons of Caleb, the brother of Jerahmeel, [were] Mesha, his firstborn, who was the father of Ziph, and of his [other] sons, Mareshah, the father of Hebron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.43'>And the sons of Hebron: Korah, Tappuah, Rekem, and Shema.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.44'>And Shema begat Raham, the father of Jorkoam; and Rekem begat Shammai.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.45'>And the son of Shammai [was] Maon, and Maon [was] the father of Bethzur.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.46'>And Ephah, Caleb's concubine, gave birth to Haran, Moza, and Gazez unto him, and Haran begat Gazez.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.47'>And the sons of Jahdai: Regem, Jotham, Geshan, Pelet, Ephah, and Shaaph.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.48'>Maachah, Caleb's concubine, gave birth to Sheber and Tirhanah unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.49'>She also gave birth to Shaaph, the father of Madmannah, Sheva, the father of Machbenah and father of Gibea. And Achsah [was] the daughter of Caleb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.50'>These were the sons of Caleb, the son of Hur, the firstborn of Ephratah: Shobal, the father of Kirjathjearim,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.51'>Salma, the father of Bethlehem, Hareph, the father of Bethgader.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.52'>And the sons of Shobal, the father of Kirjathjearim, who was [lord] of half of Manaheth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.53'>And the families of Kirjathjearim: the Ithrites and the Puhites and the Shumathites and the Mishraites; of them came the Zareathites and the Eshtaulites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.54'>The sons of Salma: Bethlehem and the Netophathites, the crowns of the house of Joab, and half of the Manahethites, the Zorites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.2.55'>And the families of the scribes who dwelt at Jabez: the Tirathites, the Shimeathites, [and] Suchathites. These [are] the Kenites that came of Hemath, the father of the house of Rechab.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.3'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.1'>Now these were the sons of David, which were born unto him in Hebron: the firstborn, Amnon of Ahinoam, the Jezreelitess; the second, Daniel of Abigail of Carmel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.2'>the third, Absalom, the son of Maachah, the daughter of Talmai, king of Geshur; the fourth, Adonijah, the son of Haggith;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.3'>the fifth, Shephatiah of Abital; the sixth, Ithream by Eglah his wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.4'>[These] six were born unto him in Hebron, and there he reigned seven years and six months, and in Jerusalem he reigned thirty-three years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.5'>And these were born unto him in Jerusalem: Shimea, Shobab, Nathan, and Solomon, four of Bathshua, the daughter of Ammiel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.6'>And [another] nine: Ibhar, Elishama, Eliphelet,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.7'>Nogah, Nepheg, Japhia,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.8'>Elishama, Eliada, and Eliphelet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.9'>[These were] all the sons of David, beside the sons of the concubines, and Tamar [was] their sister.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.10'>And Solomon's son [was] Rehoboam, Abia, his son; Asa, his son; Jehoshapha, his son;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.11'>Joram, his son; Ahaziah, his son; Joash, his son;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.12'>Amaziah, his son; Azariah, his son; Jotham, his son;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.13'>Ahaz, his son; Hezekiah, his son; Manasseh, his son;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.14'>Amon, his son; Josiah, his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.15'>And the sons of Josiah: the firstborn, Johanan; the second, Jehoiakim; the third, Zedekiah; the fourth, Shallum.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.16'>The sons of Jehoiakim: Jeconiah, his son; Zedekiah his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.17'>And the sons of Jeconiah: Assir, Salathiel, his son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.18'>Malchiram also, Pedaiah, Shenazar, Jecamiah, Hoshama, and Nedabiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.19'>And the sons of Pedaiah: Zerubbabel and Shimei. And the sons of Zerubbabel: Meshullam, Hananiah, and Shelomith, their sister.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.20'>And [of Meshullam]: Hashubah, Ohel, Berechiah, Hasadiah, and Jushabhesed, five in all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.21'>The sons of Hananiah: Pelatiah and Jesaiah, the sons of Rephaiah, the sons of Arnan, the sons of Obadiah, the sons of Shechaniah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.22'>And the son of Shechaniah: Shemaiah, and the sons of Shemaiah: Hattush, Igeal, Bariah, Neariah, and Shaphat, six.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.23'>And the sons of Neariah: Elioenai, Hezekiah, and Azrikam, three.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.3.24'>And the sons of Elioenai: Hodaiah, Eliashib, Pelaiah, Akkub, Johanan, Dalaiah, and Anani, seven.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.4'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.1'>The sons of Judah: Pharez, Hezron, Carmi, Hur, and Shobal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.2'>And Reaiah, the son of Shobal, begat Jahath, and Jahath begat Ahumai and Lahad. These [are] the families of the Zorathites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.3'>And these [were of] the father of Etam: Jezreel, Ishma, and Idbash, and the name of their sister [was] Hazelelponi.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.4'>And Penuel, the father of Gedor, and Ezer, the father of Hushah. These [were] the sons of Hur, the firstborn of Ephratah, the father of Bethlehem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.5'>And Ashur, the father of Tekoa, had two wives, Helah and Naarah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.6'>And Naarah gave birth to Ahuzam, Hepher, Temeni, and Haahashtari unto him. These [were] the sons of Naarah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.7'>And the sons of Helah: Zereth, Jezoar, and Ethnan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.8'>And Coz begat Anub and Zobebah and the family of Aharhel, the son of Harum.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.9'>And Jabez was more honoured than his brethren, and his mother called his name Jabez, saying, Because I gave birth to him with sorrow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.10'>And Jabez called on the God of Israel, saying, Oh that thou would bless me indeed and enlarge my border and that thy hand might be with me and that thou would deliver [me] from evil, that it may not grieve me! And God granted him that which he requested.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.11'>And Chelub, the brother of Shuah, begat Mehir, who [was] the father of Eshton.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.12'>And Eshton begat Bethrapha, Paseah, and Tehinnah, the father of Irnahash. These [are] the men of Rechah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.13'>The sons of Kenaz: Othniel and Seraiah. The sons of Othniel: Hathath</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.14'>and Meonothai, who begat Ophrah. And Seraiah begat Joab, the father of the inhabitants of the valley of Charashim, for they were craftsmen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.15'>The sons of Caleb, the son of Jephunneh: Iru, Elah, and Naam; and Kenaz was the son of Elah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.16'>The sons of Jehaleleel: Ziph, Ziphah, Tiria, and Asareel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.17'>And the sons of Ezra: Jether, Mered, Epher, and Jalon; and also begat Miriam, Shammai, and Ishbah, the father of Eshtemoa.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.18'>And his wife Jehudijah gave birth unto him Jered, the father of Gedor, and Heber, the father of Socho, and Jekuthiel, the father of Zanoah. And these [are] the sons of Bithiah, the daughter of Pharaoh, which Mered took.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.19'>And the sons of the wife of Hodiah, the sister of Naham, [were] the father of Keilah, the Garmite, and Eshtemoa, the Maachathite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.20'>And the sons of Shimon: Amnon, Rinnah, Benhanan, and Tilon. And the sons of Ishi: Zoheth and Benzoheth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.21'>The sons of Shelah, the son of Judah: Er, the father of Lecah, and Laadah, the father of Mareshah, and the families of the house of those that wrought fine linen, of the house of Ashbea,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.22'>and Jokim and the men of Chozeba, and Joash and Saraph, who had the dominion in Moab, and Jashubilehem. And [these are] ancient words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.23'>These [were] the potters and those that dwelt among plants and hedges, who dwelt there with the king for his work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.24'>The sons of Simeon: Nemuel, Jamin, Jarib, Zerah, Saul;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.25'>also Shallum, his son, Mibsam, his son, and Mishma, his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.26'>The sons of Mishma: Hamuel, his son, Zacchur, his son, Shimei his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.27'>And Shimei had sixteen sons and six daughters, but his brethren did not have many children, neither did all their family multiply, like the sons of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.28'>And they dwelt at Beersheba and Moladah and Hazarshual</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.29'>and at Bilhah and at Ezem and at Tolad</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.30'>and at Bethuel and at Hormah and at Ziklag</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.31'>and at Bethmarcaboth and Hazarsusim and at Bethbirei and at Shaaraim. These [were] their cities until the reign of David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.32'>And their villages [were] Etam, Ain, Rimmon, Tochen, and Ashan, five cities;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.33'>and all their villages that [were] round about the same cities, unto Baal. These [were] their habitations and their genealogy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.34'>And Meshobab and Jamlech and Joshah, the son of Amaziah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.35'>and Joel and Jehu, the son of Josibiah, the son of Seraiah, the son of Asiel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.36'>and Elioenai, Jaakobah, Jeshohaiah, Asaiah, Adiel, Jesimiel, Benaiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.37'>and Ziza, the son of Shiphi, the son of Allon, the son of Jedaiah, the son of Shimri, the son of Shemaiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.38'>These mentioned by [their] names [were] princes in their families, and they were multiplied greatly in the house of their fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.39'>And they came unto the entrance of Gedor, [even] unto the east side of the valley, to seek pasture for their flocks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.40'>And they found fat pasture and good, and the land [was] wide and spacious and quiet and peaceable, for [the sons] of Ham had dwelt there of old.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.41'>And these written by name came in the days of Hezekiah, king of Judah and smote their tents and the habitations that were found there and destroyed them utterly unto this day and dwelt in their place because [there was] pasture there for their flocks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.42'>And likewise five hundred men of them, of the sons of Simeon, went to Mount Seir, having for their captains Pelatiah and Neariah and Rephaiah and Uzziel, the sons of Ishi.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.4.43'>And they smote the rest of the Amalekites that were escaped and dwelt there unto this day.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.5'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.1'>Now the sons of Reuben, the firstborn of Israel, (for he [was] the firstborn, but because he defiled his father's bed, his birthright was given unto the sons of Joseph, the son of Israel; and he was not counted as the firstborn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.2'>For Judah prevailed above his brethren and was their prince, but the birthright [was] Joseph's:)</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.3'>The sons, [therefore], of Reuben, the firstborn of Israel, were Enoch, Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.4'>The sons of Joel: Shemaiah, his son, Gog, his son, Shimei, his son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.5'>Micah, his son, Reaia, his son, Baal, his son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.6'>Beerah, his son, whom Tilgathpilneser, king of Assyria, carried away [captive]. He [was] prince of the Reubenites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.7'>And his brethren by their families, when the genealogy of their generations was reckoned, had as princes, Jeiel and Zechariah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.8'>And Bela, the son of Azaz, the son of Shema, the son of Joel, dwelt in Aroer, even until Nebo and Baalmeon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.9'>And eastward he inhabited unto the entering in of the wilderness from the river Euphrates, because their livestock were multiplied in the land of Gilead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.10'>And in the days of Saul they made war with the Hagarites, who fell by their hand, and they dwelt in their tents throughout all the east [land] of Gilead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.11'>And the sons of Gad dwelt over against them, in the land of Bashan unto Salchah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.12'>Joel, the chief, and Shapham, second, and Jaanai and Shaphat in Bashan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.13'>And their brethren of the house of their fathers [were] Michael, Meshullam, Sheba, Jorai, Jachan, Zia, and Heber, seven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.14'>These [were] the sons of Abihail, the son of Huri, the son of Jaroah, the son of Gilead, the son of Michael, the son of Jeshishai, the son of Jahdo, the son of Buz.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.15'>Also Ahi, the son of Abdiel, the son of Guni, was the prince of the house of their fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.16'>And they dwelt in Gilead in Bashan and in her towns and in all the suburbs of Sharon, upon their goings forth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.17'>All these were reckoned by their generations in the days of Jotham, king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam, king of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.18'>The sons of Reuben and of Gad and half the tribe of Manasseh, valiant men, men able to bear buckler and sword and to shoot with bow and skillful in war [were] four-forty thousand seven hundred and sixty, that went out to the war.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.19'>And they made war with the Hagarites, with Jetur and Nephish and Nodab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.20'>And they were helped against them, and the Hagarites were delivered into their hand and all that [were] with them, for they cried to God in the battle, and he was intreated of them because they put their trust in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.21'>And they took away their livestock; fifty thousand camels and two hundred and fifty thousand sheep and two thousand asses and one hundred thousand persons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.22'>For there fell down many slain because the war [was] of God. And they dwelt in their steads until the captivity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.23'>And the sons of the half tribe of Manasseh dwelt in the land; they increased from Bashan unto Baalhermon and Senir and unto Mount Hermon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.24'>And these [were] the heads of the houses of their fathers: Epher, Ishi, Eliel, Azriel, Jeremiah, Hodaviah, and Jahdiel, mighty men of valour, famous men, [and] heads of the houses of their fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.25'>But they rebelled against the God of their fathers and fornicated after the gods of the people of the land, whom God had destroyed before them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.5.26'>And for this the God of Israel stirred up the spirit of Pul, king of Assyria, and the spirit of Tilgathpilneser, king of Assyria, and he carried away the Reubenites and the Gadites and the half tribe of Manasseh and brought them unto Halah and Habor and Hara and to the River Gozan, unto this day.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.6'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.1'>The sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.2'>The sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.3'>The sons of Amram: Aaron, Moses, and Miriam. The sons of Aaron: Nadab, Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.4'>Eleazar begat Phinehas, and Phinehas begat Abishua,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.5'>and Abishua begat Bukki, and Bukki begat Uzzi,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.6'>and Uzzi begat Zerahiah, and Zerahiah begat Meraioth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.7'>and Meraioth begat Amariah, and Amariah begat Ahitub,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.8'>and Ahitub begat Zadok, and Zadok begat Ahimaaz,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.9'>and Ahimaaz begat Azariah, and Azariah begat Johanan,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.10'>and Johanan begat Azariah, who had the priesthood in the house that Solomon built in Jerusalem,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.11'>and Azariah begat Amariah, and Amariah begat Ahitub,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.12'>and Ahitub begat Zadok, and Zadok begat Shallum,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.13'>and Shallum begat Hilkiah, and Hilkiah begat Azariah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.14'>and Azariah begat Seraiah, and Seraiah begat Jehozadak,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.15'>and Jehozadak went [into captivity], when the LORD carried away Judah and Jerusalem by the hand of Nebuchadnezzar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.16'>The sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.17'>And these [are] the names of the sons of Gershon: Libni and Shimei.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.18'>The sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.19'>The sons of Merari: Mahli, Mushi. These [are] the families of the Levites according to their fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.20'>Of Gershon: Libni, his son, Jahath his son, Zimmah his son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.21'>Joah, his son, Iddo, his son, Zerah, his son, Jeaterai, his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.22'>The sons of Kohath: Amminadab, his son, Korah, his son, Assir, his son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.23'>Elkanah, his son, and Ebiasaph, his son, and Assir, his son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.24'>Tahath, his son, Uriel, his son, Uzziah, his son, and Saul, his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.25'>The sons of Elkanah: Amasai, Ahimoth, and Elkanah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.26'>The sons of Elkanah: Zophai, his son, and Nahath, his son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.27'>Eliab, his son, Jeroham, his son, Elkanah, his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.28'>The sons of Samuel: the firstborn Vashni and Abiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.29'>The sons of Merari: Mahli, Libni, his son, Shimei, his son, Uzza, his son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.30'>Shimea, his son, Haggiah, his son, Asaiah, his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.31'>And these [are they] whom David set over the service of song in the house of the LORD, after the ark had rest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.32'>And they served before the tent of the tabernacle of the testimony with singing until Solomon had built the house of the LORD in Jerusalem, and [then] they remained in their ministry according to their right.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.33'>And these [are] those that remained with their sons. Of the sons of the Kohath: Heman, a singer, the son of Joel, the son of Shemuel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.34'>the son of Elkanah, the son of Jeroham, the son of Eliel, the son of Toah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.35'>the son of Zuph, the son of Elkanah, the son of Mahath, the son of Amasai,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.36'>the son of Elkanah, the son of Joel, the son of Azariah, the son of Zephaniah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.37'>the son of Tahath, the son of Assir, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.38'>the son of Izhar, the son of Kohath, the son of Levi, the son of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.39'>And his brother Asaph, who stood on his right hand, [even] Asaph the son of Berachiah, the son of Shimea,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.40'>the son of Michael, the son of Baaseiah, the son of Malchiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.41'>the son of Ethni, the son of Zerah, the son of Adaiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.42'>the son of Ethan, the son of Zimmah, the son of Shimei,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.43'>the son of Jahath, the son of Gershon, the son of Levi.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.44'>And their brethren, the sons of Merari, [stood] on the left hand; Ethan, the son of Kishi, the son of Abdi, the son of Malluch,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.45'>the son of Hashabiah, the son of Amaziah, the son of Hilkiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.46'>the son of Amzi, the son of Bani, the son of Shamer,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.47'>the son of Mahli, the son of Mushi, the son of Merari, the son of Levi.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.48'>Their brethren, also the Levites, [were] given over unto all the ministry of the tabernacle of the house of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.49'>But Aaron and his sons made incense upon the altar of the burnt offering and on the altar of incense, in all the work of the holy of holies, and to make reconciliation for Israel, according to all that Moses, the servant of God, had commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.50'>And these [are] the sons of Aaron: Eleazar, his son, Phinehas, his son, Abishua, his son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.51'>Bukki, his son, Uzzi, his son, Zerahiah, his son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.52'>Meraioth, his son, Amariah, his son, Ahitub, his son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.53'>Zadok, his son, Ahimaaz, his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.54'>Now these [are] their dwelling places throughout their palaces in their borders, of the sons of Aaron, of the families of the Kohathites; for theirs was the lot,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.55'>that they gave them Hebron in the land of Judah and its suburbs round about it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.56'>But the fields around the city and its villages, they gave to Caleb the son of Jephunneh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.57'>And to the sons of Aaron they gave the cities of refuge of Judah, [namely], Hebron and Libnah with their suburbs, and Jattir and Eshtemoa, with their suburbs,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.58'>and Hilen with her suburbs, Debir with her suburbs,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.59'>and Ashan with her suburbs, and Bethshemesh with her suburbs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.60'>And out of the tribe of Benjamin; Geba with her suburbs and Alemeth with her suburbs and Anathoth with her suburbs. All their cities throughout their families [were] thirteen cities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.61'>And unto the sons of Kohath, [who were] left of that family, [they gave] ten cities of the half tribe of Manasseh, by lot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.62'>And to the sons of Gershon, throughout their families, out of the tribe of Issachar and out of the tribe of Asher and out of the tribe of Naphtali and out of the tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, thirteen cities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.63'>Unto the sons of Merari [were given] by lot, throughout their families, out of the tribe of Reuben and out of the tribe of Gad and out of the tribe of Zebulun, twelve cities.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.64'>And the sons of Israel gave to the Levites [these] cities with their suburbs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.65'>And they gave by lot out of the tribe of the sons of Judah and out of the tribe of the sons of Simeon and out of the tribe of the sons of Benjamin, these cities, which are called by [their] names.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.66'>And [the residue] of the families of the sons of Kohath had cities with their borders out of the tribe of Ephraim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.67'>And they gave unto them, [of] the cities of refuge, Shechem in Mount Ephraim with her suburbs; [they gave] also Gezer with her suburbs,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.68'>and Jokmeam with her suburbs and Bethhoron with her suburbs,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.69'>and Aijalon with her suburbs and Gathrimmon with her suburbs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.70'>And out of the half tribe of Manasseh; Aner with her suburbs and Bileam with her suburbs, for the family of the remnant of the sons of Kohath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.71'>Unto the sons of Gershon [were given] out of the family of the half tribe of Manasseh, Golan in Bashan with her suburbs and Ashtaroth with her suburbs;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.72'>and out of the tribe of Issachar; Kedesh with her suburbs, Daberath with her suburbs,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.73'>and Ramoth with her suburbs, and Anem with her suburbs;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.74'>and out of the tribe of Asher, Mashal with her suburbs and Abdon with her suburbs</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.75'>and Hukok with her suburbs and Rehob with her suburbs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.76'>And out of the tribe of Naphtali; Kedesh in Galilee with her suburbs and Hammon with her suburbs and Kirjathaim with her suburbs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.77'>Unto the rest of the sons of Merari [were given] out of the tribe of Zebulun, Rimmon with her suburbs, Tabor with her suburbs;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.78'>and on the other side of the Jordan by Jericho, on the east side of the Jordan, [were given them] out of the tribe of Reuben, Bezer in the wilderness with her suburbs and Jahzah with her suburbs,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.79'>Kedemoth also with her suburbs and Mephaath with her suburbs;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.80'>and out of the tribe of Gad; Ramoth in Gilead with her suburbs and Mahanaim with her suburbs,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.6.81'>and Heshbon with her suburbs and Jazer with her suburbs.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.7'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.1'>The sons of Issachar: Tola, Puah, Jashub, and Shimron, four.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.2'>The sons of Tola: Uzzi, Rephaiah, Jeriel, Jahmai, Jibsam, and Shemuel, heads of the houses of their fathers. [Those] of Tola numbered by their families twenty-two thousand valiant men of might in the days of David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.3'>The son of Uzzi [was] Izrahiah; and the sons of Izrahiah: Michael, Obadiah, Joel, Ishiah, all of them, five princes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.4'>And with them, by their lineages, after the houses of their fathers, [were] bands of soldiers for war, thirty-six thousand [men], for they had many wives and sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.5'>And their brethren among all the families of Issachar [were] valiant men of might, reckoned in all by their genealogies eighty-seven thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.6'>[The sons] of Benjamin: Bela, Becher, and Jediael, three.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.7'>The sons of Bela: Ezbon, Uzzi, Uzziel, Jerimoth, and Iri, five, heads of the houses of [their] fathers, mighty men of valour; and were reckoned by their genealogies twenty-two thousand and thirty-four.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.8'>The sons of Becher: Zemira, Joash, Eliezer, Elioenai, Omri, Jerimoth, Abiah, Anathoth, and Alameth. All these [are] the sons of Becher.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.9'>And the number of them, after their genealogy by their generations, heads of the houses of their fathers, mighty men of valour, [was] twenty thousand two hundred.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.10'>The son of Jediael was Bilhan; and the sons of Bilhan: Jeush, Benjamin, Ehud, Chenaanah, Zethan, Tarshish, and Ahishahar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.11'>All these [were] sons of Jediael, by the heads of their fathers, mighty men of valour, seventeen thousand two hundred [soldiers], fit to go out for war [and] battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.12'>And Shuppim and Huppim were sons of Ir; [and] Hushim, the son of Aher.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.13'>The sons of Naphtali: Jahziel, Guni, Jezer, and Shallum, the sons of Bilhah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.14'>The sons of Manasseh: Ashriel, whom his concubine, the Aramitess, gave birth unto him; she also gave birth to Machir, the father of Gilead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.15'>And Machir took wifes of Huppim and Shuppim, whose sister's name [was] Maachah, and the name of the second [was] Zelophehad. And Zelophehad had daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.16'>And Maachah, the wife of Machir, gave birth to a son unto him, and she called his name Peresh, and the name of his brother [was] Sheresh, whose sons [were] Ulam and Rakem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.17'>The son of Ulam was Bedan. These [were] the sons of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.18'>And his sister Hammoleketh gave birth to Ishod, Abiezer, and Mahalah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.19'>And the sons of Shemida were, Ahian, Shechem, Likhi, and Aniam.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.20'>The sons of Ephraim: Shuthelah, Bered, his son, Tahath his son, Eladah, his son, Tahath, his son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.21'>Zabad, his son, Shuthelah, his son, Ezer, and Elead, whom the men of Gath [that were] born in [that] land slew because they came down to take away their livestock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.22'>And Ephraim, their father, mourned many days, and his brethren came to comfort him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.23'>And when he went in to his wife, she conceived and gave birth to a son, and he called his name Beriah, because he had been in affliction in his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.24'>(And his daughter [was] Sherah, who built Bethhoron, the lower and the upper, and Uzzensherah.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.25'>And Rephah [was] his son, also Resheph, and Telah his son, and Tahan, his son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.26'>Laadan, his son, Ammihud, his son, Elishama, his son,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.27'>Nun, his son, Joshua, his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.28'>And [their] inheritance and habitation was Bethel with its towns, and eastward Naaran, and westward Gezer with its towns; likewise Shechem and its towns unto Gaza and its towns,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.29'>and by the side of the sons of Manasseh, Bethshean and her towns, Taanach and her towns, Megiddo and her towns, Dor and her towns. In these dwelt the sons of Joseph, the son of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.30'>The sons of Asher: Imnah, Isuah, Ishuai, Beriah, and Serah, their sister.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.31'>And the sons of Beriah: Heber and Malchiel, who [was] the father of Birzavith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.32'>And Heber begat Japhlet, Shomer, Hotham, and Shua their sister.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.33'>The sons of Japhlet: Pasach, Bimhal, and Ashvath. These [were] the sons of Japhlet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.34'>And the sons of Shamer: Ahi, Rohgah, Jehubbah, and Aram.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.35'>The sons of his brother Helem: Zophah, Imna, Shelesh, and Amal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.36'>The sons of Zophah: Suah, Harnepher, Shual, Beri, Imrah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.37'>Bezer, Hod, Shamma, Shilshah, Ithran, and Beera.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.38'>The sons of Jether: Jephunneh, Pispah, and Ara.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.39'>And the sons of Ulla: Arah, Haniel, and Rezia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.7.40'>All these [were] sons of Asher, heads of [their] father's houses, chosen, mighty men of valour, heads of princes. And the number throughout the genealogy of those that were apt for war [and] for battle [was] twenty-six thousand men.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.8'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.1'>Now Benjamin begat Bela, his firstborn, Ashbel, the second, and Aharah, the third,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.2'>Nohah, the fourth, and Rapha, the fifth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.3'>And the sons of Bela were Addar, Gera, Abihud,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.4'>Abishua, Naaman, Ahoah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.5'>Gera, Shephuphan, and Hiram.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.6'>And these [are] the sons of Ehud: these are the heads of the fathers who inhabited Geba, and they were removed to Manahath,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.7'>That is, Naaman, Ahiah, and Gera; he removed them, and begat Uzza, and Ahihud.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.8'>And Shaharaim begat [sons] in the fields of Moab after he had sent away Hushim and Baara, his wives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.9'>And he begat of Hodesh, his wife, Jobab, Zibia, Mesha, Malcham,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.10'>Jeuz, Shachia, and Mirma. These [are] his sons, heads of the fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.11'>And of Hushim he begat Abitub and Elpaal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.12'>The sons of Elpaal: Eber, Misham, and Shamed, who built Ono, and Lod, with the towns thereof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.13'>Beriah [also] and Shema, who [were] heads of the fathers of the inhabitants of Aijalon, who drove away the inhabitants of Gath,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.14'>and Ahio, Shashak, Jeremoth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.15'>Zebadiah, Arad, Ader,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.16'>Michael, Ispah, and Joha, sons of Beriah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.17'>and Zebadiah, Meshullam, Hezeki, Heber;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.18'>Ishmerai, Jezliah, and Jobab, sons of Elpaal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.19'>And Jakim, Zichri, Zabdi,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.20'>Elienai, Zilthai, Eliel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.21'>Adaiah, Beraiah, and Shimrath, the sons of Shimhi,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.22'>and Ishpan, Heber, Eliel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.23'>Abdon, Zichri, Hanan,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.24'>Hananiah, Elam, Antothijah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.25'>Iphedeiah, and Penuel, sons of Shashak,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.26'>and Shamsherai, Shehariah, Athaliah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.27'>and Jaresiah, Eliah, and Zichri, the sons of Jeroham.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.28'>These [were] heads of the fathers, by their generations, chief [men] who dwelt in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.29'>And at Gibeon dwelt the father of Gibeon; whose wife's name [was] Maachah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.30'>and his firstborn son, Abdon, then Zur, Kish, Baal, Nadab,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.31'>Gedor, Ahio, and Zacher.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.32'>And Mikloth begat Shimeah. And these also dwelt with their brethren in Jerusalem, next to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.33'>And Ner begat Kish, and Kish begat Saul, and Saul begat Jonathan, Malchishua, Abinadab, and Eshbaal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.34'>And the son of Jonathan [was] Meribbaal; and Meribbaal begat Micah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.35'>The sons of Micah: Pithon, Melech, Tarea, and Ahaz.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.36'>And Ahaz begat Jehoadah; and Jehoadah begat Alemeth and Azmaveth and Zimri; and Zimri begat Moza,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.37'>and Moza begat Binea; Rapha [was] his son, Eleasah, his son, Azel, his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.38'>And Azel had six sons, whose names [are] these: Azrikam, Bocheru, Ishmael, Sheariah, Obadiah, and Hanan. All these [were] the sons of Azel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.39'>And the sons of Eshek, his brother: Ulam, his firstborn, Jehush, the second, and Eliphelet, the third.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.8.40'>And the sons of Ulam were mighty men of valour, expert archers who had many sons, and sons' sons, one hundred and fifty. All these [were] of the sons of Benjamin.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.9'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.1'>So all Israel were reckoned by genealogies, and behold, they [were] written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah, [who] were carried away to Babylon for their rebellion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.2'>Now the first inhabitants that [dwelt] in their possessions in their cities were thus of Israel, as of the priests, Levites, and the Nethinims.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.3'>And in Jerusalem dwelt of the sons of Judah and of the sons of Benjamin and of the sons of Ephraim and Manasseh:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.4'>Uthai, the son of Ammihud, the son of Omri, the son of Imri, the son of Bani, of the sons of Pharez, the son of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.5'>And of Shiloni: Asaiah the firstborn and his sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.6'>And of the sons of Zerah: Jeuel and their brethren, six hundred and ninety.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.7'>And of the sons of Benjamin: Sallu, the son of Meshullam, the son of Hodaviah, the son of Hasenuah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.8'>and Ibneiah the son of Jeroham; and Elah, the son of Uzzi, the son of Michri; and Meshullam, the son of Shephathiah, the son of Reuel, the son of Ibnijah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.9'>and their brethren, according to their generations, nine hundred and fifty-six. All these men [were] heads of the fathers in the houses of their fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.10'>And of the priests: Jedaiah, Jehoiarib, and Jachin;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.11'>and Azariah, the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, prince of the house of God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.12'>and Adaiah, the son of Jeroham, the son of Pashur, the son of Malchijah; and Maasiai, the son of Adiel, the son of Jahzerah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Meshillemith, the son of Immer;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.13'>and their brethren, heads of the houses of their fathers, one thousand seven hundred and sixty, mighty men of valour for the work of the ministry of the house of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.14'>And of the Levites: Shemaiah, the son of Hasshub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, of the sons of Merari;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.15'>and Bakbakkar, Heresh, and Galal, and Mattaniah, the son of Micah, the son of Zichri, the son of Asaph;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.16'>and Obadiah, the son of Shemaiah, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun; and Berechiah, the son of Asa, the son of Elkanah, who dwelt in the villages of the Netophathites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.17'>And the porters: Shallum, Akkub, Talmon, Ahiman, and their brethren; Shallum [was] the head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.18'>And until now in the companies of the sons of Levi these [have been] the porters in the king's gate towards the east.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.19'>And Shallum, the son of Kore, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah, and his brethren of the house of his father, the Korahites, [were] over the work of the ministry, keepers of the gates of the tabernacle; and their fathers, [being] over the camp of the LORD, [were] keepers of the entry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.20'>And Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, was the captain over them in time past, [and] the LORD [was] with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.21'>[And] Zechariah, the son of Meshelemiah, [was] porter of the door of the tabernacle of the testimony.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.22'>All these [which were] chosen to be porters in the gates [were] two hundred and twelve when they were reckoned by their genealogy in their villages, whom David and Samuel, the seer, ordained in their set office.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.23'>So they and their sons [had] the oversight of the gates of the house of the LORD, [namely], the house of the tabernacle, by wards.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.24'>Towards the four winds were the porters, toward the east, west, north, and Negev.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.25'>And their brethren, [who were] in their villages, came every seven days in their set times with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.26'>For these Levites, the four chief porters, were in [their] set office and were over the chambers and treasures of the house of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.27'>And they lodged round about the house of God, because the charge [was] upon them, and the opening thereof every morning [pertained] to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.28'>And [certain] of them had the charge of the vessels of ministry, that they should account for them when they were brought in and out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.29'>[Some] of them also [were] appointed to oversee the vessels and all the instruments of the sanctuary and the fine flour and the wine and the oil and the frankincense and the spices.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.30'>And [some] of the sons of the priests made the ointment of the spices.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.31'>And Mattithiah, [one] of the Levites, who [was] the firstborn of Shallum, the Korahite, had the set office over the things that were made in the pans.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.32'>And [other] of their brethren, of the sons of the Kohathites, [were] over the showbread, to order [it] every sabbath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.33'>And of these there were singers, princes of the fathers of the Levites, [who remained] in the chambers [free from other work]; for they were employed in [that] work day and night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.34'>These heads of the fathers of the Levites [were] heads throughout their generations; these dwelt at Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.35'>And in Gibeon dwelt the father of Gibeon, Jehiel, whose wife's name [was] Maachah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.36'>and his firstborn son Abdon, then Zur, Kish, Baal, Ner, Nadab,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.37'>Gedor, Ahio, Zechariah, and Mikloth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.38'>And Mikloth begat Shimeam. And they also dwelt with their brethren at Jerusalem, next to their brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.39'>And Ner begat Kish, and Kish begat Saul, and Saul begat Jonathan, Malchishua, Abinadab, and Eshbaal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.40'>And the son of Jonathan [was] Meribbaal, and Meribbaal begat Micah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.41'>And the sons of Micah: Pithon, Melech, Tahrea, [and Ahaz].</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.42'>And Ahaz begat Jarah, and Jarah begat Alemeth, Azmaveth, and Zimri; and Zimri begat Moza,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.43'>and Moza begat Binea; and Rephaiah his son, Eleasah his son, Azel his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.9.44'>And Azel had six sons, whose names [are] these: Azrikam, Bocheru, Ishmael, Sheariah, Obadiah, and Hanan: these [were] the sons of Azel.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.10'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.10.1'>Now the Philistines fought against Israel; and the men of Israel fled from before the Philistines and fell down slain in Mount Gilboa.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.10.2'>And the Philistines followed hard after Saul and after his sons; and the Philistines slew Jonathan, Abinadab, and Malchishua, the sons of Saul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.10.3'>And the battle went sore against Saul, and the archers hit him, and he was wounded of the archers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.10.4'>Then said Saul to his armourbearer, Draw thy sword and thrust me through with it lest these uncircumcised come and abuse me. But his armourbearer would not, for he was sore afraid. Then Saul took a sword and fell upon it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.10.5'>And when his armourbearer saw that Saul was dead, he fell likewise on his sword and died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.10.6'>So Saul died and his three sons and all his house died together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.10.7'>And when all the men of Israel that [were] in the valley saw that, they fled, and that Saul and his sons were dead, then they forsook their cities and fled, and the Philistines came and dwelt in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.10.8'>And it came to pass on the next day, when the Philistines came to strip the slain, that they found Saul and his sons fallen in Mount Gilboa.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.10.9'>And when they had stripped him, they took his head and his weapons and sent into the land of the Philistines round about, to carry tidings unto their idols and to the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.10.10'>And they put his weapons in the house of their gods and fastened his head in the temple of Dagon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.10.11'>And when all Jabeshgilead heard all that the Philistines had done to Saul,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.10.12'>all the valiant men arose and took away the body of Saul and the bodies of his sons and brought them to Jabesh and buried their bones under the oak in Jabesh and fasted seven days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.10.13'>So Saul died for his rebellion which he committed against the LORD, [even] against the word of the LORD, which he did not keep, and also for consulting a spiritist, to enquire [of her]</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.10.14'>and not enquire of the LORD; therefore, he slew him and turned the kingdom unto David, the son of Jesse.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.11'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.1'>Then all Israel gathered themselves to David in Hebron, saying, Behold, we [are] thy bone and thy flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.2'>And moreover yesterday and the day before yesterday, when Saul was king, it was thou that led out and brought in Israel; and the LORD thy God hath said unto thee, Thou shalt feed my people Israel, and thou shalt be ruler over my people Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.3'>Therefore, all the elders of Israel came to the king in Hebron, and David made a covenant with them in Hebron before the LORD, and they anointed David king over Israel, according to the word of the LORD by the hand of Samuel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.4'>Then David and all Israel went to Jerusalem, which [is] Jebus, for there the Jebusites [were], the inhabitants of that land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.5'>And the inhabitants of Jebus said to David, Thou shalt not enter here. Nevertheless, David took the fortress of Zion, which [is] the city of David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.6'>And David said, Whoever smites the Jebusites first shall be head and prince. So Joab, the son of Zeruiah, went up first and was made the head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.7'>And David dwelt in the fortress; therefore, they called it the city of David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.8'>And he built the city round about, even from Millo round about, and Joab restored the rest of the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.9'>So David waxed greater and greater, for the LORD of the hosts [was] with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.10'>These also [are] the chief of the mighty men whom David had, who strengthened him in his kingdom, with all Israel, to make him king over Israel, according to the word of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.11'>And this [is] the number of the mighty men whom David had: Jashobeam, of Hachmoni, the chief of the captains; he lifted up his spear against three hundred slain at one time and killed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.12'>And after him [was] Eleazar, the son of Dodo, the Ahohite, who [was one] of the three mighties.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.13'>He was with David at Pasdammim, and there the Philistines were gathered together to battle, where [there] was an inheritance of land full of barley; and as the people fled from before the Philistines,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.14'>they set themselves in the midst of [that] portion and delivered it and slew the Philistines; and the LORD saved [them] by a great salvation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.15'>Now three of the thirty principal ones went down to the rock to David, into the cave of Adullam; and the camp of the Philistines was pitched in the valley of Rephaim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.16'>And David [was] then in the fortress, and the Philistines' garrison [was] then at Bethlehem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.17'>And David longed and said, Oh, that one would give me drink of the water of the well of Bethlehem, that [is] at the gate!</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.18'>And those three broke through the camp of the Philistines and drew water out of the well of Bethlehem, that [was] by the gate and took [it] and brought [it] to David; but David would not drink [of] it, but poured it out to the LORD,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.19'>and said, May God keep me from doing this thing. Shall I drink the blood of these men that have put their lives in jeopardy? For with [the jeopardy of] their lives they brought it. Therefore, he would not drink it. These things did these three mightiest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.20'>And Abishai, the brother of Joab, was chief of three, who had lifted up his spear against three hundred, whom he slew and had a name among the three.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.21'>Of the three, he obtained the most honour in this second [group of three], for he was their prince; however, he did not attain to the [first] three.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.22'>Benaiah, the son of Jehoiada, the son of a valiant man, of great acts, of Kabzeel; he slew two lions of Moab; he also went down and slew a lion in the middle of a pit on a snowy day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.23'>And he slew an Egyptian, a man of [great] stature, five cubits high; and in the Egyptian's hand [was] a spear like a weaver's beam; and he went down to him with a staff and plucked the spear out of the Egyptian's hand and slew him with his own spear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.24'>These [things] did Benaiah, the son of Jehoiada, and had the name among the three mighties.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.25'>He was the most honoured among the thirty, but did not attain to the [first] three. And David placed him in his council.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.26'>Also the valiant men of the armies [were] Asahel the brother of Joab, Elhanan, the son of Dodo of Bethlehem,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.27'>Shammoth of Harori, Helez, the Pelonite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.28'>Ira, the son of Ikkesh, the Tekoite, Abiezer, the Antothite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.29'>Sibbecai, the Hushathite, Ilai, the Ahohite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.30'>Maharai, the Netophathite, Heled, the son of Baanah, the Netophathite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.31'>Ithai, the son of Ribai of Gibeah, [that pertained] to the sons of Benjamin, Benaiah, the Pirathonite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.32'>Hurai of the Gaash river, Abiel, the Arbathite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.33'>Azmaveth, the Baharumite, Eliahba, the Shaalbonite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.34'>the sons of Hashem, the Gizonite, Jonathan, the son of Shage, the Hararite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.35'>Ahiam, the son of Sacar, the Hararite, Eliphal, the son of Ur,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.36'>Hepher, the Mecherathite, Ahijah, the Pelonite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.37'>Hezro, the Carmelite, Naarai, the son of Ezbai,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.38'>Joel, the brother of Nathan, Mibhar, the son of Haggeri,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.39'>Zelek, the Ammonite, Naharai, the Berothite, the armourbearer of Joab, the son of Zeruiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.40'>Ira, the Ithrite, Gareb, the Ithrite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.41'>Uriah, the Hittite, Zabad, the son of Ahlai,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.42'>Adina, the son of Shiza, the Reubenite, head of the Reubenites, and thirty with him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.43'>Hanan, the son of Maachah, and Joshaphat, the Mithnite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.44'>Uzzia, the Ashterathite, Shama and Jehiel, the sons of Hothan, the Aroerite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.45'>Jediael, the son of Shimri, and Joha, his brother, the Tizite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.46'>Eliel, the Mahavite, and Jeribai, and Joshaviah, the sons of Elnaam, and Ithmah, the Moabite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.11.47'>Eliel, and Obed, and Jasiel the Mesobaite.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.12'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.1'>Now these [are] those that came to David to Ziklag, while he was yet restrained because of Saul, the son of Kish; and they [were] among the mighty men, helpers of the war.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.2'>[They were] armed with bows and could use both the right hand and the left in [hurling] stones and [shooting] arrows out of a bow, [even] of Saul's brethren of Benjamin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.3'>The chief [was] Ahiezer, then Joash, the sons of Shemaah, the Gibeathite; and Jeziel and Pelet, the sons of Azmaveth; and Berachah and Jehu, the Antothite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.4'>and Ismaiah, the Gibeonite, a mighty man among the thirty, and more than the thirty; and Jeremiah, Jahaziel, Johanan, Josabad, the Gederathite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.5'>Eluzai, Jerimoth, Bealiah, Shemariah, Shephatiah, the Haruphite;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.6'>Elkanah, Jesiah, Azareel, Joezer, Jashobeam, the Korhites,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.7'>and Joelah and Zebadiah, the sons of Jeroham of Gedor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.8'>And of the Gadites there separated themselves unto David in the fortress in the wilderness, men of might of war [fit] for the battle, put in order with shield and buckler, whose faces [were like] the faces of lions and [were] as swift as the roes upon the mountains;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.9'>Ezer, the chief, Obadiah, the second, Eliab, the third,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.10'>Mishmannah, the fourth, Jeremiah, the fifth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.11'>Attai, the sixth, Eliel, the seventh,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.12'>Johanan, the eighth, Elzabad, the ninth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.13'>Jeremiah, the tenth, Machbanai, the eleventh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.14'>These [were] of the sons of Gad, captains of the host. One of the least [was] over one hundred men, and the greatest over a thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.15'>These went over the Jordan in the first month, when it had overflown all its banks, and they put to flight all [those] of the valleys to the east and to the west.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.16'>Likewise, [some] of the sons of Benjamin and Judah came to David, to the fortress.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.17'>And David went out to meet them and answered and said unto them, If you are come peaceably unto me to help me, my heart shall be knit unto you; but if [you are come] to betray me to my enemies, seeing [there is] no violence in my hands, [let] the God of our fathers look [thereon] and rebuke [it].</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.18'>Then the spirit clothed himself in Amasai, [who was] chief of the thirty, [and he said], For thee, O David, and with thee, thou son of Jesse. Peace, peace [be] unto thee, and peace [be] to thy helpers; for thy God helps thee. Then David received them and put them among the captains of the band.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.19'>And [some] of Manasseh passed over to David, when he came with the Philistines against Saul to battle, although they did not help them, for the cardinals of the Philistines, upon counsel, sent him away, saying, He will pass over to his master Saul with our heads.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.20'>As he went to Ziklag, there passed over to him of Manasseh, Adnah, Jozabad, Jediael, Michael, Jozabad, Elihu, and Zilthai, heads of the thousands that [were] of Manasseh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.21'>And they helped David with a band; for they [were] all mighty men of valour and were captains in the host.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.22'>For at [that] time help came every day to David until [it] [was] a great camp, like the camp of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.23'>And this [is] the number of the heads of those that were ready armed for war [and] came to David in Hebron, to turn the kingdom of Saul to him, according to the word of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.24'>Of the sons of Judah that bore shield and spear, six thousand eight hundred, ready armed for war.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.25'>Of the sons of Simeon, mighty men of valour for the war, seven thousand one hundred.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.26'>Of the sons of Levi four thousand six hundred.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.27'>Likewise Jehoiada, prince [of those of the lineage] of Aaron, and with him three thousand seven hundred;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.28'>and Zadok, a young man mighty of valour, and of his father's house twenty-two captains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.29'>Of the sons of Benjamin, the kindred of Saul, three thousand; for in that time many of them had the charge of the house of Saul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.30'>And of the sons of Ephraim twenty thousand eight hundred, mighty men of valour, famous throughout the houses of their fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.31'>And of the half tribe of Manasseh eighteen thousand, who were designated by name, to come and make David king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.32'>And of the sons of Issachar, two hundred chief [men], who had understanding of the times and were wise to know what Israel ought to do; and all their brethren followed their word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.33'>Of Zebulun, such as went forth to battle, expert in war, with all weapons of war, fifty thousand, who could keep rank; [they were] not of double heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.34'>And of Naphtali a thousand captains and with them with shield and spear thirty-seven thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.35'>And of those of Dan expert in war twenty-eight thousand six hundred.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.36'>And of Asher, such as went forth to battle, expert in war, forty thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.37'>And of the other side of the Jordan, of those of Reuben and those of Gad and of the half tribe of Manasseh, with all manner of instruments of war for the battle, one hundred and twenty thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.38'>All these men of war, that could keep rank, came with a perfect heart to Hebron, to make David king over all Israel; and likewise, all the rest also of Israel [were] of one heart to make David king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.39'>And there they were with David three days, eating and drinking, for their brethren had prepared for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.12.40'>And likewise, those that were near them, [even] unto Issachar and Zebulun and Naphtali, brought bread on asses and on camels and on mules and on oxen, [and] food, meal, cakes of figs, and bunches of raisins, and wine and oil, and oxen, and sheep abundantly; for [there was] joy in Israel.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.13'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.13.1'>And David consulted with the captains of thousands and hundreds [and] with all the princes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.13.2'>And David said unto all the congregation of Israel, If [it seems] good unto you and unto the LORD our God, let us send everywhere to call our brethren who have remained in all the lands of Israel and with them [also] the priests and Levites [who are] in their cities [and] suburbs, that they may gather themselves unto us;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.13.3'>and let us bring again the ark of our God to us, for from the time of Saul we have not paid attention to it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.13.4'>And all the congregation said to do so, for the thing seemed right in the eyes of all the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.13.5'>So David gathered all Israel together, from Shihor of Egypt even unto the entering of Hemath, to bring the ark of God from Kirjathjearim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.13.6'>And David went up with all Israel to Baalah, [that is], to Kirjathjearim, which is in Judah, to bring up from there the ark of God the LORD, who dwells [between] the cherubim, whose name is called [on it].</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.13.7'>And they carried the ark of God in a new cart out of the house of Abinadab, and Uzza and his brother drove the cart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.13.8'>And David and all Israel played before God with all [their] might, with songs and with harps and with psalteries and with timbrels and with cymbals and with trumpets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.13.9'>And when they came unto the threshingfloor of Chidon, Uzza put forth his hand to hold the ark, for the oxen stumbled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.13.10'>And the anger of the LORD was kindled against Uzza, and he smote him because he had put his hand to the ark, and there he died before God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.13.11'>And David was displeased because the LORD had made a breach upon Uzza; therefore, that place is called Perezuzza to this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.13.12'>And David was afraid of God that day, saying, How shall I bring the ark of God [home] to me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.13.13'>So David did not bring the ark [home] to himself to the city of David but carried it into the house of Obededom, the Gittite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.13.14'>And the ark of God remained with the household of Obededom in his house three months. And the LORD blessed the household of Obededom and all that he had.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.14'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.1'>Now Hiram, king of Tyre, sent messengers to David, and timber of cedars, with masons and carpenters, to build him a house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.2'>And David, understanding that the LORD had confirmed him king over Israel and had lifted up his kingdom above his people Israel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.3'>took more wives at Jerusalem; and David begat more sons and daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.4'>Now these [are] the names of [his] children which were born unto him in Jerusalem: Shammua, Shobab, Nathan, Solomon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.5'>Ibhar, Elishua, Elpalet,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.6'>Nogah, Nepheg, Japhia,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.7'>Elishama, Beeliada, and Eliphalet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.8'>And when the Philistines heard that David was anointed king over all Israel, all the Philistines went up to seek David. And David heard [of it] and went out against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.9'>And the Philistines came and spread themselves in the valley of Rephaim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.10'>And David enquired of God, saying, Shall I go up against the Philistines? Wilt thou deliver them into my hand? And the LORD said unto him, Go up, for I will deliver them into thy hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.11'>So they came up to Baalperazim, and David smote them there. Then David said, God has broken in upon my enemies by my hand like the breaking forth of waters. Therefore, they called the name of that place Baalperazim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.12'>And they left their gods there, and David gave a commandment, and they were burned with fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.13'>And the Philistines yet again spread themselves abroad in the valley.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.14'>Therefore, David enquired again of God; and God said unto him, Do not go up after them; go around them to come upon them over against the mulberry trees;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.15'>and it shall be, when thou shalt hear a sound of marching in the tops of the mulberry trees, [that] then thou shalt go out to battle; for God shall go forth before thee to smite the host of the Philistines.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.16'>David, therefore, did as God commanded him, and they smote the host of the Philistines from Gibeon even to Gazer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.14.17'>And the fame of David went out into all those lands, and the LORD put the fear of him upon all the Gentiles.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.15'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.1'>And [David] made houses for himself in the city of David and prepared a place for the ark of God and pitched a tent for it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.2'>Then David said, The ark of God should not be brought except by the Levites, for the LORD has chosen them to carry the ark of God and to minister unto him perpetually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.3'>And David gathered all Israel together in Jerusalem to bring up the ark of the LORD unto its place, which he had prepared for it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.4'>And David assembled the sons of Aaron and the Levites:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.5'>of the sons of Kohath: Uriel, the chief, and his brethren, one hundred and twenty;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.6'>of the sons of Merari: Asaiah, the chief and his brethren, two hundred and twenty;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.7'>of the sons of Gershon: Joel, the chief, and his brethren one hundred and thirty;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.8'>of the sons of Elizaphan: Shemaiah, the chief, and his brethren, two hundred;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.9'>of the sons of Hebron: Eliel, the chief and his brethren, eighty;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.10'>of the sons of Uzziel: Amminadab, the chief, and his brethren, one hundred and twelve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.11'>And David also called for Zadok and Abiathar, the priests, and for the Levites, for Uriel, Asaiah, Joel, Shemaiah, Eliel, and Amminadab</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.12'>and said unto them, Ye [are] the chief of the fathers among the Levites; sanctify yourselves and your brethren and bring up the ark of the LORD God of Israel unto [the place] that I have prepared for it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.13'>for because ye did not [do it thus] at the first, the LORD our God made a breach upon us because we did not seek him according to his ordinance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.14'>So the priests and the Levites sanctified themselves to bring up the ark of the LORD God of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.15'>And the sons of the Levites bore the ark of God upon their shoulders with the staves, as Moses had commanded according to the word of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.16'>And David spoke to the chief of the Levites to appoint of their brethren as singers with instruments of music, with psalteries and harps and cymbals sounding, and to lift up their voice with joy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.17'>So the Levites appointed Heman, the son of Joel; and of his brethren, Asaph, the son of Berechiah; and of the sons of Merari and of their brethren, Ethan the son of Kushaiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.18'>and with them their brethren of the second order, Zechariah, Ben, Jaaziel, Shemiramoth, Jehiel, Unni, Eliab, Benaiah, Maaseiah, Mattithiah, Elipheleh, Mikneiah, Obededom, and Jeiel, the porters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.19'>So the singers, Heman, Asaph, and Ethan, raised their voices with cymbals of brass;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.20'>and Zechariah, Aziel, Shemiramoth, Jehiel, Unni, Eliab, Maaseiah, and Benaiah, with psalteries on Alamoth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.21'>And Mattithiah, Elipheleh, Mikneiah, Obededom, Jeiel, and Azaziah, with harps on the Sheminith to excel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.22'>And Chenaniah, prince of the Levites in prophecy, for he presided in prophecy, because he [had] understanding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.23'>And Berechiah and Elkanah [were] doorkeepers for the ark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.24'>And Shebaniah, Jehoshaphat, Nethaneel, Amasai, Zechariah, Benaiah, and Eliezer, the priests, blew the trumpets before the ark of God; and Obededom and Jehiah [were also] doorkeepers for the ark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.25'>So David and the elders of Israel and the captains over thousands went to bring up the ark of the covenant of the LORD out of the house of Obededom with joy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.26'>And with God helping the Levites that bore the ark of the covenant of the LORD, they sacrificed seven bullocks and seven rams.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.27'>And David [was] clothed with a robe of fine linen, and also all the Levites that bore the ark and the singers and Chenaniah, the prince of the prophecy of the singers. David also [had] upon him an ephod of linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.28'>Thus all Israel brought up the ark of the covenant of the LORD with shouting and with sound of the shofar and with trumpets and with cymbals, making a noise with psalteries and harps.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.15.29'>And it came to pass, [as] the ark of the covenant of the LORD came to the city of David, that Michal the daughter of Saul looking out at a window saw King David dancing and playing, and she despised him in her heart.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.16'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.1'>So they brought the ark of God and set it in the midst of the tent that David had pitched for it, and they offered burnt sacrifices and peace [offerings] before God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.2'>And when David had finished offering the burnt offerings and the peace [offerings], he blessed the people in the name of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.3'>And he dealt to all Israel, both men and women, to each one a loaf of bread and a good piece of flesh and a flagon [of wine].</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.4'>And he appointed [certain] of the Levites to minister before the ark of the LORD and to record and to thank and praise the LORD God of Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.5'>Asaph, the chief, and next to him Zechariah, Jeiel, Shemiramoth, Jehiel, Mattithiah, Eliab, Benaiah, Obededom: and Jeiel with psalteries and with harps, but Asaph resounded with cymbals;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.6'>and Benaiah and Jahaziel, the priests, with trumpets continually before the ark of the covenant of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.7'>Then, on that day, David began to thank the LORD by the hand of Asaph and his brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.8'>Give thanks unto the LORD, call upon his name, make known his deeds among the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.9'>Sing unto him, sing psalms unto him, speak of all his wondrous works.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.10'>Glory in his holy name; let the heart of those that seek the LORD rejoice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.11'>Seek the LORD and his strength, seek his face continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.12'>Remember his marvellous works that he has done, his wonders and the judgments of his mouth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.13'>O, ye seed of Israel, his servant, ye sons of Jacob, his chosen ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.14'>He [is] the LORD our God; his judgments [are] in all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.15'>Be mindful always of his covenant, the word [which] he commanded in a thousand generations,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.16'>the covenant which he cut with Abraham, and of his oath unto Isaac;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.17'>which he confirmed unto Jacob by statute, [and] to Israel in everlasting covenant,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.18'>saying, Unto thee will I give the land of Canaan, the cord of your inheritance,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.19'>when ye were but few in number, and strangers in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.20'>And they went from nation to nation and from [one] kingdom to another people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.21'>He would allow no one to oppress them; he reproved kings for their sakes,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.22'>[saying], Touch not my anointed, and do my prophets no harm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.23'>Sing unto the LORD, all the earth; show forth from day to day his saving health.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.24'>Declare his glory among the Gentiles; his marvellous works among all peoples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.25'>For great [is] the LORD, and greatly to be praised; he also [is] to be feared above all gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.26'>For all the gods of the people [are] worthless, but the LORD made the heavens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.27'>Glory and beauty [are] in his presence; strength and gladness [are] in his place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.28'>Give unto the LORD, ye families of the peoples, give unto the LORD glory and strength.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.29'>Give unto the LORD the glory of his name; bring a present and come before him; worship the LORD in the beauty of holiness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.30'>Fear before him, all the earth; the world also is being made stable, that it be not moved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.31'>Let the heavens be glad, and let the earth rejoice; and let [men] say among the Gentiles, The LORD reigns.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.32'>Let the sea roar, and the fullness thereof; let the fields rejoice, and all that [is] therein.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.33'>Then shall the trees of the wood sing out at the presence of the LORD, because he comes to judge the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.34'>O give thanks unto the LORD, for [he is] good; for his mercy is eternal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.35'>And say, Save us, O God our saving health, and gather us together and deliver us from the Gentiles, that we may give thanks to thy holy name [and] glory in thy praise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.36'>Blessed [be] the LORD God of Israel from eternity unto eternity. And all the people said, Amen and praised the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.37'>So he left there before the ark of the covenant of the LORD Asaph and his brethren to minister before the ark continually, each thing in its day;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.38'>and Obededom with their brethren, sixty-eight; Obededom also the son of Jeduthun and Hosah [to be] porters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.39'>And Zadok, the priest, and his brethren, the priests, before the tabernacle of the LORD in the high place that [was] at Gibeon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.40'>to offer burnt offerings unto the LORD upon the altar of the burnt offering continually morning and evening, according to all that is written in the law of the LORD, which he commanded Israel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.41'>and with them Heman and Jeduthun and the rest that were chosen expressly by name, to give thanks to the LORD, because his mercy is eternal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.42'>And with them Heman and Jeduthun with trumpets and cymbals to sound, and with [other] musical instruments of God. And the sons of Jeduthun [were] porters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.16.43'>And all the people departed each one to his house; and David returned to bless his house.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.17'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.1'>Now it came to pass, as David dwelt in his house, that David said to Nathan, the prophet, Behold, I dwell in a house of cedars, and the ark of the covenant of the LORD under curtains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.2'>Then Nathan said unto David, Do all that [is] in thy heart for God [is] with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.3'>And it came to pass the same night that the word of God came to Nathan, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.4'>Go and tell David my servant, Thus hath the LORD said, Thou shalt not build me a house to dwell in,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.5'>for I have not dwelt in a house since the day that I brought up Israel unto this day, but have gone from tent to tent, and from [one] tabernacle [to another].</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.6'>Wherever I have walked with all Israel, did I speak a word to any of the judges of Israel, whom I commanded to feed my people, saying, Why have ye not built me a house of cedars?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.7'>Now, therefore, thus shalt thou say unto my servant David, Thus hath the LORD of the hosts said, I took thee from the sheepfold, from following the sheep that thou should be ruler over my people Israel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.8'>and I have been with thee wherever thou hast walked and have cut off all thy enemies from before thee and have made thee a name like the name of the great men that [are] in the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.9'>Likewise I have ordained a place for my people Israel and have planted him that he dwell by himself and no longer be moved; neither shall the sons of iniquity waste them any more, as before,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.10'>since the time that I commanded judges [to be] over my people Israel. I have humbled all thy enemies and announce unto thee that the LORD will build thee a house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.11'>And it shall come to pass, when thy days are fulfilled to go to be with thy fathers, that I will raise up thy seed after thee, which shall be of thy sons; and I will establish his kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.12'>He shall build me a house, and I will establish his throne eternally.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.13'>I will be his father, and he shall be my son; and I will not take my mercy away from him, as I took [it] from [him] that was before thee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.14'>but I will confirm him in my house and in my kingdom for ever, and his throne shall be established for evermore.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.15'>According to all these words, and according to all this vision, so did Nathan speak unto David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.16'>And David, the king, came and sat before the LORD and said, Who [am] I, O LORD God, and what [is] my house, that thou hast brought me here?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.17'>And [yet] this was a small thing in thy eyes, O God, for thou hast [also] spoken of thy servant's house for a great while to come and hast regarded me according to the estate of a man of high degree, O LORD God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.18'>What more can David add asking thee to glorify thy servant? For thou knowest thy servant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.19'>O LORD, for thy servant's sake and according to thy own heart, thou hast done all this greatness, in making known all thy great things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.20'>O LORD, [there is] none like thee, neither [is there any] God beside thee, according to all that we have heard with our ears.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.21'>And what one nation in the earth [is] like thy people Israel, whom God went to ransom [to be] his own people, to make thee a name of greatness and terribleness, by driving out the Gentiles from before thy people, whom thou didst redeem out of Egypt?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.22'>For thy people Israel didst thou make thy own people for ever, and thou, LORD, didst become their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.23'>Therefore, now, LORD, let the thing that thou hast spoken concerning thy servant and concerning his house be established for ever and do as thou hast said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.24'>Let it even be established, that thy name may be magnified for ever, that it may be said, The LORD of the hosts, God of Israel, is God unto Israel; and [let] the house of David thy servant [be] established before thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.25'>For thou, O my God, hast told thy servant that thou wilt build him a house; therefore, thy servant has found [in his heart] to pray before thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.26'>And now, LORD, thou art God and hast promised this goodness unto thy servant;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.17.27'>now it has pleased thee to bless the house of thy servant, that it may be before thee for ever; for thou, O LORD, hast blessed it, and [it shall be] blessed for ever.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.18'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.1'>Now after this it came to pass that David smote the Philistines and subdued them and took Gath and her towns out of the hand of the Philistines.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.2'>And he smote Moab, and the Moabites became David's servants, bringing him presents.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.3'>And David smote Hadarezer, king of Zobah in Hamath, as he went to establish his dominion unto the River Euphrates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.4'>And David took from him a thousand chariots, seven thousand horsemen, and twenty thousand footmen; David also hamstrung all the chariot [horses], but reserved those of one hundred chariots.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.5'>And when the Syrians of Damascus came to help Hadarezer, king of Zobah, David slew of the Syrians two-twenty thousand men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.6'>Then David put [garrisons] in Syria, the [Syria] of Damascus, and the Syrians became David's servants, bringing him presents. For the LORD saved David wherever he went.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.7'>And David took the shields of gold that the servants of Hadarezer carried and brought them to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.8'>Likewise from Tibhath and from Chun, cities of Hadarezer, David took very much brass, with which Solomon made the brasen sea and the pillars and the vessels of brass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.9'>Now when Tou, king of Hamath, heard how David had smitten all the host of Hadarezer, king of Zobah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.10'>he sent Hadoram, his son, to King David, to greet him and to bless him because he had fought against Hadarezer and smitten him, for Hadarezer had war with Tou. And he [sent him] all manner of vessels of gold and silver and brass,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.11'>which king David dedicated unto the LORD, with the silver and the gold that he brought from all [these] Gentiles, from Edom and from Moab and from the sons of Ammon and from the Philistines and from Amalek.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.12'>Moreover, Abishai, the son of Zeruiah, smote Edom in the valley of salt, eighteen thousand [men].</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.13'>And he put a garrison in Edom, and all the Edomites became David's servants. Thus the LORD saved David wherever he went.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.14'>So David reigned over all Israel and executed judgment and righteousness among all his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.15'>And Joab, the son of Zeruiah, [was] over the host; and Jehoshaphat, the son of Ahilud, writer of the chronicles;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.16'>and Zadok, the son of Ahitub, and Abimelech, the son of Abiathar, [were] the priests; and Shavsha was scribe;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.18.17'>and Benaiah, the son of Jehoiada, [was] over the Cherethites and the Pelethites; and the sons of David [were] first, at the hand of the king.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.19'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.1'>Now it came to pass after this that Nahash the king of the sons of Ammon, died, and his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.2'>And David said, I will show mercy unto Hanun, the son of Nahash, because his father showed mercy to me. And David sent ambassadors to comfort him concerning his father. So the servants of David came into the land of the sons of Ammon to Hanun, to comfort him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.3'>But the princes of the sons of Ammon said to Hanun, Does it seem unto thee that David honours thy father, that he has sent comforters unto thee? Are not his servants come unto thee to search and to overthrow and to spy out the land?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.4'>Then Hanun took David's servants and shaved them, and cut off their garments in half, exposing their buttocks and sent them away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.5'>Then they left, and it was told David how the men were served. And he sent to meet them, for the men were greatly ashamed. And the king said, Tarry at Jericho until your beards are grown and [then] return.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.6'>And when the sons of Ammon saw that they had made themselves odious to David, Hanun and the sons of Ammon sent a thousand talents of silver to hire chariots and horsemen out of Syria of the rivers ([Mesopotamia]), and out of Syria of Maachah and out of Zobah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.7'>So they hired thirty-two thousand chariots, and the king of Maachah and his people, who came and pitched camp before Medeba. And the sons of Ammon gathered themselves together from their cities and came to battle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.8'>And when David heard [of it], he sent Joab and all the host of the mighty men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.9'>And the sons of Ammon came out and put the battle in order before the gate of the city, and the kings that had come [were] by themselves in the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.10'>Now when Joab saw that the battle was set against him before and behind, he chose out of all the choice of Israel and put [them] in order against the Syrians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.11'>And he put the rest of the people into the hand of Abishai, his brother, putting them in order against the sons of Ammon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.12'>And he said, If the Syrians are too strong for me, then thou shalt save me; but if the sons of Ammon are too strong for thee, then I will save thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.13'>Be of good courage, and let us behave ourselves valiantly for our people and for the cities of our God; and let the LORD do [that which is] good in his sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.14'>So Joab and the people that [were] with him drew near before the Syrians unto the battle; and they fled before him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.15'>And when the sons of Ammon saw that the Syrians had fled, they likewise fled before Abishai, his brother, and entered into the city. Then Joab returned to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.16'>And when the Syrians saw that they were smitten before Israel, they sent ambassadors and drew forth the Syrians that [were] beyond the river, whose captain was Shophach, the prince of the host of Hadarezer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.17'>And when it was told David, he gathered all Israel and passed over the Jordan and came upon them and ordered his host against them. And when David had put his troops in order against the Syrians, they fought with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.18'>But the Syrian fled before Israel, and David slew of the Syrians [those of] seven thousand chariots, and forty thousand footmen; likewise he killed Shophach, the captain of the host.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.19.19'>And when the servants of Hadarezer saw that they were smitten before Israel, they made peace with David and became his servants; neither would the Syrians help the sons of Ammon any more.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.20'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.20.1'>And it came to pass, that after the year was expired, at the time that kings go out [to battle], Joab led forth the power of the army and destroyed the country of the sons of Ammon and came and besieged Rabbah. But David tarried at Jerusalem. And Joab smote Rabbah and destroyed it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.20.2'>And David took the crown of their king from off his head and found it to weigh a talent of gold, and [there were] precious stones in it; and it was set upon David's head. And in addition to this he took exceeding much spoil out of the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.20.3'>And he brought out the people that [were] in it and dominated [them] with saws, and with harrows of iron, and with axes. Even so dealt David with all the cities of the sons of Ammon. And David and all the people returned to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.20.4'>And it came to pass after this that there arose war at Gezer with the Philistines at which time Sibbechai the Hushathite, slew Sippai, of the lineage of the giant; and they were subdued.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.20.5'>And there was war again with the Philistines, and Elhanan, the son of Jair, slew Lahmi, the brother of Goliath the Gittite, whose spear staff [was] like a weaver's beam.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.20.6'>And yet again there was war at Gath, where [there] was a man of [great] stature, who had twenty-four fingers and toes, six [on each hand], and six [on each foot]; and he also was the son of the giant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.20.7'>But when he dishonoured Israel, Jonathan, the son of Shimea, David's brother slew him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.20.8'>These were born unto the giant in Gath; and they fell by the hand of David and by the hand of his servants.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.21'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.1'>And Satan stood up against Israel and provoked David to number Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.2'>And David said to Joab and to the princes of the people, Go, number Israel from Beersheba even to Dan; and bring the number of them to me, that I may know [it].</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.3'>And Joab answered, The LORD make his people a hundred times as many more as they [are]; but, my lord the king, [are] they not all my lord's servants? Why then does my lord require this thing? Why will he be a cause of guiltiness unto Israel?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.4'>Nevertheless, the king's word prevailed against Joab. Therefore, Joab departed and went throughout all Israel and came to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.5'>And Joab gave the sum of the number of the people unto David. And they found in all Israel eleven times one hundred thousand men that drew sword, and of Judah four hundred seventy thousand men that drew sword.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.6'>Among these the Levites and the sons of Benjamin were not counted, for the king's word was abominable to Joab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.7'>And God was also displeased with this word; therefore, he smote Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.8'>And David said unto God, I have sinned greatly because I have done this thing; but now, I beseech thee, take away the iniquity of thy servant, for I have done very foolishly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.9'>And the LORD spoke unto Gad, David's seer, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.10'>Go and tell David, saying, Thus hath the LORD said, I offer thee three [things]: choose one of them that I will do unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.11'>So Gad came to David and said unto him, Thus hath the LORD said, Choose thee,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.12'>either three years' famine or three months to be destroyed before thy foes while the sword of thine enemies overtakes [thee] or else three days [of] the sword of the LORD, even the pestilence, in the land, and the angel of the LORD destroying throughout all the borders of Israel. Now therefore advise thyself what word I shall bring again to him that sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.13'>Then David said unto Gad, I am in a great strait; let me fall now into the hand of the LORD, for very great [are] his mercies, but do not let me fall into the hand of man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.14'>So the LORD sent pestilence upon Israel; and seventy thousand men of Israel fell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.15'>And God sent an angel unto Jerusalem to destroy it; and as he was destroying, the LORD beheld, and he repented of that evil and said to the angel that destroyed, It is enough, stay now thy hand. And the angel of the LORD stood by the threshingfloor of Ornan, the Jebusite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.16'>And David lifted up his eyes and saw the angel of the LORD stand between the heaven and the earth, having a drawn sword in his hand stretched out over Jerusalem. Then David and the elders [of Israel], [who were] clothed in sackcloth, fell upon their faces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.17'>And David said unto God, [Is it] not I [that] commanded the people to be numbered? Even I it is that have sinned and done evil indeed; but [as for] these sheep, what have they done? Let thy hand, I pray thee, O LORD my God, be against me and against my father's house, but not on thy people, that they should be plagued.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.18'>Then the angel of the LORD told Gad to tell David that David should go up and set up an altar unto the LORD in the threshingfloor of Ornan the Jebusite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.19'>And David went up according to the word of Gad, which he had spoken unto him in the name of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.20'>And Ornan turned back and saw the angel, and his four sons with him hid themselves. Now Ornan was threshing wheat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.21'>And as David came to Ornan, Ornan looked and saw David and went out of the threshingfloor and bowed himself to David with [his] face to the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.22'>Then David said to Ornan, Grant me the place of [this] threshingfloor, that I may build an altar therein unto the LORD; thou shalt grant it to me for the full price, that the plague may be stayed from the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.23'>And Ornan said unto David, Take [it] to thee, and let my lord the king do [that which is] good in his eyes; I even give [thee] the oxen for burnt offerings and the threshing instruments for wood and the wheat for the present; I give it all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.24'>And King David said to Ornan, No, but I will truly buy it for the full price, for I will not take [that] which [is] thine for the LORD, nor offer burnt offerings without cost.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.25'>So David gave to Ornan for the place six hundred shekels of gold by weight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.26'>And David built there an altar unto the LORD and offered burnt offerings and peace [offerings] and called upon the LORD, and he answered him from the heavens by fire upon the altar of burnt offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.27'>And when the LORD spoke to the angel, he put up his sword again into its sheath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.28'>At that time when David saw that the LORD had answered him in the threshingfloor of Ornan, the Jebusite, then he sacrificed there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.29'>For the tabernacle of the LORD, which Moses made in the wilderness, and the altar of the burnt offering [were] at that season in the high place at Gibeon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.21.30'>but David could not go before it to enquire of God, for he was afraid because of the sword of the angel of the LORD.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.22'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.1'>Then David said, This [shall be] the house of the LORD God, and this [shall be] the altar of the burnt offering for Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.2'>And David commanded to gather together the strangers that [were] in the land of Israel, and he made them masons to hew wrought stones to build the house of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.3'>Likewise, David prepared iron in abundance for the nails for the doors of the gates, and for the joinings, and brass in abundance without weight,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.4'>also cedar trees in abundance, for the Zidonians and those of Tyre brought much cedar wood to David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.5'>And David said, Solomon, my son, [is] yet young and tender, and the house [that is] to be built for the LORD [must be] magnificent par excellence, of fame and of glory throughout all lands; I will [therefore] now make preparation for it. So David prepared abundantly before his death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.6'>Then he called for Solomon, his son, and charged him to build a house for the LORD God of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.7'>And David said to Solomon, My son, as for me, it was in my heart to build a house unto the name of the LORD my God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.8'>but the word of the LORD came to me, saying, Thou hast shed blood abundantly and hast made great wars; thou shalt not build a house unto my name because thou hast shed much blood upon the earth in my sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.9'>Behold, a son shall be born to thee, who shall be a man of rest, and I will give him rest from all his enemies round about, for his name shall be Solomon, and I will give peace and quietness unto Israel in his days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.10'>He shall build a house for my name, and he shall be my son, and I [will be] his father; and I will establish the throne of his kingdom over Israel for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.11'>Now, my son, the LORD be with thee, and be thou prospered and build the house of the LORD thy God, as he has said of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.12'>Only the LORD give thee wisdom and understanding and give thee commandments for Israel, and that thou keep the law of the LORD thy God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.13'>Then shalt thou be prospered if thou shalt keep thyself to do the statutes and rights which the LORD charged Moses with concerning Israel; be strong and of good courage; dread not, nor be dismayed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.14'>Now, behold, in my trouble I have prepared for the house of the LORD one hundred thousand talents of gold and a thousand thousand talents of silver, and the brass and iron are without weight, for it is in abundance. Likewise, I have prepared timber and stone, unto which thou shalt add.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.15'>Moreover [there are] workmen with thee in abundance, hewers and workers of stone and timber and all manner of expert men for every manner of work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.16'>Of the gold, the silver, and the brass and the iron, [there is] no number. Arise [therefore], and go to work, and the LORD be with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.17'>David, likewise, commanded all the princes of Israel to help Solomon, his son, [saying],</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.18'>[Is] not the LORD your God with you who has given you rest on every side? For he has given the inhabitants of the land into my hand, and the land is subdued before the LORD and before his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.22.19'>Now set your heart and your soul to seek the LORD your God; arise therefore and build the sanctuary of the LORD God, to bring the ark of the covenant of the LORD and the holy vessels of God into the house that is to be built unto the name of the LORD.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.23'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.1'>So when David was old and full of days, he made Solomon, his son, king over Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.2'>And he gathered together all the princes of Israel, and the priests and the Levites,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.3'>were numbered from the age of thirty years and upward; and their number by their polls, man by man, was thirty-eight thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.4'>Of which, twenty-four thousand [were] to set forward the work of the house of the LORD, and six thousand [were] officers and judges;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.5'>moreover, four thousand [were] porters, and four thousand praised the LORD with the instruments which [David] had made to praise [therewith].</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.6'>And David divided them into courses according to the sons of Levi, [namely], Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.7'>The sons of Gershon: Laadan and Shimei.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.8'>The sons of Laadan: Jehiel, the first, Zetham and Joel, three.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.9'>The sons of Shimei: Shelomith, Haziel, and Haran, three. These [were] the chief of the fathers of Laadan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.10'>And the sons of Shimei: Jahath, Zina, Jeush, and Beriah. These four [were] the sons of Shimei.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.11'>And Jahath was the first, and Zizah the second, but Jeush and Beriah did not multiply [in many] sons; therefore, they were in one reckoning, according to [their] father's house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.12'>The sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel, four.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.13'>The sons of Amram: Aaron and Moses. And Aaron was separated, that he should be dedicated to the most holy things, he and his sons for ever, to burn incense before the LORD, to minister unto him and to bless in his name for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.14'>And the sons of Moses, the man of God, were counted in the tribe of Levi.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.15'>The sons of Moses [were] Gershon and Eliezer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.16'>Of the sons of Gershon, Shebuel [was] the chief.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.17'>And the son of Eliezer [was] Rehabiah, the chief. And Eliezer had no other sons, but the sons of Rehabiah were very many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.18'>The sons of Izhar: Shelomith, the chief.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.19'>The sons of Hebron: Jeriah, the first, Amariah, the second, Jahaziel, the third, and Jekameam, the fourth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.20'>The sons of Uzziel: Michah, the first, and Jesiah, the second.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.21'>The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. The sons of Mahli: Eleazar and Kish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.22'>And Eleazar died and had no sons, but daughters and their brethren, the sons of Kish, took them [as wives].</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.23'>The sons of Mushi: Mahli, Eder, and Jeremoth, three.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.24'>These [are] the sons of Levi after the houses of their fathers, [even] the chief of the fathers, as they were counted by number of names by their polls, that did work in the ministry of the house of the LORD, from the age of twenty years and upward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.25'>For David said, The LORD God of Israel has given rest unto his people, and he shall dwell in Jerusalem for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.26'>And also unto the Levites, they shall no [longer] carry the tabernacle, nor any vessels of it for its ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.27'>For by the last words of David, the Levites [were] numbered from twenty years old and above.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.28'>And their station was at the hand of the sons of Aaron for the service of the house of the LORD, in the courts, and in the chambers, and in the purifying of all holy things, and in the work of the ministry of the house of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.29'>both for the showbread and for the fine flour for the sacrifice and for the unleavened cakes and for [that which is baked in] the pan and for that which is fried and for all manner of measure and size,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.30'>and to stand every morning to thank and praise the LORD, and likewise in the evening;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.31'>and to offer all burnt sacrifices unto the LORD in the sabbaths, in the new moons and solemnities, by number, according to the order commanded unto them, continually before the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.23.32'>And that they should keep the charge of the tabernacle of the testimony and the charge of the holy [place] and the charge of the sons of Aaron, their brethren, in the ministry of the house of the LORD.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.24'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.1'>The sons of Aaron also had their courses. The sons of Aaron: Nadab, Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.2'>But Nadab and Abihu died before their father and had no children; therefore, Eleazar and Ithamar had the priesthood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.3'>And David distributed them, Zadok [being] of the sons of Eleazar, and Ahimelech of the sons of Ithamar, according to their turns in their ministry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.4'>And there were more men found of the sons of Eleazar than of the sons of Ithamar, and [thus] were they divided. Among the sons of Eleazar, [there were] sixteen chief men of the houses of [their] fathers and eight among the sons of Ithamar according to the houses of their fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.5'>They divided them, therefore, by lot, one with another for of the sons of Eleazar and of the sons of Ithamar there were princes of the sanctuary and princes of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.6'>And Shemaiah, the scribe, the son of Nethaneel, [one] of the Levites, wrote them before the king and the princes and before Zadok, the priest, and Ahimelech, the son of Abiathar, and the heads of the fathers of the priests and Levites; one paternal house being taken for Eleazar, and [one] taken for Ithamar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.7'>Now the first lot came forth to Jehoiarib, the second to Jedaiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.8'>the third to Harim, the fourth to Seorim,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.9'>the fifth to Malchijah, the sixth to Mijamin,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.10'>the seventh to Hakkoz, the eighth to Abijah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.11'>the ninth to Jeshua, the tenth to Shecaniah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.12'>the eleventh to Eliashib, the twelfth to Jakim,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.13'>the thirteenth to Huppah, the fourteenth to Jeshebeab,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.14'>the fifteenth to Bilgah, the sixteenth to Immer,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.15'>the seventeenth to Hezir, the eighteenth to Aphses,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.16'>the nineteenth to Pethahiah, the twentieth to Jehezekel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.17'>the twenty-first to Jachin, the twenty-second to Gamul,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.18'>the twenty-third to Delaiah, the twenty-fourth to Maaziah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.19'>These [were] their orderings in their service to come into the house of the LORD, according to their right, in the ministry of Aaron, their father, as the LORD God of Israel had commanded him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.20'>And of the sons of Levi that remained: Of the sons of Amram, Shubael; of the sons of Shubael, Jehdeiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.21'>Rehabiah; of the sons of Rehabiah, the chief [was] Isshiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.22'>Of the Izharite; Shelomoth; and the son of Shelomoth, Jahath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.23'>And of the sons of Jeriah: Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, Jekameam the fourth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.24'>The sons of Uzziel: Michah; and the son of Michah, Shamir.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.25'>The brother of Michah [was] Isshiah; and the son of Isshiah, Zechariah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.26'>The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi; the son of Jaaziah, Beno.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.27'>The sons of Merari by Jaaziah: Beno, Shoham, Zaccur, and Ibri.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.28'>Of Mahli [came] Eleazar, who had no sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.29'>Kish; the son of Kish, Jerahmeel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.30'>The sons of Mushi: Mahli, Eder, and Jerimoth. These [were] the sons of the Levites according to the houses of their fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.24.31'>These, likewise, cast lots over against their brethren, the sons of Aaron, in the presence of David, the king, and Zadok, and Ahimelech, and the chief of the fathers of the priests and Levites, even the principal fathers over against their younger brethren.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.25'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.1'>Moreover David and the captains of the host separated unto the ministry the sons of Asaph and of Heman and of Jeduthun, who should prophesy with harps, with psalteries, and with cymbals; and the number of men that were [suitable] for the work of their [respective] ministry was,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.2'>of the sons of Asaph: Zaccur, Joseph, Nethaniah, and Asarelah, the sons of Asaph under the direction of Asaph, who prophesied at the hand of the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.3'>Of Jeduthun: the sons of Jeduthun: Gedaliah, Zeri, Jeshaiah, Hashabiah, and Mattithiah, six, under the hand of their father Jeduthun, who prophesied with a harp, to give thanks and to praise the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.4'>Of Heman: the sons of Heman: Bukkiah, Mattaniah, Uzziel, Shebuel, Jerimoth, Hananiah, Hanani, Eliathah, Giddalti, and Romamtiezer, Joshbekashah, Mallothi, Hothir, [and] Mahazioth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.5'>All these [were] the sons of Heman, the king's seer, in the words of God, to lift up the horn. And God gave to Heman fourteen sons and three daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.6'>All these [were] under the direction of their father for song [in] the house of the LORD, with cymbals, psalteries, and harps, for the ministry of the house of God, under the hand of the king, of Asaph, of Jeduthun, and of Heman.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.7'>So the number of them, with their brethren that were instructed in the songs of the LORD, [even] all that had understanding, was two hundred eighty-eight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.8'>And they cast lots, ward against [ward], the small as well as the great, the one with understanding as well as the disciple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.9'>Now the first lot came forth for Asaph to Joseph; the second to Gedaliah, who with his brethren and sons [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.10'>the third to Zaccur, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.11'>the fourth to Izri, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.12'>the fifth to Nethaniah, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.13'>the sixth to Bukkiah, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.14'>the seventh to Jesharelah, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.15'>the eighth to Jeshaiah, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.16'>the ninth to Mattaniah, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.17'>the tenth to Shimei, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.18'>the eleventh to Azareel, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.19'>the twelfth to Hashabiah, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.20'>the thirteenth to Shubael, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.21'>the fourteenth to Mattithiah, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.22'>the fifteenth to Jeremoth, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.23'>the sixteenth to Hananiah, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.24'>the seventeenth to Joshbekashah, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.25'>the eighteenth to Hanani, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.26'>the nineteenth to Mallothi, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.27'>the twentieth to Eliathah, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.28'>the twenty-first to Hothir, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.29'>the twenty-second to Giddalti, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.30'>the twenty-third to Mahazioth, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.25.31'>the twenty-fourth to Romamtiezer, [he], his sons, and his brethren [were] twelve.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.26'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.1'>Concerning the divisions of the porters, of the Korhites: Meshelemiah, the son of Kore, of the sons of Asaph.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.2'>The sons of Meshelemiah: Zechariah, the firstborn, Jediael, the second, Zebadiah, the third, Jathniel, the fourth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.3'>Elam, the fifth, Jehohanan, the sixth, Elioenai, the seventh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.4'>The sons of Obededom: Shemaiah, the firstborn, Jehozabad, the second, Joah, the third, and Sacar, the fourth, Nethaneel, the fifth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.5'>Ammiel, the sixth, Issachar, the seventh, Peulthai, the eighth; for God had blessed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.6'>Also unto Shemaiah, his son, were sons born, that ruled throughout the house of their fathers, for they [were] mighty men of valour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.7'>The sons of Shemaiah: Othni, Rephael, Obed, Elzabad, and their brethren, strong men; likewise, Elihu and Semachiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.8'>All these of the sons of Obededom; they and their sons and their brethren, valiant men strong for the ministry, [were] sixty-two, of Obededom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.9'>And Meshelemiah had sons and brethren, valiant men, eighteen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.10'>Of Hosah, of the sons of Merari: Simri, the chief, (for [though] he was not the firstborn, yet his father made him the chief)</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.11'>Hilkiah the second, Tebaliah, the third, Zechariah, the fourth; all the sons and brethren of Hosah [were] thirteen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.12'>Among these [were] the divisions of the porters, [even] among the chief men, [having] wards one against another [two by two], to minister in the house of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.13'>And they cast lots, the small as well as the great, according to the houses of their fathers, for each gate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.14'>And the lot of the east fell to Shelemiah. Then for Zechariah, his son, a wise counsellor, they cast lots; and his lot came out for the north.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.15'>To Obededom towards the Negev; and to his sons the house of consultation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.16'>To Shuppim and Hosah to the west, with the gate Shallecheth, by the causeway of the going up, ward against ward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.17'>To the east six Levites, to the north four by day, to the Negev four by day, and toward the house of the consultation two by two.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.18'>At the chamber of the vessels to the west, four in the way [and] two in the chamber.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.19'>These [are] the divisions of the porters among the sons of Kore and among the sons of Merari.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.20'>And of the Levites, Ahijah [was] over the treasures of the house of God and over the treasures of the holy things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.21'>[As concerning] the sons of Laadan; the sons of Gershon: of Laadan; chief fathers of Laadan [were] Gershon and Jehieli.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.22'>The sons of Jehieli: Zetham and Joel, his brother, [who were] over the treasures of the house of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.23'>Of the Amramites, [and] the Izharites, the Hebronites, [and] the Uzzielites,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.24'>Shebuel, the son of Gershon, the son of Moses, [was] ruler of the treasures.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.25'>And his brother Eliezer, Rehabiah, his son, Jeshaiah, his son, Joram, his son, Zichri, his son, and Shelomith, his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.26'>This Shelomith and his brethren [were] over all the treasures of the holy things, which David, the king, and the chief fathers, the captains over thousands and hundreds, and the princes of the host had dedicated.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.27'>[That which] out of the spoils won in battles they had dedicated to maintain the house of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.28'>Likewise, all that Samuel, the seer, and Saul, the son of Kish, and Abner, the son of Ner, and Joab, the son of Zeruiah, and all that anyone had dedicated; it was under the hand of Shelomith and of his brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.29'>Of the Izharites, Chenaniah and his sons [were] governors and judges over Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.30'>Of the Hebronites, Hashabiah and his brethren, men of valour, a thousand seven hundred, presided over Israel on the other side of the Jordan westward in all the work of the LORD and in the service of the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.31'>Of the Hebronites [was] Jerijah, the chief among the Hebronites, according to the generations of his fathers. In the fortieth year of the reign of David they were sought for, and there were found among them mighty men of valour at Jazer of Gilead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.26.32'>And his brethren, men of valour, [were] two thousand seven hundred chief fathers, whom King David made rulers over the Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half tribe of Manasseh, for every matter pertaining to God and affairs of the king.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.27'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.1'>Now the sons of Israel after their number, who were chief fathers and captains of thousands and hundreds, and their officers that served the king in any matter of the courses, who came in and went out month by month throughout all the months of the year, each course [was] of twenty-four thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.2'>Over the first course for the first month [was] Jashobeam, the son of Zabdiel, and in his course [were] twenty-four thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.3'>Of the sons of Perez [was] the chief of all the captains of the host for the first month.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.4'>And over the course of the second month [was] Dodai, an Ahohite, and in his course [was] prince Mikloth; in his course likewise [were] twenty-four thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.5'>The third captain of the host for the third month [was] Benaiah, the son of Jehoiada, a chief priest: and in his course [were] twenty-four thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.6'>This [is that] Benaiah, [who was] mighty [among] the thirty, and above the thirty; and in his course [was] Ammizabad, his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.7'>The fourth for the fourth month [was] Asahel, the brother of Joab, and Zebadiah his son after him; and in his course [were] twenty-four thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.8'>The fifth for the fifth month [was] prince Shamhuth, the Izrahite; and in his course [were] twenty-four thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.9'>The sixth for the sixth month [was] Ira, the son of Ikkesh of Tekoah; and in his course [were] twenty-four thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.10'>The seventh for the seventh month [was] Helez, the Pelonite, of the sons of Ephraim; and in his course [were] twenty-four thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.11'>The eighth for the eighth month [was] Sibbecai, the Hushathite, of Zarhi; and in his course [were] twenty-four thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.12'>The ninth for the ninth month [was] Abiezer, the Anetothite, of the Benjamites; and in his course [were] twenty-four thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.13'>The tenth for the tenth month [was] Maharai, the Netophathite of Zarhi; and in his course [were] twenty-four thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.14'>The eleventh for the eleventh month [was] Benaiah, the Pirathonite, of the sons of Ephraim; and in his course [were] twenty-four thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.15'>The twelfth for the twelfth month [was] Heldai, the Netophathite of Othniel; and in his course [were] twenty-four thousand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.16'>Presiding, likewise, over the tribes of Israel: over the Reubenites [was] prince Eliezer, the son of Zichri; over the Simeonites, Shephatiah, the son of Maachah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.17'>Over the Levites, Hashabiah, the son of Kemuel. Over the Aaronites, Zadok.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.18'>Over Judah, Elihu, [one] of the brethren of David. Over those of Issachar, Omri, the son of Michael.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.19'>Over those of Zebulun, Ishmaiah, the son of Obadiah. Over those of Naphtali, Jerimoth, the son of Azriel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.20'>Over the sons of Ephraim, Hosea, the son of Azaziah. Over the half tribe of Manasseh, Joel, the son of Pedaiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.21'>Over the other half [tribe] of Manasseh in Gilead, Iddo, the son of Zechariah. Over those of Benjamin, Jaasiel, the son of Abner.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.22'>And over Dan, Azareel, the son of Jeroham. These [were] the princes of the tribes of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.23'>But David did not number those twenty years old and under because the LORD had said he would multiply Israel like to the stars of the heavens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.24'>Joab, the son of Zeruiah, had begun to number, but he did not finish; and because of this, wrath fell upon Israel; and [thus] the number was not put in the account of the chronicles of King David.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.25'>And Azmaveth, the son of Adiel, had charge of the king's treasures and of the treasures of the fields, of the cities, and of the villages, and of the castles, [was] Jehonathan, the son of Uzziah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.26'>and over those that did the work of the tillage of the ground in the fields [was] Ezri the son of Chelub;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.27'>and over the vineyards [was] Shimei, the Ramathite; over the increase of the vineyards for the wine cellars [was] Zabdi, the Shiphmite;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.28'>and over the olive trees and the sycamore trees that [were] in the low plains [was] Baalhanan, the Gederite; and over the cellars of oil, Joash;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.29'>and over the cows that fed in Sharon [was] Shitrai, the Sharonite; and over the cows [that were] in the valleys [was] Shaphat, the son of Adlai;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.30'>over the camels, Obil, the Ishmaelite; and over the asses, Jehdeiah, the Meronothite;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.31'>and over the sheep [was] Jaziz, the Hagerite. All these [were] the princes of the substance which [was] King David's.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.32'>And Jonathan, David's uncle, was a counsellor, a wise man, and a scribe; and Jehiel the son of Hachmoni had charge of the king's sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.33'>Ahithophel [was] the king's counsellor; and Hushai, the Archite, [was] the king's companion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.27.34'>And after Ahithophel [was] Jehoiada, the son of Benaiah, and Abiathar. And Joab was the general of the king's army.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.28'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.1'>And David assembled all the princes of Israel, the princes of the tribes, and the princes of the companies that ministered to the king by course, and the princes over the thousands, and princes over the hundreds, with the princes over all the substance and possession of the king, and his sons, with the officers, and with the mighty men, and with all the valiant men, unto Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.2'>Then David, the king, stood up upon his feet and said, Hear me, my brethren, and my people: [As for me], I [had] in my heart to build a house of rest for the ark of the covenant of the LORD and for the footstool of our God and had made ready for the building.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.3'>But God said unto me, Thou shalt not build a house for my name because thou [hast been] a man of war and hast shed blood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.4'>However, the LORD God of Israel chose me before all the house of my father to be king over Israel for ever, for he has chosen Judah [to be] the ruler; and of the house of Judah, the house of my father; and among the sons of my father he liked me to make [me] king over all Israel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.5'>and of all my sons (for the LORD has given me many sons) he has chosen Solomon, my son, to sit upon the throne of the kingdom of the LORD over Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.6'>And he said unto me, Solomon, thy son, he shall build my house and my courts, for I have chosen him [to be] my son, and I will be his father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.7'>Moreover, I will establish his kingdom for ever if he is constant to do my commandments and my judgments as at this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.8'>Now, therefore, in the sight of all Israel the congregation of the LORD and in the audience of our God, keep and seek for all the commandments of the LORD your God, that ye may possess this good land and leave [it] for an inheritance for your sons after you for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.9'>And thou, Solomon, my son, know thou the God of thy father and serve him with a perfect heart and with a willing soul, for the LORD searches all hearts and understands all the imaginations of the thoughts. If thou seek him, he will be found of thee; but if thou forsake him, he will cast thee off for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.10'>Take heed now, for the LORD has chosen thee to build a house for the sanctuary; be strong, and do [it].</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.11'>Then David gave to Solomon, his son, the pattern of the porch and of its houses and of its treasuries and of its upper chambers and of its inner parlours and of the place of the seat of reconciliation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.12'>and the pattern of all that he had [received] by the Spirit of the courts of the house of the LORD and of all the chambers round about, of the treasuries of the house of God and of the treasuries of the holy things;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.13'>also for the courses of the priests and the Levites, and for all the work of the ministry of the house of the LORD, and for all the vessels of ministry of the house of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.14'>[He gave] gold by weight for that of gold, for all the vessels of each manner of service; [silver also] for all the vessels of silver by weight, for all the vessels of each service.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.15'>[Gold] by weight for the candlesticks of gold, and for their lamps of gold, by weight for every candlestick, and for its lamps; and for the candlesticks of silver by weight, [both] for the candlestick and [also] for its lamps, according to the service of each candlestick.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.16'>And by weight [he gave] gold for the tables of showbread, for each table; and, [likewise], silver for the tables of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.17'>Also pure gold for the fleshhooks and the bowls and the cups, and for the golden covers [he gave gold] by weight for every basin; and [likewise silver] by weight for every basin of silver;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.18'>and for the altar of incense refined gold by weight; and gold for the pattern of the chariot of the cherubim, that spread out [their wings] and covered the ark of the covenant of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.19'>All [this], [said David], the LORD made me understand in writing by [his] hand upon me, [even] all the works of this pattern.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.20'>And David said to Solomon, his son, Be strong and of good courage, and do [it]; fear not, nor be dismayed, for the LORD God, [even] my God, [will be] with thee; he will not leave thee, nor forsake thee, until thou hast finished all the work of the service of the house of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.28.21'>Behold the courses of the priests and the Levites, in all the ministry of the house of God; [they shall be] with thee in all the work; all of them voluntarily, with wisdom in all ministry; likewise, the princes and all the people to execute all thy commands.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='1Chr.29'>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.1'>Furthermore, David, the king, said unto all the congregation, Only Solomon, my son, has God chosen; he is young and tender, and the work [is] great, for the palace [is] not for man, but for the LORD God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.2'>Now I have prepared with all my might for the house of my God, gold for the things of gold, and silver for the things of silver, and brass for the things of brass, and iron for the things of iron, and wood for the things of wood; onyx stones, and [stones] to be set, black stones and of different colours, and all manner of precious stones, and marble stones in abundance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.3'>Moreover, because I have my delight in the house of my God, I have in my own treasury, gold and silver, [which] I have given to the house of my God, over and above all that I have prepared for the house of the sanctuary:</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.4'>three thousand talents of gold, of the gold of Ophir, and seven thousand talents of refined silver, to overlay the walls of the houses;</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.5'>the gold for [things] of gold, and the silver for [things] of silver, and for all manner of work [to be made] by the hands of the workmen. And who [then] is willing to consecrate [the offering] of his hands today unto the LORD?</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.6'>Then the princes of the fathers and princes of the tribes of Israel, and the princes of thousands and of hundreds, with the rulers of the king's work, offered willingly</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.7'>and gave for the service of the house of God five thousand talents of gold and ten thousand daily wages and ten thousand talents of silver and eighteen thousand talents of brass and one hundred thousand talents of iron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.8'>And each one gave the precious stones that they had to the treasure of the house of the LORD, into the hand of Jehiel, the Gershonite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.9'>Then the people rejoiced to have offered willingly because with perfect heart they offered willingly to the LORD. Likewise, David the king rejoiced with great joy</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.10'>and blessed the LORD before all the congregation; and David said, Blessed [be] thou, LORD God of Israel our father, for ever and ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.11'>Thine, O LORD, [is] the greatness and the power and the glory and the victory and the honour, for all things in the heavens and in the earth [are thine]; thine [is] the kingdom, O LORD, and thou art exalted as head above all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.12'>The riches and the glory are before thee, and thou dost reign over all, and in thy hand [is] power and might and in thy hand the greatness and the strength of all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.13'>Now, therefore, our God, we thank thee, and praise thy glorious name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.14'>But who [am] I, and what [is] my people, that we should be able to offer so willingly after this sort? For all things [come] of thee and of thine own have we given thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.15'>For we [are] strangers before thee, and sojourners, as [were] all our fathers; our days on the earth [are] as a shadow, and [there is] no other hope.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.16'>O LORD our God, all this store that we have prepared to build thee a house for thy holy name [comes] of thy hand and [is] all thy own.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.17'>I know also, my God, that thou dost try the heart, and hast pleasure in uprightness. As for me, in the uprightness of my heart I have willingly offered all these things; and now have I seen with joy that thy people, who are present here, have given willingly unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.18'>O LORD God of Abraham, Isaac, and of Israel, our fathers, keep for ever this purpose in the thoughts of the heart of thy people and prepare their heart unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.19'>Likewise, give unto Solomon, my son, a perfect heart, to keep thy commandments, thy testimonies, and thy statutes, and to do all [these things], and to build the palace, for which I have made provision.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.20'>Then David said to all the congregation, Now bless the LORD your God. And all the congregation blessed the LORD God of their fathers and bowed down and worshipped before the LORD and the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.21'>And they sacrificed sacrifices unto the LORD and offered burnt offerings unto the LORD, on the next day, [even] a thousand bullocks, a thousand rams, [and] a thousand lambs, with their drink offerings, and sacrifices in abundance for all Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.22'>And they ate and drank before the LORD on that day with great gladness. And they made Solomon, the son of David, king the second time and anointed [him] unto the LORD as ruler and Zadok as priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.23'>Then Solomon sat on the throne of the LORD as king instead of David, his father, and was prospered; and all Israel heard him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.24'>And all the princes and the mighty men and all the sons likewise of King David, submitted themselves unto Solomon, the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.25'>And the LORD magnified Solomon exceedingly in the sight of all Israel and bestowed upon him [such] glory of the kingdom as had not been on any king before him in Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.26'>Thus David, the son of Jesse, reigned over all Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.27'>And the time that he reigned over Israel [was] forty years; he reigned seven years in Hebron, and he reigned thirty-three [years] in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.28'>And he died in a good old age, full of days, riches, and glory; and Solomon his son reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.29'>Now the acts of David, the king, first and last, behold, they [are] written in the book of Samuel, the seer, and in the book of Nathan, the prophet, and in the book of Gad, the seer,</verse>
        <verse osisID='1Chr.29.30'>with all his reign and his might, and the times that went over him and over Israel and over all the kingdoms of the lands.:</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>