<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText xml:lang='en' osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='jubl2000'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='jubl2000'>
        <title>English Jubilee 2000 Bible</title>
        <contributor>Sword Project</contributor>
        <creator>ColdHeart</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>Translated from the Original Texts in Hebrew and Greek into Spanish by Casiodoro de Reina (1569) and compared with the revision of Cipriano de Valera (1602). Based on the New Testament of Francisco de Enzinas (1543) and on the New Testament (1556) with the Psalms (1557) of Juan Perez de Pineda.\par This material was translated from Spanish into English by Russell M. Stendal and compared with the Old English Translation of William Tyndale (Pentateuch of 1530, Ploughboy Edition New Testament of 1534, Joshua to 2 Chronicles of 1537, and Jonah). It was also compared word for word with the Authorized Version (by King James) of 1611.
</description>
        <publisher>DarkBibleORG</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>jubl2000</identifier>
        <source>http://www.crosswire.org/sword/servlet/SwordMod.Verify?modName=Jubilee2000</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide th bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Copyright 2000, 2001 Russell Martin Stendal May be quoted in other works.  May be used freely in all non-profit, non-commercial Bible distribution endeavors provided the content is not altered. For all commercial reproduction express written permission from the publisher is required.
       Ransom Press Internacional 10160 Main Dr. Bonita Springs, FL  34135 </rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div type='book' osisID='Gen'>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.1'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.1'>In the beginning God created the heavens and the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.2'>And the earth was without order, and empty; and darkness [was] upon the face of the deep. And the Spirit of God moved upon the face of the waters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.3'>And God said, Let there be light, and there was light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.4'>And God saw that the light [was] good, and God divided the light from the darkness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.5'>And God called the light Day and the darkness he called Night. And the evening and the morning were the first day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.6'>And God said, Let there be a firmament in the midst of the waters, and let it divide the waters from the waters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.7'>And God made a firmament and divided the waters which [were] under the firmament from the waters which [were] above the firmament; and it was so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.8'>And God called the firmament Heavens. And the evening and the morning were the second day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.9'>And God said, Let the waters under the heavens be gathered together unto one place, and let the dry [land] appear; and it was so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.10'>And God called the dry [land] Earth, and the gathering together of the waters he called Seas; and God saw that [it was] good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.11'>And God said, Let the earth bring forth green grass, herb yielding seed, [and] the fruit tree yielding fruit after its nature, whose seed [is] in itself upon the earth; and it was so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.12'>And the earth brought forth green grass [and] herb yielding seed after its kind and the tree yielding fruit whose seed [was] in itself, according to its nature; and God saw that [it was] good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.13'>And the evening and the morning were the third day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.14'>And God said, Let there be lights in the firmament of the heavens to divide the day from the night; and let them be for signs and for appointed times and for days and years;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.15'>and let them be for lights in the firmament of the heavens to give light upon the earth; and it was so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.16'>And God made two great lights: the greater light to rule the day, and the lesser light to rule the night; [he made] the stars also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.17'>And God set them in the firmament of the heavens to give light upon the earth</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.18'>and to rule over the day and over the night and to divide the light from the darkness; and God saw that [it was] good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.19'>And the evening and the morning were the fourth day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.20'>And God said, Let the waters bring forth great quantities of creatures with living souls and fowl [that] may fly above the earth upon the face of the firmament of the heavens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.21'>And God created the great dragons and every living soul that moves, which the waters brought forth abundantly after their nature, and every winged fowl after its nature; and God saw that [it was] good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.22'>And God blessed them, saying, Be fruitful and multiply and fill the waters in the seas, and let fowl multiply in the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.23'>And the evening and the morning were the fifth day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.24'>And God said, Let the earth bring forth the living soul after its nature, beasts and serpents and animals of the earth after its nature; and it was so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.25'>And God made the beast of the earth after its kind and cattle after their kind and every thing that moves upon the earth after its kind; and God saw that [it was] good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.26'>And God said, Let us make man in our image, after our likeness; and let them have dominion over the fish of the sea and over the fowl of the air and over the beasts and over all the earth and over every serpent that moves upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.27'>So God created man in his [own] image, in the image of God created he him; male and female created he them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.28'>And God blessed them, and God said unto them, Be fruitful and multiply and fill the earth and subdue it and have dominion over the fish of the sea and over the fowl of the air and over every beast that moves upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.29'>And God said, Behold, I have given you every grass bearing seed, which [is] upon the face of all the earth, and every tree, in which [is] the fruit of a tree yielding seed; to you it shall be for food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.30'>And to every beast of the earth and to every fowl of the air and to every thing that moves upon the earth, in which [there is a] living soul, [I have given] all green grass for food; and it was so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.1.31'>And God saw every thing that he had made, and, behold, [it was] very good. And the evening and the morning were the sixth day.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.2'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.1'>Thus the heavens and the earth were finished, and all the host of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.2'>And on the seventh day God finished his work which he had made, and he rested on the seventh day from all his work which he had made.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.3'>And God blessed the seventh day and sanctified it because in it he had rested from all his work which God created in perfection.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.4'>These [are] the origins of the heavens and of the earth when they were created, in the day that the LORD God made the earth and the heavens</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.5'>and every plant of the field before it was in the earth and all the grass of the field before it grew, for the LORD God had not caused it to rain upon the earth, and neither [was there] a man to till the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.6'>But there went up a mist from the earth and watered the whole face of the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.7'>And the LORD God formed man [of] the dust of the ground and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life, and man became a living soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.8'>And the LORD God had planted a garden eastward in Eden, and there he put the man whom he had formed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.9'>And out of the ground made the LORD God to grow every tree that is desirable to the sight and good for food, the tree of life also in the midst of the garden and the tree of knowledge of good and evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.10'>And a river went out of Eden to water the garden, and from there it was divided into four heads.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.11'>The name of the first [is] Pison; that [is] it which compasses the whole land of Havilah, where [there is] gold;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.12'>and the gold of that land [is] good; there [is] bdellium and the onyx stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.13'>And the name of the second river [is] Gihon; this [is] the same that compasses the whole land of Ethiopia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.14'>And the name of the third river [is] Hiddekel; this [is] that which goes toward the east of Assyria. And the fourth river [is] Euphrates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.15'>And the LORD God took the man and put him into the garden of Eden to dress it and to keep it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.16'>And the LORD God commanded the man, saying, Of every tree of the garden thou may freely eat;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.17'>but of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, thou shalt not eat of it; for in the day that thou dost eat of it thou shalt surely die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.18'>And the LORD God said, [It is] not good that the man should be alone; I will make him a help meet for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.19'>And out of the ground the LORD God formed every beast of the field, and every fowl of the air; and brought [them] unto the man to see what he would call them; and whatever the man called every living soul, that [was] its name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.20'>And the man gave names to every beast, and [to the] fowl of the heavens, and to every animal of the field; but for the man there was not found a help meet for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.21'>And the LORD God caused a deep sleep to fall upon Adam, and he slept; and he took one of his sides and closed up the flesh in its place;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.22'>and the LORD God built [that] which he had taken from the side of the man into a woman and brought her unto the man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.23'>And the man said, This [is] now bone of my bones and flesh of my flesh; she shall be called Woman because she was taken out of Man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.24'>Therefore shall a man leave his father and his mother and shall cleave unto his wife; and they shall be one flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.2.25'>And they were both naked, the man and his wife, and were not ashamed.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.3'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.1'>Now the serpent was more astute than all the animals of the field which the LORD God had made. And he said unto the woman, Has God indeed said, Ye shall not eat of every tree of the garden?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.2'>And the woman answered unto the serpent, We may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.3'>but of the fruit of the tree which [is] in the midst of the garden, God has said, Ye shall not eat of it; neither shall ye touch it, lest ye die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.4'>Then the serpent said unto the woman, Ye shall not surely die:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.5'>For God knows that in the day ye eat of it then your eyes shall be opened, and ye shall be as gods, knowing good and evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.6'>And when the woman saw that the tree [was] good for food, and that it [was] desirable to the eyes, and a tree of covetousness to understand, she took of its fruit and ate and gave also unto her husband with her; and he ate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.7'>And the eyes of them both were opened, and they knew that they [were] naked; so they sewed fig leaves together and made themselves girdles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.8'>And they heard the voice of the LORD God walking in the garden in the cool of the day, and the man and his wife hid themselves from the presence of the LORD God among the trees of the garden.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.9'>And the LORD God called unto the man and said unto him, Where [art] thou?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.10'>And he replied, I heard thy voice in the garden, and I was afraid because I [was] naked; and I hid myself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.11'>And he said, Who told thee that thou [wast] naked? Hast thou eaten of the tree, of which I commanded thee not to eat?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.12'>And the man said, The woman whom thou gavest [to be] with me, she gave me of the tree, and I ate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.13'>Then the LORD God said unto the woman, What [is] this [that] thou hast done? And the woman said, The serpent beguiled me, and I ate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.14'>And the LORD God said unto the serpent, Because thou hast done this, thou [art] cursed above all beasts and above every animal of the field; upon thy belly shalt thou go, and dust shalt thou eat all the days of thy life;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.15'>and I will put enmity between thee and the woman and between thy seed and her seed; that [seed] shall bruise thy head, and thou shalt bruise his heel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.16'>Unto the woman he said, I will greatly multiply thy sorrow and thy conception; in sorrow thou shalt bring forth sons; and thy desire [shall be] to thy husband, and he shall rule over thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.17'>And unto Adam he said, Because thou hast hearkened unto the voice of thy wife and hast eaten of the tree of which I commanded thee, saying, Thou shalt not eat of it, cursed [shall be] the ground for thy sake; in sorrow shalt thou eat [of] it all the days of thy life;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.18'>thorns also and thistles shall it bring forth to thee; and thou shalt eat the grass of the field;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.19'>in the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat bread until thou return unto the ground; for out of it wast thou taken, for dust thou [art], and unto dust shalt thou return.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.20'>And the man called his wife's name Eve because she was the mother of all living.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.21'>Then the LORD God made coats of skins for Adam and his wife and clothed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.22'>And the LORD God said, Behold, the man is become as one of us, knowing good and evil; and now, lest he put forth his hand and take also of the tree of life and eat and live for ever,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.23'>therefore the LORD God sent him forth from the garden of Eden to till the ground from which he was taken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.3.24'>So he drove out the man; and he placed at the east of the garden of Eden Cherubim and a flaming sword which turned every way to keep the way of the tree of life.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.4'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.1'>And the man knew Eve his wife, and she conceived and bore Cain and said, I have gained a man by the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.2'>And she again bore his brother Abel. And Abel was a pastor of sheep, but Cain was a tiller of the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.3'>And in process of time it came to pass that Cain brought of the fruit of the ground a present unto the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.4'>And Abel, he also brought of the firstborn of his flock and of the fat thereof. And the LORD looked upon Abel and his present,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.5'>but he did not look upon Cain and his present. And Cain was very wroth, and his countenance fell.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.6'>Then the LORD said unto Cain, Why art thou wroth? and why is thy countenance fallen?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.7'>If thou doest good, it shall certainly be accepted; and if thou doest not good, sin lies at the door. And his desire shall be unto thee, but thou must rule over him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.8'>And Cain talked with Abel his brother, and it came to pass when they were in the field, that Cain rose up against Abel his brother and slew him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.9'>And the LORD said unto Cain, Where [is] Abel thy brother? And he said, I know not, [Am] I my brother's keeper?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.10'>And he said, What hast thou done? The voice of thy brother's blood cries unto me from the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.11'>And now thou [art] cursed from the earth, which has opened her mouth to receive thy brother's blood from thy hand;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.12'>when thou tillest the ground, from now on it shall not yield unto thee her strength; a fugitive and a vagabond shalt thou be in the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.13'>And Cain said unto the LORD, My iniquity [is] greater than I can bear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.14'>Behold, thou hast driven me out this day from the face of the earth; and from thy face shall I hide; and I shall be a fugitive and a vagabond in the earth; and it shall come to pass [that] anyone that finds me shall slay me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.15'>And the LORD said unto him, Therefore whoever slays Cain, vengeance shall be taken on him sevenfold. And the LORD set a mark upon Cain, lest any finding him should kill him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.16'>And Cain went out from the presence of the LORD and dwelt in the land of Nod on the east of Eden.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.17'>And Cain knew his wife, and she conceived and bore Enoch; and he built a city and called the name of the city after the name of his son, Enoch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.18'>And unto Enoch was born Irad, and Irad begat Mehujael, and Mehujael begat Methusael, and Methusael begat Lamech.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.19'>And Lamech took unto him two wives; the name of the one [was] Adah, and the name of the other Zillah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.20'>And Adah bore Jabal; he was the father of those who dwell in tents and [of those who have] cattle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.21'>And his brother's name [was] Jubal; he was the father of all those who play the harp and organ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.22'>And Zillah also bore Tubalcain, an instructor of every artificer in brass and iron; and the sister of Tubalcain [was] Naamah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.23'>And Lamech said unto his wives, Adah and Zillah, Hear my voice; ye wives of Lamech, hearken unto my speech, for I shall slay a man for my wound and a young man for my hurt;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.24'>if Cain shall be avenged sevenfold, truly Lamech seventy times seven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.25'>And Adam knew his wife again, and she bore a son and called his name Seth; for God, [said she], has appointed me another seed instead of Abel, whom Cain slew.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.4.26'>And to Seth, to him also there was born a son; and he called his name Enos. Then men began to call upon the name of the LORD.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.5'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.1'>This [is] the book of the decendants of Adam. In the day that God created man, he made him in the likeness of God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.2'>male and female created he them and blessed them and called their name Man, in the day when they were created.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.3'>And Adam lived one hundred and thirty years and begat [a son] in his own likeness, after his image, and called his name Seth:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.4'>And the days of Adam after he had begotten Seth were eight hundred years, and he begat sons and daughters;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.5'>and all the days that Adam lived were nine hundred and thirty years, and he died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.6'>And Seth lived one hundred and five years and begat Enos.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.7'>And Seth lived after he begat Enos eight hundred and seven years and begat sons and daughters;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.8'>and all the days of Seth were nine hundred and twelve years, and he died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.9'>And Enos lived ninety years and begat Cainan,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.10'>and Enos lived after he begat Cainan eight hundred and fifteen years and begat sons and daughters;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.11'>and all the days of Enos were nine hundred and five years, and he died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.12'>And Cainan lived seventy years and begat Mahalaleel;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.13'>and Cainan lived after he begat Mahalaleel eight hundred and forty years and begat sons and daughters;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.14'>and all the days of Cainan were nine hundred and ten years, and he died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.15'>And Mahalaleel lived sixty-five years and begat Jared;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.16'>and Mahalaleel lived after he begat Jared eight hundred and thirty years and begat sons and daughters;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.17'>and all the days of Mahalaleel were eight hundred ninety-five years and he died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.18'>And Jared lived one hundred sixty-two years and he begat Enoch;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.19'>and Jared lived after he begat Enoch eight hundred years and begat sons and daughters;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.20'>and all the days of Jared were nine hundred sixty-two years, and he died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.21'>And Enoch lived sixty-five years and begat Methuselah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.22'>And Enoch walked with God after he begat Methuselah three hundred years and begat sons and daughters;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.23'>and all the days of Enoch were three hundred sixty-five years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.24'>And Enoch walked with God; and he [was] not, for God took him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.25'>And Methuselah lived one hundred eighty-seven years, and begat Lamech;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.26'>and Methuselah lived after he begat Lamech seven hundred eighty-two years and begat sons and daughters;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.27'>and all the days of Methuselah were nine hundred sixty-nine years, and he died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.28'>And Lamech lived one hundred eighty-two years and begat a son;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.29'>and he called his name Noah, saying, This [same] shall comfort us concerning our work and toil of our hands because of the ground which the LORD has cursed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.30'>And Lamech lived after he begat Noah five hundred ninety-five years and begat sons and daughters;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.31'>and all the days of Lamech were seven hundred seventy-seven years, and he died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.5.32'>And Noah was five hundred years old; and Noah begat Shem, Ham, and Japheth.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.6'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.1'>And it came to pass, when men began to multiply on the face of the earth and daughters were born unto them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.2'>that the sons of God saw that the daughters of men [were] fair, and they took [for] themselves wives of all whom they chose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.3'>And the LORD said, My spirit shall not always strive with man, for certainly he [is] flesh; yet his days shall be one hundred and twenty years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.4'>There were giants in the earth in those days, and also after that, when the sons of God came in unto the daughters of men, and they bore [sons] to them, the same [became] mighty men who [were] of old, men of renown.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.5'>And GOD saw that the wickedness of man [was] great in the earth and [that] every imagination of the thoughts of his heart [was] only evil continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.6'>And the LORD repented of having made man on the earth, and it grieved him at his heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.7'>And the LORD said, I will destroy man whom I have created from the face of the earth, both man and beast and the animals and the fowls of the air; for I repent of having made them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.8'>But Noah found grace in the eyes of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.9'>These [are] the generations of Noah. Noah was a just man [and] perfect in his generations, [and] Noah walked with God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.10'>And Noah begat three sons, Shem, Ham, and Japheth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.11'>The earth corrupted itself before God, and the earth filled itself with violence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.12'>And God looked upon the earth, and, behold, it was corrupt, for all flesh had corrupted its way upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.13'>And God said unto Noah, The end of all flesh is come before me, for the earth is filled with violence through them; and, behold, I will destroy them with the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.14'>Make thee an ark of cedar trees; rooms shalt thou make in the ark and shalt reconcile it within and without covering it over with pitch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.15'>And this [is the fashion of] which thou shalt make it: The length of the ark [shall be] three hundred cubits, the breadth of it fifty cubits, and the height of it thirty cubits.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.16'>A window shalt thou make to the ark, and in a cubit shalt thou finish it above; and the door of the ark shalt thou set in the side thereof; [with] lower, second, and third [stories] shalt thou make it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.17'>And, behold, I, even I, do bring a flood of waters upon the earth, to destroy all flesh, in which [is] the spirit of life, from under heaven; [and] every thing that [is] in the earth shall die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.18'>But with thee I will establish my covenant; and thou shalt come into the ark, thou and thy sons and thy wife and thy sons' wives with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.19'>And of every living thing of all flesh, two of every [sort] shalt thou bring into the ark, to keep [them] alive with thee; they shall be male and female.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.20'>Of fowls after their kind and of beasts after their kind, of every animal of the earth after its kind, two of every [sort] shall come unto thee, to keep [them] alive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.21'>And take thou unto thee of all food that is eaten, and thou shalt gather [it] to thee; and it shall be for food for thee and for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.6.22'>Thus did Noah; according to all that God commanded him, so did he.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.7'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.1'>And the LORD said unto Noah, Enter thou and all thy house into the ark; for thee have I seen righteous before me in this generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.2'>Of every clean animal thou shalt take to thee seven pairs, the male and his female; but of animals that [are] not clean, two, the male and his female.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.3'>Of fowls also of the heavens by seven pairs, the male and the female; to keep seed alive upon the face of all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.4'>For yet [in] seven days, I will cause it to rain upon the earth forty days and forty nights; and every substance that I have made I will destroy from off the face of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.5'>And Noah did according unto all that the LORD commanded him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.6'>And Noah [was] six hundred years old when the flood of waters was upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.7'>And Noah went in and his sons and his wife and his sons' wives with him into the ark because of the waters of the flood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.8'>Of clean animals and of animals that [are] not clean and of fowls and of every thing that moves upon the earth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.9'>there went in two by two unto Noah into the ark, the male and the female, as God had commanded Noah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.10'>And it came to pass after seven days that the waters of the flood were upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.11'>In the six hundredth year of Noah's life in the second month, the seventeenth day of the month, the same day were all the fountains of the great deep broken up, and the windows of the heavens were opened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.12'>And there was rain upon the earth forty days and forty nights.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.13'>In that same day Noah and Shem and Ham and Japheth, the sons of Noah, and Noah's wife and the three wives of his sons with them entered into the ark,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.14'>they and every animal after its kind and all the beasts after their kind and every creeping thing that moves upon the earth after its kind and every fowl after its kind, every bird, every thing with wings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.15'>And they went in unto Noah into the ark, two by two of all flesh in which [is] the spirit of life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.16'>And those that went in went in male and female of all flesh, as God had commanded him, and the LORD shut him in.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.17'>And the flood was forty days upon the earth, and the waters multiplied and bore up the ark, and it was lifted up above the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.18'>And the waters prevailed and multiplied greatly upon the earth, and the ark went upon the face of the waters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.19'>And the waters prevailed exceedingly upon the earth, and all the high mountains that [were] under all the heavens were covered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.20'>Fifteen cubits upward did the waters prevail, and the mountains were covered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.21'>And all flesh died that moved upon the earth, both of fowl and of beasts and of animals and of every creeping thing that creeps upon the earth and every man;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.22'>all in whose nostrils [was] the breath of the spirit of life of all that [was] in the dry [land] died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.23'>And every substance was destroyed which was upon the face of the ground, both man and cattle and the animals and the fowl of the heaven; and they were destroyed from the earth, and only Noah remained [alive] and those that [were] with him in the ark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.7.24'>And the waters prevailed upon the earth one hundred and fifty days.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.8'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.1'>And God remembered Noah, and every living thing, and all the animals that [were] with him in the ark; and God made a wind to pass over the earth, and the waters ceased;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.2'>the fountains also of the deep and the windows of the heavens were stopped, and the rain from heaven was restrained;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.3'>and the waters turned back and forth upon the earth, and after the end of the hundred and fifty days the waters were abated.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.4'>And the ark rested in the seventh month, on the seventeenth day of the month, upon the mountains of Ararat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.5'>And the waters decreased continually until the tenth month; in the tenth [month], on the first [day] of the month, the tops of the mountains were seen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.6'>And it came to pass at the end of forty days that Noah opened the window of the ark which he had made,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.7'>and he sent forth a raven, which went forth to and fro until the waters were dried up from off the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.8'>Also he sent forth a dove from him to see if the waters were abated from off the face of the ground,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.9'>but the dove found no rest for the sole of her foot, and she returned unto him into the ark, for the waters [were still] upon the face of the whole earth. Then he put forth his hand and took her and pulled her in unto him into the ark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.10'>And he waited yet another seven days, and again he sent forth the dove out of the ark,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.11'>and the dove came in to him in the evening, and, behold, in her mouth [was] an olive leaf plucked off, so Noah knew that the waters were abated from off the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.12'>And he stayed yet other seven days and sent forth the dove, which returned not again unto him any more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.13'>And it came to pass in the six hundredth and first year of Noah, in the first [month], the first [day] of the month, the waters were dried up from off the earth, and Noah removed the covering of the ark and looked and, behold, the face of the ground was dry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.14'>And in the second month, on the twenty-seventh day of the month, the earth was dried.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.15'>And God spoke unto Noah, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.16'>Go forth from the ark, thou and thy wife and thy sons, and thy sons' wives with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.17'>Bring forth with thee every animal that [is] with thee, of all flesh, [both] of fowl and of beasts and of every creeping thing that moves upon the earth, that they may breed abundantly in the earth, and be fruitful, and multiply upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.18'>And Noah went forth and his sons and his wife and his sons' wives with him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.19'>all the animals, every creature and every fowl [and] whatever moves upon the earth after their kinds went forth out of the ark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.20'>And Noah built an altar unto the LORD and took of every clean animal and of every clean fowl and offered burnt offerings on the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.21'>And the LORD smelled a savour of rest, and the LORD said in his heart, I will not again curse the ground any more for man's sake, for the intent of man's heart [is] evil from his childhood; neither will I again smite any more every living thing as I have done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.8.22'>While the earth remains, seedtime and harvest, and cold and heat, and summer and winter, and day and night shall not cease.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.9'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.1'>And God blessed Noah and his sons and said unto them, Be fruitful and multiply and fill the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.2'>And the fear of you and the dread of you shall be upon every animal of the earth and upon every fowl of the heavens, upon all that moves [upon] the earth and upon all the fishes of the sea; into your hand they are delivered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.3'>Every moving thing that lives shall be food for you; even as the green grass I have given you all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.4'>But flesh with the soul ([or life]) thereof, [which is] its blood, ye shall not eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.5'>For surely your blood [which is] your souls I will require; at the hand of every animal I will require it and at the hand of man; at the hand of every man's brother I will require the soul ([or life]) of man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.6'>Whoever sheds man's blood in man, his blood shall be shed; for in the image of God is man made.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.7'>And you, be ye fruitful and multiply; bring forth abundantly in the earth and multiply therein.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.8'>And God spoke unto Noah and to his sons with him, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.9'>Behold that I establish my covenant with you and with your seed after you</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.10'>and with every living soul that [is] with you, of the fowl, of the animals, and of every beast of the earth with you, from all that go out of the ark to every animal of the earth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.11'>that I will establish my covenant with you, that all flesh shall not be cut off any more by the waters of a flood; neither shall there any more be a flood to destroy the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.12'>And God said, This [is] the sign of the covenant which I make between me and you and every living soul that [is] with you, for perpetual ages:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.13'>I set my bow in the clouds, and it shall be for a sign of a covenant between me and the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.14'>And it shall come to pass when I bring clouds over the earth, that the bow shall appear in the clouds;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.15'>and I will remember my covenant, which [is] between me and you and every living soul of all flesh; and the waters shall no more become a flood to destroy all flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.16'>And the bow shall be in the clouds, and I will look upon it that I may remember the everlasting covenant between God and every living soul of all flesh that [is] upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.17'>And God said unto Noah, This [shall be] the sign of the covenant, which I have established between me and all flesh that [is] upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.18'>And the sons of Noah, that went forth from the ark, were Shem, Ham, and Japheth; and Ham [is] the father of Canaan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.19'>These [are] the three sons of Noah; and of them was the whole earth overspread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.20'>And Noah began to till the ground, and he planted a vineyard;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.21'>and he drank of the wine and was drunken; and he was uncovered within his tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.22'>And Ham, the father of Canaan, saw the nakedness of his father and told his two brethren outside.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.23'>Then Shem and Japheth took a garment and laid [it] upon both their shoulders and went backward, and covered the nakedness of their father; and their faces [were] backward, and they did not see their father's nakedness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.24'>And Noah awoke from his wine and knew what his younger son had done unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.25'>And he said, Cursed [be] Canaan; a servant of servants shall he be unto his brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.26'>And he said, Blessed [be] the LORD God of Shem; and Canaan shall be his servant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.27'>God shall enlarge Japheth, and he shall dwell in the tents of Shem; and Canaan shall be his servant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.28'>And Noah lived after the flood three hundred and fifty years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.9.29'>And all the days of Noah were nine hundred and fifty years, and he died.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.10'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.1'>Now these [are] the generations of the sons of Noah: Shem, Ham, and Japheth; and unto them were born sons after the flood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.2'>The sons of Japheth: Gomer and Magog and Madai and Javan and Tubal and Meshech and Tiras.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.3'>And the sons of Gomer: Ashkenaz and Riphath and Togarmah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.4'>And the sons of Javan: Elishah and Tarshish, Kittim and Dodanim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.5'>By these were the isles of the Gentiles divided in their lands, each one after his tongue, after their families, in their nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.6'>And the sons of Ham: Cush and Mizraim and Phut and Canaan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.7'>And the sons of Cush: Seba and Havilah and Sabtah and Raamah and Sabtecha. And the sons of Raamah: Sheba and Dedan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.8'>And Cush begat Nimrod. He began to be powerful in the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.9'>He was a powerful hunter before the LORD; therefore it is said, Even as Nimrod, the powerful hunter before the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.10'>And the beginning of his kingdom was Babel and Erech and Accad and Calneh in the land of Shinar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.11'>Out of that land went forth Asshur, who built Nineveh and the city Rehoboth and Calah</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.12'>and Resen between Nineveh and Calah; the same [is] a great city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.13'>And Mizraim begat Ludim and Anamim and Lehabim and Naphtuhim</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.14'>and Pathrusim and Casluhim (out of whom came the Philistines) and Caphtorim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.15'>And Canaan begat Sidon, his firstborn, and Heth</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.16'>and Jebusi and Amori and Girgasi</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.17'>and Hivi and Arki and Sini</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.18'>and Arvadi and Zemari and Hamathi; and afterward were the families of the Canaanites spread abroad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.19'>And the border of the Canaanites was from Sidon, as thou comest to Gerar unto Gaza, as thou goest, unto Sodom and Gomorrah and Admah and Zeboim, even unto Lasha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.20'>These [are] the sons of Ham, after their families, after their tongues, in their countries, [and] in their nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.21'>Unto Shem also, the father of all the sons of Eber, the elder brother of Japheth, even to him were [sons] born.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.22'>The sons of Shem: Elam, Asshur, Arphaxad, Lud, and Aram.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.23'>And the sons of Aram: Uz, Hul, Gether, and Mash.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.24'>And Arphaxad begat Salah, and Salah begat Eber.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.25'>And unto Eber were born two sons; the name of one [was] Peleg, for in his days the earth was divided; and his brother's name [was] Joktan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.26'>And Joktan begat Almodad, Sheleph, Hazarmaveth, Jerah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.27'>Hadoram, Uzal, Diklah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.28'>Obal, Abimael, Sheba,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.29'>Ophir, Havilah, and Jobab; all these [were] the sons of Joktan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.30'>And their dwelling was from Mesha as thou goest unto Sephar, mount of the east.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.31'>These [are] the sons of Shem, after their families, after their tongues, in their lands, after their nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.10.32'>These [are] the families of the sons of Noah, after their descendants, in their nations; and by these were the Gentiles divided in the earth after the flood.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.11'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.1'>And the whole earth was of one language and of one speech.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.2'>And it came to pass as they journeyed from the east that they found a plain in the land of Shinar; and they dwelt there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.3'>And they said one to another, Go to, let us make brick and burn them thoroughly. And they had brick instead of stone and slime instead of mortar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.4'>And they said, Go to, let us build us a city and a tower whose top [may reach] unto heaven; and let us make us a name, lest we be scattered abroad upon the face of the whole earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.5'>And the LORD came down to see the city and the tower, which the sons of the man built.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.6'>And the LORD said, Behold, the people [are] one, and they all have one language; and they begin to do this, and now nothing will be restrained from them which they have imagined to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.7'>Now, let us go down and there confound their language that they may not understand one another's speech.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.8'>So the LORD scattered them abroad from there upon the face of all the earth, and they left off to build the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.9'>Therefore the name of it was called Babel because there the LORD confounded the language of all the earth, and from there the LORD scattered them abroad upon the face of all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.10'>These [are] the generations of Shem: Shem [was] one hundred years old and begat Arphaxad two years after the flood:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.11'>And Shem lived after he begat Arphaxad five hundred years and begat sons and daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.12'>And Arphaxad lived thirty-five years and begat Salah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.13'>and Arphaxad lived after he begat Salah four hundred and three years and begat sons and daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.14'>And Salah lived thirty years and begat Eber;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.15'>and Salah lived after he begat Eber four hundred and three years and begat sons and daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.16'>And Eber lived thirty-four years and begat Peleg;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.17'>and Eber lived after he begat Peleg four hundred and thirty years and begat sons and daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.18'>And Peleg lived thirty years and begat Reu;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.19'>and Peleg lived after he begat Reu two hundred and nine years and begat sons and daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.20'>And Reu lived thirty-two years and begat Serug;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.21'>and Reu lived after he begat Serug two hundred and seven years and begat sons and daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.22'>And Serug lived thirty years and begat Nahor;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.23'>and Serug lived after he begat Nahor two hundred years and begat sons and daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.24'>And Nahor lived twenty-nine years and begat Terah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.25'>and Nahor lived after he begat Terah one hundred and nineteen years and begat sons and daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.26'>And Terah lived seventy years and begat Abram, Nahor, and Haran.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.27'>Now these [are] the generations of Terah: Terah begat Abram, Nahor, and Haran; and Haran begat Lot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.28'>And Haran died before his father Terah in the land of his nature, in Ur of the Chaldees.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.29'>And Abram and Nahor took wives for themselves; the name of Abram's wife [was] Sarai, and the name of Nahor's wife, Milcah, the daughter of Haran, the father of Milcah and the father of Iscah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.30'>But Sarai was barren; she [had] no child.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.31'>And Terah took Abram, his son, and Lot, the son of Haran, his son's son, and Sarai, his daughter-in-law, his son Abram's wife, and they went forth with them from Ur of the Chaldees to go into the land of Canaan; and they came unto Haran and dwelt there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.11.32'>And the days of Terah were two hundred and five years, and Terah died in Haran.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.12'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.1'>But the LORD had said unto Abram, Depart out of thy country and from thy nature and from thy father's house unto a land that I will show thee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.2'>and I will make of thee a great nation, and I will bless thee and make thy name great; and thou shalt be a blessing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.3'>And I will bless those that bless thee and curse those that curse thee, and in thee shall all families of the earth be blessed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.4'>So Abram departed, as the LORD had spoken unto him, and Lot went with him, and Abram [was] seventy-five years old when he departed out of Haran.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.5'>And Abram took Sarai, his wife, and Lot, his brother's son, and all their substance that they had gathered and the souls that they had gotten in Haran; and they went forth to go into the land of Canaan; and into the land of Canaan they came.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.6'>And Abram passed through the land unto the place of Sichem, unto the plain of Moreh. And the Canaanite [was] then in the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.7'>And the LORD appeared unto Abram and said, Unto thy seed will I give this land, and there he built an altar unto the LORD, who appeared unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.8'>And he went from there unto a mountain on the east of Bethel and pitched his tent, [having] Bethel on the west and Hai on the east; and there he built an altar unto the LORD and called upon the name of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.9'>And Abram journeyed, going on still toward the Negev ([south desert]).</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.10'>And there was a famine in the land, and Abram went down into Egypt to sojourn there, for the famine [was] grievous in the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.11'>And it came to pass when he was come near to enter into Egypt that he said unto Sarai, his wife, Behold now, I know that thou [art] a fair woman to look upon;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.12'>therefore it shall come to pass, when the Egyptians shall see thee that they shall say, This [is] his wife, and they will kill me, but they will save thee alive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.13'>Say, I pray thee, thou [art] my sister, that it may be well with me for thy sake; and my soul shall live because of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.14'>And it came to pass that when Abram was come into Egypt, the Egyptians beheld the woman that she [was] very fair.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.15'>The princes also of Pharaoh saw her, and commended her before Pharaoh, and the woman was taken into Pharaoh's house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.16'>And he treated Abram well for her sake: and he had sheep and oxen and he asses and menservants and maidservants and she asses and camels.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.17'>But the LORD plagued Pharaoh and his house with great plagues because of Sarai, Abram's wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.18'>And Pharaoh called Abram and said, What [is] this [that] thou hast done unto me? Why didst thou not tell me that she [was] thy wife?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.19'>Why didst thou say, She [is] my sister? I might have taken her to me to wife; now, therefore, behold thy wife, take [her], and go away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.12.20'>Then Pharaoh commanded [his] men concerning him; and they sent him away and his wife with all that he had.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.13'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.1'>Thus Abram went up out of Egypt, he and his wife and all that he had and Lot with him into the Negev.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.2'>And Abram [was] very rich in cattle, in silver, and in gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.3'>And he retraced his journeys from [the side of] the Negev even to Bethel, unto the place where his tent had been at the beginning, between Bethel and Hai,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.4'>unto the place of the altar, which he had made there at the first: and there Abram called on the name of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.5'>And Lot also, who went with Abram, had flocks and herds and tents.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.6'>And the land was not able to bear them that they might dwell together, for their substance was so great that they could not dwell together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.7'>And there was a strife between the pastors of Abram's cattle and the pastors of Lot's cattle; and the Canaanite and the Perizzite dwelt then in the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.8'>Then Abram said unto Lot, Let there be no strife, I pray thee, between me and thee and between my pastors and thine, for we [are] brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.9'>[Is] not the whole land before thee? Separate thyself, I pray thee, from me; if [thou wilt take] the left hand, then I will go to the right; or if [thou depart] to the right hand, then I will go to the left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.10'>And Lot lifted up his eyes and beheld all the plain of the Jordan that it [was] well watered everywhere, before the LORD destroyed Sodom and Gomorrah, [even] as [a] garden of the LORD like the land of Egypt as thou comest unto Zoar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.11'>Then Lot chose for himself all the plain of the Jordan, and Lot journeyed east; and they separated themselves the one from the other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.12'>Abram dwelt in the land of Canaan, and Lot dwelt in the cities of the plain and pitched [his] tents toward Sodom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.13'>But the men of Sodom [were] wicked and sinners before the LORD exceedingly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.14'>And the LORD said unto Abram, after Lot separated himself from him, Lift up now thine eyes and look from the place where thou art towards the Aquilon and to the Negev and to the east and to the west;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.15'>for all the land which thou seest, to thee will I give it and to thy seed for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.16'>And I will make thy seed as the dust of the earth, so that if someone could number the dust of the earth, [then] shall thy seed also be numbered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.17'>Arise, walk through the land in the length of it and in the breadth of it, for I must give it unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.13.18'>Then Abram removed [his] tent and came and dwelt among the terebinth trees of Mamre, which [is] in Hebron, and built there an altar unto the LORD.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.14'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.1'>And it came to pass in [those] days [that] Amraphel king of Shinar, Arioch king of Ellasar, Chedorlaomer king of Elam, and Tidal king of the Gentiles</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.2'>made war against Bera king of Sodom and against Birsha king of Gomorrah and against Shinab king of Admah and against Shemeber king of Zeboiim and [against] the king of Bela, which is Zoar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.3'>All these were joined together in the vale of Siddim, which is the salt sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.4'>Twelve years they had served Chedorlaomer, and in the thirteenth year they rebelled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.5'>And in the fourteenth year Chedorlaomer and the kings that [were] with him came and smote the Rephaims in Ashteroth Karnaim and the Zuzims in Ham and the Emims in Shaveh Kiriathaim</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.6'>and the Horites in their mount Seir unto the plain of Paran, which [is] by the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.7'>And they returned and came to Enmishpat, which [is] Kadesh, and smote all the works of the Amalekites and also the Amorites that dwelt in Hazezontamar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.8'>And the king of Sodom and the king of Gomorrah and the king of Admah and the king of Zeboiim and the king of Bela (the same [is] Zoar) went out, and they joined battle with them in the vale of Siddim,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.9'>that is, against Chedorlaomer the king of Elam and Tidal king of the Gentiles and Amraphel king of Shinar and Arioch king of Ellasar: four kings against five.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.10'>And the vale of Siddim [was full of] slimepits, and the kings of Sodom and Gomorrah fled and fell there; and those that remained fled to the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.11'>And they took all the goods of Sodom and Gomorrah and all their provisions and went away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.12'>And they also took Lot, Abram's brother's son, who dwelt in Sodom, and his goods and departed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.13'>And one came that had escaped and told Abram [the] Hebrew, who dwelt among the terebinth trees of Mamre [the] Amorite, brother of Eshcol and brother of Aner; and these [were] confederate with Abram.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.14'>And when Abram heard that his brother was taken captive, he armed his tried and experienced [servants], born in his own house, three hundred and eighteen, and pursued [them] unto Dan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.15'>And he and his servants poured themselves out against them by night and smote them and pursued them unto Hobah, which [is] on the left hand of Damascus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.16'>And he recovered all the goods and also brought again his brother Lot and his goods and the women also and the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.17'>And the king of Sodom went out to meet him after his return from the slaughter of Chedorlaomer and of the kings that [were] with him, at the valley of Shaveh, which [is] the valley of the King.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.18'>Then Melchizedek, king of Salem, brought forth bread and wine, for he [was] the priest of the most high God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.19'>And he blessed him and said, Blessed [be] Abram of the most high God, possessor of the heavens and of the earth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.20'>and blessed be the most high God, who has delivered thine enemies into thy hand. And [Abram] gave him tithes of all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.21'>Then the king of Sodom said unto Abram, Give me the persons and take the goods to thyself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.22'>And Abram said to the king of Sodom, I have lifted up my hand unto the LORD, the most high God, the possessor of the heavens and of the earth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.23'>that I will not [take] from a thread even to a shoelatchet; I will not take any thing that [is] thine, lest thou should say, I have made Abram rich,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.14.24'>except only that which the young men have eaten and the portion of the men who went with me, Aner, Eshcol, and Mamre, who shall take their portion.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.15'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.1'>After these things the word of the LORD came unto Abram in a vision, saying, Fear not, Abram; I [am] thy shield, [and] thy exceeding great reward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.2'>And Abram said, Lord GOD, what wilt thou give me, seeing I go childless, and the steward of my house [is] this Eliezer of Damascus?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.3'>And Abram said, Behold, to me thou hast given no seed; and, behold, one born in my house is my heir.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.4'>And then the word of the LORD [came] unto him, saying, This shall not be thy heir; but he that shall come forth out of thine own bowels shall be thy heir.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.5'>And he brought him forth abroad and said, Look now toward the heavens and count the stars, if thou art able to number them. And he said unto him, So shall thy seed be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.6'>And he believed the LORD, and he counted it to him for righteousness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.7'>And he said unto him, I [am] the LORD that brought thee out of Ur of the Chaldees to give thee this land to inherit it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.8'>And he said, Lord GOD, whereby shall I know that I shall inherit it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.9'>And he said unto him, Take me a heifer three years old and a she goat three years old and a ram three years old and a turtledove and a young pigeon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.10'>And he took unto him all these and divided them in the midst and laid each piece one against another, but he did not divide the birds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.11'>And when the fowls came down upon the carcasses, Abram drove them away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.12'>And when the sun was going down, a deep sleep fell upon Abram; and, behold, a horror of great darkness fell upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.13'>Then he said unto Abram, Know of a surety that thy seed shall be a stranger in a land [that is] not theirs and shall serve them, and they shall afflict them four hundred years;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.14'>and also that nation, whom they shall serve, I will judge; and afterward shall they come out with great riches.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.15'>And thou shalt go to thy fathers in peace; thou shalt be buried in a good old age.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.16'>But in the fourth generation they shall come here again; for the iniquity of the Amorites [is] not yet full.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.17'>And it came to pass that when the sun went down and it was dark, behold a smoking furnace and a burning lamp that passed between those pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.18'>In the same day the LORD made a covenant with Abram, saying, Unto thy seed shall I give this land, from the river of Egypt unto the great river, the river Euphrates:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.19'>the Kenite and the Kenizzite and the Kadmonite</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.20'>and the Hittite and the Perizzite and the Rephaim</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.15.21'>and the Amorite and the Canaanite and the Girgashite and the Jebusite.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.16'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.1'>Now Sarai Abram's wife bore him no children; and she had a handmaid, an Egyptian, whose name [was] Hagar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.2'>And Sarai said unto Abram, Behold now, the LORD has restrained me from bearing; I pray thee, go in unto my maid; it may be that I may obtain children by her. And Abram hearkened to the voice of Sarai.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.3'>And Sarai, Abram's wife, took Hagar, her maid the Egyptian, after Abram had dwelt ten years in the land of Canaan, and gave her to her husband Abram to be his wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.4'>And he went in unto Hagar, and she conceived; and when she saw that she had conceived, her mistress was despised in her eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.5'>Then Sarai said unto Abram, My wrong [be] upon thee; I have given my maid into thy bosom, and when she saw that she had conceived, I was despised in her eyes; the LORD judge between me and thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.6'>But Abram said unto Sarai, Behold, thy maid [is] in thy hand; do to her as it pleases thee. Then Sarai afflicted her, and [she] fled from her face.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.7'>And the angel of the LORD found her by a fountain of water in the wilderness, by the fountain in the way to Shur.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.8'>And he said, Hagar, Sarai's maid, where didst thou come from and where wilt thou go? And she said, I flee from the face of my mistress Sarai.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.9'>And the angel of the LORD said unto her, Return to thy mistress, and humble thyself under her hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.10'>And the angel of the LORD [also] said unto her, I will multiply thy seed so exceedingly that it shall not be numbered for the multitude.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.11'>And the angel of the LORD [yet] said unto her, Behold, thou [art] with child and shalt bear a son and shalt call his name Ishmael, because the LORD has heard thy affliction.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.12'>And he will be a wild man; his hand [will] be against every man, and every man's hand against him; and he shall dwell in the presence of all his brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.13'>And she called the name of the LORD that spoke unto her, Thou God that is seen: for she said, Have I not also here seen the back of him that sees me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.14'>Therefore the well was called Beerlahairoi; behold, [it is] between Kadesh and Bered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.15'>And Hagar bore Abram a son; and Abram called his son's name, which Hagar bore, Ishmael.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.16.16'>And Abram [was] eighty-six years old when Hagar bore Ishmael to Abram.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.17'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.1'>And when Abram was ninety-nine years old, the LORD appeared to Abram and said unto him, I [am] the Almighty God; walk before me and be thou perfect.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.2'>And I will make my covenant between me and thee and will multiply thee exceedingly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.3'>And Abram fell on his face, and God talked with him, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.4'>Behold my covenant with thee: Thou shalt be a father of many Gentiles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.5'>Neither shall thy name any longer be called Abram, but thy name shall be Abraham; for a father of many Gentiles have I made thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.6'>And I will multiply thee exceeding, and I will make Gentiles of thee, and kings shall come out of thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.7'>And I will establish my covenant between me and thee and thy seed after thee in their generations for an everlasting covenant, to be a God unto thee and to thy seed after thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.8'>And I will give unto thee and to thy seed after thee, the land in which thou art a stranger, all the land of Canaan, for an everlasting inheritance; and I will be their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.9'>And God said [again] unto Abraham, Thou shalt keep my covenant therefore, thou and thy seed after thee in their generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.10'>This [shall be] my covenant, which ye shall keep between me and you and thy seed after thee: Every male among you shall be circumcised.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.11'>And ye shall circumcise the flesh of your foreskin, and it shall be a token of the covenant between me and you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.12'>And he that is eight days old shall be circumcised among you, every male in your generations, he that is born in the house or bought with money of any stranger, who [is] not of thy seed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.13'>He that is born in thy house and he that is bought with thy money must needs be circumcised; and my covenant shall be in your flesh for an everlasting covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.14'>And the uncircumcised male whose flesh of his foreskin is not circumcised, that person shall be cut off from his people; he has annulled my covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.15'>And God said unto Abraham, As for Sarai thy wife, thou shalt not call her name Sarai, but Sarah [shall] her name [be].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.16'>And I will bless her and give thee a son also of her; yea, I will bless her, and she shall be [a mother] of Gentiles; kings of peoples shall be of her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.17'>Then Abraham fell upon his face and laughed and said in his heart, Shall [a child] be born unto him who is one hundred years old? and shall Sarah, who is ninety years old, bear?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.18'>And Abraham said unto God, O that Ishmael might live before thee!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.19'>And God said, Sarah thy wife shall bear thee a son indeed, and thou shalt call his name Isaac ([laughter]); and I will confirm my covenant with him for an everlasting covenant [and] with his seed after him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.20'>And as for Ishmael, I have heard thee: Behold, I shall bless him and will make him fruitful and will multiply him exceedingly; he shall beget twelve princes, and I will make him a great nation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.21'>But I will establish my covenant with Isaac, who Sarah shall bear unto thee at this set time in the next year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.22'>And he left off talking with him, and God went up from Abraham.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.23'>Then Abraham took Ishmael his son and all the [servants] born in his house and all that were bought with his money, every male among the men of Abraham's house, and circumcised the flesh of their foreskin in that same day as God had said unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.24'>And Abraham [was] ninety-nine years old when he was circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.25'>And Ishmael his son [was] thirteen years old when he was circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.26'>In that same day Abraham was circumcised and Ishmael his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.17.27'>And all the men of his house, born in the house and bought with money from strangers, were circumcised with him.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.18'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.1'>And the LORD appeared unto him among the terebinth trees of Mamre; and he was sitting in the door of his tent in the heat of the day;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.2'>and he lifted up his eyes and looked, and, behold, three men stood by him; and when he saw [them], he ran to meet them from the tent door and bowed himself toward the ground</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.3'>and said, My Lord, if now I have found grace in thy sight, pass not away, I pray thee, from thy servant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.4'>Let a little water, I pray you, be brought and wash your feet and rest yourselves under a tree;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.5'>and I will bring a morsel of bread and comfort your hearts; after that ye shall pass on because for this ye are come to your servant. And they said, So do as thou hast said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.6'>And Abraham hastened into the tent unto Sarah and said, Make ready quickly three measures of fine meal, knead [it], and make bread baked under the ashes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.7'>And Abraham ran unto the herd and brought a calf tender and good and gave [it] unto a young man; and he hastened to dress it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.8'>And he took butter and milk and the calf which he had dressed and set [it] before them; and he stood by them under the tree, and they ate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.9'>And they said unto him, Where [is] Sarah thy wife? And he said, Here, in the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.10'>Then he said, I will certainly return unto thee according to the time of life; and, behold, Sarah thy wife shall have a son. And Sarah heard [it] in the tent door, which [was] behind him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.11'>Now Abraham and Sarah [were] old [and] well stricken in age, [and] it ceased to be with Sarah after the manner of women.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.12'>Therefore Sarah laughed within herself, saying, After I am waxed old, shall I have pleasure, my lord being old also?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.13'>Then the LORD said unto Abraham, Why did Sarah laugh, saying, Shall I of a surety bear a child when I am old?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.14'>Is any thing too hard for the LORD? At the time appointed I will return unto thee, according to the time of life, and Sarah shall have a son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.15'>Then Sarah denied, saying, I laughed not; for she was afraid. And he said, No, but thou didst laugh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.16'>And the men rose up from there and looked toward Sodom; and Abraham went with them to bring them on the way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.17'>And the LORD said, Shall I hide from Abraham that thing which I do,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.18'>seeing that Abraham shall surely become a great and mighty nation and that all the Gentiles of the earth shall be blessed in him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.19'>For I know him, that he will command his sons and his household after him, and they shall keep the way of the LORD, to do righteousness and judgment, that the LORD may bring upon Abraham that which he has spoken of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.20'>And the LORD said, Because the cry of Sodom and Gomorrah is great and because their sin is very grievous;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.21'>I will go down now and see whether they have done altogether according to the cry of it, which is come unto me; and if not, I will know.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.22'>And the men turned their faces from there and went toward Sodom; but Abraham stood yet before the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.23'>And Abraham drew near and said, Wilt thou also destroy the righteous with the wicked?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.24'>Peradventure there are fifty righteous within the city; wilt thou also destroy and not spare the place for the fifty righteous that [are] in it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.25'>That be far from thee to do after this manner, to slay the righteous with the wicked and that the righteous should be [treated] as the wicked that are far from thee. Shall not the Judge of all the earth do right?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.26'>And the LORD said, If I find in Sodom fifty righteous within the city, then I will spare all the place for their sakes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.27'>And Abraham answered and said, Behold now, I have taken upon me to speak unto the Lord, who [am but] dust and ashes;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.28'>peradventure there shall lack five of the fifty righteous: wilt thou destroy all the city for [lack of] five? And he said, If I find there forty-five, I will not destroy [it].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.29'>And he spoke unto him yet again, and said, Peradventure there shall be forty found there. And he said, I will not do [it] for forty's sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.30'>And he said [unto him], Oh let not the Lord now be angry if I shall speak; peradventure there shall thirty be found there. And he said, I will not do [it] if I find thirty there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.31'>And he said, Behold now, I have taken upon me to speak unto the Lord; peradventure there shall be twenty found there. And he said, I will not destroy [it] for twenty's sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.32'>And he said, Oh let not the Lord be angry, and I will speak yet but this once; peradventure ten shall be found there. And he said, I will not destroy [it] for ten's sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.18.33'>And the LORD went away as soon as he had left communing with Abraham; and Abraham returned unto his place.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.19'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.1'>And the two angels came to Sodom at evening; and Lot sat in the gate of Sodom, and Lot seeing [them] rose up to meet them, and he bowed himself with his face toward the ground,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.2'>and he said, Behold now, my lords, turn in, I pray you, into your servant's house and tarry all night and wash your feet, and ye shall rise up early and go on your ways. And they said, No, but we will abide in the street all night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.3'>And he pressed upon them greatly, and they turned in unto him and entered into his house, and he made them a banquet and baked unleavened bread, and they ate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.4'>But before they lay down, the men of the city, [even] the men of Sodom, compassed the house round, both old and young, all the people from every quarter;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.5'>and they called unto Lot and said unto him, Where [are] the men who came in to thee this night? Bring them out unto us that we may know them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.6'>And Lot went out at the door unto them and shut the door after him</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.7'>and said, I pray you, brethren, do not so wickedly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.8'>Behold now, I have two daughters who have not known man; let me, I pray you, bring them out unto you and do ye to them as [is] good in your eyes; only unto these men do nothing, for they have come under the shadow of my roof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.9'>And they said, Stand back. And they said [again], This fellow came in to sojourn and is he to lift himself up as judge? Now will we deal worse with thee than with them. And they did great violence to the man, [even] Lot, and came near to break the door.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.10'>Then the men put forth their hand and pulled Lot into the house with them and shut the door.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.11'>And they smote the men that [were] at the door of the house with blindness, both small and great so that they wearied themselves to find the door.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.12'>And the men said unto Lot, Hast thou anyone else here? Sons-in-law and thy sons and thy daughters and whatever thou hast in the city, bring [them] out of this place;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.13'>For we will destroy this place because the cry of them is waxed great before the face of the LORD, and the LORD has sent us to destroy it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.14'>And Lot went out and spoke unto his sons-in-law, those who were to marry his daughters, and said, Up, get you out of this place; for the LORD will destroy this city. But he seemed as one that mocked unto his sons-in-law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.15'>And when the morning arose, then the angels hastened Lot, saying, Arise, take thy wife and thy two daughters who are here; lest thou be consumed in the iniquity of the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.16'>And while he lingered, the men laid hold upon his hand and upon the hand of his wife and upon the hand of his two daughters, the LORD being merciful unto him; and they brought him forth and set him outside the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.17'>And it came to pass as they brought them forth outside, that he said, Escape; for thy soul, do not look behind thee, neither stop thou in all the plain; escape to the mountain, lest thou be consumed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.18'>And Lot said unto them, Oh, not so, my lords;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.19'>behold now, thy servant has found grace in thy sight, and thou hast magnified thy mercy, which thou hast showed unto me in saving my life; but I cannot escape to the mountain, lest some evil take me, and I die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.20'>Behold now, this city [is] near to flee unto, and it [is] a little one; Oh, let me escape there, ([is] it not a little one?) and my soul shall live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.21'>And he said unto him, See, I have accepted thee concerning this thing also that I will not overthrow the city for which thou hast spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.22'>Make thee haste, escape there; for I cannot do anything until thou hast arrived there. Therefore the name of the city was called Zoar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.23'>The sun was rising upon the earth when Lot entered into Zoar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.24'>Then the LORD rained upon Sodom and upon Gomorrah brimstone and fire from the LORD out of the heavens;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.25'>and he overthrew those cities and all that plain, with all the inhabitants of those cities, and the fruit of the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.26'>Then the wife of Lot looked back from behind him, and she became a pillar of salt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.27'>And Abraham rose up early in the morning to the place where he had stood before the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.28'>And he looked toward Sodom and Gomorrah and toward all the land of that plain and beheld that the smoke of the land went up as the smoke of a furnace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.29'>And it came to pass as God destroyed the cities of the plain that God remembered Abraham and sent Lot out of the midst of the destruction when he overthrew the cities in the which Lot dwelt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.30'>But Lot went up out of Zoar and dwelt in the mountain and his two daughters with him; for he feared to dwell in Zoar; and he dwelt in a cave, he and his two daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.31'>Then the firstborn said unto the younger, Our father [is] old, and [there is] not a man [left] in the earth to come in unto us after the manner of all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.32'>Come, let us make our father drink wine, and we will lie with him that we may preserve the generation of our father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.33'>And they made their father drink wine that night; and the firstborn went in and lay with her father; and he perceived not when she lay down, nor when she arose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.34'>And it came to pass on the next day that the firstborn said unto the younger, Behold, I lay last night with my father; let us make him drink wine this night also; and go thou in [and] lie with him that we may preserve the generation of our father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.35'>And they made their father drink wine that night also, and the younger arose and lay with him; and he perceived not when she lay down, nor when she arose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.36'>Thus were both the daughters of Lot with child by their father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.37'>And the firstborn bore a son and called his name Moab; the same [is] the father of the Moabites unto this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.19.38'>And the younger, she also bore a son and called his name Benammi; the same [is] the father of the sons of Ammon unto this day.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.20'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.1'>And Abraham journeyed from there toward the land of the Negev and dwelt between Kadesh and Shur and sojourned in Gerar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.2'>And Abraham said of Sarah his wife, She [is] my sister. And Abimelech king of Gerar sent and took Sarah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.3'>But God came to Abimelech in a dream by night and said to him, Behold, thou [art] a dead man, for the woman whom thou hast taken, for she [is] a man's wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.4'>But Abimelech had not come near her, and he said, Lord, wilt thou slay also a righteous person?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.5'>Did he not say unto me, She [is] my sister? And she, even she herself said, He [is] my brother; in the simplicity of my heart and cleanness of my hands I have done this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.6'>And God said unto him in a dream, Yes, I know that thou didst this in the integrity of thy heart; for I also withheld thee from sinning against me; therefore I did not allow thee to touch her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.7'>Now therefore restore the man [his] wife, for he [is] a prophet, and he shall pray for thee, and thou shalt live. And if thou restore [her] not, know thou that thou shalt surely die, thou and all that [are] thine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.8'>Therefore Abimelech rose early in the morning and called all his servants and told all these things in their ears; and the men feared greatly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.9'>Then Abimelech called Abraham and said unto him, What hast thou done unto us and [in] what have I sinned against thee that thou hast brought on me and on my kingdom such a great sin? Thou hast done deeds unto me that ought not to be done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.10'>And Abimelech said unto Abraham, What didst thou see that thou hast done this thing?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.11'>And Abraham said, Because I thought, Surely the fear of God [is] not in this place, and they will slay me for my wife's sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.12'>And yet indeed, [she is also] my sister; she [is] the daughter of my father, but not the daughter of my mother; and she became my wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.13'>And it came to pass when God caused me to wander from my father's house that I said unto her, This [is] the mercy which thou shalt show unto me: at every place where we shall come, say of me, He [is] my brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.14'>Then Abimelech took sheep and oxen and menservants and womenservants and gave [them] unto Abraham and restored him Sarah his wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.15'>And Abimelech said, Behold, my land [is] before thee; dwell where it pleases thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.16'>And unto Sarah he said, Behold, I have given thy brother a thousand [pieces] of silver; behold, he [is] to thee a covering of the eyes, unto all that [were] with thee and with everyone: thus she was reproved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.17'>So Abraham prayed unto God; and God healed Abimelech and his wife and his maidservants; and they bore [children].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.20.18'>For the LORD had completely closed up all the wombs of the house of Abimelech because of Sarah, Abraham's wife.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.21'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.1'>And the LORD visited Sarah as he had said, and the LORD did with Sarah as he had spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.2'>For Sarah conceived and bore Abraham a son in his old age at the set time of which God had spoken to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.3'>And Abraham called the name of his son that was born unto him, whom Sarah bore to him, Isaac.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.4'>And Abraham circumcised his son Isaac being eight days old as God had commanded him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.5'>And Abraham was one hundred years old when his son Isaac was born unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.6'>Then Sarah said, God has made me to laugh [so that] all that hear will laugh with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.7'>And she said, Who would have said unto Abraham, that Sarah should have given children suck? For I have born [him] a son in his old age.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.8'>And the child grew and was weaned, and Abraham made a great banquet the day that Isaac was weaned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.9'>And Sarah saw the son of Hagar the Egyptian, whom she had born unto Abraham, mocking.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.10'>Therefore she said unto Abraham, Cast out this bondwoman and her son; for the son of this bondwoman shall not be heir with my son, [even] with Isaac.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.11'>And the thing was very grievous in Abraham's sight because of his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.12'>Then God said unto Abraham, Let it not be grievous in thy sight because of the lad and because of thy bondwoman; in all that Sarah has said unto thee, hearken unto her voice; for in Isaac shall thy seed be called.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.13'>And also of the son of the bondwoman I will make a nation because he [is] thy seed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.14'>So Abraham rose up early in the morning and took bread and a bottle of water and gave [it] unto Hagar, putting [it] on her shoulder, and the child and sent her away; and she departed and wandered in the wilderness of Beersheba.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.15'>And the water was spent in the bottle, and she cast the child under a tree.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.16'>And she went and sat her down over against [him] a good way off as it were a bowshot; for she said, Let me not see the death of the child. And she sat over against [him] and lifted up her voice and wept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.17'>And God heard the voice of the lad, and the angel of God called to Hagar out of heaven and said unto her, What ails thee, Hagar? Fear not, for God has heard the voice of the lad where he [is].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.18'>Arise, lift up the lad and hold him in thy hand, for I will make him a great nation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.19'>And God opened her eyes, and she saw a well of water; and she went and filled the bottle with water and gave the lad drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.20'>And God was with the lad, and he grew and dwelt in the wilderness and became an archer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.21'>And he dwelt in the wilderness of Paran, and his mother took a wife for him out of the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.22'>And it came to pass at that time that Abimelech and Phichol, the prince of his host, spoke unto Abraham, saying, God [is] with thee in all that thou doest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.23'>Now therefore swear unto me here by God that thou wilt not deal falsely with me, nor with my son, nor with my son's son; [but] according to the mercy that I have done unto thee, thou shalt do unto me and to the land in which thou hast sojourned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.24'>And Abraham said, I will swear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.25'>And Abraham reproved Abimelech because of a well of water which Abimelech's servants had violently taken away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.26'>And Abimelech said, I know not who has done this thing; neither didst thou tell me, neither have I heard [of it], but today.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.27'>And Abraham took sheep and oxen and gave them unto Abimelech; and both of them made a covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.28'>And Abraham set seven ewe lambs of the flock by themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.29'>And Abimelech said unto Abraham, What [mean] these seven ewe lambs which thou hast set by themselves?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.30'>And he said, For [these] seven ewe lambs shalt thou take of my hand that they may be a witness unto me that I have dug this well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.31'>Therefore he called that place Beersheba; because there they swore, both of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.32'>Thus they made a covenant at Beersheba; then Abimelech rose up and Phichol, the prince of his host, and they returned into the land of the Philistines.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.33'>And [Abraham] planted a grove in Beersheba and called there on the name of the LORD, the eternal God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.21.34'>And Abraham sojourned in the Philistines' land many days.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.22'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.1'>And it came to pass after these things that God proved Abraham and said unto him, Abraham; and he said, Behold, [here] I [am].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.2'>And he said, Take now thy son, thine only [son] Isaac, whom thou dost love, and go to the land of Moriah and offer him there for a burnt offering upon one of the mountains which I will tell thee of.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.3'>And Abraham rose up early in the morning and saddled his ass and took two of his young men with him and Isaac his son, and cut the wood for the burnt offering and rose up and went unto the place of which God had told him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.4'>Then on the third day Abraham lifted up his eyes and saw the place afar off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.5'>And Abraham said unto his young men, Abide here with the ass, and I and the lad will go yonder and worship and come again to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.6'>And Abraham took the wood of the burnt offering and laid [it] upon Isaac, his son; and he took the fire in his hand and the knife; and they both went together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.7'>Then Isaac spoke unto Abraham his father and said, My father; and he said, Here [am] I, my son. And he said, Behold the fire and the wood, but where [is] the lamb for the burnt offering?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.8'>And Abraham answered, My son, God will provide himself a lamb for a burnt offering, so they both went together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.9'>And when they came to the place which God had told him of, Abraham built an altar there and laid the wood in order and bound Isaac his son and laid him on the altar upon the wood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.10'>And Abraham stretched forth his hand and took the knife to slay his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.11'>Then the angel of the LORD called unto him out of heaven and said, Abraham, Abraham; and he said, Here [am] I.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.12'>And he said, Lay not thine hand upon the lad, neither do thou anything unto him; for now I know that thou doest fear God, seeing thou hast not withheld thy son, thine only [son] from me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.13'>And Abraham lifted up his eyes and looked and beheld behind [him] a ram caught in a thicket by his horns; and Abraham went and took the ram and offered him up for a burnt offering instead of his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.14'>And Abraham called the name of that place The LORD Shall See ([YHWH-hjireh]). Therefore it is said [to] this day, In the mount of the LORD it shall be seen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.15'>And the angel of the LORD called unto Abraham out of heaven the second time</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.16'>and said, By myself I have sworn, said the LORD, for because thou hast done this thing and hast not withheld thy son, thine only [son];</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.17'>that in blessing I will bless thee and in multiplying I will multiply thy seed as the stars of the heaven and as the sand which [is] upon the sea shore; and thy seed shall possess the gates of his enemies;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.18'>and in thy seed shall all the Gentiles of the earth be blessed because thou hast hearkened unto my voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.19'>So Abraham returned unto his young men, and they rose up and went together to Beersheba; and Abraham dwelt at Beersheba.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.20'>And it came to pass after these things that it was told Abraham, saying, Behold, Milcah, she has also born sons unto thy brother Nahor;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.21'>Huz, his firstborn, and Buz, his brother, and Kemuel, the father of Aram</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.22'>and Chesed and Hazo and Pildash and Jidlaph and Bethuel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.23'>And Bethuel begat Rebekah. Milcah gave birth to these eight unto Nahor, Abraham's brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.22.24'>And his concubine, whose name [was] Reumah, also gave birth to Tebah and Gaham and Thahash and Maachah.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.23'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.1'>And Sarah was one hundred and twenty-seven years old; [these were] the years of the life of Sarah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.2'>And Sarah died in Kirjatharba; the same [is] Hebron in the land of Canaan; and Abraham came to mourn for Sarah and to weep for her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.3'>And Abraham stood up from before his dead and spoke unto the sons of Heth, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.4'>I [am] a stranger and a sojourner with you; give me a possession of a buryingplace with you, that I may bury my dead out of my sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.5'>And the sons of Heth answered Abraham, saying unto him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.6'>Hear us, my lord; thou [art] a prince of God among us; in the best of our sepulchres bury thy dead; none of us shall withhold from thee his sepulchre so that thou may bury thy dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.7'>And Abraham stood up and bowed himself to the people of the land, [even] to the sons of Heth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.8'>And he communed with them, saying, If it is your desire that I should bury my dead out of my sight, hear me and intercede for me to Ephron, the son of Zohar,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.9'>that he may give me the cave of Machpelah, which he has, which [is] in the end of his field; for as much money as it is worth he shall give it [to] me for a possession of a buryingplace amongst you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.10'>This Ephron dwelt among the sons of Heth; and Ephron, the Hittite, answered Abraham in the audience of the sons of Heth, [even] of all that went in at the gate of his city, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.11'>No, my lord, hear me; I give thee the field, and the cave that [is] therein, I give it [to] thee; in the presence of the sons of my people I give it [to] thee; bury thy dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.12'>And Abraham bowed down himself before the people of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.13'>And he spoke unto Ephron in the audience of the people of the land, saying, But if thou [wilt give it], I pray thee, hear me; I will give thee money for the field; take [it] of me, and I will bury my dead there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.14'>And Ephron answered Abraham, saying unto him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.15'>My lord, hearken unto me: the land [is worth] four hundred shekels of silver; what [is] that between me and thee? bury therefore thy dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.16'>Then Abraham hearkened unto Ephron, and Abraham weighed to Ephron the silver, which he had named in the audience of the sons of Heth, four hundred shekels of silver, current [money] with the merchant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.17'>And the field of Ephron, which [was] in Machpelah, which [was] before Mamre, the field and the cave which [was] therein, and all the trees that [were] in the field that [were] in all the borders round about were made sure</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.18'>unto Abraham for a possession in the presence of the sons of Heth, before all that went in at the gate of his city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.19'>And after this, Abraham buried Sarah his wife in the cave of the field of Machpelah before Mamre; the same [is] Hebron in the land of Canaan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.23.20'>And the field and the cave that [is] therein were made sure unto Abraham for a possession of a buryingplace by the sons of Heth.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.24'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.1'>And Abraham was old [and] well stricken in age, and the LORD had blessed Abraham in all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.2'>And Abraham said unto his eldest servant of his house, who ruled over all that he had, Put, I pray thee, thy hand under my thigh,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.3'>and I will make thee swear by the LORD, the God of the heavens and the God of the earth, that thou shalt not take a wife unto my son of the daughters of the Canaanites, among whom I dwell;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.4'>but thou shalt go unto my country and to my kindred and take a wife unto my son Isaac.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.5'>And the servant said unto him, Peradventure the woman will not be willing to follow me unto this land, must I therefore bring thy son again unto the land from which thou didst come?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.6'>And Abraham said unto him, Beware that thou not bring my son there again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.7'>The LORD God of heaven, who took me from my father's house and from the land of my kindred and who spoke unto me and swore unto me, saying, Unto thy seed will I give this land; he shall send his angel before thee, and thou shalt take a wife unto my son from there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.8'>And if the woman will not be willing to follow thee, then thou shalt be free from this my oath; only do not bring my son there again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.9'>Then the servant put his hand under the thigh of Abraham his master and swore to him concerning that matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.10'>And the servant took ten camels of the camels of his master and departed with the best of what his master had in his hand; and he arose and went to Ara-naharaim, unto the city of Nahor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.11'>And he made his camels kneel down outside the city by a well of water at the time of the evening, [even] the time that women go out to draw [water].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.12'>And he said, O LORD, God of my master Abraham, I pray thee, to have a good encounter this day and show mercy unto my master Abraham.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.13'>Behold, I stand [here] by the fountain of water, and the daughters of the men of the city come out for water:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.14'>And let it come to pass that the damsel to whom I shall say, Let down thy pitcher, I pray thee, that I may drink; and she shall say, Drink, and I will give thy camels to drink also; [let the same be] she [that] thou hast appointed for thy servant Isaac; and thereby shall I know that thou hast shown mercy unto my master.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.15'>And it came to pass before he had done speaking that, behold, Rebekah came out (who was born to Bethuel, son of Milcah, the wife of Nahor, Abraham's brother) with her pitcher upon her shoulder.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.16'>And the damsel [was] very fair to look upon, a virgin, whom no man had known; and she went down to the fountain and filled her pitcher and and was coming [back] up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.17'>Then the servant ran to meet her and said, Let me, I pray thee, drink a little water of thy pitcher.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.18'>And she said, Drink, my lord, and she hastened to let down her pitcher upon her hand and gave him drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.19'>And when she had finished giving him drink, she said, I will draw [water] for thy camels also until they have finished drinking.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.20'>And she hastened and emptied her pitcher into the trough, and ran again unto the well to draw [water] and drew for all his camels.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.21'>And the man marveled at her in silence, to see whether the LORD had prospered his journey or not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.22'>And it came to pass as the camels had finished drinking that the man took a golden pendant of half a shekel weight and two bracelets for her hands of ten [shekels] weight of gold</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.23'>and said, Whose daughter [art] thou? Tell me, I pray thee; is there room [in] thy father's house for us to lodge in?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.24'>And she said unto him, I [am] the daughter of Bethuel the son of Milcah, whom she gave birth unto Nahor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.25'>She said moreover unto him, We have both straw and fodder enough and room to lodge in.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.26'>Then the man bowed down his head and worshipped the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.27'>And he said, Blessed [be] the LORD, God of my master Abraham, who has not lifted his mercy and his truth from my master, the LORD leading me in the way to the house of my master's brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.28'>And the damsel ran and told [those of] her mother's house these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.29'>And Rebekah had a brother, and his name [was] Laban; and Laban ran out unto the man to the fountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.30'>And it came to pass when he saw the pendant and the bracelets upon his sister's hands, she said, Thus spoke the man unto me; then he came unto the man; and, behold, he stood by the camels at the fountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.31'>And he said, Come in, thou blessed of the LORD; why dost thou stand outside? For I have prepared the house, and the place for the camels.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.32'>Then the man came into the house, and [Laban] ungirded his camels and gave straw and fodder for the camels and water to wash his feet and the men's feet that [were] with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.33'>And they set [food] before him to eat, but he said, I will not eat until I have told my errand. And [he] said unto him, Speak on.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.34'>And he said, I [am] Abraham's servant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.35'>And the LORD has blessed my master greatly, and he is become great; and he has given him flocks and herds and silver and gold and menservants and maidservants and camels and asses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.36'>And Sarah, my master's wife, bore a son to my master when she was old, unto whom he has given all that he has.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.37'>And my master made me swear, saying, Thou shalt not take a wife to my son of the daughters of the Canaanites, in whose land I dwell;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.38'>but thou shalt go unto my father's house and to my kindred and take from there a wife for my son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.39'>And I said unto my master, Peradventure the woman will not follow me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.40'>And he said unto me, The LORD, before whom I walk, will send his angel with thee and prosper thy way; and thou shalt take a wife for my son of my lineage and of my father's house;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.41'>then shalt thou be free from [this] my oath, when thou hast come unto my lineage; and if they give [her] not [unto] thee, thou shalt be free from my oath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.42'>And I came this day unto the fountain and said, O LORD, God of my master Abraham, if now thou dost prosper my way by which I go,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.43'>behold, I stand by the fountain of water; let it come to pass, therefore, [that] the virgin who comes forth to draw [water] unto whom I say, Give me, I pray thee, a little water of thy pitcher to drink;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.44'>and if she shall say to me, Both drink thou, and I will also draw for thy camels, [let] the same [be] the woman whom the LORD has prepared for my master's son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.45'>And before I had finished speaking in my heart, behold, Rebekah came forth with her pitcher on her shoulder, and she went down unto the fountain and drew [water], and I said unto her, Let me drink, I pray thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.46'>And she made haste and let down her pitcher from her [shoulder] and said, Drink, and I will give thy camels drink also; so I drank, and she gave to drink unto the camels also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.47'>And I asked her and said, Whose daughter [art] thou? And she said, The daughter of Bethuel, Nahor's son, whom Milcah bore unto him. Then I put the pendant over her nose and the bracelets upon her hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.48'>And I bowed down my head and worshipped the LORD and blessed the LORD God of my master Abraham, who had led me in the way of the truth to take my master's brother's daughter unto his son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.49'>And now if ye will deal in mercy and truth with my master, tell me; and if not, tell me, that I may turn to the right hand or to the left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.50'>Then Laban and Bethuel answered and said, The thing proceeds from the LORD; we cannot speak unto thee bad or good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.51'>Behold, Rebekah [is] before thee; take [her] and go and let her be thy master's son's wife, as the LORD has spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.52'>And it came to pass that when Abraham's servant heard their words, he worshipped the LORD, [bowing himself] to the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.53'>And the servant brought forth vessels of silver and vessels of gold and raiment and gave [them] to Rebekah; he also gave precious things to her brother and to her mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.54'>And they ate and drank, he and the men that [were] with him, and slept; and they rose up in the morning, and he said, Send me away unto my master.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.55'>Then her brother and her mother said, Let the damsel abide with us a [few] days, at the least ten; after that she shall go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.56'>And he said unto them, Hinder me not, seeing the LORD has prospered my way; send me away that I may go to my master.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.57'>Then they said, We will call the damsel and enquire at her mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.58'>And they called Rebekah and said unto her, Wilt thou go with this man? And she said, I will go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.59'>So they sent away Rebekah, their sister, and her nurse and Abraham's servant and his men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.60'>And they blessed Rebekah and said unto her, Thou [art] our sister; be thou [the mother] of thousands of ten thousands, and let thy seed possess the gate of those who hate them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.61'>And Rebekah arose, and her damsels, and they rode upon the camels and followed the man; and the servant took Rebekah and went away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.62'>And Isaac came from the way of the well Lahairoi; for he dwelt in the land of the Negev.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.63'>And Isaac had gone out to pray in the field at the evening hour; and he lifted up his eyes and saw, and, behold, the camels [were] coming.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.64'>And Rebekah also lifted up her eyes, and when she saw Isaac, she lighted off the camel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.65'>For she [had] asked the servant, What man [is] this that walks in the field to meet us? And the servant [had] said, This [is] my master; therefore she took a veil and covered herself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.66'>Then the servant told Isaac all the things that he had done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.24.67'>And Isaac brought her into his mother Sarah's tent and took Rebekah as [his] wife; and he loved her; and Isaac was comforted after his mother's [death].:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.25'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.1'>Then again Abraham took a wife, and her name [was] Keturah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.2'>And she bore him Zimran, Jokshan, Medan, Midian, Ishbak, and Shuah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.3'>And Jokshan begat Sheba and Dedan. And the sons of Dedan were Asshurim, Letushim, and Leummim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.4'>And the sons of Midian: Ephah, Epher, Enoch, Abida, and Eldaah. All these [were] the sons of Keturah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.5'>And Abraham gave all that he had unto Isaac.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.6'>But unto the sons of the concubines, which Abraham had, Abraham gave gifts and sent them away from Isaac his son, while he yet lived, eastward, unto the east country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.7'>And these [were] the days of the years of Abraham's life which he lived, one hundred seventy-five years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.8'>Then Abraham expired and died in a good old age, an old man and full [of years], and was gathered to his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.9'>And his sons Isaac and Ishmael buried him in the cave of Machpelah, in the field of Ephron the son of Zohar the Hittite, which [is] in front of Mamre;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.10'>the field which Abraham purchased of the sons of Heth, there was Abraham buried, and Sarah his wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.11'>And it came to pass after the death of Abraham, that God blessed his son Isaac; and Isaac dwelt by the well Lahairoi.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.12'>Now these [are] the generations of Ishmael, son of Abraham, whom Hagar the Egyptian, Sarah's handmaid, gave birth unto Abraham:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.13'>And these [are] the names of the sons of Ishmael, by their names, according to their lineages: the firstborn of Ishmael, Nebajoth, and Kedar, Adbeel, Mibsam,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.14'>Mishma, Dumah, Massa,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.15'>Hadar, Tema, Jetur, Naphish, and Kedemah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.16'>These [are] the sons of Ishmael, and these [are] their names, by their towns and by their palaces; twelve princes according to their families.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.17'>And these [are] the years of the life of Ishmael, one hundred thirty-seven years; and Ishmael expired and died and was gathered unto his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.18'>And they dwelt from Havilah unto Shur, that [is] before Egypt, as thou goest toward Assyria; [and] he fell in the presence of all his brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.19'>And these [are] the generations of Isaac, son of Abraham. Abraham begat Isaac;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.20'>and Isaac was forty years old when he took Rebekah to wife, the daughter of Bethuel, the Aramean of Padanaram, the sister to Laban the Aramean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.21'>And Isaac prayed unto the LORD for his wife because she [was] barren; and the LORD accepted him, and Rebekah his wife conceived.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.22'>And the sons struggled together within her; and she said, If [this is] so, why should I [live]? And she went to enquire of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.23'>And the LORD said unto her, Two nations [are] in thy womb, and two [manner of] peoples shall be separated from thy bowels; and [the one] people shall be stronger than [the other] people; and the elder shall serve the younger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.24'>And when her days to be delivered were fulfilled, behold, [there were] twins in her womb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.25'>And the first came out red, all over like a hairy garment; and they called his name Esau.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.26'>And afterwards his brother came out with Esau's heel grasped in his hand; and his name was called Jacob. And Isaac [was] sixty years old when Rebekah gave birth to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.27'>And the boys grew, and Esau was a cunning hunter, a man of the field; and Jacob [was] an upright man, remaining in the tents.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.28'>And Isaac loved Esau because he ate of [his] venison; but Rebekah loved Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.29'>And Jacob boiled pottage; and Esau came from the field, and he [was] faint;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.30'>and Esau said to Jacob, Give me to eat, I pray thee, of that red [pottage]; for I [am] faint. Therefore was his name called Edom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.31'>And Jacob said, Sell me this day thy birthright.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.32'>And Esau said, Behold, I [am] at the point to die; and what profit shall this birthright do to me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.33'>And Jacob said, Swear to me this day; and he swore unto him and he sold his birthright unto Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.25.34'>Then Jacob gave Esau of the bread and of the pottage of lentils; and he ate and drank, and rose up, and went away. Thus Esau despised [his] birthright.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.26'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.1'>And there was a famine in the land, in addition to the first famine that was in the days of Abraham. And Isaac went unto Abimelech, king of the Philistines, unto Gerar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.2'>And the LORD appeared unto him and said, [Do] not go down into Egypt; dwell in the land which I shall tell thee of;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.3'>abide in this land, and I will be with thee, and will bless thee; for unto thee, and unto thy seed, I will give all these lands, and I will confirm the oath which I swore unto Abraham thy father;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.4'>and I will make thy seed to multiply as the stars of heaven and will give unto thy seed all these lands, and in thy seed shall all the Gentiles of the earth be blessed</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.5'>because Abraham hearkened unto my voice and kept my charge, my commandments, my statutes, and my laws.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.6'>Therefore Isaac dwelt in Gerar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.7'>And the men of that place asked [him] of his wife; and he said, She [is] my sister, for he feared to say, [She is] my wife, lest, [said he], the men of the place should kill me for Rebekah because she [was] fair to look upon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.8'>And it came to pass, when he had been there a long time that Abimelech, king of the Philistines, looking out a window, saw Isaac sporting with Rebekah, his wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.9'>And Abimelech called Isaac and said, Behold, of a surety she [is] thy wife; and how didst thou say, She [is] my sister? And Isaac said unto him, Because I said, Lest I die because of her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.10'>And Abimelech said, What [is] this thou hast done unto us? One of the people might easily have slept with thy wife, and thou should have brought the sin upon us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.11'>Then Abimelech charged all the people, saying, He that touches this man or his wife shall surely be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.12'>Then Isaac sowed in that land and received in the same year one hundred-fold, and the LORD blessed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.13'>And the man waxed great and went forward and grew until he became very great,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.14'>for he had possession of flocks, possession of herds, great store of servants, and the Philistines envied him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.15'>For all the wells which his father's servants had dug in the days of Abraham his father, the Philistines had stopped them and filled them with earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.16'>And Abimelech said unto Isaac, Go from us, for thou art become much mightier than we.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.17'>And Isaac departed from there and pitched his tent in the valley of Gerar and dwelt there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.18'>And Isaac reopened the wells of water, which they had opened in the days of Abraham his father, for the Philistines had stopped them [up] after the death of Abraham, and he called their names after the names by which his father had called them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.19'>And Isaac's servants dug in the valley and found there a well of living waters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.20'>And the pastors of Gerar strove with Isaac's pastors, saying, The water [is] ours; therefore he called the name of the well Esek, because they strove with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.21'>And they opened another well and strove for that [one] also; and he called the name of it Sitnah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.22'>And he left there and opened another well; and for that [one] they did not strive and he called the name of it Rehoboth, and he said, For now the LORD has made room for us, and we shall be fruitful in the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.23'>And he went up from there unto Beersheba.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.24'>And the LORD appeared unto him the same night, and said, I [am] the God of Abraham thy father; fear not, for I [am] with thee and will bless thee and multiply thy seed for my servant Abraham's sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.25'>And he built an altar there and called upon the name of the LORD and pitched his tent there; and there Isaac's servants opened a well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.26'>Then Abimelech went to him from Gerar and Ahuzzath, one of his friends, and Phichol, the chief captain of his army.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.27'>And Isaac said unto them, Why come ye to me, seeing ye hate me and have sent me away from you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.28'>And they said, We have seen certainly that the LORD is with thee; and we said, Let there be now an oath between us, [even] between us and thee, and let us make a covenant with thee,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.29'>that thou wilt do us no hurt, as we have not touched thee and as we have done unto thee nothing but good and have sent thee away in peace; thou [art] now the blessed of the LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.30'>And he made them a banquet, and they ate and drank.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.31'>And they rose up early in the morning and swore one to another; and Isaac sent them away, and they departed from him in peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.32'>And it came to pass the same day that Isaac's servants came and told him concerning the well which they had opened and said unto him, We have found water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.33'>And he called it Shebah, therefore the name of the city [is] Beersheba unto this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.34'>And Esau was forty years old when he took to wife Judith, the daughter of Beeri, the Hittite, and Bashemath the daughter of Elon, the Hittite:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.26.35'>Who were bitterness of spirit unto Isaac and to Rebekah.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.27'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.1'>And it came to pass, that when Isaac became old, and his eyes were dim so that he could not see, he called Esau, his eldest son, and said unto him, My son, and he said unto him, Behold, [here am] I.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.2'>And he said, Behold now, I am old: I know not the day of my death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.3'>Now, therefore, take I pray thee, thy weapons, thy quiver and thy bow and go out to the field and take me [some] venison</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.4'>and make me savoury food, such as I love, and bring [it] to me that I may eat, that my soul may bless thee before I die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.5'>And Rebekah heard when Isaac spoke to Esau, his son. And Esau went to the field to hunt [for] venison [and] to bring [it].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.6'>Then Rebekah spoke unto Jacob her son, saying, Behold, I heard thy father speak unto Esau, thy brother, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.7'>Bring me venison and make me savoury food that I may eat and bless thee before the LORD before my death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.8'>Now, therefore, my son, hearken unto my voice according to that which I command thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.9'>Go now to the flock and bring me from there two good kids of the goats, and I will make them savoury food for thy father, such as he loves;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.10'>and thou shalt bring [it] to thy father that he may eat and that he may bless thee before his death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.11'>And Jacob said to Rebekah his mother, Behold, Esau, my brother, [is] a hairy man, and I [am] a smooth man;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.12'>my father peradventure will feel me, and I shall seem to him as a deceiver; and I shall bring a curse upon myself, and not a blessing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.13'>And his mother said unto him, Upon me [be] thy curse, my son; only obey my voice and go bring me [them].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.14'>And he went and took them and brought [them] to his mother, and his mother made savoury food, such as his father loved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.15'>And Rebekah took good clothes of her eldest son Esau, which [were] with her in the house, and put them upon Jacob, her younger son:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.16'>And she put the skins of the kids of the goats upon his hands and upon the smooth of his neck,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.17'>and she gave the savoury food and the bread, which she had prepared, into the hand of her son Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.18'>And he came unto his father and said, My father, and he said, Here [am] I; who [art] thou, my son?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.19'>And Jacob said unto his father, I [am] Esau, thy firstborn; I have done according as thou didst command me; arise, I pray thee, sit and eat of my venison, that thy soul may bless me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.20'>Then Isaac said unto his son, How [is it] that thou hast found [it] so quickly, my son? And he said, Because the LORD thy God brought [it] to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.21'>And Isaac said unto Jacob, Come near, I pray thee, that I may feel thee, my son, whether thou [be] my very son Esau or not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.22'>And Jacob went near unto Isaac his father; and he felt him and said, The voice [is] Jacob's voice, but the hands [are] the hands of Esau.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.23'>And he discerned him not because his hands were hairy, as his brother Esau's hands; so he blessed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.24'>And he said, [Art] thou my very son Esau? And he said, I [am].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.25'>And he said, Bring [it] near to me, and I will eat of my son's venison, that my soul may bless thee. And he brought [it] near to him, and he ate; and he brought him wine, and he drank.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.26'>And his father Isaac said unto him, Come near now and kiss me, my son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.27'>And he came near and kissed him, and he smelled the smell of his clothing and blessed him and said, See, the smell of my son [is] as the smell of a field which the LORD has blessed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.28'>Therefore [let] God give thee of the dew of heaven and of the fatness of the earth and plenty of wheat and new wine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.29'>Let the peoples serve thee and nations bow down to thee; be lord over thy brethren, and let thy mother's sons bow down to thee; cursed [be] every one that curses thee, and blessed [be] he that blesses thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.30'>And it came to pass as soon as Isaac had made an end of blessing Jacob, and Jacob was yet scarce gone out from the presence of Isaac his father that Esau his brother came in from his hunting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.31'>And he also had made savory food and brought it unto his father and said unto his father, Let my father arise and eat of his son's venison that thy soul may bless me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.32'>And Isaac his father said unto him, Who [art] thou? And he said, I [am] thy son, thy firstborn Esau.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.33'>Then Isaac trembled very exceedingly and said, Who [is] he that has taken venison and brought [it to] me, and I have eaten of all before thou camest? I have blessed him and he shall be blessed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.34'>And when Esau heard the words of his father, he cried with a great and exceeding bitter cry and said unto his father, Bless me, [even] me also, O my father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.35'>And he said, Thy brother came with deceit and has taken away thy blessing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.36'>And he said, Is he not rightly named Jacob? For he has supplanted me these two times; he took away my birthright, and, behold, now he has taken away my blessing. And he said, Hast thou not reserved a blessing for me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.37'>And Isaac answered and said unto Esau, Behold, I have made him thy lord, and all his brethren I have given to him for servants, and with wheat and new wine I have sustained him. What shall I do now unto thee, my son?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.38'>And Esau said unto his father, Hast thou but one blessing, my father? Bless me, [even] me also, O my father. And Esau lifted up his voice and wept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.39'>Then Isaac his father answered and said unto him, Behold, thy dwelling shall be the fatness of the earth and of the dew of the heavens from above,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.40'>and by thy sword shalt thou live and shalt serve thy brother; yet there shall be a time when thou shalt have dominion, and thou shalt break his yoke from off thy neck.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.41'>And Esau hated Jacob because of the blessing with which his father blessed him, and Esau said in his heart, The days of mourning for my father are at hand; then I will slay my brother Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.42'>And these words of Esau, her elder son, were told to Rebekah; and she sent and called Jacob her younger son and said unto him, Behold, thy brother Esau, as concerning thee, does comfort himself, [purposing] to kill thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.43'>Now therefore, my son, hear my voice and arise; flee unto Laban, my brother, to Haran</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.44'>and dwell with him a few days until thy brother's fury turns away,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.45'>until thy brother's anger turns away from thee, and he forgets [that] which thou hast done to him; then I will send, and bring thee from there; for why should I be deprived of you both in one day?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.27.46'>And Rebekah said to Isaac, I am weary of my life because of the daughters of Heth. If Jacob takes a wife of the daughters of Heth, such as these [who are] of the daughters of this land, why should I want to live?:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.28'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.1'>Then Isaac called Jacob and blessed him and charged him, saying, Thou shalt not take a wife of the daughters of Canaan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.2'>Arise, go to Padanaram to the house of Bethuel, thy mother's father, and take thee a wife from there of the daughters of Laban, thy mother's brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.3'>And [may] God Almighty bless thee and make thee fruitful and multiply thee that thou may be a congregation of peoples</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.4'>and give thee the blessing of Abraham, to thee and to thy seed with thee; that thou may inherit the land in which thou art a stranger, which God gave unto Abraham.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.5'>Thus Isaac sent Jacob away, and he went to Padanaram unto Laban, son of Bethuel the Aramean, the brother of Rebekah, Jacob's and Esau's mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.6'>And Esau saw how Isaac had blessed Jacob and sent him away to Padanaram, to take a wife from there for himself, and that as he blessed him, he gave him a charge, saying, Thou shalt not take a wife of the daughters of Canaan,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.7'>and that Jacob had hearkened unto his father and his mother and had gone to Padanaram;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.8'>and Esau, seeing that the daughters of Canaan did not please Isaac his father,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.9'>Esau went unto Ishmael and took unto the wives which he had, Mahalath, the daughter of Ishmael, Abraham's son, the sister of Nebajoth, to be his wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.10'>And Jacob went out from Beersheba and went toward Haran.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.11'>And he found a certain place and slept there all night because the sun was set; and he took of the stones of that place and put [them for] his pillows and lay down in that place to sleep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.12'>And he dreamed, and behold a ladder set up on the earth, and the top of it reached to heaven; and behold the angels of God ascending and descending on it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.13'>And, behold, the LORD stood above it and said, I AM the God of Abraham, thy father, and the God of Isaac; the land upon which thou dost lie, to thee will I give it and to thy seed;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.14'>and thy seed shall be as the dust of the earth, and thou shalt multiply to the west and to the east and to the Aquilon and to the Negev; and in thee and in thy seed shall all the families of the earth be blessed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.15'>And, behold, I [am] with thee and will keep thee in all [places] where thou goest and will bring thee again into this land; for I will not leave thee until I have done [that] which I have spoken to thee of.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.16'>And Jacob awakened out of his sleep, and he said, Surely the LORD is in this place, and I knew [it] not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.17'>And he was afraid and said, How dreadful [is] this place! this [is] none other but the house of God, and this [is] the gate of heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.18'>And Jacob rose up early in the morning and took the stone that he had put [for] his pillows and set it up [for] a pillar and poured oil upon the top of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.19'>And he called the name of that place Bethel, since the name of that city [was called] Luz at first.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.20'>And Jacob vowed a vow, saying, If God will be with me and will keep me in this way that I go and will give me bread to eat and clothing to put on</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.21'>so that I come again to my father's house in peace, then shall the LORD be my God;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.28.22'>and this stone, which I have set [for] a pillar, shall be God's house; and of all that thou shalt give me I will surely give the tenth [part] unto thee.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.29'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.1'>Then Jacob walked [on] and came into the land of the people of the east.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.2'>And he looked and saw a well in the field, and, behold, there [were] three flocks of sheep lying by it, for out of that well they watered the flocks, and a great stone [was] upon the well's mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.3'>And all the flocks gathered there; and they would roll the stone from the well's mouth and water the sheep and put the stone again upon the well's mouth in its place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.4'>And Jacob said unto them, My brethren, where are you from? And they said, We [are] from Haran.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.5'>And he said unto them, Do you know Laban the son of Nahor? And they said, We know [him].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.6'>And he said unto them, [Is] he well? And they said, [He is] well, and, behold, Rachel, his daughter, comes with the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.7'>And he said, behold, [it is] yet high day; neither [is it] time that the livestock should be gathered together; water the sheep and go [and] feed [them].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.8'>And they said, We cannot until all the flocks are gathered together and [until] they roll the stone from the well's mouth, that we may water the sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.9'>And while he yet spoke with them, Rachel came with her father's sheep, for she was the pastor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.10'>And it came to pass when Jacob saw Rachel, the daughter of Laban, his mother's brother, and the sheep of Laban, his mother's brother, that Jacob went near and rolled the stone from the well's mouth and watered the flock of Laban, his mother's brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.11'>And Jacob kissed Rachel and lifted up his voice and wept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.12'>And Jacob told Rachel that he [was of] her father's brethren, and that he [was] Rebekah's son, and she ran and told her father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.13'>And it came to pass when Laban heard the tidings of Jacob his sister's son that he ran to meet him and embraced him and kissed him and brought him to his house. And he told Laban all these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.14'>And Laban said to him, Surely thou [art] my bone and my flesh. And he abode with him the space of a month.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.15'>And Laban said unto Jacob, Because thou [art of] my brethren, should thou therefore serve me for nothing? Tell me, what [shall] thy wages [be]?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.16'>And Laban had two daughters: the name of the elder [was] Leah, and the name of the younger [was] Rachel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.17'>Leah [was] tender eyed; but Rachel was beautiful and well favoured.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.18'>And Jacob loved Rachel and said, I will serve thee seven years for Rachel, thy younger daughter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.19'>And Laban said, [It is] better that I give her to thee than that I should give her to another man; abide with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.20'>And Jacob served seven years for Rachel, and they seemed unto him [but] a few days, for the love he had to her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.21'>And Jacob said unto Laban, Give [me] my wife, for my days are fulfilled that I may go in unto her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.22'>So Laban gathered together all the men of the place and made a banquet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.23'>And it came to pass in the evening that he took Leah, his daughter, and brought her to him, and he went in unto her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.24'>And Laban gave unto his daughter Leah Zilpah, his maid, [for] a handmaid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.25'>And it came to pass that in the morning, behold, it [was] Leah; and he said to Laban, What [is] this thou hast done unto me? Did not I serve with thee for Rachel? Why then hast thou beguiled me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.26'>And Laban said, It must not be so done in our country to give the younger before the firstborn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.27'>Fulfil her week, and we will give thee the other also for another seven years of service which thou shalt serve with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.28'>And Jacob did so and fulfilled her week; and he gave him Rachel his daughter to wife also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.29'>And Laban gave to Rachel his daughter Bilhah, his handmaid, to be her maid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.30'>And he went in also unto Rachel, and he loved also Rachel more than Leah and served with him yet another seven years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.31'>And when the LORD saw that Leah [was] hated, he opened her womb; but Rachel [was] barren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.32'>And Leah conceived and gave birth to a son, and she called his name Reuben; for she said, Surely the LORD has looked upon my affliction; now therefore my husband will love me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.33'>And she conceived again and gave birth to a son; and said, Because the LORD has heard that I [was] hated, he has therefore given me this [son] also; and she called his name Simeon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.34'>And she conceived again and gave birth to a son; and said, Now this time will my husband be joined unto me because I have born him three sons; therefore his name was called Levi.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.29.35'>And she conceived again and gave birth a son; and she said, Now I will praise the LORD; therefore she called his name Judah and stopped bearing [children].:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.30'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.1'>And when Rachel saw that she gave Jacob no children, Rachel envied her sister and said unto Jacob, Give me sons, or else I [will] die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.2'>And Jacob's anger was kindled against Rachel; and he said, [Am] I in God's stead, who has withheld from thee the fruit of the womb?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.3'>And she said, Behold my maid Bilhah, go in unto her; and she shall bear upon my knees, that I may also have children by her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.4'>And she gave him Bilhah her handmaid to wife; and Jacob went in unto her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.5'>And Bilhah conceived and gave birth to a son unto Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.6'>And Rachel said, God has judged me, and has also heard my voice, and has given me a son. Therefore she called his name Dan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.7'>And Bilhah Rachel's maid conceived again and gave birth to a second son unto Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.8'>And Rachel said, With great wrestlings I have wrestled with my sister, and I have prevailed; and she called his name Naphtali.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.9'>When Leah saw that she had stopped bearing [children], she took Zilpah, her maid and gave her Jacob to wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.10'>And Zilpah, Leah's maid, gave birth to a son unto Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.11'>And Leah said, [Good] venture has come; and she called his name Gad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.12'>And Zilpah, Leah's maid, gave birth to a second son unto Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.13'>And Leah said, Blessed am I, for the daughters will call me blessed; and she called his name Asher.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.14'>And Reuben went in the days of wheat harvest and found mandrakes in the field and brought them unto his mother Leah. Then Rachel said to Leah, Give me, I pray thee, of thy son's mandrakes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.15'>And she said unto her, [Is it] a small matter that thou hast taken my husband and would thou take away my son's mandrakes also? And Rachel said, Therefore he shall lie with thee to night for thy son's mandrakes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.16'>And Jacob came out of the field in the evening, and Leah went out to meet him and said, Thou must come in unto me; for surely I have hired thee with my son's mandrakes. And he lay with her that night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.17'>And God hearkened unto Leah, and she conceived and gave birth to a fifth son unto Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.18'>And Leah said, God has given me my hire, because I have given my maiden to my husband; and she called his name Issachar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.19'>And Leah conceived again and gave birth to the sixth son unto Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.20'>And Leah said, God has endued me [with] a good dowry; now my husband will dwell with me because I have born him six sons; and she called his name Zebulun.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.21'>And afterwards she gave birth to a daughter and called her name Dinah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.22'>And God remembered Rachel and God hearkened to her and opened her womb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.23'>And she conceived and gave birth to a son and said, God has taken away my reproach;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.24'>and she called his name Joseph, saying, Let the LORD add unto me another son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.25'>And it came to pass when Rachel had given birth to Joseph, that Jacob said unto Laban, Send me away, and I shall go unto my place and to my land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.26'>Give [me] my wives and my children, for whom I have served thee, and let me go, for thou knowest my service which I have done thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.27'>And Laban said unto him, Let me now find grace in thine eyes, I have learned by experience that the LORD has blessed me for thy sake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.28'>And he said, Appoint me thy wages, and I will give [it].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.29'>And he said unto him, Thou knowest how I have served thee and how many livestock thou hast with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.30'>For [it was] little which thou hadst before I [came], and it is [now] increased unto a multitude, and the LORD has blessed thee since my coming; and now when shall I provide for my own house also?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.31'>And he said, What shall I give thee? And Jacob said, Thou shalt not give me anything; if thou wilt do this thing for me, I will again feed [and] keep thy flock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.32'>I will pass through all thy flock today, setting apart all the speckled and spotted sheep, and all the brown rams among the rams, and the spotted and speckled among the goats; and [of such] shall be my hire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.33'>So shall my righteousness answer for me tomorrow, when my hire shall come before thy face; each one that [is] not speckled and spotted among [my] goats and brown among [my] sheep shall be counted stolen with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.34'>And Laban said, Behold, I would it might be according to thy word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.35'>And he removed that day the he goats that were ringstraked and spotted and all the she goats that were speckled and spotted [and] every one that had [some] white in it, and all the brown among the sheep and gave [them] into the hand of his sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.36'>And he set three days' journey between himself and Jacob, and Jacob fed the rest of Laban's flocks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.37'>And Jacob took rods of green poplar and of the almond and chestnut tree and peeled white strakes in them and made the white appear which [was] in the rods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.38'>And he set the rods which he had peeled before the flocks in the gutters in the watering troughs when the flocks came to drink that they should conceive when they came to drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.39'>And the flocks conceived before the rods and brought forth ringstraked, speckled, and spotted sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.40'>And Jacob separated the lambs, and put with his flock the ringstraked and all the brown in the flock of Laban; and he put his own flocks by themselves and did not put them together with Laban's sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.41'>And it came to pass, whenever the stronger sheep conceived, that Jacob laid the rods before the eyes of the sheep in the gutters that they might conceive among the rods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.42'>But when the sheep were feeble, he did not put [them] in; so the feebler were Laban's, and the stronger Jacob's.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.30.43'>And the man increased exceedingly, and had many sheep, and maidservants, and menservants, and camels, and asses.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.31'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.1'>And he heard the words of the sons of Laban, saying, Jacob has taken away all that [was] our father's; and of [that] which [was] our father's, he has gotten all this glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.2'>And Jacob beheld the countenance of Laban, and, behold, it [was] not toward him as before.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.3'>Also the LORD said unto Jacob, Return unto the land of thy fathers and to thy kindred; and I will be with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.4'>And Jacob sent and called Rachel and Leah to the field unto his sheep</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.5'>and said unto them, I see your father's countenance, that it [is] not toward me as before; but the God of my father has been with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.6'>And ye know that with all my strength I have served your father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.7'>And your father has deceived me and changed my wages ten times, but God did not allow him to hurt me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.8'>If he said thus, The speckled shall be thy wages; then all the sheep bore speckled; and if he said thus, The ringstraked shall be thy hire; then all the sheep bore ringstraked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.9'>Thus God has taken away the livestock of your father and given [them] to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.10'>And it came to pass at the time that the sheep conceived, that I lifted up my eyes and saw in dreams, and, behold, the rams which leaped upon the females [were] ringstraked, speckled, and grisled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.11'>And the angel of God spoke unto me in dreams, [saying], Jacob: And I said, Here [am] I.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.12'>And he said, Lift up now thine eyes and see, all the rams which leap upon the sheep [are] ringstraked, speckled, and grisled; for I have seen all that Laban has done unto thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.13'>I [am] the God of Bethel, where thou didst anoint the pillar [and] where thou didst vow a vow unto me. Now arise, go out out from this land and return unto the land of thy nature.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.14'>And Rachel and Leah answered and said unto him, [Is there] yet any portion or inheritance for us in our father's house?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.15'>Are we not counted of him strangers? For he has sold us and has even devoured all our price.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.16'>For all the riches which God has taken from our father, is ours and our son's; now then, whatever God has said unto thee, do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.17'>Then Jacob rose up and set his sons and his wives upon the camels;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.18'>and he carried away all his livestock and all his goods which he had gotten, the livestock of his getting, which he had gotten in Padanaram, to return unto Isaac his father in the land of Canaan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.19'>And Laban had gone to shear his sheep; and Rachel stole the idols of her father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.20'>And Jacob stole away the heart of Laban the Aramean, in that he did not tell him that he fled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.21'>So he fled with all that he had; and he rose up and passed the river and set his face [toward] mount Gilead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.22'>And it was told Laban on the third day that Jacob had fled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.23'>Then he took his brethren with him and pursued after him seven days' journey; and they overtook him in mount Gilead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.24'>And God came to Laban the Aramean in dreams by night, and said unto him, Take heed that thou speak not to Jacob either good or bad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.25'>Then Laban overtook Jacob. Now Jacob had pitched his tent in the mount; and Laban with his brethren pitched in mount Gilead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.26'>And Laban said to Jacob, What hast thou done, that thou hast stolen away my heart and carried away my daughters as captives [taken] with the sword?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.27'>Why didst thou flee away secretly and steal away from me and didst not tell me that I might have sent thee away with mirth and with songs with tambourine and with harp?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.28'>And hast not suffered me to kiss my sons and my daughters? Thou hast now done foolishly in [so] doing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.29'>It is in the power of my hand to do you hurt, but the God of your father spoke unto me last night, saying, Take thou heed that thou speak not to Jacob either good or bad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.30'>And now, [that] thou art leaving, because thy desire is after thy father's house, [yet] why hast thou stolen my gods?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.31'>And Jacob answered and said to Laban, Because I was afraid; for I said, Peradventure thou would take by force thy daughters from me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.32'>With whomsoever thou findest thy gods, let them not live; before our brethren discern what [is] thine with me and take [it] to thee. For Jacob did not know that Rachel had stolen them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.33'>And Laban went into Jacob's tent and into Leah's tent, and into the two maidservants' tents, but he did not find [them]. Then he went out of Leah's tent and came to Rachel's tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.34'>Now Rachel took the images and put them in a camel's saddle and sat upon them. And Laban searched all the tent but did not find [them].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.35'>And she said to her father, Let it not displease my lord that I cannot rise up before thee; for the custom of women [is] upon me. And he searched, but did not find the images.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.36'>Then Jacob was wroth and contended with Laban, and Jacob answered and said to Laban, What [is] my trespass? What [is] my sin that thou hast so hotly pursued after me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.37'>Whereas thou hast searched all my stuff, what hast thou found of all thy household stuff? Set [it] here before my brethren and thy brethren that they may judge between us both.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.38'>These twenty years I have been with thee; thy ewes and thy she goats have not aborted their young, and I have not eaten the rams of thy flock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.39'>That which was torn [of beasts] I did not bring unto thee; I bore the sin; thou didst require of my hand that which was stolen, [whether] by day or by night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.40'>By day the drought consumed me, and by night, the frost; and my sleep departed from mine eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.41'>Thus have I been twenty years in thy house; I served thee fourteen years for thy two daughters and six years for thy flock; and thou hast changed my wages ten times.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.42'>If the God of my father, the God of Abraham, and the fear of Isaac, were not with me, surely thou would send me away now empty. God has seen my affliction and the work of my hands and rebuked [thee] last night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.43'>And Laban answered and said unto Jacob, [These] daughters [are] my daughters, and [these] sons [are] my sons, and [these] sheep [are] my sheep, and all that thou seest [is] mine; and what can I do this day unto these my daughters, or unto their sons unto whom they have given birth?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.44'>Now therefore come thou, let us make a covenant, I and thou, and let it be for a witness between me and thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.45'>Then Jacob took a stone and set it up [for] a pillar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.46'>And Jacob said unto his brethren, Gather stones; and they took stones and made a heap; and they ate there upon the heap.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.47'>And Laban called it Jegarsahadutha, but Jacob called it Galeed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.48'>And Laban said, This heap [is] a witness between me and thee this day. Therefore was the name of it called Galeed;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.49'>and Mizpah; for he said, The LORD watch between me and thee when we are absent one from another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.50'>If thou shalt afflict my daughters, or if thou shalt take [other] wives beside my daughters, no man [is] with us; see, God [is] witness between me and thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.51'>And Laban said to Jacob, Behold this heap, and behold [this] pillar, which I have raised up between me and thee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.52'>[let] this heap [be] witness and [this] pillar [be] witness that I will not pass over this heap against thee and that thou shalt not pass over this heap and this pillar against me, for harm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.53'>The God of Abraham and the God of Nahor, the God of their fathers, judge between us. And Jacob swore by the fear of his father Isaac.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.54'>Then Jacob offered sacrifice upon the mount and called his brethren to eat bread; and they ate bread and slept in the mount.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.31.55'>And early in the morning Laban rose up and kissed his sons and his daughters and blessed them; and Laban departed and returned unto his place.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.32'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.1'>And Jacob went on his way, and the angels of God met him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.2'>And when Jacob saw them, he said, This [is] God's host; and he called the name of that place Mahanaim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.3'>And Jacob sent messengers before him to Esau his brother unto the land of Seir, the country of Edom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.4'>And he commanded them, saying, Thus shall ye speak unto my lord Esau: Thy servant Jacob saith thus, I have sojourned with Laban and stayed there until now;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.5'>and I have oxen and asses, flocks, and menservants, and womenservants; and I have sent to tell my lord, that I may find grace in thy sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.6'>And the messengers returned to Jacob, saying, We came to thy brother Esau, and also he comes to meet thee, and four hundred men with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.7'>Then Jacob was greatly afraid and distressed, and he divided the people that [were] with him, and the sheep and the cows and the camels, into two bands</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.8'>and said, If Esau comes to the one company and smites it, then the other company which is left shall escape.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.9'>And Jacob said, O God of my father Abraham and God of my father Isaac, the LORD who said unto me, Return unto thy country and to thy kindred, and I will deal well with thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.10'>I am not worthy of the least of all the mercies and of all the truth which thou hast showed unto thy servant; for with my staff I passed over this Jordan and now I am become two bands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.11'>Deliver me, I pray thee, from the hand of my brother, from the hand of Esau, for I fear him lest he come and smite me [and] the mother with the children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.12'>And thou hast said, I will surely do thee good and make thy seed as the sand of the sea, which cannot be numbered for multitude.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.13'>And he lodged there that same night and took of that which came to his hand [as] a present for Esau his brother:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.14'>two hundred she goats and twenty he goats, two hundred sheep and twenty rams,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.15'>thirty milk camels with their colts, forty cows and ten bulls, twenty she asses, and ten foals.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.16'>And he delivered [them] into the hand of his servants, every drove by themselves and said unto his servants, Pass before me and put a space between drove and drove.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.17'>And he commanded the foremost, saying, When Esau, my brother, meets thee and asks thee, saying, Whose [art] thou? And where goest thou? And for whom [are] these before thee?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.18'>Then thou shalt say, [They are] thy servant Jacob's; it [is] a present sent unto my lord Esau; and, behold, also he [is] behind us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.19'>And so commanded he the second and the third and all that followed those droves, saying, On this manner shall ye speak unto Esau when ye find him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.20'>And ye shall also say, Behold, thy servant Jacob [is] behind us. For he said, I will reconcile his wrath with the present that goes before me, and afterward I will see his face; peradventure he will accept me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.21'>So the present went over before him, and he lodged that night in the company.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.22'>And he rose up that night and took his two wives and his two womenservants and his eleven sons and passed over the ford Jabbok.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.23'>And he took them and sent them over the brook and sent over [all] that he had.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.24'>And Jacob was left alone, and a man wrestled with him until the breaking of the day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.25'>And when [the man] saw that he did not prevail against him, he touched the hollow of his thigh; and the hollow of Jacob's thigh was disjointed as he wrestled with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.26'>And he said, Let me go, for the day breaks. And he said, I will not let thee go except thou bless me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.27'>And he said unto him, What [is] thy name? And he said, Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.28'>And he said, Thy name shall no longer be called Jacob, but Israel; for thou hast fought with God and with men, and hast prevailed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.29'>And Jacob asked [him] and said, Tell [me], I pray thee, thy name. And he said, Why dost thou ask after my name? And he blessed him there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.30'>And Jacob called the name of the place Peniel; for I have seen God face to face, and my soul was saved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.31'>And as he passed over Penuel, the sun rose upon him, and he limped upon his thigh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.32.32'>Therefore the sons of Israel do not eat [of] the sinew which shrank, which [is] upon the hollow of the thigh, unto this day, because he touched the hollow of Jacob's thigh in the sinew that shrank.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.33'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.1'>And Jacob lifted up his eyes, and saw, and, behold, Esau came and with him four hundred men. And he divided the children unto Leah and unto Rachel and unto the two handmaids.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.2'>And he put the handmaids and their children in front, and Leah and her children next, and Rachel and Joseph last.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.3'>And he passed over in front of them and bowed himself to the ground seven times until he came near to his brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.4'>And Esau ran to meet him and embraced him and fell on his neck and kissed him, and they wept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.5'>And he lifted up his eyes and saw the women and the children and said, Who [are] those with thee? And he said, The children whom God hath graciously given thy servant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.6'>Then the handmaidens came near, they and their children, and they bowed themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.7'>And Leah also with her children came near and bowed themselves; and after came Joseph near and Rachel, and they also bowed themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.8'>And he said, What [meanest] thou by all these droves which I met? And he said, To find grace in the sight of my lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.9'>And Esau said, I have enough, my brother; keep what thou hast unto thyself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.10'>And Jacob said, No, I pray thee, if now I have found grace in thy sight, then receive my present from my hand, that for this I have seen thy face as though I had seen the face of God; and do me the pleasure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.11'>Take, I pray thee, my blessing that is brought to thee because God has dealt graciously with me, and all [that is here] is mine. And he urged him, and he took [it].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.12'>And he said, Let us take our journey, and let us go, and I will go before thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.13'>And he said unto him, My lord knows that the children [are] tender, and the sheep and cows with young [are] with me; and if men should overdrive them, in one day all the sheep will die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.14'>Let my lord, I pray thee, pass before his servant; and I will lead on softly, according as the property that goes before me and the children are able to endure until I come unto my lord unto Seir.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.15'>And Esau said, Let me now leave with thee [some] of the folk that [are] with me. And he said, What for? Let me find grace in the sight of my lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.16'>So Esau returned that day on his way unto Seir.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.17'>And Jacob journeyed to Succoth and built himself a house and made booths for his livestock; therefore the name of the place is called Succoth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.18'>And Jacob came safe and sound to the city of Shechem, which [is] in the land of Canaan, when he came from Padanaram, and pitched his tent before the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.19'>And he bought part of the field where he had spread his tent, from the hand of the sons of Hamor, Shechem's father, for one hundred ewes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.33.20'>And there he erected an altar, and called it Elelohe-Israel ([the Strong God of Israel]).:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.34'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.1'>And Dinah, the daughter of Leah, which she gave birth unto Jacob, went out to see the daughters of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.2'>And when Shechem, the son of Hamor the Hivite, prince of the country, saw her, he took her and lay with her and defiled her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.3'>And his soul was joined unto Dinah, the daughter of Jacob, and he fell in love with the damsel and spoke unto her heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.4'>And Shechem spoke unto his father Hamor, saying, Get me this damsel to wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.5'>And Jacob heard that he had defiled Dinah, his daughter; now his sons were with his cattle in the field, and Jacob remained silent until they were come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.6'>And Hamor, the father of Shechem, went out unto Jacob to speak with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.7'>And the sons of Jacob came out of the field when they heard [it]; and the men were grieved, and they were very wroth because he had wrought folly in Israel in lying with Jacob's daughter, [a] thing which ought not to be done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.8'>And Hamor spoke with them, saying, The soul of my son Shechem is joined to your daughter; I pray you give her to him as wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.9'>And make ye marriages with us [and] give your daughters unto us and take our daughters unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.10'>And ye shall dwell with us, and the land shall be before you; dwell and trade ye therein and take you possessions therein.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.11'>And Shechem also said unto her father and unto her brethren, Let me find grace in your eyes, and what ye shall say unto me I will give.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.12'>Ask me for as much dowry and gift as ye [desire], and I will give according as ye shall say unto me; but give me the damsel to wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.13'>And the sons of Jacob answered Shechem and Hamor his father deceitfully and talked because he had defiled Dinah their sister:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.14'>And they said unto them, We cannot do this thing, to give our sister to one that is uncircumcised, for among us that [is] a reproach.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.15'>But with this condition we will consent unto you: If ye will become as we [are] that every male of you be circumcised,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.16'>then we will give our daughters unto you, and we will take your daughters to us, and we will dwell with you, and we will become one people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.17'>But if ye will not hearken unto us, to be circumcised, then we will take our daughter, and we will be gone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.18'>And their words pleased Hamor and Shechem, Hamor's son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.19'>And the young man deferred not to do the thing, because he had delight in Jacob's daughter and he [was] the most honourable of all the house of his father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.20'>Then Hamor and Shechem, his son, came unto the gate of their city and communed with the men of their city, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.21'>These men [are] peaceable with us; therefore let them dwell in the land and trade therein; for the land, behold, [it] is large enough for them; let us take their daughters to us for wives, and let us give them our daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.22'>Only with this condition will these men consent to dwell with us that we may be one people: if every male among us be circumcised as they [are] circumcised.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.23'>[Shall] not their livestock and their substance and every beast of theirs [be] ours? Only let us consent unto them, and they will dwell with us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.24'>And unto Hamor and unto Shechem, his son, hearkened all that went out of the gate of his city; and every male was circumcised, all that went out of the gate of his city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.25'>And it came to pass on the third day, when they were sore that two of the sons of Jacob, Simeon and Levi, Dinah's brethren, took each man his sword and came upon the city boldly and slew all the males.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.26'>And they slew Hamor and Shechem, his son, with the edge of the sword and took Dinah out of Shechem's house, and went out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.27'>The sons of Jacob came upon the slain and spoiled the city because they had defiled their sister.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.28'>They took their sheep and their oxen and their asses and that which [was] in the city and that which [was] in the field</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.29'>and all their wealth and all their little ones and their wives they took captive and spoiled even all that [was] in the house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.30'>And Jacob said to Simeon and Levi, Ye have troubled me to make me to stink among the inhabitants of the land, among the Canaanites and the Perizzites; and I [being] few in number, they shall gather themselves together against me and slay me; and I shall be destroyed, I and my house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.34.31'>And they said, Should he deal with our sister as with a harlot?:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.35'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.1'>And God said unto Jacob, Arise, go up to Bethel and dwell there and make there an altar unto God, who appeared unto thee when thou didst flee from the face of Esau, thy brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.2'>Then Jacob said unto his household and to all that [were] with him, Put away the strange gods that [are] among you and be clean and change your garments:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.3'>And let us arise and go up to Bethel and I will make there an altar unto God, who answered me in the day of my distress, and has been with me in the way which I have gone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.4'>So they gave unto Jacob all the strange gods which [were] in their power and [all their] earrings which [were] in their ears, and Jacob hid them under the oak which [was] by Shechem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.5'>And they journeyed, and the terror of God was upon the cities that [were] round about them, and they did not pursue after the sons of Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.6'>And Jacob came to Luz, which [is] in the land of Canaan, that [is], Bethel, he and all the people that [were] with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.7'>And there he built an altar and called the place Elbethel because there God had appeared unto him when he fled from the face of his brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.8'>Then Deborah, Rebekah's nurse, died, and she was buried beneath Bethel under an oak, and the name of it was called Allonbachuth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.9'>And God appeared unto Jacob again when he came out of Padanaram and blessed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.10'>And God said unto him, Thy name [is] Jacob; thy name shall not be called any more Jacob, but Israel shall be thy name, and he called his name Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.11'>And God said unto him, I [am] God Almighty; be fruitful and multiply, a nation and a company of nations ([Gentiles]) shall come out of thee, and kings shall come out of thy loins;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.12'>and the land which I have given to Abraham and to Isaac, to thee will I give it and to thy seed after thee will I give the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.13'>And God went up from him in the place where he talked with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.14'>And Jacob set up a pillar in the place where he talked with him, [even] a pillar of stone; and he poured a drink offering upon it, and he poured oil upon it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.15'>And Jacob called the name of the place where God spoke with him, Bethel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.16'>And they journeyed from Bethel, and there was but a little way to come to Ephrath when Rachel travailed, and she had hard labour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.17'>And it came to pass when she was in hard labour, that the midwife said unto her, Fear not; thou shalt have this son also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.18'>And it came to pass as her soul was departing, (for she died) that she called his name Benoni, but his father called him Benjamin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.19'>Thus Rachel died and was buried in the way to Ephrath, which [is] Bethlehem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.20'>And Jacob set a pillar upon her grave; that [is] the pillar of Rachel's grave unto this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.21'>And Israel journeyed and spread his tent beyond the tower of Edar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.22'>And it came to pass when Israel dwelt in that land, that Reuben went and lay with Bilhah, his father's concubine, and Israel heard [of it]. Now the sons of Jacob were twelve:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.23'>The sons of Leah: Reuben, Jacob's firstborn, Simeon, Levi, Judah, Issachar, and Zebulun.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.24'>The sons of Rachel: Joseph and Benjamin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.25'>And the sons of Bilhah, Rachel's handmaid: Dan and Naphtali.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.26'>And the sons of Zilpah, Leah's handmaid: Gad and Asher. These [are] the sons of Jacob, who were born to him in Padanaram.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.27'>And Jacob came unto Isaac, his father, unto Mamre, unto the city of Arbah, which [is] Hebron, where Abraham and Isaac sojourned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.28'>And the days of Isaac were one hundred and eighty years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.35.29'>And Isaac expired and died and was gathered unto his people, [being] old and full of days, and his sons Esau and Jacob buried him.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.36'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.1'>Now these [are] the generations of Esau, who [is] Edom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.2'>Esau took his wives of the daughters of Canaan: Adah the daughter of Elon, the Hittite; Aholibamah, the daughter of Anah, the daughter of Zibeon, the Hivite;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.3'>and Bashemath, Ishmael's daughter, sister of Nebajoth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.4'>And Adah bore to Esau Eliphaz, and Bashemath bore Reuel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.5'>and Aholibamah bore Jeush and Jaalam and Korah: these [are] the sons of Esau, who were born unto him in the land of Canaan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.6'>And Esau took his wives and his sons and his daughters and all the persons of his house and his cattle and all his beasts and all his substance, which he had got in the land of Canaan, and went into [another] country from the face of his brother Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.7'>For their riches were more than that they might dwell together, and the land in which they were strangers could not bear them because of their livestock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.8'>Thus dwelt Esau in mount Seir; Esau [is] Edom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.9'>And these [are] the lineages of Esau, the father of the Edomites in mount Seir.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.10'>These [are] the names of Esau's sons: Eliphaz, the son of Adah, the wife of Esau; Reuel, the son of Bashemath, the wife of Esau.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.11'>And the sons of Eliphaz were Teman, Omar, Zepho, Gatam, and Kenaz.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.12'>And Timna was concubine to Eliphaz, Esau's son, and she bore to Eliphaz Amalek: these [are] the sons of Adah, Esau's wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.13'>And these [are] the sons of Reuel: Nahath, Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah; these were the sons of Bashemath, Esau's wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.14'>And these were the sons of Aholibamah, the daughter of Anah, the daughter of Zibeon, Esau's wife: she gave birth unto Esau Jeush, Jaalam, and Korah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.15'>These [are] dukes of the sons of Esau. The sons of Eliphaz, the firstborn [son] of Esau: duke Teman, duke Omar, duke Zepho, duke Kenaz,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.16'>duke Korah, duke Gatam, [and] duke Amalek: these [are] the dukes [that came] of Eliphaz in the land of Edom; these [are] the sons of Adah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.17'>And these [are] the sons of Reuel, Esau's son; duke Nahath, duke Zerah, duke Shammah, duke Mizzah: these [are] the dukes [that came] of Reuel in the land of Edom; these [are] the sons of Bashemath Esau's wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.18'>And these [are] the sons of Aholibamah, Esau's wife: duke Jeush, duke Jaalam, duke Korah; these [were] the dukes [that came] of Aholibamah the daughter of Anah, Esau's wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.19'>These [are] the sons of Esau, who [is] Edom, and these [are] their dukes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.20'>These [are] the sons of Seir, the Horite, who inhabited the land: Lotan, Shobal, Zibeon, Anah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.21'>Dishon, Ezer, and Dishan; these [are] the dukes of the Horites, the sons of Seir in the land of Edom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.22'>And the sons of Lotan were Hori and Hemam, and Lotan's sister [was] Timna.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.23'>And the sons of Shobal [were] these: Alvan, Manahath, Ebal, Shepho, and Onam.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.24'>And these [are] the sons of Zibeon: both Ajah and Anah; this [was that] Anah that invented mules in the wilderness as he fed the asses of Zibeon his father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.25'>And the children of Anah [were] these: Dishon and Aholibamah the daughter of Anah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.26'>And these [are] the sons of Dishon: Hemdan, Eshban, Ithran, and Cheran.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.27'>The sons of Ezer [are] these: Bilhan, Zaavan, and Akan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.28'>The sons of Dishan [are] these: Uz and Aran.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.29'>These [are] the dukes [that came] of the Horites: duke Lotan, duke Shobal, duke Zibeon, duke Anah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.30'>duke Dishon, duke Ezer, duke Dishan; these [are] the dukes [that came] of Hori; by their dukedoms in the land of Seir.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.31'>And these [are] the kings that reigned in the land of Edom before any king reigned over the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.32'>And Bela, the son of Beor, reigned in Edom, and the name of his city [was] Dinhabah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.33'>And Bela died, and Jobab, the son of Zerah of Bozrah, reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.34'>And Jobab died, and Husham of the land of Temani reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.35'>And Husham died, and Hadad, the son of Bedad, who smote Midian in the field of Moab, reigned in his stead; and the name of his city [was] Avith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.36'>And Hadad died, and Samlah of Masrekah reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.37'>And Samlah died, and Saul of Rehoboth [by] the river reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.38'>And Saul died, and Baalhanan, the son of Achbor, reigned in his stead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.39'>And Baalhanan, the son of Achbor, died, and Hadar reigned in his stead; and the name of his city [was] Pau; and his wife's name [was] Mehetabel, the daughter of Matred, the daughter of Mezahab.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.40'>And these [are] the names of the dukes [that came of] Esau, according to their families, after their places, by their names: duke Timnah, duke Alvah, duke Jetheth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.41'>duke Aholibamah, duke Elah, duke Pinon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.42'>duke Kenaz, duke Teman, duke Mibzar,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.36.43'>duke Magdiel, duke Iram: these [were] the dukes of Edom, according to their habitations in the land of their possession. This [is] the Esau, the father of Edom.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.37'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.1'>And Jacob dwelt in the land in which his father was a stranger, in the land of Canaan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.2'>These [are] the generations of Jacob. Joseph, [being] seventeen years old, was feeding the flock with his brethren; and the lad [was] with the sons of Bilhah and with the sons of Zilpah, his father's wives; and Joseph brought unto his father their evil report.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.3'>Now Israel loved Joseph more than all his [other] sons because he [was] the son of his old age, and he made him a coat of [many] colours.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.4'>And when his brethren saw that their father loved him more than all his brethren, they hated him and could not speak peaceably unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.5'>And Joseph dreamed a dream, and he told [it] to his brethren; and they hated him yet the more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.6'>And he said unto them, Hear, I pray you, this dream which I have dreamed:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.7'>For, behold, we [were] binding sheaves in the field, and, behold, my sheaf arose and also stood upright; and, behold, your sheaves stood round about and made obeisance to my sheaf.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.8'>And his brethren said to him, Shalt thou indeed reign over us? Or shalt thou indeed have dominion over us? And they hated him yet the more for his dreams and for his words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.9'>And he dreamed yet another dream and told it [to] his brethren, saying, Behold, I have dreamed another dream; and, behold, the sun and the moon and eleven stars made obeisance to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.10'>And he told [it] to his father and to his brethren; and his father reprehended him and said unto him, What [is] this dream that thou hast dreamed? Shall I and thy mother and thy brethren indeed come to bow down ourselves to thee to the earth?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.11'>And his brethren envied him; but his father kept the word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.12'>And his brethren went to feed their father's sheep in Shechem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.13'>And Israel said unto Joseph, Do not thy brethren feed [the sheep] in Shechem? Come and I will send thee unto them. And he said to him, Here [am] I.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.14'>And he said to him, Go, I pray thee, see whether it is well with thy brethren and well with the sheep and bring me word again. So he sent him out of the valley of Hebron, and he came to Shechem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.15'>And a certain man found him, and, behold, [he was] wandering in the field; and the man asked him, saying, What seekest thou?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.16'>And he said, I seek my brethren; tell me, I pray thee, where they feed [their flocks].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.17'>And the man said, They are departed from here; for I heard them say, Let us go to Dothan. And Joseph went after his brethren and found them in Dothan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.18'>And when they saw him afar off, even before he came near unto them, they conspired against him to slay him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.19'>And they said one to another, Behold, this dreamer comes;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.20'>now therefore, come and let us slay him and cast him into a cistern, and we will say, Some evil beast has devoured him; and we shall see what will become of his dreams.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.21'>When Reuben heard [it], he delivered him out of their hands and said, Let us not kill him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.22'>And Reuben said unto them, Shed no blood [but] cast him into this cistern that [is] in the wilderness and lay no hand upon him that he might rid him out of their hands to deliver him to his father again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.23'>And it came to pass, when Joseph was come unto his brethren, that they stripped Joseph out of his coat, [his] coat of [many] colours that [was] on him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.24'>and they took him and cast him into the cistern; and the pit [was] empty, [there was] no water in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.25'>And they sat down to eat bread; and they lifted up their eyes and looked, and, behold, a company of Ishmeelites came from Gilead with their camels bearing aromas and balm and myrrh, going to carry [it] down to Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.26'>Then Judah said unto his brethren, What profit [is it] if we slay our brother and conceal his blood?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.27'>Come and let us sell him to the Ishmeelites and let not our hand be upon him; for he [is] our brother [and] our flesh. And his brethren were content.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.28'>And when the Midianite merchantmen passed by, they took and lifted up Joseph out of the cistern and sold Joseph to the Ishmeelites for twenty [pieces] of silver. And they brought Joseph into Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.29'>And Reuben returned unto the cistern; and, behold, Joseph [was] not inside, and he rent his clothes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.30'>And he returned unto his brethren and said, The young man [is] not; and I, where shall I go?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.31'>Then they took Joseph's coat and killed a kid of the goats and dipped the coat in the blood;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.32'>and they sent the coat of [many] colours, and they brought [it] to their father and said, We have found this, recognize now whether it [is] thy son's coat or not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.33'>And he knew it and said, [It is] my son's coat; an evil beast has devoured him; Joseph is without doubt rent in pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.34'>Then Jacob rent his clothes and put sackcloth upon his loins and mourned for his son many days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.35'>And all his sons and all his daughters rose up to comfort him, but he refused to be comforted, and he said, For I will go down into the grave unto my son mourning. Thus his father wept for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.37.36'>And the Midianites sold him into Egypt unto Potiphar, an officer of Pharaoh's [and] captain of the guard.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.38'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.1'>And it came to pass at that time that Judah went down from his brethren and turned in to a certain Adullamite, whose name [was] Hirah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.2'>And Judah saw there a daughter of a certain Canaanite, whose name [was] Shuah, and he took her and went in unto her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.3'>And she conceived and gave birth to a son, and he called his name Er.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.4'>And she conceived again and gave birth to a son, and she called his name Onan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.5'>And she yet again conceived and gave birth to a son and called his name Shelah. And he was at Chezib, when she gave birth to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.6'>And Judah took a wife for Er his firstborn, whose name [was] Tamar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.7'>And Er, Judah's firstborn, was wicked in the sight of the LORD and the LORD slew him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.8'>Then Judah said unto Onan, Go in unto thy brother's wife and marry her and raise up seed to thy brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.9'>And Onan knew that the seed would not be his, and it came to pass when he went in unto his brother's wife, that he corrupted [it] on the ground, to not give seed to his brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.10'>And the thing which he did displeased the LORD, and he slew him also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.11'>Then Judah said to Tamar, his daughter in law, Remain a widow at thy father's house until Shelah, my son, is grown; for he said, Lest peradventure he die also, as his brethren [did]. And Tamar went and dwelt in her father's house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.12'>And many days passed and Judah's wife, the daughter of Shuah, died; and Judah was comforted and went up unto his sheepshearers to Timnath, he and his friend Hirah, the Adullamite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.13'>And it was told Tamar, saying, Behold, thy father in law goes up to Timnath to shear his sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.14'>And she took off her widow's garments and covered herself with a veil and wrapped herself and sat by the gate to the waters by the way to Timnath, for she saw that Shelah was grown, and she was not given unto him to wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.15'>When Judah saw her, he thought her [to be] a harlot because she had covered her face.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.16'>And he turned unto her by the way and said, Come now, I pray thee, let me come in unto thee (for he knew not that she [was] his daughter-in-law). And she said, What wilt thou give me that thou may come in unto me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.17'>And he said, I will send [thee] from the sheep a kid [from the goats]. And she said, Wilt thou give [me] a pledge until thou send [it]?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.18'>Then he said, What pledge shall I give thee? And she said, Thy signet and thy mantel and thy staff that [is] in thine hand. And he gave them [to] her, and came in unto her, and she conceived by him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.19'>And she arose and went away and took off her veil and put on the garments of her widowhood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.20'>And Judah sent the kid by the hand of his friend, the Adullamite, to receive [his] pledge from the woman's hand; but he did not find her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.21'>Then he asked the men of that place, saying, Where [is] the cult prostitute of the waters by the way side? And they said, There was no cult prostitute in this [place].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.22'>And he returned to Judah and said, I cannot find her; and also the men of the place said [that] there was no cult prostitute in this [place].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.23'>And Judah said, Let her take [the things] for herself lest we be shamed; behold, I sent this kid, and thou hast not found her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.24'>And it came to pass about three months after, that it was told Judah, saying, Tamar, thy daughter-in-law, has played the harlot; and also, behold, she [is] with child by whoredom. And Judah said, Bring her forth and let her be burnt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.25'>When she [was] brought forth, she sent to her father-in-law, saying, By the man whose these [are], [am] I with child; and she said, Discern, I pray thee, whose [are] these, the signet and mantel and staff.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.26'>Then Judah acknowledged [them], and said, She has been more righteous than I because I did not give her to Shelah, my son. And he knew her again no more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.27'>And it came to pass in the time of her travail that, behold, twins [were] in her womb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.28'>And it came to pass when she travailed, that [the one] put out [his] hand, and the midwife took and bound upon his hand a scarlet thread, saying, This came out first.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.29'>And it came to pass as he drew back his hand, that, behold, his brother came out; and she said, Why hast thou brought this breach upon thee? Therefore his name was called Pharez.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.38.30'>And afterward his brother that had the scarlet thread upon his hand came out, and his name was called Zarah.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.39'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.1'>And Joseph was brought down to Egypt; and Potiphar, an officer of Pharaoh, captain of the guard, an Egyptian, bought him from the hands of the Ishmeelites, who had brought him down there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.2'>But the LORD was with Joseph, and he was a prospered man; and he was in the house of his master the Egyptian.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.3'>And his master saw that the LORD [was] with him and that the LORD made all that he did to prosper in his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.4'>So Joseph found grace in his sight, and he served him; and he made him overseer over his house, and all [that] he had he put into his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.5'>And it came to pass from the time [that] he had made him overseer in his house and over all that he had, that the LORD blessed the Egyptian's house for Joseph's sake; and the blessing of the LORD was upon all that he had in the house and in the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.6'>And he left all that he had in Joseph's hand, and with him knew [of] nothing more than of the bread which he ate. And Joseph was handsome and well favoured.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.7'>And it came to pass after these things, that his master's wife cast her eyes upon Joseph; and she said, Lie with me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.8'>But he refused and said unto his master's wife, Behold, my master does not know what [is] with me in the house, and he has committed all that he has to my hand;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.9'>[there is] none greater in this house than I; neither has he kept back anything from me but thee because thou [art] his wife; how then can I do this great wickedness and sin against God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.10'>And it came to pass as she spoke to Joseph day by day, that he did not hearken unto her, to lie by her [or] to be with her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.11'>And it came to pass about this time, that [Joseph] went into the house to do his business, and none of those of the house were there within.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.12'>And she caught him by his garment, saying, Lie with me; and he left his garment in her hand and fled and got outside.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.13'>And it came to pass when she saw that he had left his garment in her hand and had fled forth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.14'>that she called unto those of her house and spoke unto them, saying, See, he has brought in a Hebrew unto us to mock us; he came in unto me to lie with me, and I cried with a loud voice;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.15'>and it came to pass, when he heard that I lifted up my voice and cried, that he left his garment with me and fled and left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.16'>And she laid up his garment by her until his lord came home.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.17'>And she spoke unto him according to these words, saying, The Hebrew servant, whom thou hast brought unto us, came in unto me to dishonour me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.18'>and when I lifted up my voice and cried, he left his garment with me and fled out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.19'>And it came to pass when his master heard the words of his wife, which she spoke unto him, saying, After this manner did thy servant treat me, that his wrath was kindled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.20'>And Joseph's master took him and put him into the prison, a place where the king's prisoners [were] bound; and he was there in the prison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.21'>But the LORD was with Joseph and showed him mercy and gave him grace in the sight of the prince of the house of the prison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.22'>And the prince of the house of the prison committed to Joseph's hand all the prisoners that [were] in the prison; and whatever they did there, he was the doer of [it].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.39.23'>The prince of the prison looked not to anything [that was] under his hand because the LORD was with him, and [that] which he did, the LORD made [it] to prosper.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.40'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.1'>And it came to pass after these things, [that] the butler of the king of Egypt and [his] baker had sinned against their lord, the king of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.2'>And Pharaoh was angry against his two officers, against the chief of the butlers and against the chief of the bakers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.3'>And he put them in prison in the house of the captain of the guard, into the house of the prison where Joseph [was] bound.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.4'>And the captain of the guard charged Joseph with them, and he served them; and they continued for days in prison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.5'>And both of them dreamed a dream, each man his dream in the same night, each man according to the interpretation of his dream, the butler and the baker of the king of Egypt, who [were] bound in the prison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.6'>And Joseph came in unto them in the morning and looked upon them, and, behold, they [were] sad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.7'>And he asked Pharaoh's officers that [were] with him in the prison of his lord's house, saying, Why look ye so sad today?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.8'>And they said unto him, We have dreamed a dream, and [there is] no interpreter of it. And Joseph said unto them, [Do] not interpretations [belong] to God? Tell me [the dreams], I pray you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.9'>Then the chief butler told his dream to Joseph and said to him, In my dream, behold, a vine [was] before me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.10'>and in the vine [were] three branches, and it [was] as though it budded [and] her blossoms shot forth, and the clusters thereof brought forth ripe grapes;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.11'>and Pharaoh's cup [was] in my hand, and I took the grapes and pressed them into Pharaoh's cup, and I gave the cup into Pharaoh's hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.12'>And Joseph said unto him, This [is] the interpretation of it: The three branches [are] three days;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.13'>yet within three days shall Pharaoh lift up thy head and restore thee unto thy place, and thou shalt deliver Pharaoh's cup into his hand after the former manner when thou wast his butler.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.14'>Therefore thou shalt think of me within thyself when it shall be well with thee, and show mercy, I pray thee, unto me, and make mention of me unto Pharaoh and bring me out of this house;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.15'>for indeed I was stolen away out of the land of the Hebrews; neither have I done anything here that they should put me into the prison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.16'>When the chief baker saw that the interpretation was good, he said unto Joseph, I also [was] in my dream, and, behold, [I had] three white baskets on my head;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.17'>and in the uppermost basket [there was] of all manner of baked foods for Pharaoh, and the birds ate them out of the basket upon my head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.18'>Then Joseph answered and said, This [is] the interpretation thereof: The three baskets [are] three days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.19'>Yet within three days shall Pharaoh lift up thy head from off thee and shall hang thee on a tree, and the birds shall eat thy flesh from off thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.20'>And it came to pass the third day, [which was] Pharaoh's birthday, that he made a banquet unto all his servants, and he lifted up the head of the chief butler and of the chief baker among his servants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.21'>And he restored the chief butler unto his butlership again, and he gave the cup into Pharaoh's hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.22'>But he hanged the chief baker; as Joseph had interpreted to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.40.23'>Yet the chief butler did not remember Joseph but forgot him.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.41'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.1'>And it came to pass at the end of two full years, that Pharaoh dreamed: and, behold, he stood by the river.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.2'>And, behold, there came up out of the river seven beautiful cows and very fat, and they fed in a meadow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.3'>And, behold, seven other cows came up after them out of the river, ugly and lean-fleshed, and stood by the [other] cows upon the brink of the river.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.4'>And the ugly and lean-fleshed cows ate up the seven beautiful and fat cows. So Pharaoh awoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.5'>And he slept and dreamed the second time; and, behold, seven heads of wheat came up upon one stalk, full and beautiful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.6'>And, behold, seven thin heads, blasted with the east wind sprung up after them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.7'>And the seven thin heads devoured the seven full and beautiful heads. And Pharaoh awoke, and, behold, [it was] a dream.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.8'>And it came to pass in the morning that his spirit was troubled, and he sent and called for all the magicians of Egypt and all the wise men thereof; and Pharaoh told them his dreams, but [there was] no one that could interpret them unto Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.9'>Then the chief butler spoke unto Pharaoh, saying, I remember my sins today;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.10'>Pharaoh was angry with his servants and put me in the prison of the captain of the guard's house, [both] me and the prince of the bakers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.11'>And we both dreamed a dream in one night; we dreamed each man according to the interpretation of his dream.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.12'>And [there was] there with us a young man, a Hebrew, servant to the captain of the guard; and we told him, and he interpreted our dreams to us; he interpreted to each man according to his dream.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.13'>And it came to pass, as he interpreted to us, so it was; me he restored unto my office, and him he hanged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.14'>Then Pharaoh sent and called Joseph, and they brought him hastily out of the dungeon; and they cut his hair and changed his clothes, and he came in unto Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.15'>And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, I have dreamed a dream, and [there is] no one that can interpret it; but I have heard say of thee [that] thou canst hear dreams to interpret them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.16'>And Joseph answered Pharaoh, saying, [It is] not in me; God shall give Pharaoh an answer of peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.17'>And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, In my dream, behold, I stood upon the bank of the river;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.18'>and, behold, there came up out of the river seven cows, fat-fleshed and beautiful in appearance; and they fed in a meadow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.19'>And, behold, seven other cows came up after them, lean and very ugly in appearance, and thin, such as I have never seen in all the land of Egypt for ugliness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.20'>And the lean and ugly cows ate up the first seven fat cows;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.21'>and when they had eaten them up, it could not be known that they had eaten them; but they [were] still ugly, as at the beginning. So I awoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.22'>And I also saw in my dream, and, behold, seven heads came up in one stalk, full and beautiful;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.23'>and, behold, seven heads, withered, thin, [and] blasted with the east wind, sprung up after them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.24'>And the thin heads devoured the seven good heads; and I told [this] unto the magicians, but [there was] no one that could declare [it] to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.25'>Then Joseph said unto Pharaoh, The dream of Pharaoh is one: God has showed Pharaoh what he [is] about to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.26'>The seven beautiful cows [are] seven years; and the seven good heads [are] seven years; the dream [is] one and the same.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.27'>Also the seven thin and ugly cows that came up after them [are] seven years; and the seven empty heads blasted with the east wind shall be seven years of famine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.28'>This [is] the thing which I have spoken unto Pharaoh. What God [is] about to do he has shown unto Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.29'>Behold, seven years of great plenty are coming throughout all the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.30'>And there shall arise after them seven years of famine; and all the plenty shall be forgotten in the land of Egypt; and the famine shall consume the land;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.31'>and the plenty shall not be known in the land by reason of that famine following; for it [shall be] very grievous.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.32'>And that the dream came unto Pharaoh twice, [it is] because the thing [is] established by God, and God will shortly bring it to pass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.33'>Now therefore let Pharaoh find a discreet and wise man and set him over the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.34'>Let Pharaoh do [this], and let him appoint officers over the land and take up the fifth part of the land of Egypt in the seven plenteous years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.35'>And let them gather all the food of those good years that come and lay up wheat under the hand of Pharaoh to feed the cities, and let them store [it] up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.36'>And let that food be stored for the land against the seven years of famine, which shall be in the land of Egypt; and the land shall not perish through the famine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.37'>And the word was good in the eyes of Pharaoh and in the eyes of all his servants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.38'>And Pharaoh said unto his servants, Can we find [such a one] as this [is], a man in whom the Spirit of God [is]?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.39'>And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, Forasmuch as God has showed thee all this, [there is] none so discreet and wise as thou [art].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.40'>Thou shalt be over my house, and according unto thy word shall all my people be ruled; only in the throne will I be greater than thou.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.41'>And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, See, I have set thee over all the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.42'>Then Pharaoh took off his ring from his hand and put it upon Joseph's hand and arrayed him in vestures of fine linen and put a gold chain about his neck;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.43'>and he made him to ride in his second chariot; and they cried before him, Abrech [Tender Father-honour this one as a precious father]; and he made him [ruler] over all the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.44'>And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, I [am] Pharaoh, and without thee no one shall lift up his hand or foot in all the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.45'>And Pharaoh called Joseph's name Zaphnathpaaneah, and he gave him to wife Asenath the daughter of Potipherah priest of On. And Joseph went out over [all] the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.46'>And Joseph [was] thirty years old when he stood before Pharaoh king of Egypt. And Joseph went out from the presence of Pharaoh and went throughout all the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.47'>And in the seven plenteous years the earth brought forth by handfuls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.48'>And he gathered up all the food of the seven years, which were in the land of Egypt and laid up the food in the cities, placing in each city the food of the field, which [was] round about.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.49'>And Joseph gathered wheat as the sand of the sea, very much, until he left [off] numbering; for [it was] without number.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.50'>And unto Joseph were born two sons before the years of famine came, which Asenath, the daughter of Potipherah, prince of On, bore unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.51'>And Joseph called the name of the firstborn Manasseh; For God, [said he], has made me forget all my toil and all my father's house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.52'>And the name of the second he called Ephraim, For God, [said he], has caused me to be fruitful in the land of my affliction.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.53'>And the seven years of the abundance that was in the land of Egypt were ended.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.54'>And the seven years of famine began to come, according as Joseph had said; and the famine was in all lands, but in all the land of Egypt there was bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.55'>And when all the land of Egypt was famished, the people cried to Pharaoh for bread. And Pharaoh said unto all the Egyptians, Go unto Joseph; what he saith to you, do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.56'>And the famine was over all the face of the earth. Then Joseph opened all [the storehouses] and sold unto the Egyptians; for the famine waxed sore in the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.41.57'>And all the earth came into Egypt to buy from Joseph because the famine was so sore in all lands.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.42'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.1'>Now when Jacob saw that there was food in Egypt, Jacob said unto his sons, Why are ye looking upon one another?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.2'>And he said, Behold, I have heard that there is food in Egypt; go down there and buy for us from there that we may live, and not die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.3'>And Joseph's ten brethren went down to buy wheat in Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.4'>But Jacob did not send Benjamin, Joseph's brother, with his brethren; for he said, Lest peradventure disaster befall him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.5'>And the sons of Israel came to buy among those that came, for the famine was in the land of Canaan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.6'>And Joseph [was] the lord over the land, [and] he [it was] that sold [the wheat] to all the people of the land; and Joseph's brethren came and bowed down themselves before him [with] their faces to the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.7'>And when Joseph saw his brethren, he knew them, but made himself strange unto them and spoke roughly unto them; and he said unto them, Where have you come from? And they said, From the land of Canaan to buy food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.8'>And Joseph knew his brethren but they did not know him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.9'>Then Joseph remembered the dreams which he dreamed of them and said unto them, Ye [are] spies; to see the nakedness of the land ye are come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.10'>And they said unto him, No, my lord, but to buy food are thy servants come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.11'>We [are] all one man's sons; we are men of [the] truth, thy servants have never been spies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.12'>And he said unto them, No, but to see the nakedness of the land ye are come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.13'>And they said, Thy servants [are] twelve brethren, the sons of one man in the land of Canaan; and, behold, the youngest [is] this day with our father, and one [is] not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.14'>And Joseph said unto them, That [is it] that [which] I spoke unto you, saying, Ye [are] spies:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.15'>Hereby ye shall be proved: By the life of Pharaoh ye shall not go forth from here unless your youngest brother comes here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.16'>Send one of you and let him bring your brother, and ye shall be kept in prison that your words may be proved, whether [there is any] truth in you; or else by the life of Pharaoh surely ye [are] spies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.17'>And he put them all together into prison for three days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.18'>And Joseph said unto them the third day, Do this and live, [for] I fear God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.19'>If ye [are] men of [the] truth, let one of your brethren be bound in the house of your prison; go ye, carry food for the famine of your houses</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.20'>but bring your youngest brother unto me, so shall your words be verified, and ye shall not die. And they did so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.21'>And they said one to another, We [are] truly guilty concerning our brother in that we saw the anguish of his soul when he besought us, and we would not hear; therefore is this distress come upon us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.22'>Then Reuben answered them, saying, Did I not speak unto you, saying, Do not sin against the young man, and ye would not hear? Therefore, behold, his blood is also required.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.23'>And they did not know that Joseph understood [them], for he spoke unto them by an interpreter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.24'>And he turned himself about from them and wept and returned to them again and spoke with them and took Simeon from them and bound him before their eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.25'>Then Joseph commanded to fill their sacks with wheat and to restore each man's money into his sack and to give them provisions for the way; and thus it was done unto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.26'>And they laded their asses with the wheat and departed from there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.27'>And as one of them opened his sack to give his ass fodder in the inn, he saw his money; for, behold, it [was] in his sack's mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.28'>And he said unto his brethren, My money is restored; and, behold, [it is] even in my sack. And their heart failed [them], and they were afraid, saying one to another, What [is] this [that] God has done unto us?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.29'>And they came unto Jacob, their father, unto the land of Canaan and told him all that had befallen them, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.30'>The man, [who is] the lord of the land, spoke roughly to us and took us for spies of the country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.31'>And we said unto him, We [are] men of [the] truth; we have never been spies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.32'>We [are] twelve brethren, sons of our father; one [is] not, and the youngest [is] this day with our father in the land of Canaan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.33'>And the man, the lord of the country, said unto us, Hereby I shall know that ye [are] men of [the] truth; leave one of your brethren [here] with me and take [food for] the famine of your households and go</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.34'>and bring your youngest brother unto me; then I shall know that ye [are] not spies, but [that] ye [are] men of [the] truth; [thus] I will deliver you your brother, and ye shall trade in the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.35'>And it came to pass as they emptied their sacks, that, behold, each man's bundle of money [was] in his sack; and when [both] they and their father saw the bundles of money, they were afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.36'>And Jacob, their father, said unto them, Ye have bereaved me [of my sons]: Joseph [is] not, and Simeon [is] not, and ye will take Benjamin [away]; all these things are upon me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.37'>And Reuben spoke unto his father, saying, Slay my two sons, if I do not bring him to thee; deliver him into my hand, and I will bring him to thee again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.42.38'>And he said, My son shall not go down with you; for his brother is dead, and he alone is left; if [some] disaster should befall him by the way in which ye go, then shall ye bring my gray hairs with sorrow down to Sheol.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.43'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.1'>And the famine [was] sore in the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.2'>And it came to pass when they had eaten up the wheat which they had brought out of Egypt, their father said unto them, Go again, buy us a little food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.3'>And Judah spoke unto him, saying, The man did solemnly protest unto us, saying, Ye shall not see my face unless your brother [is] with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.4'>If thou wilt send our brother with us, we will go down and buy thee food:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.5'>But if thou wilt not send [him], we will not go down; for the man said unto us, Ye shall not see my face unless your brother [is] with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.6'>And Israel said, Why did ye such evil unto me [as] to tell the man that ye had another brother?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.7'>And they said, The man asked us expressly of our state and of our kindred, saying, [Is] your father yet alive? Have ye [another] brother? And we told him according to the tenor of these words. Could we certainly know that he would say, Bring your brother down?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.8'>Then Judah said unto Israel, his father, Send the lad with me, and we will arise and go, that we may live, and not die, both we and thou [and] also our little ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.9'>I will be surety for him; of my hand shalt thou require him; if I do not bring him unto thee and set him before thee, then let me bear the sin for ever;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.10'>for if we had not lingered, surely by now we would have returned this second time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.11'>Then their father Israel answered them, If [it must be] so now, do this: take of the best fruits of the land in your vessels and take the man a present, a little balm, and a little honey, aromas, and myrrh, nuts, and almonds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.12'>And take double money in your hands and the money that was brought again in the mouth of your sacks; carry [it] again in your hand; peradventure it [was] an oversight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.13'>Take also your brother, and arise, go again unto the man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.14'>And God Almighty give you mercy before the man, that he may let your other brother go, and Benjamin. If I be bereaved [of my sons], I am bereaved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.15'>Then the men took the present, and they took double money in their hand, and Benjamin, and rose up and went down to Egypt and stood before Joseph.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.16'>And when Joseph saw Benjamin with them, he said to the ruler of his house, Bring [these] men home and slay an animal and make ready; for [these] men shall dine with me at noon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.17'>And the man did as Joseph bade, and the man brought the men into Joseph's house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.18'>And the men were afraid because they were brought into Joseph's house, and they said, Because of the money that was returned in our sacks the first time we are brought in here that he may seek occasion against us and fall upon us and take us for bondmen and our asses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.19'>And they came near to the steward of Joseph's house, and they spoke with him at the door of the house</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.20'>and said, my lord, we came indeed down the first time to buy food;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.21'>and it came to pass when we came to the inn, that we opened our sacks, and, behold, each man's money [was] in the mouth of his sack, our money in full weight; and we have brought it again in our hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.22'>And we brought down other money in our hands to buy food; we cannot tell who put our money in our sacks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.23'>And he said, Peace [be] to you, fear not; your God, and the God of your father, has given you treasure in your sacks; I had your money. And he brought Simeon out unto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.24'>And the man brought the men into Joseph's house and gave [them] water, and they washed their feet, and he gave their asses fodder.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.25'>And they made ready the present [waiting] until Joseph came at noon, for they heard that they should eat bread there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.26'>And when Joseph came home, they brought him the present which [they had] in their hand in the house and bowed themselves to him to the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.27'>And he asked them of [their] welfare and said, [Is] your father well, the old man of whom ye spoke? [Is] he yet alive?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.28'>And they answered, Thy servant our father [is] in good health, he [is] yet alive. And they bowed down their heads and made obeisance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.29'>And he lifted up his eyes and saw his brother Benjamin, his mother's son, and said, [Is] this your younger brother, of whom ye spoke unto me? And he said, God be merciful unto thee, my son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.30'>Then Joseph made haste; for his bowels did yearn upon his brother; and he sought [where] to weep, and he entered into [his] chamber and wept there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.31'>And he washed his face and went out and refrained himself and said, Serve bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.32'>And they served for him by himself, and for them by themselves, and for the Egyptians, who ate with him, by themselves; because the Egyptians may not eat bread with the Hebrews, for that [is] an abomination unto the Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.33'>And they sat before him, the firstborn according to his birthright and the youngest according to his youth; and the men marvelled one at another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.43.34'>And he took [and sent] portions unto them from before him; but Benjamin's portion was five times as much as any of theirs. And they drank, and were drunk with him.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.44'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.1'>And he commanded the steward of his house, saying, Fill these men's sacks [with] food, as much as they can carry, and put every man's money in his sack's mouth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.2'>and put my cup, the silver cup, in the sack's mouth of the youngest, with the money of his wheat. And he did according to the word that Joseph had spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.3'>As soon as the morning was light, the men were sent away, they and their asses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.4'>[And] when they were gone out of the city, [and] not [yet] far off, Joseph said unto his steward, Rise up, follow after those men; and when thou dost overtake them, say unto them, Why have ye rewarded evil for good?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.5'>[Is] this not [the one] in which my lord drinks and in which indeed he divines? Ye have done evil in so doing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.6'>When he overtook them, he spoke unto them these same words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.7'>And they said unto him, Why saith my lord these words? In no wise should thy servants do according to this thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.8'>Behold, the money, which we found in our sacks' mouths, we brought again unto thee out of the land of Canaan; how then should we steal out of thy lord's house silver or gold?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.9'>With whoever of thy servants it is found, both let him die and we also will be my lord's bondmen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.10'>And he said, Now also [let] it [be] according unto your words; he with whom it is found shall be my servant, and ye shall be blameless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.11'>Then they made haste, and each one took his sack down to the ground, and each one opened his sack.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.12'>And he searched [and] began at the eldest and finished at the youngest; and the cup was found in Benjamin's sack.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.13'>Then they rent their clothes, and each one laded his ass, and they returned to the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.14'>And Judah and his brethren came to Joseph's house, for he [was] yet there; and they fell before him on the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.15'>And Joseph said unto them, What deed [is] this that ye have done? Know ye not that such a man as I can certainly divine?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.16'>Then Judah said, What shall we say unto my lord? What shall we speak or how shall we clear ourselves? God has found out the iniquity of thy servants; behold, we [are] my lord's servants, both we and [he] also with whom the cup is found.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.17'>And he said, in no wise should I do so; [but] the man in whose hand the cup is found, he shall be my servant; and as for you, go up in peace unto your father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.18'>Then Judah came near unto him and said, Oh my lord, let thy servant, I pray thee, speak a word in my lord's ears, and let not thine anger burn against thy servant; for thou [art] even as Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.19'>My lord asked his servants, saying, Have ye a father or a brother?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.20'>And we said unto my lord, We have a father, an old man, and a young man of his old age, yet a lad; and his brother is dead, and he alone is left of his mother, and his father loves him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.21'>And thou didst say unto thy servants, Bring him down unto me that I may set my eyes upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.22'>And we said unto my lord, The lad cannot leave his father; for [if] he should leave his father, [his father] would die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.23'>And thou didst say unto thy servants, Unless your youngest brother comes down with you, ye shall see my face no more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.24'>And it came to pass when we came up unto thy servant my father, we told him the words of my lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.25'>And our father said, Go again [and] buy us a little food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.26'>And we said, We cannot go down; if our youngest brother is with us, then will we go down; for we may not see the man's face unless our youngest brother [is] with us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.27'>Then thy servant my father said unto us, Ye know that my wife bore me two [sons];</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.28'>and the one went out from me, and I said, Surely he is torn in pieces, and I have not seen him since;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.29'>and if ye take this one also from me and [some] disaster should befall him, ye shall bring my gray hairs with sorrow down to Sheol.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.30'>Now therefore when I come to thy servant my father, and the lad [is] not with us, seeing that his soul is bound up in the lad's soul,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.31'>it shall come to pass when he sees that the lad [is] not [with us], that he will die: and thy servants shall bring the gray hairs of thy servant our father down with sorrow to Sheol.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.32'>For thy servant became surety for the lad unto my father, saying, If I bring him not unto thee, then I shall bear the sin before my father for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.33'>Now therefore, I pray thee, let thy servant remain instead of the lad as a bondman to my lord, and let the lad go up with his brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.44.34'>For how shall I go up to my father and the lad not [be] with me? I cannot [go] lest I see the evil that shall come on my father.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.45'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.1'>Then Joseph could not refrain himself before all those that stood by him, and he cried, Cause everyone to go out from me. And no one stood with him while Joseph made himself known unto his brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.2'>And he wept aloud; and the Egyptians and the house of Pharaoh heard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.3'>And Joseph said unto his brethren, I [am] Joseph; does my father yet live? And his brethren could not answer him, for they were terrified at his presence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.4'>Then Joseph said unto his brethren, Now come near to me, I pray you. And they came near. And he said, I [am] Joseph your brother, whom ye sold into Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.5'>Now therefore be not grieved, nor angry with yourselves that ye sold me here, for God sent me before you for life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.6'>For these two years the famine [has been] in the land, and yet [there are] five years in which [there shall] neither [be] plowing nor harvest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.7'>And God sent me before you that you might remain in the earth and that you might be given life by great liberty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.8'>So now [it was] not you [that] sent me here, but God; and he has made me [as] a father to Pharaoh and lord of all his house and a ruler throughout all the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.9'>Make haste and go up to my father and say unto him: Thus saith thy son Joseph, God has made me lord of all Egypt; come down unto me, tarry not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.10'>And thou shalt dwell in the land of Goshen, and thou shalt be near unto me, thou and thy sons and thy sons's sons and thy herds and thy cows and all that thou hast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.11'>And there I will nourish thee, for yet [there are] five years of famine, lest thou and thy household and all that thou hast perish of poverty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.12'>And, behold, your eyes see and the eyes of my brother Benjamin that [it is] my mouth that speaks unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.13'>And ye shall tell my father of all my glory in Egypt and of all that ye have seen; and ye shall haste and bring down my father here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.14'>And he fell upon his brother Benjamin's neck and wept, and Benjamin wept upon his neck.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.15'>Moreover he kissed all his brethren and wept upon them, and after that his brethren talked with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.16'>And the fame of this was heard in Pharaoh's house, saying, Joseph's brethren have come; and it pleased Pharaoh well, and his servants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.17'>And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, Say unto thy brethren, Do this: lade your beasts and go, return unto the land of Canaan</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.18'>and take your father and your households and come unto me; and I will give you the good of the land of Egypt, and ye shall eat the fat of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.19'>Now thou art commanded, do this: take wagons out of the land of Egypt for your little ones and for your wives and bring your father and come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.20'>Also regard not your stuff, for the good of all the land of Egypt [is] yours.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.21'>And the sons of Israel did so, and Joseph gave them wagons, according to the commandment of Pharaoh, and gave them provisions for the way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.22'>To each one of them all he gave changes of clothing; but to Benjamin he gave three hundred [pieces] of silver and five changes of clothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.23'>And to his father he sent after this [manner]: ten asses laden with the best of Egypt and ten she asses laden with wheat and bread and food for his father on the way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.24'>So he sent his brethren away, and they departed. And he said unto them, See that ye do not fight along the way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.25'>And they went up out of Egypt and came into the land of Canaan unto Jacob, their father,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.26'>and told him, saying, Joseph [is] yet alive, and he [is] lord over all the land of Egypt. And his heart fainted, for he did not believe them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.27'>And they told him all the words of Joseph, which he had said unto them; and when he saw the wagons which Joseph had sent to carry him, the spirit of Jacob, their father, revived:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.45.28'>Then Israel said, [It is] enough; Joseph my son [is] yet alive; I will go and see him before I die.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.46'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.1'>And Israel took his journey with all that he had and came to Beersheba and offered sacrifices unto the God of his father Isaac.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.2'>And God spoke unto Israel in visions of the night and said, Jacob, Jacob. And he said, Here [am] I.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.3'>And he said, I [am] the God, the God of thy father; fear not to go down into Egypt; for there I will make of thee a great people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.4'>I will go down with thee into Egypt; and I will also surely bring thee up [again]; and Joseph shall put his hand upon thine eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.5'>And Jacob rose up from Beersheba, and the sons of Israel took Jacob their father and their little ones and their wives in the wagons which Pharaoh had sent to carry him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.6'>And they took their cattle and their goods which they had gotten in the land of Canaan and came into Egypt, Jacob and all his seed with him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.7'>his sons, and his sons' sons with him, his daughters, and his sons' daughters, and all his seed he brought with him into Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.8'>And these [are] the names of the sons of Israel, who came into Egypt, Jacob and his sons: Reuben, Jacob's firstborn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.9'>And the sons of Reuben: Enoch, Phallu, Hezron, and Carmi.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.10'>And the sons of Simeon: Jemuel, Jamin, Ohad, Jachin, Zohar, and Saul the son of a Canaanite woman.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.11'>And the sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.12'>And the sons of Judah: Er and Onan and Shelah and Pharez and Zerah; but Er and Onan died in the land of Canaan. And the sons of Pharez were Hezron and Hamul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.13'>And the sons of Issachar: Tola, Phuvah, Job, and Shimron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.14'>And the sons of Zebulun: Sered, Elon, and Jahleel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.15'>These [are] the sons of Leah, whom she bore unto Jacob in Padanaram, with his daughter Dinah; all the souls of his sons and his daughters [were] thirty-three.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.16'>And the sons of Gad: Ziphion, Haggi, Shuni, Ezbon, Eri, Arodi, and Areli.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.17'>And the sons of Asher: Jimnah, Ishuah, Isui, Beriah, and Serah, their sister. The sons of Beriah: Heber and Malchiel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.18'>These [are] the sons of Zilpah, whom Laban gave to Leah his daughter, and these she gave birth unto Jacob: sixteen souls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.19'>The sons of Rachel, Jacob's wife: Joseph and Benjamin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.20'>And unto Joseph in the land of Egypt were born Manasseh and Ephraim, whom Asenath the daughter of Potipherah priest of On gave birth unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.21'>And the sons of Benjamin [were] Belah, Becher, Ashbel, Gera, Naaman, Ehi, Rosh, Muppim, Huppim, and Ard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.22'>These [are] the sons of Rachel, who were born to Jacob, [in] all, fourteen souls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.23'>And the sons of Dan: Hushim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.24'>And the sons of Naphtali: Jahzeel, Guni, Jezer, and Shillem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.25'>These [are] the sons of Bilhah, who Laban gave unto Rachel his daughter, and she gave birth to these unto Jacob; [in] all seven souls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.26'>All the souls that came with Jacob into Egypt, which came out of his loins, besides Jacob's sons' wives, all the souls [were] sixty-six;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.27'>and the sons of Joseph, who were born him in Egypt, [were] two souls. All the souls of the house of Jacob, who came into Egypt, [were] seventy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.28'>And he sent Judah before him unto Joseph, to direct his face unto Goshen; and they came into the land of Goshen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.29'>And Joseph made ready his chariot and went up to meet Israel his father, to Goshen, and manifested himself unto him; and he fell on his neck and wept on his neck a good while.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.30'>Then Israel said unto Joseph, Now let me die since I have seen thy face because thou [art] yet alive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.31'>And Joseph said unto his brethren and unto his father's house, I will go up and tell Pharaoh and say unto him, My brethren and my father's house, who [were] in the land of Canaan, are come unto me;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.32'>and the men [are] pastors of sheep, for their trade has been to feed livestock; and they have brought their sheep and their cows and all that they have.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.33'>And it shall come to pass when Pharaoh shall call you and shall say, What [is] your occupation?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.46.34'>Then ye shall say, Thy servants' trade has been about livestock from our youth even until now, both we [and] also our fathers, that ye may dwell in the land of Goshen; for every pastor of sheep [is] an abomination unto the Egyptians.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.47'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.1'>Then Joseph came and told Pharaoh and said, My father and my brethren and their sheep and their cows and all that they have are come out of the land of Canaan; and, behold, they [are] in the land of Goshen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.2'>And of the least of his brethren he took five men and presented them unto Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.3'>And Pharaoh said unto his brethren, What [is] your occupation? And they said unto Pharaoh, Thy servants [are] pastors of sheep, both we [and] also our fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.4'>They said moreover unto Pharaoh, For to sojourn in the land are we come, for thy servants have no pasture for their sheep, for the famine [is] sore in the land of Canaan; now therefore, we pray thee, let thy servants dwell in the land of Goshen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.5'>And Pharaoh spoke unto Joseph, saying, Thy father and thy brethren are come unto thee;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.6'>the land of Egypt [is] before thee; in the best of the land make thy father and brethren to dwell; in the land of Goshen let them dwell; and if thou knowest [any] men of valour among them, then make them rulers over my livestock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.7'>And Joseph brought in Jacob his father and set him before Pharaoh; and Jacob blessed Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.8'>And Pharaoh said unto Jacob, How old [art] thou?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.9'>And Jacob said unto Pharaoh, The days of the years of my pilgrimage [are] one hundred and thirty years; few and evil have the days of the years of my life been and have not attained unto the days of the years of the life of my fathers in the days of their pilgrimage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.10'>And Jacob blessed Pharaoh and went out from before Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.11'>Thus Joseph placed his father and his brethren and gave them a possession in the land of Egypt in the best of the land, in the land of Rameses, as Pharaoh had commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.12'>And Joseph nourished his father and his brethren, and all his father's household with bread, according to [their] families.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.13'>And [there was] no bread in all the land, for the famine [was] very sore, so that the land of Egypt and [all] the land of Canaan fainted by reason of the famine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.14'>And Joseph gathered up all the money that was found in the land of Egypt and in the land of Canaan for the food which they bought from him; and Joseph brought the money into Pharaoh's house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.15'>And when money failed in the land of Egypt and in the land of Canaan, all the Egyptians came unto Joseph and said, Give us bread, for why should we die in thy presence for the money fails?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.16'>And Joseph said, Give your livestock, and I will give you for your livestock if the money [has] failed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.17'>And they brought their livestock unto Joseph, and Joseph gave them bread [in exchange] for horses and for the sheep and for the bovine livestock and for the asses, and he fed them with bread for all their livestock that year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.18'>When that year was ended, they came unto him the second year and said unto him, We will not hide [it] from my lord how that the money is gone; my lord also has our herds of cattle; there is not nothing left in the sight of my lord, but our bodies and our lands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.19'>Why shall we die before thine eyes, both we and our land? Buy us and our land for bread, and we and our land will be servants unto Pharaoh, and give [us] seed that we may live, and not die, that the land not be desolate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.20'>Then Joseph bought all the land of Egypt for Pharaoh, for each one of the Egyptians sold his field because the famine prevailed over them; so the land became Pharaoh's.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.21'>And as for the people, he removed them to cities from [one] end of the borders of Egypt even to the [other] end thereof.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.22'>Only the land of the priests he did not buy, for the priests had a portion [assigned them] of Pharaoh and ate their portion which Pharaoh gave them; therefore they did not sell their lands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.23'>Then Joseph said unto the people, Behold, I have bought you this day and your land for Pharaoh; behold, [here is] seed for you, and ye shall sow the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.24'>And it shall come to pass in the increase that ye shall give the fifth [part] unto Pharaoh, and four parts shall be your own for seed of the field and for your food and for those of your households and for food for your little ones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.25'>And they said, Thou hast saved our lives; let us find grace in the sight of my lord that we might be Pharaoh's servants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.26'>And Joseph made it a statute over the land of Egypt unto this day, [that] Pharaoh should have the fifth [part]; except the land of the priests only, [which] did not become Pharaoh's.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.27'>Thus Israel dwelt in the land of Egypt, in the land of Goshen; and they had possessions therein and grew and multiplied exceedingly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.28'>And Jacob lived in the land of Egypt seventeen years; so the whole age of Jacob was one hundred forty-seven years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.29'>And the time drew nigh that Israel must die; and he called his son Joseph and said unto him, If now I have found grace in thy sight, put, I pray thee, thy hand under my thigh and deal with me in mercy and truth; do not bury me, I pray thee, in Egypt;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.30'>but I will lie with my fathers, and thou shalt carry me out of Egypt and bury me in their buryingplace. And he said, I will do as thou hast said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.47.31'>And he said, Swear unto me. And he swore unto him. Then Israel bowed himself upon the bed's head.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.48'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.1'>And it came to pass after these things [that] it was told Joseph, Behold, thy father [is] sick; and he took with him his two sons, Manasseh and Ephraim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.2'>And [one] told Jacob and said, Behold, thy son Joseph comes unto thee. Then Israel strengthened himself and sat upon the bed</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.3'>and said unto Joseph, God Almighty appeared unto me at Luz in the land of Canaan and blessed me</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.4'>and said unto me, Behold, I will make thee fruitful and multiply thee, and I will make of thee a multitude of peoples and will give this land to thy seed after thee [for] an everlasting possession.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.5'>And now thy two sons, Ephraim and Manasseh, who were born unto thee in the land of Egypt before I came unto thee into Egypt, [are] mine; as Reuben and Simeon, they shall be mine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.6'>And those whom thou hast begotten after them shall be thine [and] shall be called after the name of their brethren in their inheritance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.7'>Because when I came from Padanaram, Rachel died unto me in the land of Canaan in the way when yet [there was] but a little way to come unto Ephrath; and I buried her there in the way of Ephrath, which [is] Bethlehem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.8'>And Israel beheld Joseph's sons and said, Who [are] these?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.9'>And Joseph said unto his father, They [are] my sons, whom God has given me in this [place]. And he said, Bring them, I pray thee, unto me, and I will bless them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.10'>Now the eyes of Israel were so dim for age [that] he could not see. And he brought them near unto him, and he kissed them and embraced them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.11'>And Israel said unto Joseph, I had not thought to see thy face, and, behold, God has showed me also thy seed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.12'>Then Joseph brought them out from between his knees, and he bowed himself with his face to the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.13'>And Joseph took them both, Ephraim in his right hand toward Israel's left hand and Manasseh in his left hand toward Israel's right hand and brought [them] near unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.14'>Then Israel stretched out his right hand and laid [it] upon Ephraim's head, who [was] the younger, and his left hand upon Manasseh's head, guiding his hands with understanding; for Manasseh [was] the firstborn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.15'>And he blessed Joseph and said, God, before whom my fathers Abraham and Isaac walked, the God who has fed me all my life long unto this day,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.16'>the Angel who frees me from all evil, bless these young men, and let my name be named on them, and the name of my fathers Abraham and Isaac; and let them grow into a multitude in the midst of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.17'>Then Joseph seeing that his father laid his right hand upon the head of Ephraim, it displeased him; and he held up his father's hand, to remove it from Ephraim's head unto Manasseh's head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.18'>And Joseph said unto his father, Not so, my father, for this [is] the firstborn; put thy right hand upon his head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.19'>And his father refused and said, I know [it], my son, I know [it]; he also shall become a people, and he also shall be great; but truly his younger brother shall be greater than he, and his seed shall become a multitude of Gentiles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.20'>And he blessed them that day, saying, In thee shall Israel bless, saying, God make thee as Ephraim and as Manasseh. And he set Ephraim before Manasseh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.21'>And Israel said unto Joseph, Behold, I die; but God shall be with you and bring you again unto the land of your fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.48.22'>Moreover I have given to thee one portion above thy brethren, which I took out of the hand of the Amorite with my sword and with my bow.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.49'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.1'>And Jacob called unto his sons and said, Gather yourselves together that I may tell you [that] which shall befall you in the last days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.2'>Gather yourselves together and hear, ye sons of Jacob, and hearken unto Israel your father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.3'>Reuben, thou [art] my firstborn, my might, and the beginning of my strength, principal in dignity, and the principal in power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.4'>Unstable as water, thou shalt not be principal because thou didst go up to thy father's bed; then thou became defiled, going up to my couch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.5'>Simeon and Levi [are] brethren; instruments of injustice are their weapons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.6'>Let my soul not enter into their secret; nor let my honour join their assembly; for in their anger they slew a man, and in their own will they dug down a wall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.7'>Cursed [be] their anger, which [is] strong, and their wrath, which is hard; I will divide them in Jacob and scatter them in Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.8'>Judah, thou [art he] whom thy brethren shall praise; thy hand [shall be] on the neck of thine enemies; thy father's sons shall bow down before thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.9'>Judah [is] a lion's whelp; from the prey, my son, thou art gone up; he stooped down, he couched as a lion and as an [old] lion; who shall rouse him up?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.10'>The sceptre shall not be taken from Judah, nor the lawgiver from between his feet until Shiloh comes; and unto him shall the gathering of the people [be].</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.11'>Binding his foal unto the vine and his ass's colt unto the choice roots; he washed his garments in wine and his covering in the blood of grapes;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.12'>His eyes red with wine, and his teeth white with milk.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.13'>Zebulun shall dwell at the port of the sea; and he [shall be] for a port of ships; and his border [shall be] unto Zidon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.14'>Issachar [is] a strong ass couching down between two burdens;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.15'>and he saw that rest [was] good and the land that [it was] pleasant and bowed his shoulder to bear and became a servant unto tribute.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.16'>Dan shall judge his people, as one of the tribes of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.17'>Dan shall be a serpent by the way, an adder in the path, that bites the horse heels, so that his rider shall fall backward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.18'>I have waited for thy saving health, O LORD.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.19'>Gad, an army shall invade him, but he shall invade at the last.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.20'>Out of Asher his bread [shall be] fat, and he shall yield delight unto the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.21'>Naphtali [is] a hind let loose, who shall give forth a good word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.22'>Joseph [is] a fruitful bough, [even] a fruitful bough by a fountain, [whose] daughters run over the wall.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.23'>The arches have sorely grieved him and shot at [him] and hated him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.24'>but his bow abode in strength, and the arms of his hands were made strong by the hands of the Mighty [one] of Jacob; from there did the stone of Israel shepherd,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.25'>by the God of thy father, who shall help thee, and by the Almighty, who shall bless thee with blessings of the heavens above, with blessings of the deep that lies under, with blessings of the breasts and of the womb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.26'>The blessings of thy father were greater than the blessings of my progenitors; unto the borders of the eternal hills they shall be upon the head of Joseph and on the crown of the Nazarite of his brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.27'>Benjamin, ravening wolf: in the morning he shall devour the prey, and in the evening he shall divide the spoil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.28'>All these [were] the twelve tribes of Israel, and this [is] what their father spoke unto them and blessed them; each one according to his blessing he blessed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.29'>And he charged them and said unto them, I am to be gathered unto my people; bury me with my fathers in the cave that [is] in the field of Ephron, the Hittite,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.30'>in the cave that [is] in the field of Machpelah, which [is] before Mamre, in the land of Canaan, which Abraham bought with the field of Ephron, the Hittite for a possession of a buryingplace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.31'>There they buried Abraham and Sarah, his wife; there they buried Isaac and Rebekah, his wife; and there I buried Leah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.32'>The purchase of the field and of the cave that [is] therein [was] from the sons of Heth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.49.33'>And when Jacob had made an end of commanding his sons, he gathered up his feet into the bed and expired and was gathered unto his people.:</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Gen.50'>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.1'>Then Joseph fell upon his father's face and wept upon him and kissed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.2'>And Joseph commanded his servants, the physicians, to embalm his father; and the physicians embalmed Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.3'>And forty days were fulfilled for him; for so are fulfilled the days of those who are embalmed; and the Egyptians mourned for him seventy days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.4'>And when the days of his mourning were past, Joseph spoke unto those of the house of Pharaoh, saying, If now I have found grace in your eyes, speak, I pray you, in the ears of Pharaoh, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.5'>My father made me swear, saying, Behold, I die; in my grave which I have dug for me in the land of Canaan, there shalt thou bury me. Now therefore let me go up, I pray thee and bury my father, and I will come again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.6'>And Pharaoh said, Go up and bury thy father, according as he made thee swear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.7'>Then Joseph went up to bury his father, and with him went up all the servants of Pharaoh, the elders of his house, and all the elders of the land of Egypt,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.8'>and all the house of Joseph and his brethren and his father's house; only their little ones and their sheep and their cows, they left in the land of Goshen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.9'>And both chariots and horsemen went up with him, and it was a very great company.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.10'>And they came to the threshingfloor of Atad, which [is] beyond Jordan, and there they mourned with a great and very sore lamentation; and [Joseph] made a mourning for his father seven days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.11'>And when the inhabitants of the land, the Canaanites, saw the mourning in the floor of Atad, they said, This [is] a great mourning of the Egyptians; therefore the name of it was called Abelmizraim, which [is] beyond the Jordan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.12'>And his sons did unto him according as he commanded them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.13'>for his sons carried him into the land of Canaan and buried him in the cave of the field of Machpelah, which Abraham bought with the field for a possession of a buryingplace from Ephron the Hittite, before Mamre.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.14'>And Joseph returned into Egypt, he, and his brethren, and all that went up with him to bury his father, after he had buried his father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.15'>And when Joseph's brethren saw that their father was dead, they said, Joseph will peradventure hate us and will certainly requite us all the evil which we did unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.16'>And they sent a messenger unto Joseph, saying, Thy father did command before he died, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.17'>So shall ye say unto Joseph, Forgive, I pray thee now, the trespass of thy brethren and their sin, for they did unto thee evil; and now, we pray thee, forgive the trespass of the servants of the God of thy father. And Joseph wept when they spoke unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.18'>And his brethren also went and fell down before his face, and they said, Behold, we [are] thy servants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.19'>And Joseph said unto them, Fear not; for [am] I in the place of God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.20'>But as for you, ye thought evil against me; [but] God thought it [out] unto good, to bring to pass that which we see this day, to give life to many people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.21'>Now therefore fear ye not; I will nourish you and your little ones. Thus he comforted them and spoke to their heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.22'>And Joseph dwelt in Egypt, he, and his father's house: and Joseph lived one hundred and ten years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.23'>And Joseph saw Ephraim's sons unto the third generation; the sons also of Machir, the son of Manasseh, were brought up upon Joseph's knees.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.24'>And Joseph said unto his brethren, I die; but God will surely visit you and bring you out of this land unto the land which he swore to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.25'>And Joseph took an oath of the sons of Israel, saying, God will surely visit you, and ye shall carry up my bones from here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Gen.50.26'>So Joseph died, [being] one hundred and ten years old; and they embalmed him, and he was put in an ark in Egypt.:</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>