<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='XXX' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='XXX'>
        <title>VW-Edition 2006</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject/>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>English translation of the Bible from the Masoretic and Textus Receptus Hebrew/Greek texts. A 'literal' translation with the readability of a NKJV or MKJV. In print: www.a-voice.org/bible-vw/print.htm  "About this Edition" www.a-voice.org/bible-vw/preface.htm</description>
        <publisher>A Voice in the Wilderness, POBox 9531, Spokane, WA 99209, USA (www.a-voice.org)</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>XXX</identifier>
        <source/>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>Freely copy and distribute</coverage>
        <rights>This module is not to be sold. Do not modify or reconfigure for other software without authorization from publisher</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div osisID='Exod' type='book'>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.1'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.1'>Now these are the names of the sons of Israel who came into Egypt; each man and his house came with Jacob:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.2'>Reuben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.3'>Issachar, Zebulun, and Benjamin;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.4'>Dan, Naphtali, Gad, and Asher.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.5'>All those who came out of the loins of Jacob were seventy souls (for Joseph was in Egypt already).</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.6'>And Joseph died, all his brothers, and all that generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.7'>And the children of Israel were fruitful and increased abundantly, multiplied and grew exceedingly numerous; and the land was filled with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.8'>And there arose a new king over Egypt, who did not know Joseph.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.9'>And he said to his people, Behold, the people of the children of Israel are more numerous and vast than we.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.10'>Come, let us deal wisely with them, lest they multiply, and it happen in the event of war, that they also join our enemies and fight against us, and thus go up out of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.11'>Therefore they set taskmasters over them to afflict them with their burdens. And they built for Pharaoh supply cities, Pithom and Raamses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.12'>But the more they afflicted them, the more they multiplied and grew. And they were in dread of the children of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.13'>So the Egyptians made the children of Israel work with harshness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.14'>And they made their lives bitter with hard labor; in mortar, in brick, and in all manner of labor in the field. All their labor in which they made them work was with harshness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.15'>And the king of Egypt spoke to the Hebrew midwives, of whom the name of one was Shiphrah and the name of the other Puah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.16'>and he said: When you do the duties of a midwife for the Hebrew women, and see them on the birthstools, if it is a son, then you shall kill him; but if it is a daughter, then she shall live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.17'>But the midwives feared God, and did not do as the king of Egypt commanded them, but saved the male children alive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.18'>And the king of Egypt summoned the midwives and said to them, Why have you done this thing, and saved the male children alive?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.19'>And the midwives said to Pharaoh, Because the Hebrew women are not like the Egyptian women; for they are vigorous and give birth before the midwives come to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.20'>Therefore God dealt well with the midwives, and the people multiplied and grew exceedingly numerous.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.21'>And so it was, because the midwives feared God, that He provided houses for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.1.22'>And Pharaoh commanded all his people, saying, Every son who is born you shall cast into the river, and every daughter you shall save alive.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.2'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.1'>And a man of the house of Levi went and took a daughter of Levi.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.2'>And the woman conceived and bore a son. And when she saw that he was good, she hid him three months.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.3'>And when she could no longer hide him, she took a vessel of reeds for him, daubed it with asphalt and pitch, put the child in it, and laid it in the reeds by the river bank.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.4'>And his sister stood at a distance, to know what would be done to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.5'>And the daughter of Pharaoh came down to bathe at the river. And her maidens were walking along the riverside; and when she saw the vessel among the reeds, she sent her maid to fetch it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.6'>And when she opened it, she saw the child, and behold, the boy wept. And she had compassion on him, and said, This is one of the Hebrews children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.7'>Then his sister said to Pharaohs daughter, Shall I go and call a wet nurse for you from the Hebrew women, that she may nurse the child for you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.8'>And Pharaohs daughter said to her, Go. So the maiden went and called the childs mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.9'>And Pharaohs daughter said to her, Take this child away and nurse him for me, and I will give you your wages. So the woman took the child and nursed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.10'>And the child grew, and she brought him to Pharaohs daughter, and he became her son. And she called his name Moses, saying, Because I drew him out of the water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.11'>And it came to pass in those days, when Moses was grown, that he went out to his brethren and looked upon their burdens. And he saw an Egyptian beating a Hebrew, one of his brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.12'>And he looked this way and that, and when he saw no one, he killed the Egyptian and hid him in the sand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.13'>And when he went out the second day, behold, two Hebrew men were fighting, and he said to the guilty one, Why are you striking the other fellow?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.14'>And he said, Who made you a ruler and a judge over us? Do you intend to kill me as you killed the Egyptian? And Moses feared and said, Surely this thing is known!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.15'>And when Pharaoh heard of the matter, he sought to kill Moses. But Moses fled from the face of Pharaoh and dwelt in the land of Midian; and he sat down by a well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.16'>Now the priest of Midian had seven daughters. And they came and drew water, and they filled the troughs to water their fathers flock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.17'>And the shepherds came and drove them away; but Moses stood up and delivered them, and watered their flock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.18'>And when they came to Reuel their father, he said, How is it that you have made haste today?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.19'>And they said, An Egyptian man delivered us from the hand of the shepherds, and proceeded to draw for us and watered the flock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.20'>And he said to his daughters, And where is he? Why is it that you have left the man? Invite him, that he may eat bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.21'>And Moses agreed to live with the man, and he gave Zipporah his daughter to Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.22'>And she bore him a son, and he called his name Gershom; for he said, I have become a sojourner in a foreign land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.23'>And it came to pass after many days that the king of Egypt died. And the children of Israel groaned because of the bondage, and they cried out; and their cry came up to God because of the bondage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.24'>And God heard their groaning, and God remembered His covenant with Abraham, with Isaac, and with Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.2.25'>And God gave attention to the children of Israel, and God acknowledged them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.3'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.1'>Now Moses was with the flock of Jethro his father-in-law, the priest of Midian. And he led the flock to the back of the wilderness, and came to Horeb, the mountain of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.2'>And the Angel of Jehovah appeared to him in a flame of fire from the midst of a bush. And he looked, and behold, the bush was burning with fire, but the bush was not consumed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.3'>And Moses thought, I will now turn aside and see this great sight, why the bush is not burned up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.4'>And when Jehovah saw that he turned aside to look, God called to him from the midst of the bush and said, Moses! Moses! And he said, Here am I.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.5'>And He said, Do not approach here. Take your sandals off your feet, for the place where you are standing is holy ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.6'>Moreover He said, I am the God of your fathers; the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob. And Moses hid his face, for he was afraid to look upon God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.7'>And Jehovah said: I have given attention to see the affliction of My people who are in Egypt, and have heard their cry because of their taskmasters, for I have acknowledged their pain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.8'>And I have come down to deliver them out of the hand of the Egyptians, and to bring them up from that land to a good and broad land, to a land flowing with milk and honey, to the place of the Canaanites and the Hittites and the Amorites and the Perizzites and the Hivites and the Jebusites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.9'>Now therefore, behold, the cry of the children of Israel has come unto Me, and I have also seen the oppression with which the Egyptians oppress them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.10'>Come now, therefore, and I will send you to Pharaoh that you may bring My people, the children of Israel, out of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.11'>And Moses said to God, Who am I that I should go to Pharaoh, and that I should bring the children of Israel out of Egypt?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.12'>And He said, I will certainly be with you. And this shall be a sign to you that I have sent you: When you have brought the people out of Egypt, you shall serve God on this mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.13'>And Moses said to God, Behold, when I come to the sons of Israel and say to them, The God of your fathers has sent me to you, and they say to me, What is His name? what shall I say to them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.14'>And God said to Moses, I AM THAT I AM. And He said, Thus you shall say to the sons of Israel, I AM has sent me to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.15'>Moreover God said to Moses, Thus you shall say to the sons of Israel: Jehovah the God of your fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has sent me to you. This is My eternal name, and this is My memorial from generation to generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.16'>Go and gather the elders of Israel together, and say to them, Jehovah the God of your fathers, the God of Abraham, of Isaac, and of Jacob, appeared to me, saying, I have surely visited you and seen what is being done to you in Egypt;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.17'>and I intend to bring you up out of the affliction of Egypt to the land of the Canaanites and the Hittites and the Amorites and the Perizzites and the Hivites and the Jebusites, to a land flowing with milk and honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.18'>And they will heed your voice; and you shall come, you and the elders of Israel, to the king of Egypt; and you shall say to him, Jehovah the God of the Hebrews has met with us; and now, please, let us go three days journey into the wilderness, that we may sacrifice unto Jehovah our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.19'>And I have taken into consideration that the king of Egypt will not let you go, no, not except by a mighty hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.20'>So I will stretch out My hand and strike Egypt with all My wonders which I will do in its midst; and after that he will let you go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.21'>And I will give this people favor in the eyes of the Egyptians; and it shall come to pass, when you go, that you shall not leave empty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.3.22'>But every woman shall ask of her neighbor, of her who sojourns in her house, articles of silver, articles of gold, and clothing; and you shall put them on your sons and on your daughters. Thus you shall plunder the Egyptians.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.4'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.1'>And Moses answered and said, But suppose they will not believe, nor listen to my voice; suppose they say, Jehovah has not appeared to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.2'>And Jehovah said to him, What is that in your hand? He said, A staff.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.3'>And He said, Throw it on the ground. So he threw it on the ground, and it became a serpent; and Moses fled before it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.4'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Stretch out your hand and take it by the tail; and he stretched out his hand and caught it, and it became a staff in his hand;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.5'>that they may believe that Jehovah the God of their fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has appeared to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.6'>Furthermore Jehovah said to him, Now put your hand into your bosom. And he put his hand into his bosom, and when he took it out, behold, his hand was leprous, like snow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.7'>And He said, Put your hand back into your bosom. So he put his hand back into his bosom, and drew it out of his bosom, and behold, it was restored like his other flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.8'>And it shall come to pass when they do not believe, nor heed the voice of the first sign, that perhaps they will believe the voice of the subsequent sign.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.9'>And it shall come to pass when they do not believe even these two signs, nor listen to your voice, that you shall take water from the river and pour it on the dry land. And the water which you take from the river shall become blood on the dry land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.10'>And Moses said to Jehovah, O my Lord, I am not a man of words, neither formerly in times past nor since You have spoken to Your servant; but I have a heavy mouth and a dull tongue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.11'>And Jehovah said to him, Who has made mans mouth? Or who makes the mute, the deaf, the seeing, or the blind? Is it not I, Jehovah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.12'>Now therefore, go, and I will be with your mouth and teach you what you shall speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.13'>And he said, O my Lord, please send by the hand of whomever You may send.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.14'>And the anger of Jehovah burned against Moses, and He said: Is not Aaron the Levite your brother? I know that he can form words to speak. And behold, he is also coming out to meet you; and when he sees you, he will be glad in his heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.15'>And you shall speak to him and put the words in his mouth. And I will be with your mouth and with his mouth, and I will teach you what you shall do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.16'>And he shall speak for you to the people. And he shall be as a mouth for you, and you shall be to him as God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.17'>And you shall take this staff in your hand, with which you shall do the signs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.18'>So Moses went and returned to Jethro his father-in-law, and said to him, Please let me go and return to my brethren who are in Egypt, and see whether they are still alive. And Jethro said to Moses, Go in peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.19'>And Jehovah said to Moses in Midian, Go, return to Egypt; for all the men who sought your life are dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.20'>And Moses took his wife and his sons and mounted them on a donkey, and he returned to the land of Egypt. And Moses took the staff of God in his hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.21'>And Jehovah said to Moses, When you go back to Egypt, see that you do all those wonders before Pharaoh which I have put in your hand. And I will harden his heart, so that he will not let the people go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.22'>And you shall say to Pharaoh, Thus says Jehovah: Israel is My son, My firstborn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.23'>And I say unto you, Let My son go that he may serve Me. And if you refuse to let him go, behold, I will kill your son, your firstborn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.24'>And it came to pass on the way, at the lodging place, that Jehovah met him and sought to kill him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.25'>And Zipporah took a flint and cut off the foreskin of her son and cast it at his feet, and said, Surely you are a husband of blood to me!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.26'>So He let him go. Then she said, You are a husband of blood; because of the circumcision.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.27'>And Jehovah said to Aaron, Go into the wilderness to meet Moses. So he went and met him on the mountain of God, and kissed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.28'>And Moses told Aaron all the words of Jehovah who had sent him, and all the signs which He had commanded him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.29'>And Moses and Aaron went and gathered together all the elders of the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.30'>And Aaron spoke all the words which Jehovah had spoken to Moses. And he did the signs in the eyes of the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.4.31'>And the people believed. And when they heard that Jehovah had visited the children of Israel and that He had given attention to their affliction, they bowed down and prostrated themselves.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.5'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.1'>Afterward Moses and Aaron went in and said to Pharaoh, Thus says Jehovah the God of Israel: Let My people go, that they may hold a feast unto Me in the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.2'>And Pharaoh said, Who is Jehovah, that I should obey His voice to let Israel go? I do not know Jehovah; neither will I let Israel go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.3'>And they said, The God of the Hebrews has met with us. Now, let us go three days journey into the desert and sacrifice unto Jehovah our God, that He not fall upon us with pestilence or with the sword.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.4'>And the king of Egypt said to them, Moses and Aaron, why do you restrain the people from their work? Go to your burdens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.5'>And Pharaoh said, Behold, the people of the land are many now, and you have made them cease from their burdens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.6'>So the same day Pharaoh commanded the taskmasters of the people and their officers, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.7'>You shall no longer give the people straw to make brick as before. Let them go and gather straw for themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.8'>And you shall lay on them the tally of bricks which they made before. You shall not diminish it. For they are idle; therefore they cry out, saying, Let us go and sacrifice to our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.9'>Let more labor be laid upon the men, that they may work in it, and let them not regard deceptive words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.10'>And the taskmasters of the people and their officers went out and spoke to the people, saying, Thus says Pharaoh: I will not give you straw.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.11'>Go, get yourselves straw where you can find it; yet none of your labor shall be diminished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.12'>So the people were scattered abroad throughout all the land of Egypt to gather stubble instead of straw.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.13'>And the taskmasters were pressing upon them saying, Fulfill your work, the matter of each day, as when there was straw.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.14'>And the officers of the children of Israel, whom Pharaohs taskmasters had set over them, were beaten and were asked, Why have you not completed the prescribed amount to make brick, both yesterday and today, as before?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.15'>Then the officers of the children of Israel came and cried out to Pharaoh, saying, Why are you dealing thus with your servants?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.16'>There is no straw given to your slaves, and they say to us, Make brick! And behold, your servants are beaten, but the fault is in your own people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.17'>But he said, You are idle! Idle! Therefore you say, Let us go and sacrifice to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.18'>Therefore go now and work; for no straw shall be given you, yet you shall deliver the amount of bricks.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.19'>And the officers of the children of Israel saw that they were in a bad way after it was said, You shall not diminish any bricks from the matter day by day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.20'>And, as they came out from Pharaoh, they met Moses and Aaron standing there to meet them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.21'>And they said to them, Jehovah look upon you and judge, because you have made us abhorrent in the eyes of Pharaoh and in the eyes of his servants, to put a sword in their hand to kill us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.22'>And Moses returned to Jehovah and said, Lord, why have You brought hurt upon this people? Why then have You sent me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.5.23'>For since I came to Pharaoh to speak in Your name, he has done evil to this people; neither have You rescued to deliver Your people.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.6'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.1'>Then Jehovah said to Moses, Now you shall see what I will do to Pharaoh. For with a strong hand he will let them go, and with a strong hand he will drive them out of his land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.2'>And God spoke to Moses and said to him: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.3'>I appeared unto Abraham, unto Isaac, and unto Jacob, as God Almighty, but by My name Jehovah I have not been known to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.4'>I have also established My covenant with them, to give them the land of Canaan, the land of their pilgrimage, in which they were sojourners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.5'>And I have also heard the groaning of the sons of Israel whom the Egyptians keep in bondage, and I have remembered My covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.6'>Therefore say to the sons of Israel: I am Jehovah; I will bring you out from under the burdens of the Egyptians, I will rescue you from their bondage, and I will redeem you with an outstretched arm and with great judgments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.7'>I will take you to Myself as a people, and I will be God to you. And you shall know that I am Jehovah your God, who brings you out from under the burdens of the Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.8'>And I will bring you into the land which I raised My hand and swore to give to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob; and I will give it to you for a possession. I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.9'>And Moses spoke thus to the sons of Israel; but they did not listen to Moses, because of anguish of spirit and cruel bondage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.10'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.11'>Go, speak to Pharaoh king of Egypt, that he let the children of Israel go out of his land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.12'>And Moses spoke before Jehovah, saying, The sons of Israel have not listened to me. How then shall Pharaoh heed me, for I am of uncircumcised lips?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.13'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses and Aaron, and gave them a command for the sons of Israel, and for Pharaoh king of Egypt, to bring the children of Israel out of the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.14'>These were the heads of their fathers houses: The sons of Reuben, the firstborn of Israel, were Hanoch, Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi. These were the families of Reuben.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.15'>And the sons of Simeon were Jemuel, Jamin, Ohad, Jachin, Zohar, and Shaul the son of a Canaanite woman. These were the families of Simeon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.16'>These were the names of the sons of Levi according to their generations: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari. And the years of the life of Levi were one hundred and thirty-seven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.17'>The sons of Gershon were Libni and Shimi according to their families.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.18'>And the sons of Kohath were Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel. And the years of the life of Kohath were one hundred and thirty-three.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.19'>The sons of Merari were Mahli and Mushi. These were the families of Levi according to their generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.20'>Now Amram took for himself Jochebed, his fathers sister, as wife; and she bore him Aaron and Moses. And the years of the life of Amram were one hundred and thirty-seven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.21'>The sons of Izhar were Korah, Nepheg, and Zichri.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.22'>And the sons of Uzziel were Mishael, Elzaphan, and Zithri.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.23'>Aaron took to himself Elisheba, daughter of Amminadab, sister of Nahshon, as wife; and she bore him Nadab, Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.24'>And the sons of Korah were Assir, Elkanah, and Abiasaph. These were the families of the Korahites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.25'>Eleazar, Aarons son, took for himself one of the daughters of Putiel as wife; and she bore him Phinehas. These were the heads of the fathers houses of the Levites according to their families.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.26'>These were the same Aaron and Moses to whom Jehovah said, Bring out the children of Israel from the land of Egypt according to their hosts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.27'>These were the ones who spoke to Pharaoh king of Egypt, to bring out the children of Israel from Egypt. These were the same Moses and Aaron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.28'>And it came to pass, on the day Jehovah spoke to Moses in the land of Egypt,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.29'>that Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying, I am Jehovah. Speak to Pharaoh king of Egypt all that I say unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.6.30'>But Moses said before Jehovah, Behold, I am of uncircumcised lips, and how shall Pharaoh heed me?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.7'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.1'>And Jehovah said to Moses: See, I have made you as a god to Pharaoh, and Aaron your brother shall be your prophet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.2'>You shall speak all that I command you. And Aaron your brother shall speak to Pharaoh to send the children of Israel out of his land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.3'>And I will harden Pharaohs heart, and multiply My signs and My wonders in the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.4'>But Pharaoh will not heed you, so that I may lay My hand upon Egypt and bring My hosts, My people, the children of Israel, out of the land of Egypt with great judgments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.5'>And the Egyptians shall know that I am Jehovah when I stretch forth My hand upon Egypt and bring out the children of Israel from among them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.6'>And Moses and Aaron did as Jehovah commanded them; thus they did.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.7'>And Moses was eighty years old and Aaron eighty-three years old when they spoke to Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.8'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.9'>When Pharaoh speaks to you, saying, Show a sign for yourselves, then you shall say to Aaron, Take your staff and cast it before Pharaoh, and let it become a serpent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.10'>And Moses and Aaron went in to Pharaoh, and they did so, just as Jehovah commanded. And Aaron cast down his staff before Pharaoh and before his servants, and it became a serpent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.11'>And Pharaoh also called the wise men and the sorcerers. So the magicians of Egypt, they also did so with their enchantments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.12'>For every man threw down his staff, and they became serpents. But Aarons staff swallowed up their staffs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.13'>And Pharaohs heart was hardened, and he did not heed them, as Jehovah had said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.14'>And Jehovah said to Moses: Pharaohs heart is hard; he refuses to let the people go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.15'>Go to Pharaoh in the morning, when he goes out to the water, and you shall stand by the rivers bank to meet him; and the staff which was turned to a serpent you shall take in your hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.16'>And you shall say to him, Jehovah the God of the Hebrews has sent me to you, saying, Let My people go, that they may serve Me in the wilderness; but behold, until now you have not given heed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.17'>Therefore thus says Jehovah: By this you shall know that I am Jehovah. Behold, I will strike the waters in the river with the staff that is in my hand, and they shall be turned to blood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.18'>And the fish that are in the river shall die, the river shall stink, and the Egyptians shall weary themselves to drink the water of the river.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.19'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, Say to Aaron, Take your staff and stretch out your hand over the waters of Egypt, over their streams, over their rivers, over their ponds, and over all their bodies of water, that they may become blood. And there shall be blood throughout all the land of Egypt, in vessels of both wood and stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.20'>And Moses and Aaron did so, as Jehovah commanded. And he lifted up the staff and struck the waters that were in the river, in the eyes of Pharaoh and in the eyes of his servants. And all the waters in the river were turned to blood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.21'>And the fish in the river died, the river stunk, and the Egyptians could not drink the water of the river. So there was blood throughout all the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.22'>And the magicians of Egypt did so with their enchantments; and Pharaohs heart was hardened, and he did not heed them, as Jehovah had said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.23'>And Pharaoh turned and went into his house. Neither did he lay any of this to heart.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.24'>And all the Egyptians dug all around the river for water to drink, because they could not drink the water of the river.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.7.25'>And seven days passed after Jehovah had struck the river.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.8'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, Go to Pharaoh and say to him, Thus says Jehovah: Let My people go, that they may serve Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.2'>And if you refuse to let them go, behold, I will smite all your territory with frogs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.3'>And the river shall swarm with frogs, which shall go up and come into your house, into your bedroom, onto your bed, into the houses of your servants, onto your people, into your ovens, and into your kneading bowls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.4'>And the frogs shall come up upon you, upon your people, and upon all your servants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.5'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Say to Aaron, Stretch out your hand with your staff over the streams, over the rivers, and over the ponds, and cause frogs to come up upon the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.6'>And Aaron stretched out his hand over the waters of Egypt, and the frogs came up and covered the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.7'>And the magicians did so with their enchantments, and brought up frogs upon the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.8'>Then Pharaoh summoned Moses and Aaron, and said, Entreat Jehovah that He may take away the frogs from me and from my people; and I will let the people go, that they may sacrifice unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.9'>And Moses said to Pharaoh, Be glorified: For when shall I make supplication for you, for your servants, and for your people, to destroy the frogs from you and your houses, that they may remain in the river only?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.10'>And he said, Tomorrow. And he said, Let it be according to your word, that you may come to understand that there is no one like Jehovah our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.11'>And the frogs shall depart from you, from your houses, from your servants, and from your people. They shall remain in the river only.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.12'>And Moses and Aaron went out from Pharaoh. And Moses cried out to Jehovah concerning the frogs which He had brought against Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.13'>And Jehovah did according to the word of Moses. And the frogs died out of the houses, out of the courtyards, and out of the fields.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.14'>And they piled them up in heaps, and the land stunk.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.15'>But when Pharaoh saw that there was relief, his heart was hardened and he did not heed them; as Jehovah had said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.16'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Say to Aaron, Stretch out your staff, and strike the dust of the land, so that it may become lice throughout all the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.17'>And they did so. For Aaron stretched out his hand with his staff and struck the dust of the earth, and it became lice upon man and beast. All the dust of the land became lice throughout all the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.18'>And the magicians did so with their enchantments to bring forth lice, but they could not. And there were lice upon man and beast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.19'>Then the magicians said to Pharaoh, This is the finger of God. But Pharaohs heart was hardened, and he did not listen to them; as Jehovah had said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.20'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Rise early in the morning and stand before Pharaoh as he comes out to the water, and say to him, Thus says Jehovah: Let My people go, that they may serve Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.21'>Or else, if you will not let My people go, behold, I will send swarms of flies upon you and your servants, upon your people and into your houses. The houses of the Egyptians shall be full of swarms of flies, and also the ground where they are.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.22'>And for that day I have set apart the land of Goshen, in which My people remain, that no swarms of flies shall be there, in order that you may know that I am Jehovah in the midst of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.23'>I have appointed a ransom for My people from your people. This sign shall be tomorrow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.24'>And Jehovah did so. Thick swarms of flies came into the house of Pharaoh, into his servants houses, and into all the land of Egypt. The land was spoiled because of the swarms of flies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.25'>And Pharaoh summoned Moses and Aaron, and said, Go! Sacrifice to your God in the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.26'>And Moses said, It is not right to do so, for we sacrifice the abomination of the Egyptians unto Jehovah our God. If we sacrifice the abomination of the Egyptians before their eyes, then will they not stone us?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.27'>We will go three days journey into the wilderness and sacrifice unto Jehovah our God as He will command us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.28'>And Pharaoh said, I will let you go, that you may sacrifice unto Jehovah your God in the wilderness; only you shall not go very far away. Make supplication for me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.29'>And Moses said, Indeed I am going out from you, and I will entreat Jehovah, that the swarms of flies may depart tomorrow from Pharaoh, from his servants, and from his people. But let Pharaoh not continue dealing deceitfully in not letting the people go to sacrifice unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.30'>And Moses went out from Pharaoh and entreated Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.31'>And Jehovah did according to the word of Moses; He removed the swarms of flies from Pharaoh, from his servants, and from his people. Not one remained.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.8.32'>And Pharaoh hardened his heart this time also; neither would he let the people go.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.9'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.1'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Go in to Pharaoh and speak to him, Thus says Jehovah the God of the Hebrews: Let My people go, that they may serve Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.2'>And if you refuse to let them go, and still hold them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.3'>behold, the hand of Jehovah will be upon your cattle in the field, upon the horses, upon the donkeys, upon the camels, upon the oxen, and upon the sheep; a very heavy pestilence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.4'>And Jehovah will make a distinction between the livestock of Israel and the livestock of Egypt, and nothing shall die of all that belongs to the children of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.5'>And Jehovah appointed a set time, saying, Tomorrow Jehovah will do this thing in the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.6'>And Jehovah did this thing on the next day, and all the livestock of Egypt died; but of the livestock of the children of Israel, not one died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.7'>And Pharaoh sent, and behold, not even one of the livestock of the Israelites was dead. And Pharaohs heart was hardened, and he did not let the people go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.8'>And Jehovah said to Moses and Aaron, Take for yourselves handfuls of ashes from a furnace, and let Moses toss it toward the heavens before Pharaohs eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.9'>And it shall become fine dust in all the land of Egypt, and it shall be an inflammation breaking out into boils upon man and beast throughout all the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.10'>And they took ashes from the furnace and stood before Pharaoh, and Moses tossed them toward the heavens. And they became inflammations breaking out into boils upon man and beast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.11'>And the magicians could not stand before Moses because of the inflammations, for the inflammations were upon the magicians and upon all the Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.12'>And Jehovah hardened the heart of Pharaoh; and he did not heed them, as Jehovah had spoken to Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.13'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Rise early in the morning and stand before Pharaoh, and say to him, Thus says Jehovah the God of the Hebrews: Let My people go, that they may serve Me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.14'>for at this time I will send all My plagues upon your heart, and upon your servants and upon your people, that you may come to understand that there is no one like Me in all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.15'>For if I had stretched forth My hand and struck you and your people with pestilence, then you would have been cut off from the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.16'>And indeed for this purpose I have ordained you, to show My power in you, and to declare My name in all the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.17'>As yet you exalt yourself against My people in that you will not let them go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.18'>Behold, tomorrow about this time I will cause very heavy hail to rain down, such as has not been in Egypt since its founding until now.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.19'>Therefore send now and gather your livestock and all that you have in the field, for the hail shall come down upon every man and every animal which is found in the field and is not brought into shelter; and they shall die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.20'>The ones who feared the word of Jehovah among the servants of Pharaoh made their servants and their livestock flee to the shelters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.21'>But the ones who did not set their heart upon the word of Jehovah left their servants and their livestock in the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.22'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Stretch forth your hand toward the heavens, that there may be hail in all the land of Egypt; upon man, upon beast, and upon every plant of the field, throughout the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.23'>And Moses stretched forth his staff toward the heavens; and Jehovah sent thunder and hail, and fire went to the ground. And Jehovah rained hail upon the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.24'>So there was hail, and fire in the midst of the hail, so very heavy that there was none like it in all the land of Egypt since it became a nation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.25'>And the hail struck throughout the whole land of Egypt, all that was in the field, both man and beast; and the hail struck every plant of the field and shattered every tree of the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.26'>Only in the land of Goshen, where the children of Israel were, there was no hail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.27'>And Pharaoh sent and summoned Moses and Aaron, and said to them, I have sinned this time. Jehovah is righteous, and I and my people are wicked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.28'>Entreat Jehovah, that there be no more Divine thundering and hail, for it is enough. I will let you go, and you shall stay no longer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.29'>And Moses said to him, As soon as I have gone out of the city, I will spread out my hands to Jehovah. The thunder shall cease, and there shall be no more hail; that you may know that the earth is Jehovahs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.30'>But as for you and your servants, I know that you do not yet fear before Jehovah God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.31'>Now the flax and the barley were struck, for the barley was in the head and the flax was in bud.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.32'>But the wheat and the spelt were not struck, for they are late crops.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.33'>And Moses went out of the city from Pharaoh and spread out his hands to Jehovah. And the thunder and the hail ceased, and the rain was not poured upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.34'>And when Pharaoh saw that the rain, the hail, and the thunder had ceased, he sinned again, and hardened his heart; he and his servants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.9.35'>And the heart of Pharaoh was hardened; neither would he let the children of Israel go, as Jehovah had spoken by the hand of Moses.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.10'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.1'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Go in to Pharaoh; for I have hardened his heart and the hearts of his servants, in order to perform these signs of Mine among them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.2'>and that you may recount in the ears of your son and your sons son how I have dealt ruthlessly in Egypt, and My signs which I have brought to pass among them, that you have come to know that I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.3'>And Moses and Aaron came in to Pharaoh and said to him, Thus says Jehovah the God of the Hebrews: How long will you refuse to humble yourself before Me? Let My people go, that they may serve Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.4'>Or else, if you refuse to let My people go, behold, tomorrow I will bring locusts into your territory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.5'>And they shall cover the face of the earth, so that no one will be able to see the land; and they shall eat the rest of what is left, which remains to you from the hail, and they shall eat every tree which grows up for you out of the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.6'>And they shall fill your houses, the houses of all your servants, and the houses of all the Egyptians; which neither your fathers nor your fathers fathers have seen, since the day that they were on the earth to this day. And he turned and went out from Pharaoh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.7'>And Pharaohs servants said to him, How long shall this man be a snare to us? Let the men go, that they may serve Jehovah their God. Do you not yet realize that Egypt has vanished?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.8'>And Moses and Aaron were brought back to Pharaoh, and he said to them, Go, serve Jehovah your God. Who are the ones going?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.9'>And Moses said, We will go with our young and our old; with our sons and our daughters, with our flocks and our herds we will go, for it is a feast unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.10'>And he said to them, Jehovah be with you if ever I let you and your little ones go! Consider, for evil is before you!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.11'>Not so! Go now, you who are men, and serve Jehovah, for that is what you desired. And they were driven out from Pharaohs presence.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.12'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Stretch out your hand over the land of Egypt for the locusts, that they may come upon the land of Egypt, and eat every plant of the land; all that the hail has left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.13'>And Moses stretched out his staff over the land of Egypt, and Jehovah brought an east wind upon the land all that day and all that night. When it was morning, the east wind brought the locusts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.14'>And the locusts went up over all the land of Egypt and rested on all the territory of Egypt. Exceedingly numerous; previously there had been no such locusts as they, nor shall there be such after them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.15'>For they covered the eye of the whole earth, so that the land was darkened; and they ate every plant of the land and all the fruit of the trees which the hail had left. So there remained nothing green on the trees or on the plants of the field throughout all the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.16'>And Pharaoh summoned Moses and Aaron in haste, and said, I have sinned against Jehovah your God and against you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.17'>Now therefore, please forgive my sin only this once, and entreat Jehovah your God, that He may take away from me this death only.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.18'>And he went out from Pharaoh and entreated Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.19'>And Jehovah turned a very strong wind from the west, which took the locusts away and blew them into the Red Sea. There remained not one locust in all the territory of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.20'>And Jehovah hardened Pharaohs heart, and he did not let the children of Israel go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.21'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Stretch out your hand toward the heavens, that there may be darkness over the land of Egypt, darkness which may even be felt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.22'>And Moses stretched out his hand toward the heavens, and there was thick darkness in all the land of Egypt three days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.23'>They did not see one another; nor did anyone rise from his place for three days. But all the children of Israel had light in their dwellings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.24'>And Pharaoh summoned Moses and said, Go, serve Jehovah; only let your flocks and your herds be kept back. Let your little ones also go with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.25'>And Moses said, You must also give us sacrifices and burnt offerings, that we may make offerings unto Jehovah our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.26'>Our livestock also shall go with us; not a hoof shall be left behind. For we must take some of them to serve Jehovah our God, and even we do not know with what we must serve Jehovah until we arrive there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.27'>And Jehovah hardened Pharaohs heart, and he would not let them go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.28'>And Pharaoh said to him, Depart from me! Take heed to yourself and do not see my face again! For in the day you see my face you shall die!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.10.29'>And Moses said, You have spoken correctly. I will not see your face again.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.11'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.1'>And Jehovah said unto Moses, I will bring yet one more plague upon Pharaoh and upon Egypt. Afterward he will let you go from here. When he lets you go, he will be driving to drive you out from here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.2'>Speak now in the ears of the people, and let every man ask from his neighbor and every woman from her neighbor, articles of silver and articles of gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.3'>And Jehovah gave the people favor in the eyes of the Egyptians. Moreover the man Moses was very great in the land of Egypt, in the eyes of Pharaohs servants and in the eyes of the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.4'>And Moses said, Thus says Jehovah: About midnight I will go out into the midst of Egypt;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.5'>and every firstborn in the land of Egypt shall die, from the firstborn of Pharaoh who sits on his throne, even to the firstborn of the female servant who is behind the mill, and every firstborn of the animals.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.6'>And there shall be a great cry throughout all the land of Egypt, such as was not like it before, nor shall be like it again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.7'>But against the children of Israel shall not a single dog move its tongue, against man or beast, that you may know that Jehovah makes a separation between Egypt and Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.8'>And all these your servants shall come down to me and prostrate themselves to me, saying, Get out, you and all the people at your feet! After that I will go out. And he went out from Pharaoh in burning anger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.9'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Pharaoh will not heed you, so that My signs may be multiplied in the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.11.10'>And Moses and Aaron did all these signs before Pharaoh; and Jehovah hardened Pharaohs heart, and he did not let the children of Israel go out of his land.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.12'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses and Aaron in the land of Egypt, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.2'>This month shall be to you the beginning of months; it shall be the first month of the year to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.3'>Speak to all the congregation of Israel, saying: On the tenth day of this month every man shall take for himself a lamb, according to the house of his father, a lamb for a house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.4'>And if the house is too small for the lamb, let him and his neighbor next to his house take it according to the number of souls; according to each mans eating you shall reckon it for the lamb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.5'>Your lamb shall be whole, a male of the first year. You may take it from the sheep or from the goats.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.6'>And you shall keep it until the fourteenth day of the same month. Then the whole assembly of the congregation of Israel shall kill it within the evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.7'>And they shall take some of the blood and put it upon the two doorposts and upon the lintel of the houses where they eat it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.8'>And they shall eat the flesh in that night; roasted with fire, with unleavened bread and with bitter herbs they shall eat it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.9'>Do not eat it raw, nor cooked with boiling in water, but roasted with fire; its head with its legs and its entrails.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.10'>And you shall let none of it remain until morning; and whatever remains of it until morning you shall burn with fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.11'>And thus you shall eat it: with your loins girded, your sandals on your feet, and your staff in your hand. And you shall eat it in haste. It is Passover unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.12'>For I will pass through the land of Egypt this night, and will strike every firstborn in the land of Egypt, both man and beast; and against all the gods of Egypt I will execute judgment. I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.13'>And the blood shall be a sign unto you on the houses where you are. And when I see the blood, I will pass over you; and the plague shall not be upon you to destroy you when I strike the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.14'>And this day shall be to you a memorial; and you shall keep it as a feast unto Jehovah throughout your generations. You shall keep it as a feast by a perpetual ordinance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.15'>Seven days you shall eat unleavened bread. On the first day you shall remove leaven from your houses. For whoever eats anything leavened from the first day until the seventh day, that soul shall be cut off from Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.16'>On the first day there shall be a holy convocation, and on the seventh day there shall be a holy convocation for you. No manner of work shall be done on them; except for each soul for eating; that only may be done by you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.17'>And you shall observe Unleavened Bread, for on this same day I have brought your armies out of the land of Egypt. Therefore you shall observe this day throughout your generations as a perpetual ordinance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.18'>In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month at evening, you shall eat unleavened bread, until the twenty-first day of the month, at evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.19'>For seven days no leaven shall be found in your houses, for whoever eats what is leavened, that soul shall be cut off from the congregation of Israel, whether he is a sojourner or a native of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.20'>You shall eat nothing leavened; in all your dwellings you shall eat unleavened bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.21'>Then Moses summoned all the elders of Israel and said to them, Draw out and take lambs for yourselves according to your families, and kill the Passover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.22'>And you shall take a bunch of hyssop, dip it in the blood that is in the basin, and apply the lintel and the two doorposts with the blood that is in the basin. And none of you shall go out of the door of his house until morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.23'>For Jehovah will pass through to strike Egypt; and when He sees the blood on the lintel and on the two doorposts, Jehovah will pass over the door and not allow the destroyer to come into your houses to strike you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.24'>And you shall observe this matter as an ordinance for you and your sons perpetually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.25'>And it shall come to pass when you come to the land which Jehovah shall give you, just as He promised, that you shall keep this service.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.26'>And it shall be, when your children say to you, What do you mean by this service?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.27'>that you shall say, It is the Passover sacrifice of Jehovah, who passed over the houses of the children of Israel in Egypt when He struck Egypt and delivered our houses. So the people bowed down and prostrated themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.28'>And the sons of Israel departed and did as Jehovah had commanded Moses and Aaron; so they did.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.29'>And it came to pass at midnight that Jehovah struck every firstborn in the land of Egypt, from the firstborn of Pharaoh who sat on his throne to the firstborn of the captive who was in the prison house, and every firstborn of livestock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.30'>And Pharaoh arose in the night, he, all his servants, and all the Egyptians; and there was a great outcry in Egypt, for there was not a house where there was not one who died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.31'>And he summoned Moses and Aaron by night, and said, Arise, go out from among my people, both you and the children of Israel. And go, serve Jehovah as you have said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.32'>Also take your flocks and your herds, as you have said, and be gone; and bless me also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.33'>And the Egyptians prevailed upon the people, that they might send them out of the land in haste. For they thought, We shall all die!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.34'>And the people took their dough before it was leavened, having their kneading bowls bound up in their clothes on their shoulders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.35'>And the children of Israel had done according to the word of Moses, and they asked from the Egyptians articles of silver, articles of gold, and clothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.36'>And Jehovah had given the people favor in the eyes of the Egyptians, so that they granted their requests. Thus they plundered the Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.37'>And the children of Israel journeyed from Rameses to Succoth, about six hundred thousand men on foot, besides children.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.38'>And a mixed multitude also went up with them, and flocks and herds; exceedingly many cattle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.39'>And they baked unleavened cakes from the dough which they had brought out of Egypt; for it was not leavened, because they were driven out of Egypt and could not delay, nor had they prepared food for themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.40'>Now the time the children of Israel who dwelt in Egypt remained there was four hundred and thirty years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.41'>And it came to pass at the end of the four hundred and thirty years, on the same day it came to pass, that all the armies of Jehovah went out from the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.42'>It is a night of observance unto Jehovah for bringing them out of the land of Egypt. This is that night of Jehovah, an observance for all the children of Israel throughout their generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.43'>And Jehovah said to Moses and Aaron, This is the ordinance of the Passover: No son of a foreigner shall eat of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.44'>But every mans servant who is bought for money, when you have circumcised him, then he may eat of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.45'>A sojourner and a hired servant shall not eat of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.46'>In one house shall it be eaten; you shall not carry any of the flesh outside the house, nor shall you break any of its bones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.47'>All the congregation of Israel shall observe it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.48'>And when a sojourner stays with you and wishes to keep the Passover unto Jehovah, let every male of his be circumcised, and then let him draw near to observe it; and he shall be as a native of the land. For no uncircumcised person shall eat it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.49'>One law shall be for the native, and for the sojourner who stays among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.50'>Thus all the children of Israel did; as Jehovah commanded Moses and Aaron, so they did.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.12.51'>And it came to pass on the same day, that Jehovah brought the children of Israel out of the land of Egypt according to their armies.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.13'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.2'>Consecrate unto Me every firstborn, whatever opens the womb among the children of Israel, both of man and beast; it is Mine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.3'>And Moses said to the people: Remember this day in which you went out of Egypt, out of the house of bondage; for by strength of hand Jehovah has brought you out from here. Nothing leavened shall be eaten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.4'>On this day you are going out, in the month Abib.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.5'>And it shall be, when Jehovah brings you into the land of the Canaanites and the Hittites and the Amorites and the Hivites and the Jebusites, which He swore to your fathers to give you, a land flowing with milk and honey, that you shall do this service in this month.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.6'>Seven days you shall eat unleavened bread, and on the seventh day there shall be a feast unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.7'>Unleavened bread shall be eaten seven days. And nothing leavened shall be seen among you, nor shall leaven be seen among you in all your territories.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.8'>And you shall make known to your son in that day, saying, This is because of what Jehovah did for me when I came up out of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.9'>It shall be for a sign to you on your hand and as a memorial between your eyes, that the Law of Jehovah may be in your mouth; for with a strong hand Jehovah has brought you out of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.10'>You shall therefore keep this ordinance in its season year after year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.11'>And it shall be, when Jehovah brings you into the land of the Canaanites, as He swore to you and your fathers, and gives it to you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.12'>that you shall devote unto Jehovah all that open the womb: every firstborn offspring from an animal which you have; the males belong to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.13'>But every firstborn of a donkey you shall redeem with a lamb; and if you will not redeem it, then you shall break its neck. And every firstborn of man among your children you shall redeem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.14'>And it shall be, when your son asks you in time to come, saying, What is this? that you shall say to him, By strength of hand Jehovah brought us out of Egypt, from the house of bondage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.15'>And it came to pass, when Pharaoh was stubborn about letting us go, that Jehovah killed every firstborn in the land of Egypt, both the firstborn of man and the firstborn of beast. Therefore I sacrifice unto Jehovah every male that opens the womb, but every firstborn of my sons I redeem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.16'>And it shall be for a sign on your hand and as frontlets between your eyes, for by strength of hand Jehovah has brought us forth out of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.17'>And it came to pass, when Pharaoh had let the people go, that God did not lead them by way of the land of the Philistines, although that was near; for God thought, Lest perhaps the people change their minds when they see war, and return to Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.18'>So God led the people around by way of the wilderness of the Red Sea. And the children of Israel went up in battle array out of the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.19'>And Moses took the bones of Joseph with him, for he had sworn the sons of Israel to oath saying, God will attend to visit you, and you shall bring up my bones from here with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.20'>So they took their journey from Succoth and camped in Etham at the edge of the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.21'>And Jehovah went before them by day in a pillar of cloud to lead the way, and by night in a pillar of fire to shine on them, to go by day and night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.13.22'>The pillar of cloud by day and the pillar of fire by night did not depart from before the people.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.14'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.2'>Speak to the children of Israel, that they return and camp before Pi Hahiroth, between Migdol and the sea, opposite Baal Zephon; you shall camp before it by the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.3'>For Pharaoh will say of the children of Israel, They are perplexed by the land; the wilderness has closed them in.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.4'>And I will harden Pharaohs heart, so that he will pursue them; and I will glorify Myself over Pharaoh and over all his army, that the Egyptians may know that I am Jehovah. And they did so.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.5'>And it was told the king of Egypt that the people had fled, and the heart of Pharaoh and his servants was turned against the people; and they said, Why have we done this, that we have let Israel go from serving us?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.6'>And he made ready his chariot and took his people with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.7'>And he took six hundred choice chariots, and all the chariots of Egypt with officers over every one of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.8'>And Jehovah hardened the heart of Pharaoh king of Egypt, and he pursued the children of Israel; and the children of Israel went out with a high hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.9'>And the Egyptians pursued them, all the horses and chariots of Pharaoh, his horsemen and his army, and overtook them camping by the sea beside Pi Hahiroth, before Baal Zephon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.10'>And when Pharaoh drew near, the children of Israel lifted up their eyes, and behold, the Egyptians were pulling up after them. And they were greatly afraid, and the children of Israel cried out unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.11'>And they said unto Moses, Because there were no graves in Egypt, have you taken us away to die in the wilderness? Why have you dealt so with us, to bring us up out of Egypt?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.12'>Was this not the word we spoke to you in Egypt, saying, Let us alone that we may serve the Egyptians? For it would have been better for us to serve the Egyptians than to die in the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.13'>And Moses said to the people, Do not be afraid. Take your stand, and see the salvation of Jehovah, which He will accomplish for you today. For the Egyptians whom you see today, you shall not see again forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.14'>Jehovah will fight for you, and you shall keep silent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.15'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Why do you cry out to Me? Speak to the children of Israel that they set out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.16'>And lift up your staff, and stretch out your hand over the sea and divide it. And the children of Israel shall go on dry ground through the midst of the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.17'>And behold, I will harden the hearts of the Egyptians, and they shall follow them. And I will glorify Myself over Pharaoh and over all his army, his chariots, and his horsemen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.18'>And the Egyptians shall know that I am Jehovah, when I have glorified Myself over Pharaoh, his chariots, and his horsemen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.19'>And the Angel of God, who went before the camp of Israel, moved and went behind them; and the pillar of cloud went from before them and stood behind them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.20'>And it came between the camp of the Egyptians and the camp of Israel. Thus it was a cloud and darkness to the one, and it gave light by night to the other, so that the one did not come near the other all that night.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.21'>And Moses stretched out his hand over the sea; and Jehovah caused the sea to go back by a strong east wind all that night, and made the sea into dry land, and the waters were divided.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.22'>So the children of Israel went into the midst of the sea on the dry ground, and the waters were a wall to them on their right hand and on their left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.23'>And the Egyptians pursued and went after them into the midst of the sea, all Pharaohs horses, his chariots, and his horsemen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.24'>And it came to pass in the morning watch, that Jehovah looked down upon the camp of the Egyptians through the pillar of fire and cloud, and He confused the camp of the Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.25'>And He took off their chariot wheels, so that they drove them with difficulty; and the Egyptians said, Let us flee from the face of Israel, for Jehovah is fighting for them against the Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.26'>Then Jehovah said unto Moses, Stretch out your hand over the sea, that the waters may come back upon the Egyptians, upon their chariots, and upon their horsemen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.27'>And Moses stretched out his hand over the sea; and when it turned to daybreak, the sea returned to normal, while the Egyptians were fleeing into it. And Jehovah shook out the Egyptians into the midst of the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.28'>And the waters returned and covered the chariots, the horsemen, and all the army of Pharaoh that came into the sea after them. Not so much as one of them remained.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.29'>But the children of Israel had walked upon dry ground in the midst of the sea, and the waters were a wall to them on their right hand and on their left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.30'>Thus Jehovah saved Israel that day out of the hand of the Egyptians, and Israel saw the Egyptians dead on the seashore.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.14.31'>And Israel saw the great hand which Jehovah had dealt against Egypt. And the people feared Jehovah, and believed Jehovah and His servant Moses.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.15'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.1'>Then Moses and the children of Israel sang this song unto Jehovah, and spoke, saying: I will sing unto Jehovah, for He has triumphed gloriously! The horse and its rider He has thrown into the sea!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.2'>Jehovah is my strength and song, and He has become my salvation; He is my Mighty God, and I will adorn Him; my fathers God, and I will exalt Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.3'>Jehovah is a man of war; Jehovah is His name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.4'>Pharaohs chariots and his army He has cast into the sea; his chosen officers also are drowned in the Red Sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.5'>The abyss has covered them; they have sunk to the depths like a stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.6'>Your right hand, O Jehovah, is glorious in power; Your right hand, O Jehovah, has dashed the enemy to pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.7'>And in the greatness of Your majesty You have overthrown those who rose against You; You sent forth Your wrath; it consumed them like stubble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.8'>And with the blast of Your nostrils the waters were heaped up; the flowing waters stood upright like a heap; the depths hardened in the heart of the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.9'>The enemy said, I will pursue, I will overtake, I will divide the spoils; my desire shall be satisfied on them. I will draw my sword, my hand shall destroy them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.10'>You blew with Your wind, the sea covered them; they sank like lead in the mighty waters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.11'>Who is like You, O Jehovah, among the gods? Who is like You, glorious in holiness, fearful in praises, doing wonders?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.12'>You stretched out Your right hand; the earth swallowed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.13'>You in Your mercy have led forth the people whom You have redeemed; You have guided them in Your strength unto Your holy habitation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.14'>The people have heard and are afraid; anguish has taken hold of the inhabitants of Philistia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.15'>Then the chiefs of Edom have been dismayed; the mighty men of Moab, trembling takes hold of them; all the inhabitants of Canaan have melted away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.16'>Fear and dread falls upon them; by the greatness of Your arm they are as still as a stone, till Your people pass over, O Jehovah, till the people whom You have redeemed pass over.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.17'>You bring them in and plant them in the mountain of Your inheritance, in the place, O Jehovah, which You have made for Your own dwelling, the sanctuary, O Jehovah, which Your hands have established.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.18'>Jehovah reigns from everlasting and forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.19'>For the horses of Pharaoh went with his chariots and his horsemen into the sea, and Jehovah brought back the waters of the sea upon them. But the children of Israel have walked on dry ground in the midst of the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.20'>And Miriam the prophetess, the sister of Aaron, took the timbrel in her hand; and all the women went out after her with timbrels and with dances.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.21'>And Miriam answered them: Sing unto Jehovah, for He has risen up to be exalted! The horse and its rider He has thrown into the sea!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.22'>And Moses brought Israel from the Red Sea. And they went out into the Wilderness of Shur, and they went three days in the wilderness and found no water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.23'>And when they came to Marah, they could not drink the waters of Marah, for they were bitter. Therefore the name of it was called Marah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.24'>And the people grumbled against Moses, saying, What shall we drink?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.25'>And he cried out unto Jehovah, and Jehovah showed him a tree. When he cast it into the waters, the waters were made sweet. There He made a statute and an ordinance for them. And there He tested them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.26'>and said: If you diligently heed the voice of Jehovah your God and do what is right in His eyes, give ear to His commandments and keep all His statutes, I will put none of the diseases on you which I have brought upon the Egyptians. For I am Jehovah who heals you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.15.27'>And they came to Elim, where there were twelve springs of water and seventy palm trees; so they camped there by the waters.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.16'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.1'>And they journeyed from Elim, and all the congregation of the children of Israel came to the Wilderness of Sin, which is between Elim and Sinai, on the fifteenth day of the second month after they departed from the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.2'>And the whole congregation of the children of Israel grumbled against Moses and Aaron in the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.3'>And the children of Israel said to them, Oh, that we had died at the hand of Jehovah in the land of Egypt, when we sat by the pots of flesh and when we ate bread to the full! For you have brought us out into this wilderness to kill this whole assembly with hunger.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.4'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Behold, I will rain bread from the heavens for you. And the people shall go out and gather in this matter day by day, that I may test them, whether they will walk in My Law or not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.5'>And it shall be on the sixth day that they shall prepare what they bring in, and it shall be twice as much as they gather day by day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.6'>And Moses and Aaron said to all the children of Israel, At evening you shall know that Jehovah has brought you out of the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.7'>And in the morning you shall see the glory of Jehovah; for He hears your murmuring against Jehovah. But what are we, that you grumble against us?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.8'>And Moses said, You shall see when Jehovah gives you flesh to eat in the evening, and in the morning bread to the full; for Jehovah hears your murmurings which you grumble against Him. And what are we? Your murmurings are not against us but against Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.9'>And Moses spoke to Aaron, Say to all the congregation of the children of Israel, Come near before Jehovah, for He has heard your murmurings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.10'>And it came to pass, as Aaron spoke to the whole congregation of the children of Israel, that they turned and looked toward the wilderness, and behold, the glory of Jehovah appeared in the cloud.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.11'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.12'>I have heard the murmurings of the children of Israel. Speak to them, saying, At evening you shall eat flesh, and in the morning you shall be filled with bread. And you shall know that I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.13'>And it came to pass that quails came up at evening and covered the camp, and in the morning there was a layer of dew all around the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.14'>And when the layer of dew lifted, there, on the surface of the wilderness, were small flakes, as fine as frost on the ground.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.15'>And when the children of Israel saw it, they said to one another, Manna? For they did not know what it was. And Moses said to them, This is the bread which Jehovah has given you for food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.16'>This is the thing which Jehovah has commanded: Let every man gather up food for each mouth, one omer per head; according to the number of souls let every man take for those in his tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.17'>And the children of Israel did so and gathered, some more, some less.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.18'>And when they measured it with the omer, he who gathered much had nothing left over, and he who gathered little had no lack. They gathered according to the food for each mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.19'>And Moses said, Let no one leave any of it till morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.20'>Nevertheless they did not heed Moses; but some of them left part of it until morning, and it bred worms and stunk. And Moses was furious with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.21'>So they gathered it every morning, every man the food for his mouth. And when the sun became hot, it melted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.22'>And it came to pass on the sixth day, that they gathered twice as much bread, two omers for each one. And all the leaders of the congregation came and reported to Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.23'>And he said to them, This is what Jehovah has said: Tomorrow is a rest, a holy Sabbath unto Jehovah. Bake what you will bake today, and boil what you will boil; and lay up for yourselves all that remains, to be kept until morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.24'>So they laid it up till morning, as Moses commanded; and it did not stink, nor were there any worms in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.25'>Then Moses said, Eat that today, for today is a Sabbath unto Jehovah; today you will not find it in the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.26'>Six days you shall gather it, but on the seventh day, which is the Sabbath, there will be none.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.27'>And it happened that some of the people went out on the seventh day to gather, and they found none.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.28'>And Jehovah said to Moses, How long do you refuse to keep My commandments and My Laws?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.29'>Pay attention! For Jehovah has given you the Sabbath; therefore He gives you on the sixth day bread for two days. Let every man remain in his place; let no man go out of his place on the seventh day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.30'>So the people rested on the seventh day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.31'>And the house of Israel called its name Manna. And it was like white coriander seed, and the taste of it was like wafers made with honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.32'>Then Moses said, This is the thing which Jehovah has commanded: Fill an omer with it, to be kept for your generations, that they may see the bread with which I fed you in the wilderness, when I brought you out of the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.33'>And Moses said to Aaron, Take a pot and put an omer full of manna in it, and lay it up before Jehovah, to be kept for your generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.34'>As Jehovah commanded Moses, so Aaron laid it up before the Testimony, to be kept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.35'>And the children of Israel ate manna forty years, until they came to an inhabited land; they ate manna until they came into the borders of the land of Canaan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.16.36'>Now an omer is one-tenth of an ephah.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.17'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.1'>And all the congregation of the children of Israel set out on their journey from the Wilderness of Sin, at the mouth of Jehovah, and camped in Rephidim; and there was no water for the people to drink.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.2'>Therefore the people quarreled with Moses, and said, Give us water, that we may drink. And Moses said to them, Why do you quarrel with me? Why do you tempt Jehovah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.3'>And the people thirsted there for water, and the people grumbled against Moses, and said, Why is it you have brought us up out of Egypt, to kill us and our children and our livestock with thirst?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.4'>And Moses cried out to Jehovah, saying, What shall I do with this people? They are almost ready to stone me!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.5'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Pass over before the people, and take with you some of the elders of Israel. Also take in your hand your staff with which you struck the river, and go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.6'>Behold, I will stand before you there on the rock in Horeb; and you shall strike the rock, and water will come out of it, that the people may drink. And Moses did so before the eyes of the elders of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.7'>And he called the name of the place Massah and Meribah, because of the quarreling of the children of Israel, and because they tempted Jehovah, saying, Is Jehovah in our midst or not?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.8'>And Amalek came and fought against Israel in Rephidim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.9'>And Moses said to Joshua, Choose some men and go fight against Amalek. Tomorrow I will stand on the top of the hill with the staff of God in my hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.10'>So Joshua did as Moses said to him, to fight against Amalek. And Moses, Aaron, and Hur went up to the top of the hill.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.11'>And so it was, when Moses held up his hand, that Israel prevailed; and when he let down his hand, Amalek prevailed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.12'>But Moses hands became heavy; so they took a stone and put it under him, and he sat on it. And Aaron and Hur supported his hands, one on one side, and the other on the other side; and his hands were steady until the going down of the sun.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.13'>And Joshua defeated Amalek and his people with the edge of the sword.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.14'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Write this for a memorial in the book and recount it in the ears of Joshua, that I will utterly blot out the remembrance of Amalek from under the heavens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.15'>And Moses built an altar and called its name, Jehovah-My-Banner;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.17.16'>saying, Because Jehovah has sworn with His hand on the throne: Jehovah is at war with Amalek from generation to generation.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.18'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.1'>And Jethro, the priest of Midian, Moses father-in-law, heard all that God had done for Moses and for His people Israel; that Jehovah had brought Israel out of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.2'>And Jethro, Moses father-in-law, took Zipporah, Moses wife (after Moses had sent her away),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.3'>with her two sons, of whom the name of one was Gershom (for he said, I have been a sojourner in a foreign land)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.4'>and the name of the other was Eliezer (for he said, The God of my father was my help, and delivered me from the sword of Pharaoh);</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.5'>and Jethro, Moses father-in-law, came with his sons and his wife to Moses in the wilderness, where he was encamped at the mountain of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.6'>And he said to Moses, I, your father-in-law Jethro, am coming to you with your wife and her two sons with her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.7'>And Moses went out to meet his father-in-law, bowed down, and kissed him. And they asked each other about their welfare, and they went into the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.8'>And Moses told his father-in-law all that Jehovah had done to Pharaoh and to the Egyptians on account of Israel, all the distress that they had encountered along the way, and how Jehovah had delivered them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.9'>And Jethro rejoiced for all the good which Jehovah had done for Israel, whom He had delivered out of the hand of the Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.10'>And Jethro said, Blessed be Jehovah, who has delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians and out of the hand of Pharaoh, and who has delivered the people from under the hand of the Egyptians.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.11'>Now I know that Jehovah is greater than all the gods; for in the very things in which they behaved proudly, He was above them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.12'>And Jethro, Moses father-in-law, took a burnt offering and sacrifices unto God. And Aaron came with all the elders of Israel to eat bread with Moses father-in-law before God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.13'>And so it was, on the next day, that Moses sat to judge the people; and the people stood before Moses from morning until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.14'>And when Moses father-in-law saw all that he did for the people, he said, What is this thing that you are doing for the people? Why do you alone sit, and all the people stand before you from morning until evening?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.15'>And Moses said to his father-in-law, Because the people come to me to inquire of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.16'>When they have a matter, they come to me, and I judge between a man and his neighbor; and I make known the statutes of God and His Laws.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.17'>And Moses father-in-law said to him, The thing that you do is not good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.18'>Both you and these people who are with you will droop to exhaustion. For this thing is too much of a burden for you; you are not able to do it by yourself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.19'>Listen now to my voice; I will give you counsel, and God be with you: Be before God for the people, so that you may bring the matters to God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.20'>And you shall teach them the statutes and the Laws, and show them the way in which they should walk and the work they should do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.21'>Moreover you shall select from all the people able men, who fear God, men of truth, hating unjust gain; and place these over them as rulers of thousands, rulers of hundreds, rulers of fifties, and rulers of tens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.22'>And let them judge the people at all times. Then it will be that every great matter they shall bring to you, but every small matter they themselves shall judge. So it will be easier for you, and they shall bear the burden with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.23'>If you do this thing, and God so commands you, then you will be able to endure, and all this people will also go to their place in peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.24'>So Moses heeded the voice of his father-in-law and did all that he had said.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.25'>And Moses chose able men out of all Israel, and made them heads over the people: rulers of thousands, rulers of hundreds, rulers of fifties, and rulers of tens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.26'>And they judged the people at all times; the hard matters they brought to Moses, but they judged every small matter themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.18.27'>And Moses sent his father-in-law away, and he departed to his own land.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.19'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.1'>In the third month after the children of Israel had gone out of the land of Egypt, on the same day, they came to the Wilderness of Sinai.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.2'>For they had departed from Rephidim, had come to the Wilderness of Sinai, and camped in the wilderness. And Israel camped there before the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.3'>And Moses went up to God, and Jehovah called to him from the mountain, saying, Thus you shall say to the house of Jacob, and tell the children of Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.4'>You have seen what I did to the Egyptians, and how I bore you on eagles wings and brought you unto Myself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.5'>Now therefore, if you will listen to obey My voice and keep My covenant, then you shall be a special treasure to Me above all people; for all the earth is Mine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.6'>And you shall be unto Me a kingdom of priests and a holy nation. These are the words which you shall speak unto the children of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.7'>And Moses came and summoned the elders of the people, and laid before them all these words which Jehovah had commanded him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.8'>And all the people answered together and said, All that Jehovah has spoken we will do. So Moses brought back the words of the people unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.9'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Behold, I am coming to you in the thick cloud, that the people may hear when I speak with you, and believe you forever. And Moses reported the words of the people unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.10'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Go to the people and sanctify them today and tomorrow, and let them wash their clothes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.11'>And let them be ready for the third day. For on the third day Jehovah will come down upon Mount Sinai in the eyes of all the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.12'>And you shall set bounds for the people all around, saying, Take heed to yourselves that you do not go up to the mountain nor touch its border. Whoever touches the mountain shall be executed to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.13'>Not a hand shall touch him, but he shall be stoned with stones or shot with an arrow; whether man or beast, he shall not live. When the rams horn sounds long, they shall go up to the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.14'>And Moses went down from the mountain to the people and sanctified the people, and they washed their clothes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.15'>And he said to the people, Be ready for the third day; do not approach your wives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.16'>And it came to pass on the third day, in the morning, that there were thunders and lightnings, and a thick cloud on the mountain; and the sound of the shofar was very loud, so that all the people who were in the camp trembled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.17'>And Moses brought the people out of the camp to meet with God, and they stood at the lower part of the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.18'>And Mount Sinai was completely in smoke, because Jehovah had descended upon it in fire. Its smoke ascended like the smoke of a furnace, and the whole mountain quaked greatly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.19'>And when the sound of the shofar continued its sound and became exceedingly loud, Moses spoke, and God answered him by voice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.20'>And Jehovah came down upon Mount Sinai, on the top of the mountain. And Jehovah called Moses to the top of the mountain, and Moses went up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.21'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Go down and warn the people, that they not break through to gaze at Jehovah, and many of them be attacked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.22'>And let the priests who come near Jehovah sanctify themselves, that Jehovah not break forth against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.23'>And Moses said to Jehovah, The people cannot come up to Mount Sinai; for You have warned us, saying, Set bounds around the mountain and consecrate it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.24'>And Jehovah said to him, Away! Go down and then come up, you and Aaron with you. But do not let the priests and the people break through to come up to Jehovah, lest He break forth against them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.19.25'>So Moses went down to the people and spoke to them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.20'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.1'>And God spoke all these words, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.2'>I am Jehovah your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.3'>You shall have no other gods before Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.4'>You shall not make for yourself a graven image, or any likeness of anything in the heavens above, or in the earth beneath, or in the waters under the earth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.5'>you shall not bow down to them nor serve them; for I, Jehovah your God, am a jealous Mighty God, visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the sons to the third and fourth generations of those who hate Me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.6'>but showing goodness to thousands, to those who love Me and keep My commandments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.7'>You shall not take the name of Jehovah your God in vain, for Jehovah will not leave unpunished one who takes His name in vain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.8'>Remember the Sabbath day, to keep it holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.9'>Six days you shall labor and do all your work,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.10'>and the seventh day is the Sabbath of Jehovah your God. In it you shall not do any work; you, nor your son, nor your daughter, nor your male servant, nor your female servant, nor your cattle, nor your sojourner who is within your gates.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.11'>For in six days Jehovah made the heavens and the earth, the sea, and all that is in them, and rested the seventh day. Therefore Jehovah has blessed the Sabbath day and consecrated it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.12'>Honor your father and your mother, that your days may be long upon the land which Jehovah your God is giving you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.13'>You shall not murder.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.14'>You shall not commit adultery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.15'>You shall not steal.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.16'>You shall not testify a witness of falsehood against your neighbor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.17'>You shall not covet your neighbors house; you shall not covet your neighbors wife, nor his male servant, nor his female servant, nor his ox, nor his donkey, nor anything that belongs to your neighbor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.18'>And all the people saw the thunders, the lightning flashes, the sound of the shofar, and the smoking mountain; and when the people saw it, they trembled and stood at a distance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.19'>And they said unto Moses, You speak with us, and we will listen; but let not God speak with us, that we not die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.20'>And Moses said to the people, Do not fear; for God has come to test you, and that His fear may be before you, that you not sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.21'>And the people stood at a distance, and Moses drew near the thick darkness where God was.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.22'>And Jehovah said unto Moses, Thus you shall say to the children of Israel: You have seen that I have spoken with you from the heavens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.23'>You shall not make for yourselves, along with Me, gods of silver or gods of gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.24'>An altar of earth you shall make for Me, and you shall sacrifice on it your burnt offerings and your peace offerings, your sheep and your oxen. In every place where I cause My name to be remembered, I will come to you, and I will bless you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.25'>And if you make Me an altar of stone, you shall not build it of hewn stone; for if you wield your tool upon it, you defile it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.20.26'>Nor shall you go up by steps to My altar, that your nakedness may not be exposed on it.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.21'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.1'>Now these are the judgments which you shall set before them:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.2'>If you buy a Hebrew servant, he shall serve six years; and in the seventh he shall go out free without payment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.3'>If he comes in by himself, he shall go out by himself; if he was the husband of a wife, then his wife shall go out with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.4'>If his master gives him a wife, and she has borne him sons or daughters, the wife and her children shall be her masters, and he shall go out by himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.5'>But if the servant answers to say, I love my master, my wife, and my children; I will not go out free,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.6'>then his master shall bring him to God. He shall also bring him to the door, or to the doorpost, and his master shall pierce his ear with an awl; and he shall serve him always.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.7'>And if a man sells his daughter to be a female slave, she shall not go out as the male slaves go out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.8'>If she is disagreeable to the eye of her master, who has betrothed her to himself, then he shall let her be redeemed. He shall have no power to sell her to a foreign people, since he has dealt deceitfully with her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.9'>And if he has betrothed her to his son, he shall deal with her according to the manner of daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.10'>If he takes another wife, he shall not diminish her food, her clothing, and her conjugal rights.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.11'>And if he does not do these three for her, then she shall go out free, without money.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.12'>He who strikes a man so that he dies shall be executed to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.13'>However, if he did not lie in wait, but God allowed the meeting into his hand, then I will appoint for you a place where he may flee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.14'>But if a man comes presumptuously against his neighbor, to kill him by deceit, you shall take him even from My altar, that he may die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.15'>And he who strikes his father or his mother shall be executed to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.16'>He who steals a man and sells him, or if he is found in his hand, shall be executed to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.17'>And he who curses his father or his mother shall be executed to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.18'>If men strive with each other, and one strikes the other with a stone or with his fist, and he does not die but is confined to his bed,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.19'>if he rises again and walks about outside with his staff, then he who struck him shall be acquitted. He shall only pay for the loss of his time, and shall provide for him to be healed of his injuries.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.20'>And if a man beats his male or female servant with a rod, so that he dies under his hand, vengeance shall be taken to avenge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.21'>Nevertheless, if he continues a day or two, vengeance shall not be taken; for he is part of his assets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.22'>If men fight, and strike a pregnant woman, so that the child comes forth, without harm, he shall be punished to pay a fine as the womans husband imposes upon him; and he shall pay according to the assessment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.23'>But if there is harm, then you shall requite soul for soul;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.24'>eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.25'>burn for burn, wound for wound, stripe for stripe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.26'>If a man strikes the eye of his male or female servant, and destroys it, he shall let him go free in exchange for his eye.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.27'>And if he knocks out the tooth of his male or female servant, he shall let him go free for his tooth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.28'>If an ox gores a man or a woman to death, then the ox shall be stoned to death with stones, and its flesh shall not be eaten; but the owner of the ox shall be acquitted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.29'>But if the ox tended to thrust with its horn in times past, and the owner has been given warning, and he has not kept it restrained, so that it has killed a man or a woman, the ox shall be stoned and its owner also shall be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.30'>If a ransom is imposed upon him, then he shall pay to redeem his life, whatever is imposed upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.31'>Whether it has gored a son or gored a daughter, according to this judgment it shall be done unto him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.32'>If the ox gores a male or female servant, he shall give to their master thirty shekels of silver, and the ox shall be stoned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.33'>And if a man opens a pit, or if a man digs a pit and does not cover it, and an ox or a donkey falls into it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.34'>the owner of the pit shall make compensation; he shall give money to the owner, and the dead animal shall be his.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.35'>If one mans ox strikes against the ox of his neighbor, so that it dies, then they shall sell the live ox and divide the money; and the dead ox they shall also divide.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.21.36'>Or if it was known that the ox tended to thrust in time past, and its owner has not kept it restrained, he shall make compensation to pay, ox for ox, and the dead shall be his.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.22'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.1'>If a man steals an ox or a sheep, and slaughters it or sells it, he shall restore five oxen for an ox and four sheep for a sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.2'>If the thief is found breaking in, and he is struck so that he dies, there shall be no blood shed for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.3'>If the sun has risen upon him, there shall be guilt for his bloodshed. He shall make compensation to pay; if he has nothing, then he shall be sold for his theft.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.4'>If the thing stolen is found in his possession alive in his hand, whether it is an ox or donkey or sheep, he shall restore double.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.5'>If a man causes a field or vineyard to be consumed, and lets loose his animal, and it consumes another mans field, he shall make restitution from the best of his own field and the best of his own vineyard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.6'>If fire breaks out and lights upon thorns, so that stacked grain, standing grain, or the field has been consumed, he who kindled the fire shall make compensation to pay.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.7'>If a man delivers to his neighbor money or articles to keep, and it is stolen out of the mans house, if the thief is found, he shall restore double.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.8'>If the thief is not found, then the master of the house shall be brought to the judges to see whether he has put his hand into his neighbors goods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.9'>For any kind of trespass, whether it be an ox, a donkey, a sheep, or clothing, or for any kind of lost item which another says is his, the matter of both of them shall come before the judges; and whomever the judges declare guilty shall restore double to his neighbor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.10'>If a man delivers to his neighbor a donkey, an ox, a sheep, or any animal to keep, and it dies, is hurt, or driven away, no one seeing it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.11'>then an oath of Jehovah shall be between them both, that he has not put his hand into his neighbors goods; and the owner of it shall accept it, and he shall not make it good.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.12'>But if, in fact, it is stolen from him, he shall make restitution to the owner of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.13'>If it is rent and torn to pieces by a beast, then he shall bring it as evidence, and he shall not make good what was torn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.14'>And if a man borrows anything from his neighbor, and it becomes injured or dies, the owner of it not being with it, he shall make compensation to pay.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.15'>If its owner was with it, he shall not make it good; if it was hired, it came for its hire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.16'>If a man seduces a virgin who is not betrothed, and lies with her, he shall give a dowry, the purchase price for her to be his wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.17'>If her father utterly refuses to give her to him, he shall pay money according to the dowry of virgins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.18'>You shall not allow a sorceress to live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.19'>Whoever lies with an animal shall be executed to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.20'>He who sacrifices to any god, except to Jehovah only, he shall be utterly destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.21'>You shall neither mistreat a sojourner nor oppress him, for you were sojourners in the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.22'>You shall not afflict any widow or fatherless child.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.23'>If you afflict them to humiliate them, and they make an outcry to cry out unto Me, I will hear and give heed to their cry;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.24'>and My anger will burn, and I will kill you with the sword; your wives shall be widows, and your children fatherless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.25'>If you lend money to My people who are poor among you, you shall not be like a moneylender to him; you shall not lay interest on him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.26'>If you indeed take your neighbors garment as a pledge, you shall return it to him by the going down of the sun.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.27'>For that is his only covering, it is his garment for his skin. What will he sleep in? And it will be that when he cries out to Me, I will give heed, for I am gracious.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.28'>You shall not curse God, nor curse a chief of your people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.29'>You shall not delay to offer the first of your ripe produce and your juices. The firstborn of your sons you shall give unto Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.30'>Likewise you shall do with your oxen and your sheep. It shall be with its mother seven days; on the eighth day you shall give it unto Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.22.31'>And you shall be holy men unto Me: you shall not eat flesh torn by beasts in the field; you shall throw it to the dogs.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.23'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.1'>You shall not raise a false report. Do not put your hand with the wicked to be an unjust witness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.2'>You shall not follow the majority in doing evil; nor shall you testify in a dispute so as to turn aside after the majority to thrust aside justice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.3'>You shall not show partiality to a poor man in his dispute.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.4'>If you encounter your enemys ox or his donkey going astray, you shall bring it back to restore it to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.5'>If you see the donkey of one who hates you lying under its burden, you shall refrain from leaving it to him; you shall help him set it free.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.6'>You shall not thrust aside the justice of your needy one in his dispute.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.7'>Keep yourself far away from a false matter; do not kill the innocent and righteous. For I will not justify the wicked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.8'>And you shall not take a bribe, for a bribe blinds the clear-sighted and perverts the words of the righteous.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.9'>Also you shall not oppress a sojourner, for you know the soul of a sojourner, because you were sojourners in the land of Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.10'>Six years you shall sow your land and gather in its produce,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.11'>but the seventh year you shall let it rest and lie fallow, that the needy of your people may eat; and what they leave, the beasts of the field may eat. In like manner you shall do with your vineyard and your olive grove.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.12'>Six days you shall do your work, and on the seventh day you shall rest, that your ox and your donkey may rest, and the son of your female servant and the sojourner may be refreshed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.13'>And in all that I have said to you, beware and make no mention of any other gods by name, nor let it be heard from your mouth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.14'>Three times a year you shall keep a feast unto Me:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.15'>You shall keep the Feast of Unleavened Bread (you shall eat unleavened bread seven days, as I have commanded you, at the time appointed in the month of Abib, for in it you came out of Egypt; no one shall appear before Me empty);</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.16'>and the Feast of Harvest, the firstfruits of your labors which you have sown in the field; and the Feast of Ingathering at the end of the year, when you have gathered in your produce from the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.17'>Three times a year all your males shall appear before the Lord Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.18'>You shall not offer the blood of My sacrifice with anything leavened; nor shall the fat of My feast remain until morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.19'>The first of the firstfruits of your land you shall bring into the house of Jehovah your God. You shall not boil a young goat in its mothers milk.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.20'>Behold, I am sending an Angel before you to keep you in the way and to bring you into the place which I have prepared.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.21'>Be on guard before Him and obey His voice; do not grieve Him, for He will not endure your transgressions; for My name is in Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.22'>But if you indeed obey His voice and do all that I speak, then I will be an enemy to your enemies and will afflict those who besiege you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.23'>For My Angel will go before you and bring you in to the Amorites and the Hittites and the Perizzites and the Canaanites and the Hivites and the Jebusites; and I will cut them off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.24'>You shall not bow down to their gods, nor serve them, nor do according to their works; but you shall tear them down to overthrow them, and break and shatter their pillars.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.25'>And you shall serve Jehovah your God, and He will bless your bread and your water. And I will take sickness away from the midst of you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.26'>No one shall suffer miscarriage nor be barren in your land; I will fulfill the number of your days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.27'>I will send My dread before you, I will cause confusion among all the people to whom you come, and will give the neck of all your enemies to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.28'>And I will send hornets before you, which shall drive out the Hivite, the Canaanite, and the Hittite before you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.29'>I will not drive them out before you in one year, that the land not become desolate and the beasts of the field become too numerous for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.30'>Little by little I will drive them out before you, until you are fruitful, and have taken possession of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.31'>And I have set your borders from the Red Sea to the sea of the Philistines, and from the wilderness to the River. For I will deliver up the inhabitants of the land into your hand, and you shall drive them out before you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.32'>You shall not make any covenants with them, nor with their gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.23.33'>They shall not dwell in your land, lest they make you sin against Me. For if you serve their gods, it will surely be a snare to you.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.24'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.1'>And He said to Moses, Come up to Jehovah, you and Aaron, Nadab and Abihu, and seventy of the elders of Israel, and prostrate yourselves from a distance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.2'>And Moses alone shall approach Jehovah, but they shall not approach; nor shall the people go up with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.3'>And Moses came and told the people all the words of Jehovah and all the judgments. And all the people answered with one voice and said, All the words which Jehovah has spoken we will do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.4'>And Moses wrote all the Words of Jehovah. And he arose early in the morning, and built an altar at the base of the mountain, and twelve pillars according to the twelve tribes of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.5'>And he sent young men of the sons of Israel, who offered burnt offerings and slaughtered oxen for sacrifices of peace unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.6'>And Moses took half the blood and put it in basins, and half the blood he sprinkled on the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.7'>And he took the Book of the Covenant and read in the ears of the people. And they said, All that Jehovah has spoken we will do and obey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.8'>And Moses took the blood, sprinkled it on the people, and said, This is the blood of the covenant which Jehovah has made with you according to all these words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.9'>And Moses went up, along with Aaron, Nadab, and Abihu, and seventy of the elders of Israel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.10'>and they saw the God of Israel. And there was under His feet as it were a paved work of sapphire stone, and it was like the essence of the heavens in its clarity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.11'>And He did not let loose His hand against the nobles of the children of Israel. And they saw God, and they ate and drank.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.12'>And Jehovah said unto Moses, Come up to Me on the mountain and be there; and I will give you tablets of stone, and the Law and commandments which I have written, to teach them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.13'>And Moses arose with Joshua who ministered, and Moses went up to the mountain of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.14'>And he said to the elders, Wait here for us until we return to you. Behold, Aaron and Hur, who are rulers, are with you. Whoever has a matter, let him go to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.15'>And Moses went up into the mountain, and a cloud covered the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.16'>And the glory of Jehovah settled down upon Mount Sinai, and the cloud covered it six days. And on the seventh day He summoned Moses out of the midst of the cloud.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.17'>The appearance of the glory of Jehovah was like a consuming fire on the top of the mountain before the eyes of the children of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.24.18'>And Moses went into the midst of the cloud and went up into the mountain. And Moses was on the mountain forty days and forty nights.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.25'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.2'>Speak to the sons of Israel, that they take an offering for Me. From every man whose heart stirs him, you shall take My offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.3'>And this is the offering which you shall take from them: gold, silver, and bronze;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.4'>violet, purple, and scarlet material, fine linen, and goats hair;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.5'>ram skins dyed red, badger skins, and acacia wood;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.6'>oil for the light, and spices for the anointing oil and for the spiced incense;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.7'>onyx stones, and stones to be set in the ephod and in the breastplate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.8'>And let them make Me a sanctuary, that I may dwell among them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.9'>According to all that I show you, the pattern of the tabernacle and the pattern of all its articles, even so you shall do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.10'>And they shall make an ark of acacia wood; two and a half cubits shall be its length, a cubit and a half its width, and a cubit and a half its height.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.11'>And you shall overlay it with pure gold, inside and out you shall overlay it, and shall make on it a molding of gold all around.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.12'>You shall cast four rings of gold for it, and put them on its four feet; two rings shall be on one side, and two rings on the other side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.13'>And you shall make poles of acacia wood, and overlay them with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.14'>You shall put the poles into the rings on the sides of the ark, that the ark may be carried with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.15'>The poles shall be in the rings of the ark; they shall not be removed from it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.16'>And you shall put into the ark the Testimony which I am giving you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.17'>You shall make a mercy seat of pure gold; two and a half cubits shall be its length and a cubit and a half its width.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.18'>And you shall make two cherubim of gold; of hammered work you shall make them at the two ends of the mercy seat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.19'>Make one cherub at one end, and one cherub at the other end; you shall make the cherubim at the two ends of it from one piece with the mercy seat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.20'>And the cherubim shall spread over their wings above, covering the mercy seat with their wings, and their faces one toward another; the faces of the cherubim shall be toward the mercy seat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.21'>You shall put the mercy seat on top of the ark, and in the ark you shall put the Testimony that I will give you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.22'>And there I will meet with you, and I will speak with you from above the mercy seat, from between the two cherubim which are on the ark of the Testimony, everything which I will command you concerning the children of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.23'>You shall also make a table of acacia wood; two cubits shall be its length, a cubit its width, and a cubit and a half its height.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.24'>And you shall overlay it with pure gold, and make a molding of gold all around.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.25'>You shall make for it a rim of a handbreadth all around, and you shall make a gold molding for the rim all around.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.26'>And you shall make for it four rings of gold, and put the rings on the four corners that are at its four legs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.27'>The rings shall be close to the rim, as housings for the poles to carry the table.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.28'>And you shall make the poles of acacia wood, and overlay them with gold, that the table may be carried with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.29'>You shall make its dishes, its pans, its pitchers, and its bowls for pouring. You shall make them of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.30'>And you shall set the Bread of the Presence on the table before Me continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.31'>You shall also make a lampstand of pure gold; the lampstand shall be of hammered work. Its shaft, its branches, its bowls, its bulbs, and flowers shall be one piece.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.32'>And six branches shall come out of its sides: three branches of the lampstand out of one side, and three branches of the lampstand out of the other side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.33'>Three bowls shall be made like almond blossoms on one branch, each with a bulb and a flower, and three bowls made like almond blossoms on the other branch, each with a bulb and a flower; and so for the six branches that come out of the lampstand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.34'>On the lampstand itself shall be four bowls like almond blossoms, each with its bulb and flower.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.35'>And there shall be a bulb under the first two branches of it, a bulb under the second two branches of it, and a bulb under the third two branches of it, according to the six branches that extend from the lampstand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.36'>Their bulbs and their branches shall be of one piece; all of it shall be one hammered piece of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.37'>You shall make seven lamps for it, and they shall arrange its lamps so that they give light in front of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.38'>And its snuffers and snuff dishes shall be of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.39'>It shall be made of a talent of pure gold, with all these utensils.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.25.40'>And see to it that you make them according to the pattern which was shown you on the mountain.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.26'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.1'>Moreover you shall make the tabernacle with ten curtains of fine twisted linen of violet, purple, and scarlet thread; with cherubim of quality workmanship you shall make them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.2'>The length of each curtain shall be twenty-eight cubits, and the width of each curtain four cubits; one measurement for all the curtains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.3'>Five curtains shall be joined to one another, and the other five curtains shall be joined to one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.4'>And you shall make loops of violet material on the edge of the one curtain on the extremity at the joint, and likewise you shall do on the outer edge of the other curtain at the second joint.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.5'>Fifty loops you shall make on the one curtain, and fifty loops you shall make on the edge of the curtain that is on the end of the second joint, that the loops may fit to one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.6'>And you shall make fifty hooks of gold, and join the curtains together with the hooks, so that it may be one tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.7'>You shall also make curtains of goats hair, to be a tent over the tabernacle. You shall make eleven curtains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.8'>The length of each curtain shall be thirty cubits, and the width of each curtain four cubits; one measurement for the eleven curtains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.9'>And you shall join five curtains by themselves and six curtains by themselves, and you shall double over the sixth curtain at the front of the face of the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.10'>You shall make fifty loops on the edge of the curtain that is outermost at the one joint, and fifty loops on the edge of the curtain at the second joint.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.11'>And you shall make fifty bronze hooks, put the hooks into the loops, and join the tent together, that it may be one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.12'>The remnant that remains of the curtains of the tent, the half curtain that remains, shall hang over the back of the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.13'>And a cubit on one side and a cubit on the other side, of what remains of the length of the curtains of the tent, shall hang over the sides of the tabernacle, on this side and on that side, to cover it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.14'>You shall also make a covering of ram skins dyed red for the tent, and a covering of badger skins above that.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.15'>And for the tabernacle you shall make the boards of acacia wood, standing upright.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.16'>Ten cubits shall be the length of a board, and a cubit and a half shall be the width of each board.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.17'>Two tenons shall be in each board to join one to another. Thus you shall do for all the boards of the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.18'>And you shall make the boards for the tabernacle, twenty boards for the south side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.19'>You shall make forty sockets of silver for the twenty boards: two sockets for each of the boards for its two tenons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.20'>And for the second side of the tabernacle, the north side, twenty boards</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.21'>and their forty sockets of silver: two sockets for each of the boards.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.22'>For the side of the tabernacle, westward, you shall make six boards.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.23'>And you shall also make two boards for the two back corners of the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.24'>They shall be joined together at the bottom and they shall be joined together at the top by one ring. Thus it shall be for both of them. They shall be for the two corners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.25'>Thus there shall be eight boards with their sockets of silver; sixteen sockets; two sockets for each board.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.26'>And you shall make bars of acacia wood: five for the boards on one side of the tabernacle,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.27'>five bars for the boards on the other side of the tabernacle, and five bars for the boards of the side of the tabernacle, for the side westward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.28'>The middle bar shall pass through the midst of the boards from end to end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.29'>You shall overlay the boards with gold, make their rings of gold as housings for the bars, and overlay the bars with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.30'>And you shall erect the tabernacle according to the ordinance which you were shown on the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.31'>You shall make a veil of violet, purple, and scarlet thread, and fine twisted linen. It shall be done with cherubim of quality workmanship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.32'>You shall hang it upon four pillars of acacia wood overlaid with gold. Their hooks shall be gold, upon four sockets of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.33'>And you shall hang the veil from the hooks. And you shall bring the ark of the Testimony in there, inside the veil. The veil shall divide for you between the holy and the Holy of Holies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.34'>You shall put the mercy seat upon the ark of the Testimony in the Holy of Holies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.35'>And you shall set the table outside the veil, and the lampstand across from the table on the side of the tabernacle toward the south; and you shall put the table on the north side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.36'>And you shall make a screen for the opening of the tent, of violet, purple, and scarlet thread, and fine twisted linen, the product of skillful weaving.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.26.37'>And you shall make for the screen five pillars of acacia wood, and overlay them with gold; their hooks shall be of gold, and you shall cast five sockets of bronze for them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.27'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.1'>And you shall make an altar of acacia wood, five cubits long and five cubits wide; the altar shall be square; and its height three cubits.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.2'>And you shall make its horns on its four corners; its horns shall be of one piece with it. And you shall overlay it with bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.3'>Also you shall make its pans to receive its ashes, and its shovels and its basins and its forks and its firepans; you shall make all its utensils of bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.4'>You shall make a grating for it, a network of bronze; and on the network you shall make four bronze rings at its four corners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.5'>You shall put it under the rim of the altar beneath, that the network may be midway up the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.6'>And you shall make poles for the altar, poles of acacia wood, and overlay them with bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.7'>And the poles shall be put into the rings, and the poles shall be on the two sides of the altar to carry it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.8'>You shall make it hollow with boards; as it was shown you on the mountain, thus shall they make it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.9'>You shall also make the court of the tabernacle. For the south side there shall be hangings for the court made of fine twisted linen, one hundred cubits long for one side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.10'>And its twenty pillars and their twenty sockets shall be bronze. The hooks of the pillars and their bands shall be silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.11'>Likewise along the length of the north side there shall be hangings one hundred cubits long, with its twenty pillars and their twenty sockets of bronze, and the hooks of the pillars and their bands of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.12'>And along the width of the court on the west side shall be hangings of fifty cubits, with their ten pillars and their ten sockets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.13'>The width of the court on the east side shall be fifty cubits.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.14'>The hangings on one side of the gate shall be fifteen cubits, with their three pillars and their three sockets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.15'>And on the other side shall be hangings of fifteen cubits, with their three pillars and their three sockets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.16'>For the gate of the court there shall be a screen twenty cubits long, of violet, purple, and scarlet thread, and fine twisted linen, the product of skillful weaving; with four pillars and four sockets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.17'>All the pillars around the court shall have bands of silver; their hooks of silver and their sockets of bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.18'>The length of the court shall be one hundred cubits, the width fifty to fifty, and the height five cubits, made of fine twisted linen, and its sockets of bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.19'>All the utensils of the tabernacle for all its service, all its pegs, and all the pegs of the court, shall be of bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.20'>And you shall command the children of Israel that they bring you pure oil of beaten olives for the light, to cause the flame of the lamp to ascend continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.27.21'>In the tent of meeting, outside the veil which is before the Testimony, Aaron and his sons shall arrange it from evening until morning before Jehovah. It shall be a perpetual statute to their generations on behalf of the children of Israel.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.28'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.1'>Now take Aaron your brother, and his sons with him, from among the sons of Israel, that he may serve Me as priest, Aaron and Aarons sons: Nadab, Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.2'>And you shall make holy garments for Aaron your brother, for glory and for beauty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.3'>And you shall speak to all who are wise-hearted, whom I have filled with the spirit of wisdom, that they may make Aarons garments, to consecrate him to serve as priest unto Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.4'>And these are the garments which they shall make: a breastplate, an ephod, a robe, a tunic of woven work, a turban, and a sash. And they shall make holy garments for Aaron your brother and his sons, to serve as priests unto Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.5'>They shall take the gold, violet, purple, and scarlet thread, and fine linen,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.6'>and they shall make the ephod of gold, violet, purple, and scarlet thread, and fine twisted linen; the product of skillful work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.7'>It shall have two shoulder pieces joined at its two edges, and thus it shall be joined together.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.8'>And the intricately woven band of the ephod, which is on it, shall be of the same workmanship, of gold, violet, purple, and scarlet thread, and fine twisted linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.9'>And you shall take two onyx stones and engrave on them the names of the sons of Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.10'>six of their names on one stone, and six names on the other stone, according to their birth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.11'>With the work of an engraver in stone, like the engravings of a signet, you shall engrave the two stones with the names of the sons of Israel. You shall set them in settings of gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.12'>And you shall put the two stones on the shoulder pieces of the ephod as memorial stones for the sons of Israel. Thus Aaron shall bear their names before Jehovah on his two shoulders as a memorial.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.13'>You shall also make settings of gold,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.14'>and you shall make two chains of pure gold like the product of braiding, and fasten the braided chains to the settings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.15'>You shall make the breastplate of judgment. The product of skillful work, according to the workmanship of the ephod you shall make it: of gold, violet, purple, and scarlet thread, and fine twisted linen, you shall make it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.16'>It shall be folded into a square: a span shall be its length, and a span shall be its width.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.17'>And you shall put settings of stones in it, four rows of stones: The first row shall be a ruby, a topaz, and an emerald; this the first row.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.18'>The second row shall be a turquoise, a sapphire, and a diamond;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.19'>the third row, a jacinth, an agate, and an amethyst;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.20'>and the fourth row, a beryl, an onyx, and a jasper. They shall be set in gold settings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.21'>And the stones shall have the names of the sons of Israel, twelve according to their names, like the engravings of a signet, each one with its own name, according to the twelve tribes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.22'>You shall make chains for the breastplate, the work of twisted cords of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.23'>And you shall make two rings of gold for the breastplate, and put the two rings on the two ends of the breastplate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.24'>And you shall put the two cords of gold in the two rings which are on the ends of the breastplate;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.25'>and the other two ends of the two cords you shall fasten to the two settings, and put them on the shoulder pieces of the ephod in the front.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.26'>And you shall make two rings of gold, and put them on the two ends of the breastplate, on the edge of it, on the inner side of the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.27'>And two rings of gold you shall make, and put them on the two shoulder pieces, underneath the ephod toward its front, right at the seam above the intricately woven band of the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.28'>And they shall bind the breastplate by means of its rings to the rings of the ephod, with a violet cord, so that it is above the intricately woven band of the ephod, and so that the breastplate does not come loose from the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.29'>And Aaron shall bear the names of the sons of Israel on the breastplate of judgment over his heart, when he goes into the holy place, as a memorial before Jehovah continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.30'>And you shall put in the breastplate of judgment the Urim and the Thummim, and they shall be over Aarons heart when he goes in before Jehovah. Thus Aaron shall bear the judgment of the children of Israel over his heart before Jehovah continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.31'>And you shall make the robe of the ephod all of violet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.32'>There shall be an opening for his head in the middle of it; it shall have an edge of woven work all around its opening, like the opening in a coat of mail, so that it does not tear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.33'>And on its hem you shall make pomegranates of violet, purple, and scarlet, all around its hem, and bells of gold between them all around:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.34'>a golden bell and a pomegranate, a golden bell and a pomegranate, on the hem of the robe all around.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.35'>And it shall be upon Aaron when he ministers, and its sound shall be heard when he goes into the holy place before Jehovah and when he comes out, that he not die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.36'>You shall also make a plate of pure gold and engrave on it, like the engravings of a signet: HOLY TO JEHOVAH.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.37'>And you shall put it on a violet cord, that it may be on the turban; it shall be on the front of the turban.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.38'>Thus it shall be on Aarons forehead, that Aaron may bear the iniquity of the holy things which the children of Israel consecrate in all their holy gifts; and it shall be on his forehead continually, that they may be accepted before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.39'>You shall weave the tunic of fine linen, you shall make the turban of fine linen, and you shall make the sash a product of skillful weaving.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.40'>And for Aarons sons you shall make tunics, and you shall make sashes for them. And you shall make turbans for them, for glory and beauty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.41'>Thus you shall clothe Aaron your brother with them, and his sons with him. You shall anoint them, confirm their hands, and consecrate them, that they may serve Me as priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.42'>And you shall make for them linen trousers to cover their naked flesh; they shall reach from the hips to the thighs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.28.43'>And they shall be on Aaron and on his sons when they come into the tent of meeting, or when they come near the altar to minister in the holy place, that they not bear iniquity and die. It shall be a perpetual statute to him and his seed after him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.29'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.1'>And this is what you shall do to them to consecrate them to serve Me as priests: Take one young bull and two rams that are whole,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.2'>and unleavened bread, unleavened cakes mixed with oil, and unleavened wafers anointed with oil; you shall make them of fine wheat flour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.3'>You shall put them into one basket and bring them in the basket, with the bull and the two rams.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.4'>And Aaron and his sons you shall bring to the door of the tent of meeting, and you shall wash them with water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.5'>And you shall take the garments, put the tunic on Aaron, and the robe of the ephod, the ephod, and the breastplate, and gird him with the intricately woven band of the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.6'>You shall put the turban on his head, and put the holy crown upon the turban.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.7'>And you shall take the anointing oil, pour it upon his head, and anoint him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.8'>And you shall bring his sons and put tunics on them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.9'>And you shall gird them with sashes, Aaron and his sons, and bind the turbans on them. The priesthood shall be theirs for a perpetual statute. Thus you shall confirm the hands of Aaron and his sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.10'>You shall also have the bull brought before the tent of meeting, and Aaron and his sons shall lay their hands on the head of the bull.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.11'>And you shall kill the bull before Jehovah, by the door of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.12'>You shall take some of the blood of the bull and put it on the horns of the altar with your finger, and pour out all the blood at the base of the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.13'>And you shall take all the fat that covers the entrails, the fatty lobe attached to the liver, and the two kidneys and the fat that is on them, and burn them on the altar like incense.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.14'>But the flesh of the bull, with its skin and its dung, you shall burn with fire outside the camp. It is a sin offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.15'>You shall also take one ram, and Aaron and his sons shall lay their hands on the head of the ram;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.16'>and you shall kill the ram, and you shall take its blood and sprinkle it all around on the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.17'>And you shall cut the ram in pieces, wash its entrails and its legs, and put them with its pieces and with its head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.18'>And you shall burn the whole ram on the altar like incense. It is a burnt offering unto Jehovah; it is a soothing aroma, an offering by fire unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.19'>You shall also take the other ram, and Aaron and his sons shall lay their hands on the head of the ram.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.20'>And you shall kill the ram, and take some of its blood and put it on the tip of the right ear of Aaron and on the tip of the right ear of his sons, on the thumb of their right hand and on the big toe of their right foot, and sprinkle the blood all around on the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.21'>And you shall take some of the blood that is on the altar, and some of the anointing oil, and sprinkle it on Aaron and on his garments, on his sons and on the garments of his sons with him. Thus he and his garments shall be consecrated, and his sons and his sons garments with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.22'>Also you shall take the fat of the ram, the fat tail, the fat that covers the entrails, the fatty lobe attached to the liver, the two kidneys and the fat on them, the right thigh (for it is a ram of ordination),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.23'>one loaf of bread, one cake made with oil, and one wafer from the basket of the unleavened bread that is before Jehovah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.24'>and you shall put all these in the hands of Aaron and in the hands of his sons, and you shall wave them as a wave offering before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.25'>And you shall take them from their hands and burn them on the altar like incense as a burnt offering, as a soothing aroma before Jehovah. It is an offering by fire unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.26'>And you shall take the breast of the ram of Aarons ordination and wave it as a wave offering before Jehovah; and it shall be your portion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.27'>And from the ram of the ordination you shall consecrate the breast of the wave offering which is waved, and the thigh of the heave offering which is raised, of that which is for Aaron and of that which is for his sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.28'>It shall be for Aaron and his sons from the children of Israel as a perpetual statute; for it is a heave offering. It shall be a heave offering from the children of Israel from the sacrifices of their peace offerings, their heave offering unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.29'>And the holy garments of Aaron shall be his sons after him, to be anointed in them and to confirm their hands in them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.30'>That son who becomes priest in his place shall put them on for seven days, when he enters the tent of meeting to minister in the holy place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.31'>And you shall take the ram of ordination and boil its flesh in the consecrated place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.32'>And Aaron and his sons shall eat the flesh of the ram, and the bread that is in the basket, by the door of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.33'>They shall eat those things with which the atonement was made, to confirm their hands and to consecrate; but a stranger shall not eat them, because they are holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.34'>And if any of the flesh of ordination, or of the bread, remains until the morning, then you shall burn the remainder with fire. It shall not be eaten, because it is holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.35'>Thus you shall do to Aaron and his sons, according to all that I have commanded you. Seven days you shall confirm their hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.36'>And you shall offer a bull every day as a sin offering for atonement. You shall purify the altar when you make atonement for it, and you shall anoint it to consecrate it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.37'>Seven days you shall make atonement for the altar and consecrate it. And the altar shall be set apart, holy. Whatever touches the altar is consecrated.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.38'>And this is what you shall offer on the altar: two lambs of the first year, day by day continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.39'>One lamb you shall offer in the morning, and the other lamb you shall offer at evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.40'>With the one lamb shall be one-tenth of an ephah of flour mixed with one-fourth of a hin of beaten oil, and one-fourth of a hin of wine as a drink offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.41'>And the other lamb you shall offer at evening; and you shall offer with it the grain offering and the drink offering, as in the morning, for a soothing aroma, an offering by fire unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.42'>This shall be a continual burnt offering throughout your generations at the door of the tent of meeting before Jehovah, where I will meet you to speak with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.43'>And there I will meet with the children of Israel, and it shall be honored by My glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.44'>Thus I will consecrate the tent of meeting and the altar. I will also consecrate Aaron and his sons unto Me as priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.45'>I will dwell among the children of Israel and will be their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.29.46'>And they shall know that I am Jehovah their God, who brought them up out of the land of Egypt, that I may dwell among them. I am Jehovah their God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.30'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.1'>You shall make an altar on which to burn incense; you shall make it of acacia wood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.2'>A cubit shall be its length and a cubit its width; it shall be square; and two cubits shall be its height. Its horns shall be from the same piece.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.3'>And you shall overlay its top, its sides all around, and its horns with pure gold; and you shall make for it a molding of gold all around.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.4'>Two gold rings you shall make for it, under the molding on both its sides. You shall place them on its two sides, and they shall be housings for the poles with which to carry it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.5'>You shall make the poles of acacia wood, and overlay them with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.6'>And you shall put it in front of the veil that is before the ark of the Testimony, before the mercy seat that is over the Testimony, where I will meet with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.7'>Aaron shall burn spiced incense on it every morning; when he tends the lamps, he shall burn it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.8'>And when Aaron stirs up the lamps at evening, he shall burn it, a perpetual incense before Jehovah throughout your generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.9'>You shall not offer strange incense on it, nor a burnt offering, nor a grain offering; nor shall you pour out a drink offering upon it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.10'>And Aaron shall make atonement upon its horns once a year with the blood of the sin offering of atonement; once a year he shall make atonement upon it throughout your generations. It is set apart, holy, unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.11'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.12'>When you take a head count of the sons of Israel in numbering them, each man shall give a ransom for his soul unto Jehovah when you number them, that there may be no plague among them when you number them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.13'>This is what everyone passing over to be numbered shall give: half a shekel according to the shekel of the sanctuary (a shekel is twenty gerahs). The half-shekel shall be an offering unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.14'>Everyone passing over to be numbered, from twenty years old and above, shall give an offering unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.15'>The rich shall not give more and the poor shall not give less than half a shekel, when you give an offering unto Jehovah, to make atonement for your souls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.16'>And you shall take the money of atonement from the sons of Israel, and shall designate it for the service of the tent of meeting, that it may be a memorial for the sons of Israel before Jehovah, to make atonement for your souls.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.17'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.18'>You shall also make a laver of bronze, its base also of bronze, with which to wash. You shall put it between the tent of meeting and the altar. And you shall put water in it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.19'>for Aaron and his sons to wash their hands and their feet there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.20'>When they go into the tent of meeting, or when they come near the altar to minister, to burn an offering by fire like incense unto Jehovah, they shall wash with water, that they not die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.21'>Thus they shall wash their hands and their feet, that they not die. And it shall be a perpetual statute to them; to him and his seed throughout their generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.22'>Moreover Jehovah spoke unto Moses, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.23'>Take for yourself choice spices; five hundred shekels of flowing myrrh, half as much sweet-smelling cinnamon (two hundred and fifty shekels), two hundred and fifty shekels of sweet-smelling calamus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.24'>five hundred shekels of cassia, according to the shekel of the sanctuary, and a hin of olive oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.25'>And you shall make from these a holy anointing oil, an ointment compound the product of the perfumer. It shall be a holy anointing oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.26'>With it you shall anoint the tent of meeting and the ark of the Testimony;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.27'>the table and all its utensils, the lampstand and its utensils, and the altar of incense;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.28'>the altar of burnt offering with all its utensils, and the laver and its base.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.29'>You shall consecrate them, that they may be set apart, holy. Whatever touches them is holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.30'>And you shall anoint Aaron and his sons, and consecrate them, to serve Me as priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.31'>And you shall speak to the children of Israel, saying: This shall be a holy anointing oil unto Me throughout your generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.32'>It shall not be poured upon mans flesh; nor shall you make any other like it, according to its proportions. It is holy, and it shall be holy unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.33'>Whoever compounds any like it, or whoever gives any of it to a stranger, shall be cut off from his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.34'>And Jehovah said to Moses: Take spices; stacte and onycha and galbanum, and pure frankincense with these incense spices; part equal to part.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.35'>You shall make of these an incense, a spice mixture the product of the perfumer, salted, pure, and holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.36'>And you shall pulverize some of it very fine, and put some of it before the Testimony in the tent of meeting where I will meet with you. It shall be set apart, holy, unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.37'>And the incense which you make, you shall not make any for yourselves according to its proportions. It shall be holy unto you for Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.30.38'>Whoever makes any like it, to smell it, he shall be cut off from his people.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.31'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.2'>Observe that I have called by name Bezalel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.3'>and I have filled him with the Spirit of God, in wisdom, in understanding, in knowledge, and in all manner of workmanship,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.4'>to devise designs, to work in gold, in silver, in bronze,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.5'>in cutting stones to finish them, in carving wood, and to work in all manner of workmanship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.6'>And I, behold I, have appointed with him Aholiab the son of Ahisamach, of the tribe of Dan; and I have given wisdom into the hearts of all the wise-hearted, that they may produce all that I have commanded you:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.7'>the tent of meeting, the ark of the Testimony and the mercy seat that is on it, and all the implements of the tent;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.8'>the table and its utensils, the pure gold lampstand with all its utensils, the altar of incense,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.9'>the altar of burnt offering with all its utensils, and the laver and its base;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.10'>the woven garments, the holy garments for Aaron the priest and the garments of his sons, to serve as priests,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.11'>and the anointing oil and spiced incense for the holy place. According to all that I have commanded you they shall do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.12'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.13'>Speak also to the children of Israel, saying: Surely My Sabbaths you shall keep, for it is a sign between Me and you throughout your generations, that you may know that I am Jehovah who sanctifies you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.14'>You shall keep the Sabbath, therefore, for it is holy to you. Everyone who violates it shall be executed to death; for whoever does any work on it, that soul shall be cut off from among his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.15'>Work may be done six days, but the seventh is the the rest of Sabbath observance, holy unto Jehovah. Whoever does any work on the Sabbath day, he shall be executed to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.16'>Therefore the children of Israel shall keep the Sabbath, to observe the Sabbath throughout their generations as a perpetual covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.17'>It is a perpetual sign between Me and the children of Israel; for in six days Jehovah made the heavens and the earth, and on the seventh day He rested and was refreshed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.31.18'>And when He had made an end of speaking with him on Mount Sinai, He gave Moses two tablets of the Testimony, tablets of stone, written with the finger of God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.32'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.1'>Now when the people saw that Moses delayed coming down from the mountain, the people gathered together to Aaron, and said to him, Arise, make us gods that shall go before us; for as for this Moses, the man who brought us up out of the land of Egypt, we do not know what has become of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.2'>And Aaron said to them, Break off the golden earrings which are in the ears of your wives, your sons, and your daughters, and bring them to me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.3'>So all the people broke off the golden earrings which were in their ears, and brought them to Aaron.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.4'>And he took up the gold from their hand, and he fashioned it with an engraving tool after he had made a molten calf. And they said, This is your god, O Israel, that brought you up out of the land of Egypt!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.5'>And when Aaron saw it, he built an altar before it. And Aaron made a proclamation and said, Tomorrow is a feast unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.6'>And they arose early the next day, offered burnt offerings, and brought peace offerings; and the people sat down to eat and drink, and rose up to play.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.7'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Go! Get down! For your people whom you brought up out of the land of Egypt have corrupted themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.8'>They have quickly turned aside from the way which I commanded them. They have made themselves a molten calf, and bowed down to it and sacrificed to it, and said, This is your god, O Israel, that brought you up out of the land of Egypt!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.9'>And Jehovah said to Moses, I have seen this people, and behold it is a stiff-necked people!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.10'>Now therefore, let Me alone, that My wrath may burn against them, that I may consume them. And I will make of you a great nation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.11'>And Moses entreated the face of Jehovah his God, and said: Jehovah, why does Your wrath burn against Your people whom You have brought up out of the land of Egypt with great power and with a mighty hand?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.12'>Why should the Egyptians speak, and say, He brought them out to harm them, to kill them in the mountains, and to consume them from the face of the earth? Turn away from Your burning wrath, and have compassion regarding this evil to Your people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.13'>Remember Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, Your servants, to whom You swore by Your own self, and said to them, I will multiply your seed as the stars of the heavens; and all this land that I have spoken of I give to your seed, and they shall always possess it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.14'>And Jehovah was moved to compassion from the evil which He had spoken to do unto His people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.15'>And Moses turned and went down from the mountain, and the two tablets of the Testimony were in his hand. The tablets were written on both sides; on the one side and on the other they were written.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.16'>And the tablets were the work of God, and the writing was the writing of God, engraved on the tablets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.17'>And when Joshua heard the sound of the people of their shouting, he said to Moses, It is a sound of war in the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.18'>And he said: It is not the sound of the shout of victory, nor the sound of the cry of defeat, but the sound of singing I am hearing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.19'>And it came to pass, as soon as he came near the camp, and saw the calf and the dancing, that Moses anger was kindled, and he cast the tablets out of his hands and broke them at the base of the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.20'>And he took the calf which they had made, burned it with fire, and ground it fine, and scattered it on the water and made the children of Israel drink it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.21'>And Moses said to Aaron, What did this people do to you that you have brought so great a sin upon them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.22'>And Aaron said, Do not let the anger of my lord be kindled. You know the people, that they are set on evil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.23'>For they said to me, Make us gods that shall go before us; as for this Moses, the man who brought us up out of the land of Egypt, we do not know what has become of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.24'>And I said to them, Whoever has any gold, let them break it off. So they gave it to me, and I cast it into the fire, and this calf came out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.25'>And when Moses saw that the people were lacking restraint (for Aaron had let them loose, to the derision of their enemies),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.26'>that Moses stood in the gate of the camp, and said, Whoever is for Jehovah, come to me. And all the sons of Levi gathered together to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.27'>And he said to them, Thus says Jehovah the God of Israel: Let every man put his sword on his side, and go and return from gate to gate throughout the camp, and let every man kill his brother, every man his companion, and every man his neighbor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.28'>And the sons of Levi did according to the word of Moses. And about three thousand men of the people fell that day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.29'>And Moses said, Fulfill your hand today unto Jehovah, that He may bestow upon you a blessing this day, for every man has been against his son and his brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.30'>And it came to pass on the next day that Moses said to the people, You have sinned a great sin. And now I will go up to Jehovah; perhaps I can make atonement for your sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.31'>And Moses returned to Jehovah and said, Oh, these people have sinned a great sin, and have made for themselves a god of gold!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.32'>Yet now, if You will, take away their sin; and if not, I pray, blot me out of Your book which You have written.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.33'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Whoever has sinned against Me, I will blot him out of My book.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.34'>Now therefore, go, lead the people to the place of which I have spoken to you. Behold, My Angel shall go before you. Nevertheless, in the day when I visit, I will punish them for their sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.32.35'>And Jehovah plagued the people because they had made the calf which Aaron had made.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.33'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.1'>And Jehovah said unto Moses, Depart and go up from here, you and the people whom you have brought up out of the land of Egypt, to the land of which I swore to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, saying, To your seed I will give it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.2'>And I will send an Angel before you, and I will drive out the Canaanite and the Amorite and the Hittite and the Perizzite and the Hivite and the Jebusite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.3'>Go up to a land flowing with milk and honey; for I will not go up in your midst, lest I consume you on the way, for you are a stiff-necked people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.4'>And when the people heard this evil word, they mourned, and no one put on his ornaments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.5'>For Jehovah had said to Moses, Say unto the children of Israel, You are a stiff-necked people. I should come up into your midst in one moment and consume you. Now therefore, take off your ornaments, that I may know what to do with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.6'>So the children of Israel stripped themselves of their ornaments by Mount Horeb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.7'>And Moses took the tent and pitched it outside the camp, far from the camp, and called it the tent of meeting. And it came to pass that everyone who sought Jehovah went out to the tent of meeting which was outside the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.8'>And it came to pass, whenever Moses went out to the tent, that all the people rose, and each man stood at his tent door and watched Moses until he had gone into the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.9'>And it came to pass, when Moses entered the tent, that the pillar of cloud descended and stood at the door of the tent, and spoke with Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.10'>And all the people saw the pillar of cloud standing at the door of the tent, and all the people arose and prostrated themselves, each man at the opening of his tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.11'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses face to face, as a man speaks to his friend. And he would return to the camp, and his servant Joshua the son of Nun, a young man, did not depart from the tent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.12'>And Moses said unto Jehovah, Consider how You say to me, Bring up this people. But You have not let me know whom You will send with me. Yet You have said, I know you by name, and you have also found favor in My eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.13'>Now therefore, I pray, if I have found favor in Your eyes, show me now Your way, that I may know You and that I may find favor in Your eyes. And consider that this nation is Your people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.14'>And He said, My Presence will go with you, and I will give you rest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.15'>And he said unto Him, If Your Presence does not go with us, do not bring us up from here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.16'>For how then will it be known that Your people and I have found favor in Your eyes, except You go with us? So we shall be distinct, Your people and I, from all the people who are upon the face of the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.17'>And Jehovah said unto Moses, I will also do this thing that you have spoken; for you have found favor in My eyes, and I know you by name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.18'>And he said, Please, let me see Your glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.19'>And He said, I will make all My goodness pass before you, and I will proclaim the name of Jehovah before you. I will be gracious to whom I will be gracious, and I will have compassion on whom I will have compassion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.20'>But He said, You are not able to see My face; for no man shall see Me, and live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.21'>And Jehovah said, Here is a place by Me, and you shall stand on the rock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.22'>So it shall be, while My glory passes by, that I will put you in the cleft of the rock, and will cover you with My hand while I pass by.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.33.23'>Then I will take away My hand, and you shall see My back; but My face shall not be seen.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.34'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.1'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Cut two tablets of stone like the first ones, and I will write on these tablets the words that were on the first tablets which you broke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.2'>And be ready in the morning, and come up in the morning to Mount Sinai, and station yourself next to Me there on the top of the mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.3'>And no man shall come up with you, and let no man be seen throughout all the mountain; let neither flocks nor herds feed before that mountain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.4'>And he cut two tablets of stone like the first ones. And Moses arose early in the morning and went up into Mount Sinai, as Jehovah had commanded him; and he took in his hand the two tablets of stone.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.5'>And Jehovah descended in the cloud and stood with him there, and proclaimed the name of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.6'>And Jehovah passed before him and proclaimed: Jehovah, Jehovah Mighty God, merciful and gracious, slow to anger, and abounding in goodness and truth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.7'>keeping mercy for thousands, forgiving iniquity and transgression and sin, by no means clearing the guilty, visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the sons and the sons sons to the third and the fourth generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.8'>And Moses made haste and bowed down toward the earth, and prostrated himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.9'>And he said, If now I have found favor in Your eyes, O Lord, let my Lord, I pray, go among us, even though we are a stiff-necked people; and forgive our iniquity and our sin, and take us as Your possession.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.10'>And He said: Behold, I make a covenant. Before all your people I will do extraordinary things such as have not been done in all the earth, nor in any nation; and all the people among whom you are shall see the work of Jehovah. For it is an awesome thing that I will do with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.11'>Observe what I command you this day. Behold, I am driving out before you the Amorite and the Canaanite and the Hittite and the Perizzite and the Hivite and the Jebusite.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.12'>Take heed to yourself, that you not make a covenant with the inhabitants of the land where you are going, that it not be a snare in your midst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.13'>But you shall destroy their altars, break their sacred pillars, and chop down their groves</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.14'>(for you shall bow down to no other god, for Jehovah, whose name is Jealous, is a jealous Mighty God),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.15'>that you not make a covenant with the inhabitants of the land, and you go whoring after their gods and sacrifice to their gods, and they invite you and you eat of their sacrifices,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.16'>and you take of their daughters for your sons, and their daughters go whoring after their gods and make your sons go whoring after their gods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.17'>You shall make no molten gods for yourselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.18'>The Feast of Unleavened Bread you shall keep. Seven days you shall eat unleavened bread, as I have commanded you, at the appointed time of the month of Abib; for in the month of Abib you came out from Egypt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.19'>Everything that opens the womb is Mine, and every male firstborn among your livestock, whether ox or sheep.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.20'>But the firstborn of a donkey you shall redeem with a lamb. And if you will not redeem him, then you shall break his neck. All the firstborn of your sons you shall redeem. And no one shall appear before Me empty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.21'>Six days you shall work, but on the seventh day you shall rest; in plowing time and in harvest you shall rest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.22'>And you shall observe the Feast of Weeks, of the firstfruits of wheat harvest, and the Feast of Ingathering at the turn of the year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.23'>Three times in the year all your males shall appear before the Lord Jehovah the God of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.24'>For I will dispossess the nations before you and enlarge your borders; neither will any man covet your land when you go up to appear before Jehovah your God three times in the year.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.25'>You shall not offer the blood of My sacrifice with leaven, nor shall the sacrifice of the Feast of the Passover be left until morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.26'>The first of the firstfruits of your land you shall bring unto the house of Jehovah your God. You shall not boil a young goat in its mothers milk.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.27'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Write these words; according to these words at My mouth, I have made a covenant with you and with Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.28'>And he was there with Jehovah forty days and forty nights; he neither ate bread nor drank water. And He wrote on the tablets the words of the covenant, the Ten Commandments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.29'>And it came to pass, when Moses came down from Mount Sinai (the two tablets of the Testimony being in Moses hand when he came down from the mountain), that Moses did not know that the skin of his face shone while He spoke with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.30'>And when Aaron and all the children of Israel saw Moses, behold, the skin of his face shone, and they were afraid to come near him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.31'>And Moses called to them, and Aaron and all the leaders of the congregation returned to him; and Moses spoke with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.32'>And afterward all the children of Israel came near, and he commanded them with all that Jehovah had spoken with him on Mount Sinai.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.33'>And when Moses was finished speaking with them, he put a veil on his face.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.34'>But whenever Moses went in before Jehovah to speak with Him, he took the veil off until he came out; and he came out and spoke to the children of Israel whatever he was commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.34.35'>And whenever the children of Israel saw the face of Moses, that the skin of Moses face shone, then Moses would put the veil on his face again, until he went in to speak with Him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.35'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.1'>And Moses gathered all the congregation of the children of Israel together, and said to them, These are the words which Jehovah has commanded you to do:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.2'>Work shall be done six days, but the seventh day shall be holy for you, a rest of Sabbath observance unto Jehovah. Whoever does any work on it shall be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.3'>You shall kindle no fire throughout your dwellings on the Sabbath day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.4'>And Moses spoke to all the congregation of the children of Israel, saying, This is the thing which Jehovah has commanded, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.5'>Take from among you an offering unto Jehovah. Everyone of a willing heart, let him bring it as an offering of Jehovah: gold, silver, and bronze;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.6'>violet, purple, and scarlet thread, fine linen, and goats hair;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.7'>ram skins dyed red, badger skins, and acacia wood;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.8'>oil for the light, and spices for the anointing oil and for the spiced incense;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.9'>onyx stones, and stones to be set in the ephod and in the breastplate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.10'>All who are wise-hearted among you shall come and make all that Jehovah has commanded:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.11'>the tabernacle, its tent, its covering, its hooks, its boards, its bars, its pillars, and its sockets;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.12'>the ark and its poles, with the mercy seat, and the veil of the covering;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.13'>the table and its poles, all its utensils, and the Bread of the Presence;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.14'>also the lampstand for the light, its utensils, its lamps, and the oil for the light;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.15'>the incense altar, its poles, the anointing oil, the spiced incense, and the screen for the door at the entrance of the tabernacle;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.16'>the altar of burnt offering with its bronze grating, its poles, all its utensils, and the laver and its base;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.17'>the hangings of the court, its pillars, their sockets, and the screen for the gate of the court;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.18'>the pegs of the tabernacle, the pegs of the court, and their cords;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.19'>the woven garments for service in the holy place; the holy garments for Aaron the priest and the garments of his sons, to serve as priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.20'>And all the congregation of the children of Israel departed from the presence of Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.21'>And everyone came whose heart was raised up, and everyone whose spirit was willing, and they brought the offering of Jehovah for the work of the tent of meeting, for all its service, and for the holy garments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.22'>And they came, both men and women, everyone of a willing heart, and brought bracelets and nose rings, rings and ornaments, all sorts of gold articles, everyone who made an offering of gold unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.23'>And everyone with whom was found violet, purple, and scarlet thread, fine linen, and goats hair, red skins of rams, and badger skins, brought them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.24'>Everyone who offered an offering of silver or bronze brought the offering of Jehovah. And everyone with whom was found acacia wood for any work of the service, brought it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.25'>And all the women who were wise-hearted spun with their hands, and brought what they had spun, of violet, purple, and scarlet, and fine linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.26'>And all the women whose hearts were raised up with wisdom spun goats hair.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.27'>And the leaders brought onyx stones, and the stones to be set in the ephod and in the breastplate,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.28'>and spices and oil for the light, for the anointing oil, and for the spiced incense.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.29'>The children of Israel brought a freewill offering unto Jehovah, every man and woman whose heart was willing to bring for all the work which Jehovah, by the hand of Moses, had commanded to be done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.30'>And Moses said to the children of Israel, Behold, Jehovah has called by name Bezalel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.31'>and He has filled him with the Spirit of God, in wisdom and understanding, in knowledge and all manner of workmanship,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.32'>to devise designs, to work in gold and silver and bronze,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.33'>in cutting stones for setting, in carving wood, and to work in all manner of designed workmanship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.34'>And He has put in his heart to teach, in him and Aholiab the son of Ahisamach, of the tribe of Dan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.35.35'>He has filled them with wisdom of heart to do all manner of work of the engraver and the designer and the tapestry maker, in violet, purple, and scarlet thread, and fine linen, and of the weaver; those who do every work and those who devise designs.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.36'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.1'>And Bezalel and Aholiab, and everyone of wise heart in whom Jehovah has put wisdom and understanding, to know how to do all manner of work for the service of the sanctuary, shall do according to all that Jehovah has commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.2'>And Moses called Bezalel and Aholiab, and every wise-hearted one in whose heart Jehovah had put wisdom, everyone whose heart was raised up to come and do the work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.3'>And they received from Moses all the offering which the children of Israel had brought for the work of the service of making the sanctuary. And they continued bringing to him freewill offerings every morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.4'>And all the wise men who were doing all the work of the sanctuary came, each from the work he was doing,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.5'>and they spoke to Moses, saying, The people are bringing more than enough for the service of the work which Jehovah has commanded us to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.6'>And Moses commanded, and they caused it to be proclaimed throughout the camp, saying, Let neither man nor woman do any more work for the offering of the sanctuary. And the people were restrained from bringing,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.7'>for the material they had was sufficient for all the work to be done; indeed too much.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.8'>And all the wise-hearted among them who worked on the tabernacle made ten curtains woven of fine linen, and of violet, purple, and scarlet thread; with cherubim of quality workmanship they made them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.9'>The length of each curtain was twenty-eight cubits, and the width of each curtain four cubits; the curtains were all of one measurement.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.10'>And he joined five curtains to one another, and the other five curtains he joined to one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.11'>He made loops of violet on the edge of the curtain on the end at one joint; likewise he did on the outer edge of the other curtain at the second joint.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.12'>Fifty loops he made on one curtain, and fifty loops he made on the edge of the curtain at the end of the second joint; the loops fit one curtain to another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.13'>And he made fifty hooks of gold, and joined the curtains one to another with the hooks, that it might be one tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.14'>He made curtains of goats hair for the tent over the tabernacle; he made eleven curtains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.15'>The length of each curtain was thirty cubits, and the width of each curtain four cubits; the eleven curtains were of one measurement.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.16'>He joined five curtains by themselves and six curtains by themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.17'>And he made fifty loops on the edge of the curtain that is outermost at the one joint, and fifty loops he made on the edge of the curtain at the second joint.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.18'>He also made fifty bronze hooks to join the tent together, that it might be one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.19'>And he made a covering for the tent of ram skins dyed red, and a covering of badger skins above that.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.20'>For the tabernacle he made boards of acacia wood, standing upright.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.21'>The length of each board was ten cubits, and the width of each board a cubit and a half.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.22'>Each board had two tenons for joining one to another. Thus he did for all the boards of the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.23'>And he made boards for the tabernacle, twenty boards for the south side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.24'>Forty sockets of silver he made to go under the twenty boards: two sockets under each board for its two tenons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.25'>And for the other side of the tabernacle, the north side, he made twenty boards</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.26'>and their forty sockets of silver: two sockets under each board.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.27'>For the west side of the tabernacle he made six boards.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.28'>He also made two boards for the two back corners of the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.29'>And they were joined at the bottom and joined together at the top by one ring. Thus he made both of them for the two corners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.30'>And there were eight boards and their sockets; sixteen sockets of silver; two sockets under each board.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.31'>And he made bars of acacia wood: five for the boards on one side of the tabernacle,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.32'>five bars for the boards on the other side of the tabernacle, and five bars for the boards of the tabernacle for the side westward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.33'>And he made the middle bar to pass through the boards from end to end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.34'>He overlaid the boards with gold, made their rings of gold as housings for the bars, and overlaid the bars with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.35'>And he made a veil of violet, purple, and scarlet thread, and fine twisted linen; it was done with cherubim of quality workmanship.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.36'>He made for it four pillars of acacia wood, and overlaid them with gold, with their hooks of gold; and he cast four sockets of silver for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.37'>He also made a screen for the opening of the tent, of violet, purple, and scarlet thread, and fine twisted linen, the product of skillful weaving,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.36.38'>and its five pillars with their hooks. And he overlaid their tops and their bands with gold, and their five sockets were bronze.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.37'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.1'>And Bezalel made the ark of acacia wood; two and a half cubits was its length, a cubit and a half its width, and a cubit and a half its height.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.2'>He overlaid it with pure gold inside and outside, and made a molding of gold all around it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.3'>And he cast for it four rings of gold to be set in its four feet: two rings on one side, and two rings on the other side of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.4'>He made poles of acacia wood, and overlaid them with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.5'>And he put the poles into the rings at the sides of the ark, to carry the ark.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.6'>He also made the mercy seat of pure gold; two and a half cubits was its length and a cubit and a half its width.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.7'>He made two cherubim of hammered gold; he made them at the two ends of the mercy seat:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.8'>one cherub at one end on this side, and the other cherub at the other end on that side. He made the cherubim at the two ends of one piece with the mercy seat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.9'>The cherubim spread out their wings above, and covered the mercy seat with their wings. They faced one another; the faces of the cherubim were toward the mercy seat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.10'>He made the table of acacia wood; two cubits was its length, a cubit its width, and a cubit and a half its height.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.11'>And he overlaid it with pure gold, and made a molding of gold all around it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.12'>He also made a rim of a handbreadth all around it, and made a molding of gold for the rim all around it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.13'>And he cast for it four rings of gold, and put the rings on the four corners that were at its four legs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.14'>The rings were close to the rim, as housings for the poles to carry the table.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.15'>And he made the poles of acacia wood to carry the table, and overlaid them with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.16'>He made of pure gold the utensils which were on the table: its dishes, its pans, its bowls, and its pitchers for pouring.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.17'>He also made the lampstand of pure gold; of hammered work he made the lampstand. Its shaft, its branches, its bowls, its bulbs, and its flowers were one piece.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.18'>And six branches came out of its sides: three branches of the lampstand out of one side, and three branches of the lampstand out of the other side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.19'>There were three bowls made like almond blossoms on one branch, with a bulb and a flower, and three bowls made like almond blossoms on the other branch, with a bulb and a flower; and thus for the six branches coming out of the lampstand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.20'>And on the lampstand itself were four bowls made like almond blossoms, each with its bulb and flower.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.21'>There was a bulb under the first two branches of it, a bulb under the second two branches of it, and a bulb under the third two branches of it, according to the six branches extending from it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.22'>Their bulbs and their branches were of one piece; all of it was one hammered piece of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.23'>And he made its seven lamps, its snuffers, and its snuff dishes of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.24'>Of a talent of pure gold he made it, with all its utensils.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.25'>He made the incense altar of acacia wood. Its length was a cubit and its width a cubit; it was square; and two cubits was its height. Its horns were of one piece with it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.26'>And he overlaid it with pure gold: its top, its sides all around, and its horns. He also made for it a molding of gold all around it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.27'>He made two rings of gold for it under its molding, by its two corners on both sides, as housings for the poles with which to carry it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.28'>And he made the poles of acacia wood, and overlaid them with gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.37.29'>He also made the holy anointing oil and the pure incense of spices, the product of the perfumer.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.38'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.1'>He made the altar of burnt offering of acacia wood; five cubits was its length and five cubits its width; it was square; and its height was three cubits.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.2'>He made its horns on its four corners; the horns were of one piece with it. And he overlaid it with bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.3'>He made all the utensils for the altar: the pans, the shovels, the basins, the forks, and the firepans; all its utensils he made of bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.4'>And he made a grating of bronze network for the altar, under its rim, midway from the bottom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.5'>He cast four rings for the four corners of the bronze grating, as housings for the poles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.6'>And he made the poles of acacia wood, and overlaid them with bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.7'>And he put the poles into the rings on the sides of the altar, with which to carry it. He made the altar hollow with boards.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.8'>He made the laver of bronze and its base of bronze, from the bronze mirrors of the serving women who served at the door of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.9'>And he made the court on the south side; the hangings of the court were of fine twisted linen, one hundred cubits long.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.10'>There were twenty pillars for them, with twenty bronze sockets. The hooks of the pillars and their bands were silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.11'>On the north side the hangings were one hundred cubits long, with twenty pillars and their twenty bronze sockets. The hooks of the pillars and their bands were silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.12'>And on the west side there were hangings of fifty cubits, with ten pillars and their ten sockets. The hooks of the pillars and their bands were silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.13'>For the east side the hangings were fifty cubits.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.14'>The hangings of one side of the gate were fifteen cubits long, with their three pillars and their three sockets,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.15'>and the same for the other side of the court gate; on this side and that were hangings of fifteen cubits, with their three pillars and their three sockets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.16'>All the hangings of the court all around were of fine twisted linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.17'>The sockets for the pillars were bronze, the hooks of the pillars and their bands were silver, and the overlay of their tops was silver; and all the pillars of the court were banded with silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.18'>The screen for the gate of the court was the product of skillful weaving of violet, purple, and scarlet thread, and of fine twisted linen. The length was twenty cubits, and the height along its width was five cubits, corresponding to the hangings of the court.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.19'>And there were four pillars with their four sockets of bronze; their hooks were silver, and the overlay of their tops and their bands was silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.20'>All the pegs of the tabernacle, and of the court all around, were bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.21'>This is the reckoning of the tabernacle, the tabernacle of the Testimony, which was counted according to the commandment of Moses, for the service of the Levites, by the hand of Ithamar, son of Aaron the priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.22'>Bezalel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah, made all that Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.23'>And with him was Aholiab the son of Ahisamach, of the tribe of Dan, an engraver and designer, a skillful weaver of violet, purple, and scarlet thread, and of fine linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.24'>All the gold that was used in all the work of the holy place, that is, the gold of the offering, was twenty-nine talents and seven hundred and thirty shekels, according to the shekel of the sanctuary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.25'>And the silver from those who were numbered of the congregation was one hundred talents and one thousand seven hundred and seventy-five shekels, according to the shekel of the sanctuary:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.26'>a bekah per head (that is, half a shekel, according to the shekel of the sanctuary), for everyone passing over to be numbered from twenty years old and above, for six hundred and three thousand, five hundred and fifty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.27'>And from the hundred talents of silver were cast the sockets of the sanctuary and the bases of the veil: one hundred sockets from the hundred talents, one talent per socket.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.28'>And from the one thousand seven hundred and seventy-five shekels he made hooks for the pillars, overlaid their tops, and banded them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.29'>The offering of bronze was seventy talents and two thousand four hundred shekels.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.30'>And with it he made the sockets for the door of the tent of meeting, the bronze altar, the bronze grating for it, and all the utensils for the altar,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.38.31'>the sockets for the court all around, the bases for the court gate, all the pegs for the tabernacle, and all the pegs for the court all around.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.39'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.1'>Of the violet, purple, and scarlet thread they made woven garments, to serve in the holy place, and made the holy garments for Aaron, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.2'>He made the ephod of gold, violet, purple, and scarlet thread, and of fine twisted linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.3'>And they beat the gold into thin sheets and cut it into threads, to work it in with the violet, purple, and scarlet thread and the fine linen, products of skillful designs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.4'>They made shoulder pieces for it to join it together; it was joined together at its two edges.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.5'>And the intricately woven band of his ephod that was on it was of the same workmanship, woven of gold, violet, purple, and scarlet thread, and of fine twisted linen, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.6'>And they set onyx stones, enclosed in settings of gold; they were engraved, as signets are engraved, with the names of the sons of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.7'>He put them on the shoulders of the ephod as memorial stones for the sons of Israel, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.8'>And he made the breastplate, the product of skillful work, like the workmanship of the ephod, of gold, violet, purple, and scarlet thread, and of fine twisted linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.9'>They made the breastplate square by folding it; a span was its length and a span its width when folded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.10'>And they set in it four rows of stones: a row with a ruby, a topaz, and an emerald was the first row;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.11'>the second row, a turquoise, a sapphire, and a diamond;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.12'>the third row, a jacinth, an agate, and an amethyst;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.13'>the fourth row, a beryl, an onyx, and a jasper. They were enclosed in settings of gold in their mountings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.14'>There were twelve stones according to the names of the sons of Israel; according to their names, engraved like a signet, each one with its own name according to the twelve tribes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.15'>And they made chains for the breastplate at the ends, the product of braiding, of pure gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.16'>They also made two settings of gold and two gold rings, and put the two rings on the two ends of the breastplate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.17'>And they put the two cords of gold in the two rings on the ends of the breastplate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.18'>The two ends of the two braided cords they fastened in the two settings, and put them on the shoulder pieces of the ephod in the front.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.19'>And they made two rings of gold and put them on the two ends of the breastplate, on the edge of it, which was on the inward side of the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.20'>They made two other gold rings and put them on the two shoulder pieces, underneath the ephod toward its front, right at the seam above the intricately woven band of the ephod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.21'>And they bound the breastplate by means of its rings to the rings of the ephod with a violet cord, so that it would be above the intricately woven band of the ephod, and that the breastplate would not come loose from the ephod, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.22'>He made the robe of the ephod of woven work, all of violet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.23'>And there was an opening in the middle of the robe, like the opening in a coat of mail, with an edge around the opening, so that it would not tear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.24'>They made on the hem of the robe pomegranates of violet, purple, and scarlet, and of fine twisted linen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.25'>And they made bells of pure gold, and put the bells between the pomegranates on the hem of the robe all around between the pomegranates:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.26'>a bell and a pomegranate, a bell and a pomegranate, all around the hem of the robe to serve in, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.27'>They made tunics of woven work of fine linen, for Aaron and his sons,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.28'>a turban of fine linen, ornamental turbans of fine linen, trousers of fine twisted linen,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.29'>and a sash of fine twisted linen with violet, purple, and scarlet thread, the product of a skillful weaver, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.30'>And they made the plate of the holy crown of pure gold, and wrote on it an inscription like the engravings of a signet: HOLY TO JEHOVAH.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.31'>And they tied to it a violet cord, to set it above on the turban, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.32'>Thus all the work of the tabernacle of the tent of meeting was finished. And the children of Israel did according to all that Jehovah had commanded Moses; thus they did.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.33'>And they brought the tabernacle unto Moses, the tent and all its articles: its hooks, its boards, its bars, its pillars, and its sockets;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.34'>the covering of ram skins dyed red, the covering of badger skins, and the veil of the covering;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.35'>the ark of the Testimony with its poles, and the mercy seat;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.36'>the table, all its utensils, and the Bread of the Presence;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.37'>the pure gold lampstand with its lamps (the lamps set in order), all its utensils, and the oil for light;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.38'>the gold altar, the anointing oil, and the spiced incense; the screen for the tent opening;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.39'>the bronze altar, its grating of bronze, its poles, and all its utensils; the laver with its base;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.40'>the hangings of the court, its pillars and its sockets, the screen for the court gate, its cords, and its pegs; all the utensils for the service of the tabernacle, for the tent of meeting;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.41'>and the woven garments, to serve in the holy place: the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and his sons garments, to serve as priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.42'>According to all that Jehovah had commanded Moses, thus the children of Israel did all the work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.39.43'>And Moses inspected all the work, and indeed they had done it; as Jehovah had commanded, thus they had done it. And Moses blessed them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Exod.40'>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.2'>On the first day of the first month you shall set up the tabernacle of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.3'>You shall put in it the ark of the Testimony, and screen the ark with the veil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.4'>You shall bring in the table and arrange the things that are to be set in order upon it; and you shall bring in the lampstand and light its lamps.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.5'>You shall also set the altar of gold for the incense before the ark of the Testimony, and set up the screen for the door of the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.6'>And you shall set the altar of the burnt offering before the door of the tabernacle of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.7'>And you shall set the laver between the tent of meeting and the altar, and put water in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.8'>You shall set up the court all around, and put up the screen at the court gate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.9'>And you shall take the anointing oil, and anoint the tabernacle and all that is in it; and you shall consecrate it and all its utensils, and it shall be holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.10'>You shall anoint the altar of the burnt offering and all its utensils, and consecrate the altar. The altar shall be set apart, holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.11'>And you shall anoint the laver and its base, and consecrate it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.12'>And you shall bring Aaron and his sons to the door of the tent of meeting and wash them with water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.13'>You shall put the holy garments on Aaron, and anoint him and consecrate him, that he may serve Me as priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.14'>And you shall bring his sons and clothe them with tunics.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.15'>You shall anoint them, as you anointed their father, and they shall serve Me as priests; for their anointing shall be a perpetual priesthood throughout their generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.16'>Thus Moses did; according to all that Jehovah had commanded him, so he did.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.17'>And it came to pass in the first month of the second year, on the first day of the month, that the tabernacle was raised up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.18'>And Moses raised up the tabernacle, set its sockets, set up its boards, put in its bars, and raised up its pillars.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.19'>And he spread out the tent over the tabernacle and put the covering of the tent on top of it, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.20'>And he took the Testimony and put it into the ark, inserted the poles through the rings of the ark, and put the mercy seat on the ark from above.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.21'>And he brought the ark into the tabernacle, put up the veil of the covering, and screened the ark of the Testimony, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.22'>He put the table in the tent of meeting, on the north side of the tabernacle, outside the veil;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.23'>and he set the bread in order upon it before Jehovah, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.24'>He put the lampstand in the tent of meeting, across from the table, on the south side of the tabernacle;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.25'>and he lit the lamps before Jehovah, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.26'>He put the gold altar in the tent of meeting in front of the veil;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.27'>and he burned spiced incense on it, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.28'>He set up the screen at the door of the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.29'>And he put the altar of burnt offering before the door of the tabernacle of the tent of meeting, and offered upon it the burnt offering and the grain offering, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.30'>He set the laver between the tent of meeting and the altar, and put water there with which to wash;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.31'>and Moses, Aaron, and his sons washed their hands and their feet there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.32'>Whenever they went into the tent of meeting, and when they came near the altar, they washed, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.33'>And he raised up the court all around the tabernacle and the altar, and put up the screen of the court gate. Thus Moses finished the work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.34'>And the cloud covered over the tent of meeting, and the glory of Jehovah filled the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.35'>And Moses was not able to enter the tent of meeting, because the cloud had settled down upon it, and the glory of Jehovah filled the tabernacle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.36'>Whenever the cloud was taken up from over the tabernacle, the children of Israel would set out in all their journeys.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.37'>But if the cloud was not taken up, then they did not journey till the day that it was taken up.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Exod.40.38'>For the cloud of Jehovah was on the tabernacle by day, and fire was on it by night, in the eyes of all the house of Israel, throughout all their journeys.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>