<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='XXX' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='XXX'>
        <title>VW-Edition 2006</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject/>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>English translation of the Bible from the Masoretic and Textus Receptus Hebrew/Greek texts. A 'literal' translation with the readability of a NKJV or MKJV. In print: www.a-voice.org/bible-vw/print.htm  "About this Edition" www.a-voice.org/bible-vw/preface.htm</description>
        <publisher>A Voice in the Wilderness, POBox 9531, Spokane, WA 99209, USA (www.a-voice.org)</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>XXX</identifier>
        <source/>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>Freely copy and distribute</coverage>
        <rights>This module is not to be sold. Do not modify or reconfigure for other software without authorization from publisher</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div osisID='Ezra' type='book'>
      <chapter osisID='Ezra.1'>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.1.1'>Now in the first year of Cyrus king of Persia, that the Word of Jehovah by the mouth of Jeremiah might be fulfilled, Jehovah stirred up the spirit of Cyrus king of Persia, so that he made a proclamation throughout all his kingdom, and also put it in writing, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.1.2'>Thus says Cyrus king of Persia: Jehovah the God of Heaven, has given me all the kingdoms of the earth; and He has commanded me to build Him a house at Jerusalem which is in Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.1.3'>Who is there among you of all His people? His God be with him, and let him go up to Jerusalem which is in Judah, and build the house of Jehovah the God of Israel (He is God), which is in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.1.4'>And whoever remains in any place where he dwells, let the men of his place help him with silver and gold, with goods and livestock, besides the freewill offerings for the house of God which is in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.1.5'>Then the heads of the fathers of Judah and Benjamin, and the priests and the Levites, with all those whose spirit God had aroused to go up and build the house of Jehovah which is in Jerusalem,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.1.6'>and all those who were around them, encouraged their hands with articles of silver and gold, with goods and livestock, and with precious things, besides all that was willingly offered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.1.7'>King Cyrus also brought out the articles of the house of Jehovah, which Nebuchadnezzar had brought out of Jerusalem and had put them in the house of his gods;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.1.8'>and Cyrus king of Persia brought them out by the hand of Mithredath the treasurer, and counted them out to Sheshbazzar, the prince of Judah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.1.9'>This is the number of them: thirty gold platters, one thousand silver platters, twenty-nine knives,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.1.10'>thirty gold basins, four hundred and ten silver basins of a second kind, and one thousand other articles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.1.11'>All the articles of gold and silver were five thousand four hundred. All these Sheshbazzar took with the captives who were brought from Babylon to Jerusalem.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Ezra.2'>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.1'>Now these are the people of the province who came back from the captivity, of those who had been carried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away to Babylon, and who returned to Jerusalem and Judah, everyone to his own city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.2'>Those who came with Zerubbabel were Jeshua, Nehemiah, Seraiah, Reelaiah, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispar, Bigvai, Rehum, and Baanah. The number of the men of the people of Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.3'>the sons of Parosh, two thousand one hundred and seventy-two;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.4'>the sons of Shephatiah, three hundred and seventy-two;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.5'>the sons of Arah, seven hundred and seventy-five;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.6'>the sons of Pahath-Moab, of the sons of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand eight hundred and twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.7'>the sons of Elam, one thousand two hundred and fifty-four;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.8'>the sons of Zattu, nine hundred and forty-five;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.9'>the sons of Zaccai, seven hundred and sixty;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.10'>the sons of Bani, six hundred and forty-two;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.11'>the sons of Bebai, six hundred and twenty-three;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.12'>the sons of Azgad, one thousand two hundred and twenty-two;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.13'>the sons of Adonikam, six hundred and sixty-six;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.14'>the sons of Bigvai, two thousand and fifty-six;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.15'>the sons of Adin, four hundred and fifty-four;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.16'>the sons of Ater of Hezekiah, ninety-eight;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.17'>the sons of Bezai, three hundred and twenty-three;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.18'>the sons of Jorah, one hundred and twelve;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.19'>the sons of Hashum, two hundred and twenty-three;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.20'>the sons of Gibbar, ninety-five;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.21'>the sons of Bethlehem, one hundred and twenty-three;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.22'>the men of Netophah, fifty-six;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.23'>the men of Anathoth, one hundred and twenty-eight;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.24'>the sons of Azmaveth, forty-two;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.25'>the sons of Kirjath Arim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred and forty-three;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.26'>the sons of Ramah and Geba, six hundred and twenty-one;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.27'>the men of Michmash, one hundred and twenty-two;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.28'>the men of Bethel and Ai, two hundred and twenty-three;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.29'>the sons of Nebo, fifty-two;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.30'>the sons of Magbish, one hundred and fifty-six;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.31'>the sons of the other Elam, one thousand two hundred and fifty-four;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.32'>the sons of Harim, three hundred and twenty;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.33'>the sons of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred and twenty-five;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.34'>the sons of Jericho, three hundred and forty-five;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.35'>the sons of Senaah, three thousand six hundred and thirty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.36'>The priests: the sons of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred and seventy-three;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.37'>the sons of Immer, one thousand and fifty-two;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.38'>the sons of Pashhur, one thousand two hundred and forty-seven;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.39'>the sons of Harim, one thousand and seventeen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.40'>The Levites: the sons of Jeshua and Kadmiel, of the sons of Hodaviah, seventy-four.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.41'>The singers: the sons of Asaph, one hundred and twenty-eight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.42'>The sons of the gatekeepers: the sons of Shallum, the sons of Ater, the sons of Talmon, the sons of Akkub, the sons of Hatita, and the sons of Shobai, one hundred and thirty-nine in all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.43'>The temple slaves: the sons of Ziha, the sons of Hasupha, the sons of Tabbaoth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.44'>the sons of Keros, the sons of Siaha, the sons of Padon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.45'>the sons of Lebanah, the sons of Hagabah, the sons of Akkub,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.46'>the sons of Hagab, the sons of Shalmai, the sons of Hanan,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.47'>the sons of Giddel, the sons of Gahar, the sons of Reaiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.48'>the sons of Rezin, the sons of Nekoda, the sons of Gazzam,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.49'>the sons of Uzza, the sons of Paseah, the sons of Besai,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.50'>the sons of Asnah, the sons of Mehunim, the sons of Nephusim,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.51'>the sons of Bakbuk, the sons of Hakupha, the sons of Harhur,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.52'>the sons of Bazluth, the sons of Mehida, the sons of Harsha,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.53'>the sons of Barkos, the sons of Sisera, the sons of Tamah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.54'>the sons of Neziah, and the sons of Hatipha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.55'>The sons of Solomons servants: the sons of Sotai, the sons of Sophereth, the sons of Peruda,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.56'>the sons of Jaala, the sons of Darkon, the sons of Giddel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.57'>the sons of Shephatiah, the sons of Hattil, the sons of Pochereth of Zebaim, and the sons of Ami.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.58'>All the temple slaves and the sons of Solomons servants were three hundred and ninety-two.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.59'>And these were the ones who came up from Tel Melah, Tel Harsha, Cherub, Addan, and Immer; but they could not identify their fathers house or their seed, whether they were of Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.60'>the sons of Delaiah, the sons of Tobiah, and the sons of Nekoda, six hundred and fifty-two;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.61'>and of the sons of the priests: the sons of Habaiah, the sons of Koz, and the sons of Barzillai, who took a wife of the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite, and was called by their name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.62'>These sought their listing among those who were registered by genealogy, but they were not found; therefore they were considered desecrated, and excluded from the priesthood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.63'>And the governor said to them that they should not eat of the set apart, holy, things till a priest should stand with Urim and Thummim.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.64'>The whole assembly together was forty-two thousand three hundred and sixty,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.65'>besides their male and female servants, of whom there were seven thousand three hundred and thirty-seven; and there were two hundred singing men and singing women.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.66'>Their horses were seven hundred and thirty-six, their mules two hundred and forty-five,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.67'>their camels four hundred and thirty-five, and their donkeys six thousand seven hundred and twenty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.68'>Some of the heads of the fathers, when they came to the house of Jehovah which is in Jerusalem, offered freely for the house of God, to erect it in its place:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.69'>According to their ability, they gave to the treasury for the work sixty-one thousand gold drachmas, five thousand minas of silver, and one hundred priestly garments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.2.70'>So the priests and the Levites, some of the people, the singers, the gatekeepers, and the temple slaves, dwelt in their cities, and all Israel in their cities.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Ezra.3'>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.3.1'>And when the seventh month had come, and the children of Israel were in the cities, the people gathered together as one man to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.3.2'>Then Jeshua the son of Jozadak and his brethren the priests, and Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel and his brethren, arose and built the altar of the God of Israel, to offer burnt offerings on it, as it is written in the Law of Moses the man of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.3.3'>Though fear had come upon them because of the people of those lands, they set the altar on its bases; and they offered burnt offerings on it to Jehovah, both the morning and evening burnt offerings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.3.4'>They also kept the Feast of Booths, as it is written, and offered day by day the burnt offerings by number, as commanded by ordinance, day by day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.3.5'>Afterward they offered the continual burnt offering, and those for the new moons and for all the appointed meetings of Jehovah that were consecrated, and those of everyone who willingly offered a freewill offering to Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.3.6'>From the first day of the seventh month they began to offer burnt offerings to Jehovah, although the foundation of the temple of Jehovah had not been laid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.3.7'>They also gave money to the masons and the craftsmen, and food, drink, and oil to the people of Sidon and Tyre to bring cedar logs from Lebanon to the sea, to Joppa, according to the permission which they had from Cyrus king of Persia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.3.8'>Now in the second month of the second year of their coming to the house of God at Jerusalem, Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and the rest of their brethren the priests and the Levites, and all those who had come out of the captivity to Jerusalem, began, and appointed the Levites from twenty years old and above to oversee the work of the house of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.3.9'>Then Jeshua with his sons and brothers, Kadmiel with his sons, and the sons of Judah, arose as one to oversee those working on the house of God: the sons of Henadad with their sons and their brethren the Levites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.3.10'>When the builders laid the foundation of the temple of Jehovah, the priests stood in their apparel with trumpets, and the Levites, the sons of Asaph, with cymbals, to praise Jehovah, according to the ordinance of David king of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.3.11'>And they sang responsively, praising and giving thanks to Jehovah: For He is good, for His mercy is eternal toward Israel. Then all the people shouted with a great shout when they praised Jehovah, because the foundation of the house of Jehovah was laid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.3.12'>But many of the priests and Levites and heads of the fathers, old men who had seen the first house, wept with a loud voice when the foundation of this house was laid before their eyes. And many shouted aloud for joy,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.3.13'>so that the people could not discern the sound of the shout of joy from the sound of the weeping of the people, for the people shouted with a loud shout, and the sound was heard afar off.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Ezra.4'>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.1'>Now when the adversaries of Judah and Benjamin heard that the sons of the captivity were building the temple of Jehovah the God of Israel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.2'>they came to Zerubbabel and the heads of the fathers, and said to them, Let us build with you, for we seek your God as you do; and we have sacrificed to Him since the days of Esarhaddon king of Assyria, who brought us here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.3'>But Zerubbabel and Jeshua and the rest of the heads of the fathers of Israel said to them, It is not for you to build a house for our God with us; but we ourselves together will build unto Jehovah the God of Israel, as King Cyrus the king of Persia has commanded us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.4'>Then the people of the land weakened the hands of the people of Judah. They troubled them in building,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.5'>and hired counselors against them to frustrate their purpose all the days of Cyrus king of Persia, even until the reign of Darius king of Persia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.6'>In the reign of Ahasuerus, in the beginning of his reign, they wrote an accusation against the inhabitants of Judah and Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.7'>And in the days of Artaxerxes, Bishlam, Mithredath, Tabel, and the rest of their associates wrote to Artaxerxes king of Persia; and the letter was written in Aramaic, and translated from the Aramaic.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.8'>Rehum the commander and Shimshai the scribe wrote a letter against Jerusalem to King Artaxerxes as follows:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.9'>From Rehum the commander, Shimshai the scribe, and the rest of their associates; representatives of Dinah, Apharsath, Tarpelah, the people of Persia and Erech and Babylon and Shushan, Dehah, the Elam,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.10'>and the rest of the nations whom the great and noble Osnappar took captive and settled in the cities of Samaria and the remainder beyond the River; and now:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.11'>(This is a copy of the letter that they sent him) To King Artaxerxes from your servants, the men of the region beyond the River, and now:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.12'>Let it be known to the king that the Jews who came up from you have come to us at Jerusalem, and are building the rebellious and evil city, and are finishing its walls and repairing the foundations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.13'>Let it now be known to the king, that if this city is rebuilt and the walls completed, they will not pay tax, tribute, or toll, and the kings treasury will be damaged.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.14'>Now because we derive our subsistence from the palace, it was not proper for us to see the kings dishonor; therefore we have sent and informed the king,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.15'>that search may be made in the book of the records of your fathers; and you will find in the book of the records and know that this city is a rebellious city, harmful to kings and provinces, and that they have carried out revolts within the city in ancient times, for which cause this city was destroyed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.16'>We inform the king that if this city is rebuilt and its walls are completed, then because of it you will have no possession beyond the River.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.17'>The king sent an answer: To Rehum the commander, to Shimshai the scribe, to the rest of their associates who dwell in Samaria, and to the rest beyond the River: Peace! And now:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.18'>The letter which you sent to us has been clearly read before me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.19'>And I gave command, and a search has been made, and it was found that this city in ancient times has risen up against kings, and rebellion and revolt have been carried out in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.20'>There have also been mighty kings over Jerusalem, who have ruled over all the region beyond the River; and tax, tribute, and toll were paid to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.21'>Now give the command to make these men cease, that this city not be built until the command is given from me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.22'>Take heed now that you do not fail to do this. Why should damage increase to the hurt of the kings?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.23'>Now when the copy of King Artaxerxes letter was read before Rehum, Shimshai the scribe, and their associates, they went up in haste to Jerusalem against the Jews, and by force of arms made them cease.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.4.24'>Thus the work of the house of God which is at Jerusalem ceased, and it came to be ceased until the second year of the reign of Darius king of Persia.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Ezra.5'>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.1'>Then the prophets, Haggai the prophet and Zechariah the son of Iddo, prophesied to the Jews who were in Judah and Jerusalem, in the name of the God of Israel, who was over them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.2'>So Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel and Jeshua the son of Jozadak rose up and began to build the house of God which is in Jerusalem; and the prophets of God were with them, helping them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.3'>At the same time Tatnai the governor of the region beyond the River and Shethar-Boznai and their associates came to them and spoke thus to them: Who has commanded you to build this house and finish this wall?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.4'>And then spoke to them in this manner: What are the names of the men building this building?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.5'>But the eye of their God was upon the elders of the Jews, so that they could not make them cease till the matter should be brought before Darius. Then they replied by letter concerning this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.6'>This is a copy of the letter that Tatnai, the governor of the region beyond the River, and Shethar-Boznai, and his associates, the Persians who were in the region beyond the River, sent to Darius the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.7'>They sent a letter to him, in which was written thus: To Darius the king: All peace.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.8'>Let it be known to the king that we went into the province of Judea, to the house of the great God, which is being built with rolling stones, and timber is being laid in the walls; and this work goes on diligently and prospers in their hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.9'>Then we asked those elders, and spoke thus to them: Who commanded you to build this house and to finish these walls?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.10'>We also asked them their names to inform you, that we might write the names of the men who are chief among them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.11'>And thus they returned an answer to us, saying: We are the servants of the God of Heaven and earth, and we are rebuilding the house that was built many years ago, which a great king of Israel built and completed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.12'>But because our fathers provoked the God of Heaven to wrath, He gave them into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, the Chaldean, who has destroyed this house and carried the people away to Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.13'>However, in the first year of Cyrus king of Babylon, King Cyrus issued a decree to build this house of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.14'>Also, the gold and silver articles of the house of God, which Nebuchadnezzar had taken from the temple that was in Jerusalem and carried into the temple of Babylon; those King Cyrus took from the temple of Babylon, and they were given to one named Sheshbazzar, whom he had made governor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.15'>And he said to him, Take these articles; go, carry them to the temple in Jerusalem, and let the house of God be rebuilt on its place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.16'>Then that same Sheshbazzar came and laid the foundation of the house of God in Jerusalem; but from that time even until now it has been building, and it is not yet finished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.5.17'>Now therefore, if it seems good to the king, let a search be made in the kings treasure house, which is there in Babylon, to find out whether it is so that a decree was issued by King Cyrus to build this house of God at Jerusalem, and let the king send us his will concerning this matter.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Ezra.6'>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.1'>Then King Darius issued a decree, and a search was made in the house of the scrolls, where the treasures were stored in Babylon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.2'>And at Achmetha, in the palace that is in the province of Media, a scroll was found, and in it a record was written thus:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.3'>In the first year of King Cyrus, King Cyrus issued a decree concerning the house of God at Jerusalem: Let the house be rebuilt, the place where they offered sacrifices; and let the foundations of it be firmly laid, its height sixty cubits and its width sixty cubits,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.4'>with three rows of heavy stones and one row of new timber. Let the expenses be paid out of the kings house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.5'>Also let the gold and silver articles of the house of God, which Nebuchadnezzar took out of the temple in Jerusalem and brought to Babylon, be restored and taken back to the temple in Jerusalem, each to its place; and deposit them in the house of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.6'>Now therefore, Tatnai, governor of the region beyond the River, and Shethar-Boznai, and your associates the Persians who are beyond the River, keep yourselves far from there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.7'>Let the work of this house of God alone; let the governor of the Jews and the elders of the Jews build this house of God on its place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.8'>Moreover I issue a decree as to what you shall do for the elders of these Jews, for the building of this house of God: Let the kings riches from the tribute of the region beyond the River be diligently given to these men for their expenses, so that they are not hindered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.9'>And whatever they need; young bulls, rams, and lambs for the burnt offerings of the God of Heaven, wheat, salt, wine, and oil, according to the command of the priests who are in Jerusalem; let it be given them day by day without fail,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.10'>that they may offer sacrifices of soothing aroma unto the God of Heaven, and pray for the life of the king and his sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.11'>Also I issue a decree that whoever alters this edict, let a timber be pulled from his house and erected, and let him be hanged on it; and let his house be made a refuse heap for this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.12'>And may the God who causes His name to dwell there destroy any king or people who put their hand to alter it, or to destroy this house of God which is in Jerusalem. I, Darius, issue a decree; let it be done diligently.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.13'>Then Tatnai, governor of the region beyond the River, Shethar-Boznai, and their associates diligently did according to what King Darius had sent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.14'>So the elders of the Jews built, and they prospered through the prophesying of Haggai the prophet and Zechariah the son of Iddo. And they built and finished it, according to the commandment of the God of Israel, and according to the command of Cyrus, Darius, and Artaxerxes, kings of Persia.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.15'>And the house was finished on the third day of the month of Adar, which was in the sixth year of the reign of Darius the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.16'>Then the children of Israel, the priests and the Levites and the rest of the sons of the captivity, carried out the dedication of this house of God with joy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.17'>And they offered at the dedication of this house of God, one hundred bulls, two hundred rams, four hundred lambs, and as a sin offering for all Israel twelve male goats, according to the number of the tribes of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.18'>They assigned the priests to their divisions and the Levites to their divisions, over the service of God in Jerusalem, as it is written in the book of Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.19'>And the sons of the captivity observed the Passover on the fourteenth day of the first month.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.20'>For the priests and the Levites were purified together; all of them were pure. And they slaughtered the Passover lambs for all the sons of the captivity, for their brethren the priests, and for themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.21'>Then the children of Israel who had returned from the captivity ate together with all who had separated themselves from the uncleanness of the nations of the land in order to seek Jehovah the God of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.6.22'>And they observed the Feast of Unleavened Bread seven days with joy; for Jehovah had made them joyful, and had turned the heart of the king of Assyria toward them, to strengthen their hands in the work of the house of God, the God of Israel.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Ezra.7'>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.1'>Now after these things, in the reign of Artaxerxes king of Persia, Ezra the son of Seraiah, the son of Azariah, the son of Hilkiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.2'>the son of Shallum, the son of Zadok, the son of Ahitub,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.3'>the son of Amariah, the son of Azariah, the son of Meraioth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.4'>the son of Zerahiah, the son of Uzzi, the son of Bukki,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.5'>the son of Abishua, the son of Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron the chief priest;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.6'>this Ezra came up from Babylon; and he was a skilled scribe in the Law of Moses, which Jehovah the God of Israel had given. The king granted him all his request, according to the hand of Jehovah his God upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.7'>Some of the children of Israel, the priests, the Levites, the singers, the gatekeepers, and the temple slaves came up to Jerusalem in the seventh year of King Artaxerxes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.8'>And Ezra came to Jerusalem in the fifth month, which was in the seventh year of the king.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.9'>On the first day of the first month he began his journey from Babylon, and on the first day of the fifth month he came to Jerusalem, according to the good hand of his God upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.10'>For Ezra had prepared his heart to seek the Law of Jehovah, and to do it, and to teach the statutes and ordinances in Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.11'>This is a copy of the letter that King Artaxerxes gave Ezra the priest, the scribe, expert in the words of the commandments of Jehovah, and of His statutes to Israel:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.12'>Artaxerxes, king of kings, To Ezra the priest, a scribe of the Law of the God of Heaven: Perfect peace, and now:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.13'>I issue a decree that all those of the people of Israel and the priests and Levites in my realm, who volunteer to go up to Jerusalem, may go with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.14'>And whereas you are being sent by the king and his seven counselors to inquire concerning Judah and Jerusalem, with regard to the Law of your God which is in your hand;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.15'>and whereas you are to carry the silver and gold which the king and his counselors have freely offered to the God of Israel, whose dwelling is in Jerusalem;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.16'>and whereas all the silver and gold that you may find in all the province of Babylon, along with the freewill offering of the people and the priests, are to be freely offered for the house of their God in Jerusalem;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.17'>now therefore, be diligent to buy with this money bulls, rams, and lambs, with their grain offerings and their drink offerings, and offer them on the altar of the house of your God in Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.18'>And whatever seems good to you and your brethren to do with the rest of the silver and the gold, do it according to the will of your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.19'>Also the articles that are given to you for the service of the house of your God, deliver in full before the God of Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.20'>And whatever more may be needed for the house of your God, which you may have occasion to provide, pay for it from the kings treasure house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.21'>And I, even I, Artaxerxes the king, issue a decree to all the treasurers beyond the River, that whatever Ezra the priest, the scribe of the Law of the God of Heaven, may require of you, let it be done diligently,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.22'>up to one hundred talents of silver, one hundred kors of wheat, one hundred baths of wine, one hundred baths of oil, and salt without stipulation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.23'>Whatever is commanded by the God of Heaven, let it diligently be done for the house of the God of Heaven. For why should there be wrath against the realm of the king and his sons?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.24'>Also we inform you that it shall not be lawful to impose tax, tribute, or toll upon any of the priests, Levites, singers, gatekeepers, temple slaves, or servants of this house of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.25'>And you, Ezra, according to the wisdom of your God in your hand, appoint magistrates and judges who may judge all the people who are beyond the River, all such as know the Laws of your God; and teach those who do not know them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.26'>Whoever will not observe the Law of your God and the law of the king, let judgment be executed diligently upon him, whether it be death, or banishment, or confiscation of goods, or imprisonment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.27'>Blessed be Jehovah the God of our fathers, who has put such a thing as this into the kings heart, to beautify the house of Jehovah in Jerusalem,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.7.28'>and has extended mercy to me before the king and his counselors, and before all the kings mighty rulers. So I was encouraged, as the hand of Jehovah my God was upon me; and I gathered chief men of Israel to go up with me.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Ezra.8'>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.1'>These are the heads of their fathers, and this is the genealogy of those who went up with me from Babylon, in the reign of King Artaxerxes:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.2'>of the sons of Phinehas, Gershom; of the sons of Ithamar, Daniel; of the sons of David, Hattush;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.3'>of the sons of Shecaniah, of the sons of Parosh, Zechariah; and registered with him were one hundred and fifty males;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.4'>of the sons of Pahath-Moab, Eliehoenai the son of Zerahiah, and with him two hundred males;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.5'>of the sons of Shechaniah, the son of Jahaziel, and with him three hundred males;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.6'>of the sons of Adin, Ebed the son of Jonathan, and with him fifty males;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.7'>of the sons of Elam, Jeshaiah the son of Athaliah, and with him seventy males;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.8'>of the sons of Shephatiah, Zebadiah the son of Michael, and with him eighty males;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.9'>of the sons of Joab, Obadiah the son of Jehiel, and with him two hundred and eighteen males;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.10'>of the sons of Shelomith, the son of Josiphiah, and with him one hundred and sixty males;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.11'>of the sons of Bebai, Zechariah the son of Bebai, and with him twenty-eight males;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.12'>of the sons of Azgad, Johanan the son of Hakkatan, and with him one hundred and ten males;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.13'>of the last sons of Adonikam, whose names are these: Eliphelet, Jeiel, and Shemaiah; and with them sixty males;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.14'>also of the sons of Bigvai, Uthai and Zabbud, and with them seventy males.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.15'>Now I gathered them by the river that flows to Ahava, and we camped there three days. And I considered the people and the priests, and found none of the sons of Levi there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.16'>Then I sent for Eliezer, Ariel, Shemaiah, Elnathan, Jarib, Elnathan, Nathan, Zechariah, and Meshullam, chief men; also for Joiarib and Elnathan, men of understanding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.17'>And I gave them a command for Iddo, chief of the place Casiphia, and I put words in their mouth to speak to Iddo and his brethren the temple slaves at the place Casiphia; that they should bring to us servants for the house of our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.18'>Then, by the good hand of our God upon us, they brought us a man of understanding, of the sons of Mahli the son of Levi, the son of Israel, namely Sherebiah, with his sons and brothers, eighteen;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.19'>and Hashabiah, and with him Jeshaiah of the sons of Merari, his brothers and their sons, twenty;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.20'>also of the temple slaves, whom David and the rulers had appointed for the service of the Levites, two hundred and twenty temple slaves. All of them were designated by name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.21'>Then I proclaimed a fast there at the river of Ahava, that we might humble ourselves before our God, to seek from Him the right way for us and our little ones and all our possessions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.22'>For I was ashamed to request of the king troops and horsemen to help us against the enemy along the road, because we had spoken to the king, saying, The hand of our God is upon all those for good who seek Him, but His power and His wrath are against all those who forsake Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.23'>So we fasted and entreated our God for this, and He was entreated of us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.24'>Then I separated twelve of the chiefs of the priests; Sherebiah, Hashabiah, and ten of their brethren with them;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.25'>and weighed out to them the silver, the gold, and the articles, the offering for the house of our God which the king and his counselors and his rulers, and all Israel who were present, had contributed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.26'>I weighed into their hand six hundred and fifty talents of silver, silver articles weighing one hundred talents, one hundred talents of gold,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.27'>twenty gold basins worth a thousand drachmas, and two vessels of fine polished bronze, precious as gold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.28'>And I said to them, You are holy unto Jehovah; the articles are holy also; and the silver and the gold are a freewill offering unto Jehovah the God of your fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.29'>Watch and keep them until you weigh them before the chief of the priests and the Levites and heads of the fathers of Israel in Jerusalem, in the chambers of the house of Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.30'>So the priests and the Levites accepted the silver and the gold by weight and the articles, to bring them to Jerusalem to the house of our God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.31'>Then we departed from the river of Ahava on the twelfth day of the first month, to go to Jerusalem. And the hand of our God was upon us, and He delivered us from the hand of the enemy and from ambush along the road.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.32'>So we came to Jerusalem, and remained there three days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.33'>Now on the fourth day the silver and the gold and the articles were weighed in the house of our God by the hand of Meremoth the son of Uriah the priest, and with him was Eleazar the son of Phinehas; with them were the Levites, Jozabad the son of Jeshua and Noadiah the son of Binnui;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.34'>with the number and weight of everything. All the weight was written down at that time.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.35'>The children of those who had been carried away captive, who had come from the captivity, offered burnt offerings to the God of Israel: twelve bulls for all Israel, ninety-six rams, seventy-seven lambs, and twelve male goats as a sin offering. All this was a burnt offering unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.8.36'>And they delivered the kings orders to the kings satraps and the governors in the region beyond the River. So they gave support to the people and the house of God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Ezra.9'>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.9.1'>When these things were done, the rulers came to me, saying, The people of Israel and the priests and the Levites have not separated themselves from the peoples of the lands, with respect to the abominations of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Jebusites, the Ammonites, the Moabites, the Egyptians, and the Amorites.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.9.2'>For they have taken some of their daughters for themselves and their sons, so that the holy seed is mixed with the peoples of those lands. Indeed, the hand of the rulers and officials has been foremost in this treachery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.9.3'>So when I heard this thing, I tore my garment and my robe, and plucked out some of the hair of my head and beard, and sat down astonished.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.9.4'>Then everyone who trembled at the Words of the God of Israel assembled to me, because of the treachery of those who had been carried away captive, and I sat astonished until the evening sacrifice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.9.5'>At the evening sacrifice I arose from my fasting; and having torn my garment and my robe, I fell on my knees and spread out my hands to Jehovah my God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.9.6'>And I said: O my God, I am too ashamed and humiliated to lift up my face to You, my God; for our iniquities have increased over our heads, and our guilt has grown up to the Heavens.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.9.7'>Since the days of our fathers to this day we have been in great guilt, and for our iniquities we, our kings, and our priests have been delivered into the hand of the kings of the lands, to the sword, to captivity, to plunder, and to shame of faces, to this day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.9.8'>And now for a little while grace has been shown from Jehovah our God, to leave us a remnant to escape, and to give us a peg in His holy place, that our God may enlighten our eyes and give us a little reviving in our bondage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.9.9'>For we were slaves; yet our God did not forsake us in our bondage; but He extended mercy to us in the sight of the kings of Persia, to revive us, to set up the house of our God, to rebuild its ruins, and to give us a wall in Judah and Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.9.10'>And now, O our God, what shall we say after this? For we have forsaken Your commandments,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.9.11'>which You have commanded by Your servants the prophets, saying, The land which you are entering to possess is an unclean land, with the impurity of the peoples of the lands, with their abominations which have filled it from end to end with their uncleanness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.9.12'>Now therefore, do not give your daughters for their sons, nor take their daughters to your sons; nor seek after their peace or prosperity forever, that you may be strong and eat the good of the land, and leave it as an inheritance to your children forever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.9.13'>And after all that has come upon us for our evil deeds and for our great guilt, since You our God have held back from the bending down in punishment of our iniquities, and have given us such deliverance as this,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.9.14'>should we again break Your commandments, and join in marriage with the people of these abominations? Would You not be angry with us until You had finished us off, so that there would be no remnant or escapee?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.9.15'>O Jehovah the God of Israel, You are righteous, for we are left as refugees, as it is this day. Here we are before You, in our guilt, for no one can stand before You because of this!</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Ezra.10'>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.1'>Now while Ezra was praying, and while he was confessing, weeping, and falling prostrate before the house of God, a very large assembly of men, women, and children gathered to him out of Israel; for the people wept with a great weeping.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.2'>And Shechaniah the son of Jehiel, one of the sons of Elam, answered and said to Ezra, We have trespassed against our God, and are dwelling with foreign women from the peoples of the land; yet now there is hope in Israel in spite of this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.3'>Now therefore, let us make a covenant with our God to bring out all these women and those who have been born to them, according to the counsel of the Lord and of those who tremble at the commandment of our God; and let it be done according to the Law.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.4'>Arise, for this matter is up to you. We also are with you. Be strong, and do it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.5'>Then Ezra arose, and made the chief priests, the Levites, and all Israel swear an oath that they would do according to this word. So they swore.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.6'>Then Ezra rose up from before the house of God, and went into the chamber of Jehohanan the son of Eliashib; and when he came there, he ate no bread and drank no water, for he mourned because of the guilt of those from the captivity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.7'>And they issued a proclamation throughout Judah and Jerusalem to all the sons of the captivity, to assemble at Jerusalem,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.8'>and that whoever would not come within three days, according to the counsel of the rulers and elders, all his property would be destroyed, and he himself would be excluded from the assembly of those from the captivity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.9'>So all the men of Judah and Benjamin gathered at Jerusalem within three days. It was the ninth month, on the twentieth of the month; and all the people sat in the open square of the house of God, trembling because of this matter and because of the heavy rain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.10'>Then Ezra the priest stood up and said to them, You have transgressed and have dwelt with foreign women, adding to the guilt of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.11'>Now therefore, make confession to Jehovah the God of your fathers, and do His will; separate yourselves from the peoples of the land, and from the foreign women.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.12'>Then all the assembly answered and said with a loud voice, Yes! As you have said, so we need to do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.13'>But there are many people; it is the season for heavy rain, and we are not able to stand outside. Nor is this the work of one or two days, for there are many of us who have transgressed in this matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.14'>Please, let our rulers be appointed out of the whole assembly; and let all those in our cities who have dwelt with foreign women come at appointed times, together with the elders and judges of their cities, until the fierce wrath of our God in this matter is turned away from us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.15'>Only Jonathan the son of Asahel and Jahaziah the son of Tikvah stood against this, and Meshullam and Shabbethai the Levite supported them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.16'>And the sons of the captivity did so. And Ezra the priest set apart some of the men, heads of fathers, according to the houses of their fathers, each of them by name; and they sat down on the first day of the tenth month to examine the matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.17'>By the first day of the first month they finished investigating all the men who had dwelt with foreign women.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.18'>And among the sons of the priests who had dwelt with foreign women, the following were found of the sons of Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and his brothers: Maaseiah, Eliezer, Jarib, and Gedaliah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.19'>And they gave their hands that they would put away their women; and being guilty, they offered a ram of the flock for their sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.20'>Also of the sons of Immer: Hanani and Zebadiah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.21'>of the sons of Harim: Maaseiah, Elijah, Shemaiah, Jehiel, and Uzziah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.22'>of the sons of Pashhur: Elioenai, Maaseiah, Ishmael, Nethanel, Jozabad, and Elasah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.23'>Also of the Levites: Jozabad, Shimei, Kelaiah (the same is Kelita), Pethahiah, Judah, and Eliezer.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.24'>Also of the singers: Eliashib; and of the gatekeepers: Shallum, Telem, and Uri.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.25'>And others of Israel: of the sons of Parosh: Ramiah, Jeziah, Malchiah, Mijamin, Eleazar, Malchijah, and Benaiah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.26'>of the sons of Elam: Mattaniah, Zechariah, Jehiel, Abdi, Jeremoth, and Eliah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.27'>of the sons of Zattu: Elioenai, Eliashib, Mattaniah, Jeremoth, Zabad, and Aziza;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.28'>of the sons of Bebai: Jehohanan, Hananiah, Zabbai, and Athlai;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.29'>of the sons of Bani: Meshullam, Malluch, Adaiah, Jashub, Sheal, and Ramoth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.30'>of the sons of Pahath-Moab: Adna, Chelal, Benaiah, Maaseiah, Mattaniah, Bezalel, Binnui, and Manasseh;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.31'>of the sons of Harim: Eliezer, Ishijah, Malchijah, Shemaiah, Shimeon,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.32'>Benjamin, Malluch, and Shemariah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.33'>of the sons of Hashum: Mattenai, Mattattah, Zabad, Eliphelet, Jeremai, Manasseh, and Shimei;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.34'>of the sons of Bani: Maadai, Amram, Uel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.35'>Benaiah, Bedeiah, Cheluh,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.36'>Vaniah, Meremoth, Eliashib,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.37'>Mattaniah, Mattenai, Jaasau,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.38'>Bani, Binnui, Shimei,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.39'>Shelemiah, Nathan, Adaiah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.40'>Machnadebai, Shashai, Sharai,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.41'>Azarel, Shelemiah, Shemariah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.42'>Shallum, Amariah, and Joseph;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.43'>of the sons of Nebo: Jeiel, Mattithiah, Zabad, Zebina, Jadau, Joel, and Benaiah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Ezra.10.44'>All these had taken foreign women, some being women with whom they brought forth children.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>