<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='XXX' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='XXX'>
        <title>VW-Edition 2006</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject/>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>English translation of the Bible from the Masoretic and Textus Receptus Hebrew/Greek texts. A 'literal' translation with the readability of a NKJV or MKJV. In print: www.a-voice.org/bible-vw/print.htm  "About this Edition" www.a-voice.org/bible-vw/preface.htm</description>
        <publisher>A Voice in the Wilderness, POBox 9531, Spokane, WA 99209, USA (www.a-voice.org)</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>XXX</identifier>
        <source/>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>Freely copy and distribute</coverage>
        <rights>This module is not to be sold. Do not modify or reconfigure for other software without authorization from publisher</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div osisID='Lev' type='book'>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.1'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.1'>And Jehovah called unto Moses, and spoke to him from the tent of meeting, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.2'>Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them: If any one of you brings an offering unto Jehovah, you shall bring your offering of the livestock; of the herd and of the flock.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.3'>If his offering is a burnt offering of the herd, let him offer a male that is whole; he shall offer it of his own free will at the door of the tent of meeting before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.4'>And he shall put his hand on the head of the burnt offering, and it will be accepted for him to make atonement for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.5'>He shall kill the young bull before Jehovah; and the priests, Aarons sons, shall bring the blood and sprinkle the blood all around on the altar that is by the door of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.6'>And he shall flay the burnt offering and cut it into its pieces.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.7'>The sons of Aaron the priest shall put fire on the altar, and lay the wood in order on the fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.8'>And the priests, Aarons sons, shall lay the parts, the head, and the fat in order upon the wood that is on the fire upon the altar;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.9'>but he shall wash its entrails and its legs with water. And the priest shall burn all of it on the altar with smoke as a burnt offering, an offering by fire, a soothing aroma unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.10'>If his offering is of the flocks, of the sheep or of the goats, as a burnt offering, he shall bring a male that is whole.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.11'>He shall kill it on the north side of the altar before Jehovah; and the priests, Aarons sons, shall sprinkle its blood all around upon the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.12'>And he shall cut it into its pieces, with its head and its fat; and the priest shall lay them in order upon the wood that is on the fire upon the altar;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.13'>but he shall wash the entrails and the legs with water. And the priest shall bring it all and burn it upon the altar with smoke; it is a burnt offering, an offering by fire, a soothing aroma unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.14'>And if the burnt offering of his offering unto Jehovah is of birds, then he shall bring his offering of turtledoves or young pigeons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.15'>The priest shall bring it to the altar, nip off its head, and burn it on the altar with smoke; its blood shall be drained out at the side of the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.16'>And he shall remove its crop with its feathers and cast it beside the altar on the east side, into the place for ashes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.1.17'>And he shall cleave it at its wings, but shall not divide it completely; and the priest shall burn it on the altar with smoke, on the wood that is on the fire. It is a burnt offering, an offering by fire, a soothing aroma unto Jehovah.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.2'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.1'>When anyone offers a grain offering unto Jehovah, his offering shall be of fine flour. And he shall pour oil on it, and put frankincense on it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.2'>He shall bring it to Aarons sons, the priests, one of whom shall take from it a full handful of fine flour and oil with all the frankincense. And the priest shall burn it as a memorial on the altar with smoke, an offering by fire, a soothing aroma unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.3'>The rest of the grain offering shall be for Aaron and his sons. Of the offerings unto Jehovah by fire, it is set apart, holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.4'>And if you bring as an offering a grain offering baked in the oven, it shall be unleavened cakes of fine flour mixed with oil, or unleavened wafers anointed with oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.5'>And if your offering is a grain offering baked in a pan, it shall be of fine flour, unleavened, mixed with oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.6'>You shall break it in pieces and pour oil on it; it is a grain offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.7'>If your offering is a grain offering baked in a sauce pan, it shall be made of fine flour with oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.8'>You shall bring the grain offering that is made of these things unto Jehovah. And when it has been presented to the priest, he shall bring it to the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.9'>And the priest shall take from the grain offering a memorial portion, and burn it on the altar with smoke. It is an offering by fire, a soothing aroma unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.10'>And what is left of the grain offering shall be for Aaron and his sons. Of the offerings unto Jehovah by fire, it is set apart, holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.11'>No grain offering which you bring to Jehovah shall be made with leaven, for you shall burn no leaven nor any honey with smoke in any offering unto Jehovah by fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.12'>As for the offering of the firstfruits, you shall offer them unto Jehovah, but they shall not be burned on the altar for a soothing aroma.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.13'>And every offering of your grain offerings you shall season with salt; you shall not allow the salt of the covenant of your God to be lacking from your grain offerings. With all your offerings you shall offer salt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.14'>If you offer a grain offering of your firstfruits unto Jehovah, you shall offer for the grain offering of your firstfruits green heads of grain roasted with fire, grain beaten out from full heads.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.15'>And you shall put oil on it, and lay frankincense on it. It is a grain offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.2.16'>And the priest shall burn the memorial portion with smoke: part of its beaten grain and part of its oil, with all the frankincense, as an offering by fire unto Jehovah.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.3'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.1'>And if his offering is a sacrifice of peace offerings, if he offers it from the herd, whether male or female, he shall offer one that is whole before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.2'>And he shall lay his hand on the head of his offering, and kill it at the door of the tent of meeting; and Aarons sons, the priests, shall sprinkle the blood all around on the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.3'>And he shall offer from the sacrifice of the peace offering an offering by fire unto Jehovah. The fat that covers the entrails and all the fat that is on the entrails,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.4'>the two kidneys and the fat that is on them by the flanks, and the fatty lobe attached to the liver above the kidneys, he shall remove;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.5'>and Aarons sons shall burn it with smoke on the altar upon the burnt offering, which is on the wood that is on the fire, as an offering by fire, a soothing aroma unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.6'>If his offering as a sacrifice of a peace offerings unto Jehovah is of the flock, whether male or female, he shall offer one that is whole.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.7'>If he offers a lamb as his offering, then he shall offer it before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.8'>And he shall lay his hand on the head of his offering, and kill it before the tent of meeting; and Aarons sons shall sprinkle its blood all around on the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.9'>And he shall offer from the sacrifice of the peace offering, as an offering by fire unto Jehovah, its fat and the whole fat tail which he shall remove close to the backbone. And the fat that covers the entrails and all the fat that is on the entrails,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.10'>the two kidneys and the fat that is on them by the flanks, and the fatty lobe attached to the liver above the kidneys, he shall remove;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.11'>and the priest shall burn them with smoke on the altar as a food offering by fire unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.12'>And if his offering is a goat, then he shall offer it before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.13'>He shall lay his hand on its head and kill it before the tent of meeting; and the sons of Aaron shall sprinkle its blood all around on the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.14'>And he shall offer from it his offering, as an offering by fire unto Jehovah. The fat that covers the entrails and all the fat that is on the entrails,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.15'>the two kidneys and the fat that is on them by the flanks, and the fatty lobe attached to the liver above the kidneys, he shall remove;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.16'>and the priest shall burn them on the altar with smoke as a food offering by fire for a soothing aroma; all the fat is Jehovahs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.3.17'>This shall be a perpetual statute throughout your generations in all your dwellings: you shall eat neither fat nor blood.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.4'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.1'>And Jehovah spoke unto Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.2'>Speak to the children of Israel, saying: If a soul sins unintentionally against any of the commandments of Jehovah in anything which ought not to be done, and does any of them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.3'>if the anointed priest sins, bringing guilt upon the people, then let him present unto Jehovah for his sin which he has sinned a young bull that is whole, as a sin offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.4'>He shall bring the bull to the door of the tent of meeting before Jehovah, lay his hand on the bulls head, and kill the bull before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.5'>And the anointed priest shall take some of the bulls blood and bring it to the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.6'>And the priest shall dip his finger in the blood and sprinkle some of the blood seven times before Jehovah, in front of the veil of the holy place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.7'>And the priest shall put some of the blood on the horns of the altar of spiced incense before Jehovah, which is in the tent of meeting; and he shall pour the remaining blood of the bull at the base of the altar of the burnt offering, which is at the door of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.8'>He shall take from it all the fat of the bull as the sin offering. The fat that covers the entrails and all the fat which is on the entrails,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.9'>the two kidneys and the fat that is on them by the flanks, and the fatty lobe attached to the liver above the kidneys, he shall remove,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.10'>as it was taken from the bull of the sacrifice of the peace offering; and the priest shall burn them with smoke upon the altar of the burnt offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.11'>But the skin of the bull and all its flesh, with its head and legs, its entrails and dung;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.12'>the whole bull he shall bring outside the camp to a clean place, where the ashes are poured out, and burn it on wood with fire; where the ashes are poured out it shall be burned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.13'>And if the whole congregation of Israel sins unintentionally, and the thing is hidden from the eyes of the assembly, and they have done something against any of the commandments of Jehovah in anything which should not be done, and are guilty;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.14'>when the sin which they have sinned becomes known, then the assembly shall offer a young bull for the sin, and bring it before the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.15'>And the elders of the congregation shall lay their hands on the head of the bull before Jehovah, and the bull shall be killed before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.16'>The anointed priest shall bring some of the bulls blood to the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.17'>And the priest shall dip his finger in the blood and sprinkle it seven times before Jehovah, in front of the veil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.18'>And he shall put some of the blood on the horns of the altar which is before Jehovah, which is in the tent of meeting; and he shall pour the remaining blood at the base of the altar of burnt offering, which is at the door of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.19'>He shall take all the fat from it and burn it on the altar with smoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.20'>And he shall do with the bull as he did with the bull of the sin offering; thus he shall do with it. Thus the priest shall make atonement for them, and it shall be forgiven them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.21'>And he shall bring the bull outside the camp, and burn it as he burned the first bull. It is a sin offering for the assembly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.22'>When a ruler has sinned, and done something unintentionally against any of the commandments of Jehovah his God in anything which should not be done, and is guilty,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.23'>or if his sin which he has sinned comes to his knowledge, he shall bring as his offering a kid of the goats, a male that is whole.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.24'>And he shall lay his hand on the head of the goat, and kill it at the place where they kill the burnt offering before Jehovah. It is a sin offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.25'>And the priest shall take some of the blood of the sin offering with his finger, put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and pour its blood at the base of the altar of burnt offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.26'>And he shall burn all its fat on the altar with smoke, like the fat of the sacrifice of the peace offering. Thus the priest shall make atonement for him concerning his sin, and it shall be forgiven him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.27'>If any soul of the people of the land sins unintentionally by doing something against any of the commandments of Jehovah in anything which ought not to be done, and is guilty,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.28'>or if his sin which he has sinned comes to his knowledge, then he shall bring as his offering a kid of the goats, a female that is whole, for his sin which he has sinned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.29'>And he shall lay his hand on the head of the sin offering, and kill the sin offering at the place of the burnt offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.30'>And the priest shall take some of its blood with his finger, put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and pour all the remaining blood at the base of the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.31'>He shall remove all its fat, as fat is removed from the sacrifice of the peace offering; and the priest shall burn it on the altar with smoke for a soothing aroma unto Jehovah. Thus the priest shall make atonement for him, and it shall be forgiven him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.32'>If he brings a lamb as his sin offering, he shall bring a female that is whole.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.33'>And he shall lay his hand on the head of the sin offering, and kill it as a sin offering at the place where they kill the burnt offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.34'>The priest shall take some of the blood of the sin offering with his finger, put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and pour all the remaining blood at the base of the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.4.35'>He shall remove all its fat, as the fat of the lamb is removed from the sacrifice of the peace offering. And the priest shall burn it on the altar with smoke, according to the offerings by fire unto Jehovah. Thus the priest shall make atonement for his sin that he has sinned, and it shall be forgiven him.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.5'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.1'>If a soul sins and has heard the utterance of an oath, and is a witness, whether he has seen or known of the matter; if he does not report it, he bears guilt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.2'>Or if a soul touches any unclean thing, whether it is the carcass of an unclean beast, or the carcass of unclean livestock, or the carcass of unclean creeping things, and he is unaware of it, he also shall be unclean and guilty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.3'>Or if he touches human uncleanness; whatever uncleanness with which a man may be defiled, and he is unaware of it; when he has found out about it, then he shall be guilty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.4'>Or if a soul swears, speaking thoughtlessly with his lips to do evil or to do good, whatever it is that a man may speak rashly with an oath, and it is concealed from him; when he has found out about it, then he shall be guilty in any of these matters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.5'>And it shall be, when he is guilty in any of these matters, that he shall confess that he has sinned;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.6'>and he shall bring his trespass offering unto Jehovah for his sin which he has sinned, a female from the flock, a lamb or a kid of the goats as a sin offering. Thus the priest shall make atonement for him concerning his sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.7'>If he cannot afford a lamb, then he shall bring unto Jehovah, for his guilt which he has sinned, two turtledoves or two young pigeons: one as a sin offering and the other as a burnt offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.8'>And he shall bring them to the priest, who shall offer that which is for the sin offering first, and nip off its head from its neck, but shall not divide it completely.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.9'>And he shall sprinkle some of the blood of the sin offering on the side of the altar, and the rest of the blood shall be drained out at the base of the altar. It is a sin offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.10'>And he shall offer the second as a burnt offering according to the ordinance. Thus the priest shall make atonement for his sin which he has sinned, and it shall be forgiven him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.11'>And if he cannot afford two turtledoves or two young pigeons, then he who sinned shall bring for his offering one-tenth of an ephah of fine flour as a sin offering. He shall put no oil on it, nor shall he put frankincense on it, for it is a sin offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.12'>And he shall bring it to the priest, and the priest shall take his full handful of it as a memorial portion, and burn it on the altar with smoke according to the offerings by fire unto Jehovah. It is a sin offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.13'>The priest shall make atonement for him, for his sin that he has sinned in any of these matters; and it shall be forgiven him. The rest is for the priest as a grain offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.14'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.15'>If a soul commits a trespass, and sins unintentionally in regard to the holy things of Jehovah, then he shall bring unto Jehovah for his trespass a ram that is whole from the flocks, with your valuation in shekels of silver according to the shekel of the sanctuary, as a trespass offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.16'>And he shall make good for his sin with regard to the holy thing, and shall add one-fifth to it and give it to the priest. Thus the priest shall make atonement for him with the ram of the trespass offering, and it shall be forgiven him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.17'>If a soul sins, and has done any of these things which are forbidden to be done by the commandments of Jehovah, though he does not know it, yet he is guilty and shall bear his iniquity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.18'>And he shall bring to the priest a ram that is whole from the flock, with your valuation, as a trespass offering. Thus the priest shall make atonement for him regarding his unintentional error in which he did not know it, and it shall be forgiven him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.5.19'>It is a trespass offering; he has trespassed against Jehovah to become guilty.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.6'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.2'>If a soul sins and commits a trespass against Jehovah by lying to his neighbor about what was delivered into his hand for safekeeping, or about a pledge, or about a robbery, or if he has extorted from his neighbor,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.3'>or if he has found what was lost and lies concerning it, and swears falsely; in any one of these things that a man may do in which he sins:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.4'>then it shall be, because he has sinned and is guilty, that he shall restore what he has stolen, or the thing which he has extorted, or what was delivered to him for safekeeping, or the lost thing which he found,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.5'>or all that about which he has sworn falsely. He shall restore the principal, add one-fifth more to it, and give it to whomever it belongs, on the day of his guilt offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.6'>And he shall bring his trespass offering unto Jehovah, a ram that is whole from the flock, with your valuation, as a trespass offering, to the priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.7'>And the priest shall make atonement for him before Jehovah, and he shall be forgiven for any of these things that he has done in which he is guilty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.8'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.9'>Command Aaron and his sons, saying, This is the law of the burnt offering: The burnt offering shall be on the hearth upon the altar all night until morning, and the fire of the altar shall be kept burning on it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.10'>And the priest shall put on his linen garment, and his linen trousers he shall put on his flesh, and take up the ashes of the burnt offering which the fire has consumed on the altar, and he shall put them beside the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.11'>And he shall take off his garments, put on other garments, and carry the ashes outside the camp to a clean place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.12'>And the fire on the altar shall be kept burning on it; it shall not be put out. And the priest shall burn wood on it every morning, and lay the burnt offering in order upon it; and he shall burn on it the fat of the peace offerings with smoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.13'>The fire shall continually be burning on the altar; it shall never go out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.14'>This is the law of the grain offering: The sons of Aaron shall present it before Jehovah in front of the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.15'>And he shall take from it his handful of the fine flour of the grain offering, with its oil, and all the frankincense which is on the grain offering, and shall burn it on the altar with smoke for a soothing aroma, as a memorial unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.16'>And the remainder of it Aaron and his sons shall eat; with unleavened bread it shall be eaten in the holy place; in the court of the tent of meeting they shall eat it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.17'>It shall not be baked with leaven. I have given it as their portion of My offerings by fire; it is set apart, holy; like the sin offering and the trespass offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.18'>All the males among the sons of Aaron shall eat it. It is a perpetual statute throughout your generations concerning the offerings by fire unto Jehovah. Everyone who touches them shall be holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.19'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.20'>This is the offering for Aaron and his sons, which they shall offer unto Jehovah, on the day when he is anointed: one-tenth of an ephah of fine flour as a continual grain offering, half of it in the morning and half of it in the evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.21'>It shall be made in a pan with oil. You shall bring it in mixed, and the baked pieces of the grain offering you shall offer for a soothing aroma unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.22'>The priest from among his sons, who is anointed in his place, shall do it. It is a perpetual statute unto Jehovah. It shall be completely burned with smoke;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.23'>for every grain offering for the priests shall be completely burned. It shall not be eaten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.24'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.25'>Speak to Aaron and to his sons, saying, This is the law of the sin offering: In the place where the burnt offering is killed, the sin offering shall be killed before Jehovah. It is set apart, holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.26'>The priest who offers it for sin shall eat it. In the holy place it shall be eaten, in the court of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.27'>Everyone who touches its flesh shall be holy. And when its blood is sprinkled on any garment, you shall wash that on which it was sprinkled, in the holy place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.28'>But the earthen vessel in which it is boiled shall be broken. And if it is boiled in a bronze vessel, it shall be scoured and rinsed in water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.29'>All the males among the priests shall eat of it. It is set apart, holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.6.30'>But the sin offering, from which any of the blood is brought into the tent of meeting, to make atonement in the holy place, shall not be eaten. It shall be burned with fire.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.7'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.1'>Likewise this is the law of the trespass offering (it is set apart, holy):</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.2'>In the place where they kill the burnt offering they shall kill the trespass offering. And its blood shall be sprinkled all around on the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.3'>And he shall offer from it all its fat. The fat tail and the fat that covers the entrails,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.4'>the two kidneys and the fat that is on them by the flanks, and the fatty lobe attached to the liver above the kidneys, he shall remove;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.5'>and the priest shall burn them on the altar with smoke as an offering by fire unto Jehovah. It is a trespass offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.6'>Every male among the priests shall eat of it. It shall be eaten in the holy place. It is set apart, holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.7'>The trespass offering is like the sin offering; there is one law for them both: it is for the priest who makes atonement with it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.8'>And the priest who offers anyones burnt offering, that priest shall have for himself the skin of the burnt offering which he has offered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.9'>Also every grain offering that is baked in the oven and all that is prepared in the sauce pan, or in a pan, shall be for the priest who offers it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.10'>Every grain offering, whether mixed with oil, or dry, shall be for all the sons of Aaron, for one as for the other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.11'>This is the law of the sacrifice of peace offerings which he shall offer unto Jehovah:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.12'>If he offers it for a thanksgiving, then he shall offer, with the sacrifice of thanksgiving, unleavened cakes mixed with oil, unleavened wafers anointed with oil, or cakes of fine flour mixed with oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.13'>Besides the cakes, as his offering he shall offer leavened bread with the sacrifice of thanksgiving of his peace offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.14'>And from it he shall offer one cake from each offering as a heave offering unto Jehovah. It shall be for the priest who sprinkles the blood of the peace offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.15'>And the flesh of the sacrifice of his peace offering for thanksgiving shall be eaten the same day it is offered. He shall not leave any of it until morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.16'>But if the sacrifice of his offering is a vow or a freewill offering, it shall be eaten the same day that he offers his sacrifice; and on the next day the remainder of it may also be eaten;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.17'>but the remainder of the flesh of the sacrifice on the third day shall be burned with fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.18'>And if any of the flesh of the sacrifice of his peace offering is eaten at all on the third day, it shall not be accepted, nor shall it be imputed to him; it shall be an abomination unto him who offers it, and the soul who eats of it shall bear his iniquity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.19'>The flesh that touches any unclean thing shall not be eaten. It shall be burned with fire. And as for the other flesh, all who are clean shall eat of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.20'>But the soul who eats the flesh of the sacrifice of the peace offering that belongs to Jehovah, while he is unclean, that soul shall be cut off from his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.21'>Moreover the soul who touches any unclean thing, such as human uncleanness, an unclean animal, or any abominable unclean thing, and who eats the flesh of the sacrifice of the peace offering that belongs to Jehovah, that soul shall be cut off from his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.22'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.23'>Speak to the children of Israel, saying: You shall not eat any fat, of ox or sheep or goat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.24'>And the fat of an animal that dies naturally, and the fat of what is torn by wild beasts, may be used for any work; but you shall not eat to devour it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.25'>For whoever eats the fat of the animal of which men offer an offering by fire unto Jehovah, the soul who eats it shall be cut off from his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.26'>Moreover you shall not eat any blood in any of your dwellings, whether of bird or beast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.27'>Whoever eats any blood, that soul shall be cut off from his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.28'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.29'>Speak to the children of Israel, saying: He who offers the sacrifice of his peace offering unto Jehovah shall bring his offering unto Jehovah from the sacrifice of his peace offerings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.30'>His own hands shall bring the offerings by fire unto Jehovah. The fat with the breast he shall bring, that the breast may be waved as a wave offering before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.31'>And the priest shall burn the fat on the altar with smoke, but the breast shall be for Aaron and his sons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.32'>Also the right thigh you shall give to the priest as a heave offering from the sacrifices of your peace offerings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.33'>He among the sons of Aaron, who offers the blood of the peace offering and the fat, shall have the right thigh for his portion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.34'>For the breast of the wave offering and the thigh of the heave offering I have taken from the children of Israel, from the sacrifices of their peace offerings, and I have given them to Aaron the priest and to his sons, from the children of Israel, as a perpetual statute.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.35'>This is the portion for the anointing of Aaron and the anointing of his sons, from the offerings by fire unto Jehovah, on the day he presented them to serve Jehovah as priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.36'>Jehovah commanded this to be given to them by the children of Israel, on the day that he anointed them, as a perpetual statute throughout their generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.37'>This is the law of the burnt offering, the grain offering, the sin offering, the trespass offering, the consecrations, and the sacrifice of the peace offerings,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.7.38'>which Jehovah had commanded Moses on Mount Sinai, on the day when He commanded the children of Israel to offer their offerings unto Jehovah in the Wilderness of Sinai.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.8'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.2'>Take Aaron and his sons with him, and the garments, the anointing oil, a bull as the sin offering, two rams, and a basket of unleavened bread;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.3'>and gather all the congregation together at the door of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.4'>And Moses did as Jehovah commanded him. And the congregation was gathered together at the door of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.5'>And Moses said to the congregation, This is what Jehovah has commanded to be done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.6'>And Moses brought Aaron and his sons and washed them with water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.7'>And he put the tunic on him, girded him with the sash, clothed him with the robe, and put the ephod on him; and he girded him with the intricately woven band of the ephod, and with it tied the ephod on him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.8'>And he put the breastplate on him, and he put the Urim and the Thummim in the breastplate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.9'>And he put the turban on his head. Also on the turban, on its front, he put the golden plate, the holy crown, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.10'>Also Moses took the anointing oil, and anointed the tabernacle and all that was in it, and consecrated them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.11'>He sprinkled some of it on the altar seven times, anointed the altar and all its utensils, and the laver and its base, to consecrate them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.12'>And he poured some of the anointing oil on Aarons head and anointed him, to consecrate him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.13'>And Moses brought Aarons sons and put tunics on them, girded them with sashes, and tied the turbans on them, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.14'>And he brought the bull of the sin offering. And Aaron and his sons laid their hands on the head of the bull of the sin offering,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.15'>and Moses killed it. And he took the blood, and put some on the horns of the altar all around with his finger, and purified the altar. And he poured the blood at the base of the altar, and consecrated it, to make atonement on it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.16'>And he took all the fat that was on the entrails, the fatty lobe attached to the liver, and the two kidneys with their fat, and Moses burned them with smoke like incense on the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.17'>And the bull, its hide, its flesh, and its dung, he burned with fire outside the camp, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.18'>And he brought the ram as the burnt offering. And Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the head of the ram,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.19'>and Moses killed it. And he sprinkled the blood all around on the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.20'>And he cut the ram into pieces; and Moses burned the head, the pieces, and the fat with smoke like incense.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.21'>And he washed the entrails and the legs in water. And Moses burned the whole ram on the altar with smoke like incense. It was a burnt offering for a soothing aroma, an offering by fire unto Jehovah, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.22'>And he brought the second ram, the ram of ordination. And Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the head of the ram,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.23'>and Moses killed it. And he took some of its blood and put it on the tip of Aarons right ear, on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.24'>And he brought Aarons sons, and Moses put some of the blood on the tips of their right ears, on the thumbs of their right hands, and on the big toes of their right feet. And Moses sprinkled the blood all around on the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.25'>And he took the fat and the fat tail, all the fat that was on the entrails, the fatty lobe attached to the liver, the two kidneys and their fat, and the right thigh;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.26'>and from the basket of unleavened bread that was before Jehovah he took one unleavened cake, a cake of bread anointed with oil, and one wafer, and put them on the fat and on the right thigh;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.27'>and he put all these in Aarons hands and in his sons hands, and waved them as a wave offering before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.28'>And Moses took them from their hands and burned them with smoke upon the altar, upon the burnt offering. They were ordination offerings for a soothing aroma; an offering by fire unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.29'>And Moses took the breast and waved it as a wave offering before Jehovah. It was Moses portion of the ram of ordination, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.30'>And Moses took some of the anointing oil and some of the blood which was on the altar, and sprinkled it on Aaron, on his garments, on his sons, and on the garments of his sons with him; and he consecrated Aaron, his garments, his sons, and the garments of his sons with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.31'>And Moses said to Aaron and his sons, Boil the flesh at the door of the tent of meeting, and eat it there with the bread that is in the basket of ordination offerings, as I have commanded, saying, Aaron and his sons shall eat it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.32'>And whatever remains of the flesh and of the bread you shall burn with fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.33'>And you shall not go outside the door of the tent of meeting for seven days, for the days of your ordination to be fulfilled. For seven days he shall confirm your hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.34'>As he has done this day, thus Jehovah has commanded to do, to make atonement for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.35'>Therefore you shall stay at the door of the tent of meeting day and night for seven days, and keep the charge of Jehovah, so that you may not die; for thus I have been commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.8.36'>Thus Aaron and his sons did all the things that Jehovah had commanded by the hand of Moses.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.9'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.1'>It came to pass on the eighth day that Moses called for Aaron and his sons and the elders of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.2'>And he said to Aaron, Take for yourself a young bull as a sin offering and a ram as a burnt offering, that are whole, and offer them before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.3'>And to the children of Israel you shall speak, saying, Take a kid of the goats as a sin offering, and a calf and a lamb, both of the first year, that are whole, as a burnt offering,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.4'>also a bull and a ram as peace offerings, to sacrifice before Jehovah, and a grain offering mixed with oil; for today Jehovah will appear unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.5'>And they brought what Moses commanded before the tent of meeting. And all the congregation drew near and stood before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.6'>And Moses said, This is the thing which Jehovah has commanded you to do, and the glory of Jehovah shall appear unto you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.7'>And Moses said to Aaron, Go to the altar, offer your sin offering and your burnt offering, and make atonement for yourself and for the people. Offer the offering of the people, and make atonement for them, as Jehovah has commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.8'>Aaron therefore went to the altar and killed the calf of the sin offering, which was for himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.9'>And the sons of Aaron brought the blood to him. And he dipped his finger in the blood, put it on the horns of the altar, and poured the blood at the base of the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.10'>But the fat, the kidneys, and the fatty lobe from the liver of the sin offering he burned on the altar with smoke, as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.11'>And the flesh and the hide he burned with fire outside the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.12'>And he killed the burnt offering; and Aarons sons presented the blood to him, which he sprinkled all around on the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.13'>And they presented the burnt offering to him, with its pieces and head, and he burned them on the altar with smoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.14'>And he washed the entrails and the legs, and burned them with smoke with the burnt offering on the altar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.15'>And he brought the peoples offering, and took the goat, which was the sin offering for the people, and killed it and offered it for sin, like the first one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.16'>And he brought the burnt offering and offered it according to the ordinance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.17'>And he brought the grain offering, took a handful of it, and burned it on the altar with smoke, besides the burnt offering of the morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.18'>He also killed the bull and the ram as sacrifices of peace offerings, which were for the people. And Aarons sons presented to him the blood, which he sprinkled all around on the altar,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.19'>and the fat from the bull and the ram; the fatty tail, that covers the entrails and the kidneys, and the fatty lobe attached to the liver;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.20'>and they put the fat on the breasts, and he burned the fat on the altar with smoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.21'>And the breasts and the right thigh Aaron waved as a wave offering before Jehovah, as Moses had commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.22'>And Aaron lifted his hand toward the people, blessed them, and came down from offering the sin offering, the burnt offering, and peace offerings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.23'>And Moses and Aaron went into the tent of meeting, and came out and blessed the people. And the glory of Jehovah appeared to all the people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.9.24'>and fire came out from before Jehovah and consumed the burnt offering and the fat on the altar. When all the people saw it, they cried aloud and fell on their faces.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.10'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.1'>And Nadab and Abihu, the sons of Aaron, each took his censer and put fire in it, put incense on it, and offered strange fire before Jehovah, which He had not commanded them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.2'>And fire went out from Jehovah and consumed them, and they died before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.3'>And Moses said to Aaron, This is what Jehovah has spoken, saying: By those who come near Me I will be honored as holy, and before all the people I will be glorified. And Aaron kept still.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.4'>And Moses called Mishael and Elzaphan, the sons of Uzziel the uncle of Aaron, and said to them, Come near, carry your brethren from before the sanctuary out of the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.5'>So they went near and carried them out of the camp by their tunics, as Moses had spoken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.6'>And Moses said to Aaron, and to Eleazar and Ithamar, his sons, Do not uncover your heads nor tear your clothes, that you not die, and wrath come upon all the people. But let your brethren, the whole house of Israel, bewail the burning which Jehovah has kindled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.7'>You shall not go out from the door of the tent of meeting, lest you die; for the anointing oil of Jehovah is upon you. And they did according to the word of Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.8'>And Jehovah spoke to Aaron, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.9'>Do not drink wine or strong drink, you, nor your sons with you, when you go into the tent of meeting, that you not die. It shall be a perpetual statute throughout your generations,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.10'>to make a distinction between holy and unholy, and between unclean and clean,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.11'>and to teach the children of Israel all the statutes which Jehovah has spoken to them by the hand of Moses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.12'>And Moses spoke to Aaron, and to Eleazar and Ithamar, his sons who were left: Take the grain offering that remains of the offerings by fire unto Jehovah, and eat it without leaven beside the altar; for it is set apart, holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.13'>You shall eat it in the holy place, because it is your due and your sons due, of the sacrifices by fire unto Jehovah; for thus I have been commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.14'>The breast of the wave offering and the thigh of the heave offering you shall eat in a clean place, you, your sons, and your daughters with you; for they are your due and your sons due, which are given from the sacrifices of peace offerings of the children of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.15'>The thigh of the heave offering and the breast of the wave offering they shall bring with the offerings of fat by fire, to offer as a wave offering before Jehovah. And it shall be yours and your sons with you, by a perpetual statute, as Jehovah has commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.16'>And Moses investigated to inquire about the goat of the sin offering, and behold, it had been burned up. And he was angry with Eleazar and Ithamar, the sons of Aaron who were left, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.17'>Why have you not eaten the sin offering in a holy place, since it is set apart, holy, and God has given it to you to bear the iniquity of the congregation, to make atonement for them before Jehovah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.18'>Behold, its blood has not been brought inside the holy place; indeed you should have eaten it in the holy place, as I have commanded.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.19'>And Aaron said to Moses, Behold, this day they have offered their sin offering and their burnt offering before Jehovah, and such things have befallen me! If I had eaten the sin offering today, would it have been accepted in the eyes of Jehovah?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.10.20'>And when Moses heard that, it was good in his eyes.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.11'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying to them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.2'>Speak to the children of Israel, saying, These are the animals which you may eat among all the beasts of the earth:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.3'>Among the beasts, whatever divides the hoof, being cloven and split, and bringing up the cud; that you may eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.4'>Nevertheless these you shall not eat among those that bring up the cud or those that divide the hoof: the camel, because it brings up the cud but does not divide the hoof, is unclean to you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.5'>the hyrax, because it brings up the cud but does not divide the hoof, is unclean to you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.6'>the hare, because it brings up the cud but does not divide the hoof, is unclean to you;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.7'>and the swine, though it divides the hoof, being cloven and split, yet does not bring up the cud, is unclean to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.8'>Their flesh you shall not eat, and their carcasses you shall not touch. They are unclean to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.9'>These you may eat of all that are in the waters: whatever in the water has fins and scales, whether in the seas or in the rivers; that you may eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.10'>But all in the seas or in the rivers that do not have fins and scales, all that swarm in the water or any living creature which is in the water, they are detestable to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.11'>They shall be detestable to you; you shall not eat their flesh, but you shall detest their carcasses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.12'>Whatever in the water does not have fins or scales; it shall be detestable to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.13'>And these you shall detest among the birds; they shall not be eaten, they are detestable: the eagle, the vulture, the buzzard,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.14'>the kite, and the falcon after its kind;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.15'>every raven after its kind,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.16'>the ostrich, the owl, the sea gull, and the hawk after its kind;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.17'>the little owl, the cormorant, and the great horned owl;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.18'>the white owl, the pelican, and the carrion vulture;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.19'>the stork, the heron after its kind, the hoopoe, and the bat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.20'>All flying creatures that swarm, going upon all fours shall be detestable to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.21'>Yet these you may eat of every flying creature that swarms, going upon all fours: those which have jointed legs above their feet with which to leap upon the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.22'>These you may eat: the swarming locust after its kind, the locust after its kind, the cricket after its kind, and the grasshopper after its kind.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.23'>But all other flying creatures that swarm, having four feet shall be detestable to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.24'>By these you shall become unclean; whoever touches the carcass of them shall be unclean until evening;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.25'>whoever carries part of the carcass of them shall wash his clothes and be unclean until evening:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.26'>Any beast that divides the hoof, but is not cloven and split and does not bring up the cud, is unclean to you. Everyone who touches it shall be unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.27'>And whatever goes on its paws, among all the animals that go on all fours, those are unclean to you. Whoever touches their carcass shall be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.28'>Whoever carries their carcass shall wash his clothes and be unclean until evening. They are unclean to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.29'>These also shall be unclean to you among the swarming things that swarm on the earth: the mole, the mouse, and the great lizard after its kind;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.30'>the gecko, the monitor lizard, the sand reptile, the sand lizard, and the chameleon.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.31'>These are unclean to you among all that swarm. Whoever touches them when they are dead shall be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.32'>Anything upon which any of them falls when they are dead is unclean, whether it is any item of wood or clothing or skin or sack, whatever item it is, in which work is done, it shall be put in water. And it shall be unclean until evening; then it shall be clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.33'>Any earthen vessel into which any of them falls you shall break; and whatever is in it shall be unclean:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.34'>in such a vessel, any edible food upon which water falls shall be unclean, and any drink that may be drunk from it shall be unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.35'>And everything on which any part of their carcass falls shall be unclean; whether it is an oven or cooking stove, it shall be broken down; for they are unclean, and shall be unclean to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.36'>Nevertheless a spring or a cistern, in which there is a collection of water, shall be clean, but whatever touches the carcass shall be unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.37'>And if any part of the carcass falls on any planting seed which is to be sown, it is clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.38'>But if water is put on the seed, and if any part of the carcass has fallen on it, it shall be unclean to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.39'>And if any beast which is for your food dies, he who touches its carcass shall be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.40'>He who eats of its carcass shall wash his clothes and be unclean until evening. He also who carries its carcass shall wash his clothes and be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.41'>And every swarming thing that swarms on the earth shall be detestable. It shall not be eaten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.42'>Whatever goes on its belly, whatever goes on all fours, or whatever has many feet among all swarming things that swarm on the earth; these you shall not eat, for they are detestable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.43'>You shall not make yourselves detestable with any swarming thing that swarms; nor shall you make yourselves unclean with them, that you should be defiled by them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.44'>For I am Jehovah your God. You shall therefore sanctify yourselves, and you shall be holy; for I am holy. Neither shall you defile yourselves with any swarming thing that swarms on the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.45'>For I am Jehovah who brings you up out of the land of Egypt, to be your God. You shall therefore be holy, for I am holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.46'>This is the law of the beasts and the flying creatures and every living creature that moves in the waters, and of every creature that swarms on the earth,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.11.47'>to distinguish between the unclean and the clean, and between the animals that may be eaten and the animals that may not be eaten.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.12'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.12.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.12.2'>Speak to the children of Israel, saying: If a woman has conceived seed, and borne a male, then she shall be unclean seven days; as in the days when she is ill with menstruation, she shall be unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.12.3'>And on the eighth day the flesh of his foreskin shall be circumcised.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.12.4'>She shall then continue in the blood of her menstruation thirty-three days. She shall not touch any holy thing, nor come into the sanctuary until the days of her purification are fulfilled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.12.5'>But if she bears a female, then she shall be unclean two weeks, as in her menstruation, and she shall continue in the blood of her menstruation sixty-six days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.12.6'>When the days of her purification are fulfilled, whether for a son or a daughter, she shall bring to the priest a lamb of the first year for a burnt offering, and a young pigeon or a turtledove for a sin offering, to the door of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.12.7'>And he shall offer it before Jehovah, and make atonement for her. And she shall be cleansed from the flow of her blood. This is the law for her who has borne a male or a female.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.12.8'>And if she cannot afford to bring a lamb, then she shall bring two turtledoves or two young pigeons; one as a burnt offering and the other as a sin offering. Thus the priest shall make atonement for her, and she shall be cleansed.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.13'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.2'>When a man has on the skin of his flesh a swelling, a scab, or a bright spot, and it becomes on the skin of his flesh like a leprous sore, then he shall be brought to Aaron the priest or to one of his sons the priests.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.3'>The priest shall examine the sore on the skin of the flesh; and if the hair on the sore has turned white, and the sore appears to be deeper than the skin of his flesh, it is a leprous sore. Then the priest shall examine him, and pronounce him unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.4'>And if the bright spot is white on the skin of his flesh, and does not appear to be deeper than the skin, and its hair has not turned white, then the priest shall shut up the one who has the sore seven days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.5'>And the priest shall examine him on the seventh day; and behold, if the sore appears to be as it was, and the sore has not spread on the skin, then the priest shall shut him up another seven days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.6'>And the priest shall examine him again on the seventh day; and behold, if the sore has faded, and the sore has not spread on the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him clean; it is only a scab, and he shall wash his clothes and be clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.7'>But if the scab should at all spread over the skin, after he has been seen by the priest for his cleansing, he shall be seen by the priest again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.8'>And if the priest sees that, behold, the scab has spread on the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is leprosy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.9'>When the leprous sore is on a person, then he shall be brought to the priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.10'>And the priest shall examine him; and behold, if the swelling on the skin is white, and it has turned the hair white, and there is raw flesh in the swelling,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.11'>it is an old leprosy on the skin of his flesh. The priest shall pronounce him unclean, and shall not shut him up, for he is unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.12'>And if leprosy breaks out all over the skin, and the leprosy covers all the skin of the one who has the sore, from his head to his foot, whatever is seen by the priests eyes,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.13'>then the priest shall consider; and behold, if the leprosy has covered all his flesh, he shall pronounce the sore clean. It has all turned white. He is clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.14'>But in the day raw flesh appears on him, he shall be unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.15'>And the priest shall examine the raw flesh and pronounce him unclean; for the raw flesh is unclean. It is leprosy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.16'>Or if the raw flesh returns and has changed to white again, he shall come to the priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.17'>And the priest shall examine him; and behold, if the sore has returned to white, then the priest shall pronounce the sore clean. He is clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.18'>If the flesh has a boil in the skin, and it is healed,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.19'>and in place of the boil there comes a white swelling or a bright spot, reddish-white, then it shall be seen by the priest;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.20'>and if, when the priest sees it, behold, it appears deeper than the skin, and its hair has turned white, the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is a leprous sore which has broken out of the boil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.21'>But if the priest examines it, and behold, there are no white hairs in it, and it is not deeper than the skin, but has faded, then the priest shall shut him up seven days;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.22'>and if it should spread abroad over the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is the plague.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.23'>But if the bright spot stays in one place, and has not spread, it is the scar of the boil; and the priest shall pronounce him clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.24'>Or if the skin of the flesh is burned by fire, and the raw flesh of the burn develops a bright spot, reddish-white or white,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.25'>then the priest shall examine it; and behold, if the hair of the bright spot has turned white, and it appears deeper than the skin, it is leprosy broken out in the burn. Therefore the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is a leprous sore.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.26'>But if the priest examines it, and behold, there are no white hairs in the bright spot, and it is not deeper than the skin, but has faded, then the priest shall shut him up seven days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.27'>And the priest shall examine him on the seventh day. If it has spread abroad over the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is a leprous sore.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.28'>But if the bright spot stays in one place, and has not spread on the skin, but has faded, it is a swelling from the burn. The priest shall pronounce him clean, for it is the scar from the burn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.29'>If a man or woman has a sore on the head or in the beard,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.30'>then the priest shall examine the sore; and indeed if it appears deeper than the skin, and there is in it thin yellow hair, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is a scaly leprosy of the head or beard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.31'>But if the priest examines the scaly sore, and behold, it does not appear deeper than the skin, and there is no black hair in it, then the priest shall shut up the one who has the scall seven days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.32'>And on the seventh day the priest shall examine the sore; and behold, if the scall has not spread, and there is no yellow hair in it, and the scall does not appear deeper than the skin,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.33'>he shall shave himself, but the scall he shall not shave. And the priest shall shut up the one who has the scall another seven days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.34'>On the seventh day the priest shall examine the scall; and behold, if the scall has not spread over the skin, and does not appear deeper than the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him clean. He shall wash his clothes and be clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.35'>But if the scall should spread abroad over the skin after his cleansing,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.36'>then the priest shall examine him; and behold, if the scall has spread over the skin, the priest shall not look for yellow hair. He is unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.37'>But if the scall appears to have come to a standstill, and black hair has grown up in it, the scall has healed. He is clean, and the priest shall pronounce him clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.38'>If a man or a woman has bright spots on the skin of the flesh, white bright spots,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.39'>then the priest shall look; and behold, if the bright spots on the skin of the flesh are dull white, it is a skin spot that grows on the skin. He is clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.40'>As for the man whose hair has fallen from his head, he is bald, but he is clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.41'>He whose hair has fallen from his forehead, he is bald on the forehead, but he is clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.42'>And if there is on the bald head or bald forehead a reddish-white sore, it is leprosy breaking out on his bald head or his bald forehead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.43'>And the priest shall examine it; and behold, if the swelling of the sore is reddish-white on his bald head or on his bald forehead, as the appearance of leprosy on the skin of the flesh,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.44'>he is a leprous man. He is unclean. The priest shall pronounce to declare him unclean; his plague is on his head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.45'>And the leper on whom the plague is, his clothes shall be torn and his head bared; and he shall cover his mustache, and call out, Unclean! Unclean!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.46'>He shall be unclean. All the days he has the plague he shall be unclean. He is unclean, and he shall dwell alone; his dwelling shall be outside the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.47'>And if a garment has a leprous spot in it, whether it is a woolen garment or a linen garment,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.48'>whether it is in the warp or woof of linen or wool, whether in leather or in anything made of leather,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.49'>and if the spot is greenish or reddish in the garment or in the leather, whether in the warp or in the woof, or in anything made of leather, it is a leprous spot and shall be shown to the priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.50'>The priest shall examine the spot and shut up that which has the spot seven days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.51'>And he shall examine the spot on the seventh day. If the spot has spread in the garment, either in the warp or in the woof, in the leather or in anything made of leather, the spot is an active leprosy. It is unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.52'>He shall therefore burn that garment in which is the plague, whether warp or woof, in wool or in linen, or anything of leather, for it is an active leprosy; it shall be burned in the fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.53'>And if the priest examines it, and behold, the spot has not spread in the garment, either in the warp or in the woof, or in anything made of leather,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.54'>then the priest shall command that they wash the thing in which is the spot; and he shall shut it up another seven days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.55'>And the priest shall examine the spot after it has been washed; and indeed if the spot has not changed its color, though the spot has not spread, it is unclean, and you shall burn it in the fire; it continues eating away, whether the damage is outside or inside.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.56'>If the priest examines it, and behold, the spot has faded after washing it, then he shall tear it out of the garment, whether out of the warp or out of the woof, or out of the leather.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.57'>And if it appears again in the garment, either in the warp or in the woof, or in anything made of leather, it is a spreading plague; you shall burn with fire that in which is the plague.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.58'>And if you wash the garment, either warp or woof, or whatever is made of leather, if the spot has gone from it, then it shall be washed a second time, and shall be clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.13.59'>This is the law of the leprous plague in a garment of wool or linen, either in the warp or woof, or in anything made of leather, to pronounce it clean or to pronounce it unclean.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.14'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.1'>Then Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.2'>This shall be the law of the leper in the day of his cleansing: He shall be brought to the priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.3'>And the priest shall go out of the camp, and the priest shall examine him; and behold, if the leprosy is healed in the leper,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.4'>then the priest shall command to take for him who is being cleansed two living and clean birds, cedar wood, scarlet, and hyssop.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.5'>And the priest shall command that one of the birds be killed on an earthen vessel over running water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.6'>As for the living bird, he shall take it, the cedar wood and the scarlet and the hyssop, and dip them and the living bird in the blood of the bird that was killed over the running water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.7'>And he shall sprinkle it seven times on him who is being cleansed from the leprosy, and shall pronounce him clean, and shall let the living bird loose in the open field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.8'>And he who is being cleansed shall wash his clothes, shave off all his hair, and wash himself in water, that he may be clean. After that he shall come into the camp, and shall remain outside his tent seven days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.9'>And on the seventh day he shall shave all the hair off his head and his beard and his eyebrows; all his hair he shall shave off. He shall wash his clothes and wash his flesh in water, and he shall be clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.10'>And on the eighth day he shall take two male lambs that are whole, one ewe lamb of the first year that is whole, three-tenths of an ephah of fine flour mixed with oil as a grain offering, and one log of oil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.11'>And the priest who pronounces him clean shall present the man who is being cleansed, and those things, before Jehovah, at the door of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.12'>And the priest shall take one male lamb and offer it as a trespass offering, and the log of oil, and wave them as a wave offering before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.13'>And he shall kill the lamb in the place where he kills the sin offering and the burnt offering, in a holy place; for as the sin offering is the priest s, so is the trespass offering. It is set apart, holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.14'>And the priest shall take some of the blood of the trespass offering, and the priest shall put it on the tip of the right ear of him who is being cleansed, on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.15'>And the priest shall take some of the log of oil, and pour it into the palm of his own left hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.16'>And the priest shall dip his right finger in the oil that is in his left hand, and shall sprinkle some of the oil with his finger seven times before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.17'>And of the rest of the oil in his hand, the priest shall put some on the tip of the right ear of him who is being cleansed, on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot, on the blood of the trespass offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.18'>And the rest of the oil that is in the priests hand he shall put on the head of him who is being cleansed. Thus the priest shall make atonement for him before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.19'>And the priest shall offer the sin offering, and make atonement for him who is being cleansed from his uncleanness. Afterward he shall kill the burnt offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.20'>And the priest shall offer the burnt offering and the grain offering on the altar. Thus the priest shall make atonement for him, and he shall be clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.21'>But if he is poor and cannot afford it, then he shall take one male lamb as a trespass offering to be waved, to make atonement for him, one-tenth of an ephah of fine flour mixed with oil as a grain offering, a log of oil,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.22'>and two turtledoves or two young pigeons, such as he is able to afford: one shall be a sin offering and the other a burnt offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.23'>He shall bring them to the priest on the eighth day for his cleansing, to the door of the tent of meeting, before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.24'>And the priest shall take the lamb of the trespass offering and the log of oil, and the priest shall wave them as a wave offering before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.25'>And he shall kill the lamb of the trespass offering, and the priest shall take some of the blood of the trespass offering and put it on the tip of the right ear of him who is being cleansed, on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.26'>And the priest shall pour some of the oil into the palm of his own left hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.27'>And the priest shall sprinkle with his right finger some of the oil that is in his left hand seven times before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.28'>And the priest shall put some of the oil that is in his hand on the tip of the right ear of him who is being cleansed, on the thumb of the right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot, on the place of the blood of the trespass offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.29'>And the rest of the oil that is in the priests hand he shall put on the head of him who is being cleansed, to make atonement for him before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.30'>And he shall offer one of the turtledoves or young pigeons, such as he can afford;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.31'>such as he is able to afford, the one as a sin offering and the other as a burnt offering, with the grain offering. Thus the priest shall make atonement for him who is being cleansed before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.32'>This is the law for one who had a leprous plague, who cannot afford the usual cleansing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.33'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.34'>When you have come into the land of Canaan, which I am giving you as a possession, and I have put the leprous plague in a house in the land of your possession,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.35'>and he who owns the house comes and informs the priest, saying, There appears to be a plague in the house,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.36'>then the priest shall command that they empty the house, before the priest goes into it to examine the plague, that all that is in the house may not be made unclean; and afterward the priest shall go in to inspect the house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.37'>And he shall examine the plague; and indeed if the plague is on the walls of the house with ingrained streaks, greenish or reddish, which appear to be deep in the wall,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.38'>then the priest shall go out of the house, to the door of the house, and shut up the house seven days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.39'>And the priest shall come again on the seventh day and look; and behold, if the plague has spread in the walls of the house,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.40'>then the priest shall command that they take away the stones in which is the plague, and they shall cast them into an unclean place outside the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.41'>And he shall cause the house to be scraped inside, all around, and the dust that they scrape off they shall pour out in an unclean place outside the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.42'>And they shall take other stones and put them in the place of those stones, and he shall take other mortar and plaster the house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.43'>And if the plague comes back and breaks out in the house, after he has taken away the stones, after he has scraped the house, and after it is plastered,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.44'>then the priest shall come and look; and behold, if the plague has spread in the house, it is an active leprosy in the house. It is unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.45'>And he shall break down the house, its stones, its timber, and all the plaster of the house, and he shall carry them outside the city to an unclean place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.46'>Moreover he who goes into the house at all while it is shut up shall be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.47'>And he who lies down in the house shall wash his clothes, and he who eats in the house shall wash his clothes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.48'>And if the priest comes in and examines it, and behold, the plague has not spread in the house after the house was plastered, then the priest shall pronounce the house clean, because the plague is healed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.49'>And he shall take, to cleanse the house, two birds, cedar wood, scarlet, and hyssop.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.50'>And he shall kill one of the birds on an earthen vessel over running water;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.51'>and he shall take the cedar wood, the hyssop, the scarlet, and the living bird, and dip them in the blood of the slain bird and in the running water, and sprinkle the house seven times.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.52'>And he shall cleanse the house with the blood of the bird and the running water and the living bird, with the cedar wood, the hyssop, and the scarlet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.53'>And he shall let the living bird loose outside the city in the open field, and make atonement for the house, and it shall be clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.54'>This is the law for any leprous plague and scall,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.55'>for the leprosy of a garment and of a house,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.56'>for a swelling and a scab and a bright spot,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.14.57'>to teach when it is unclean and when it is clean. This is the law of leprosy.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.15'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.2'>Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them: When any man has a discharge from his flesh, his discharge is unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.3'>And this shall be his uncleanness in regard to his discharge; whether his flesh runs with his discharge, or his flesh is stopped up by his discharge, it is his uncleanness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.4'>Every bed on which he who has the discharge lies is unclean, and everything on which he sits shall be unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.5'>And whoever touches his bed shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.6'>He who sits on anything on which he who has the discharge sat shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.7'>And he who touches the flesh of him who has the discharge shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.8'>If he who has the discharge spits on him who is clean, then he shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.9'>Any saddle on which he who has the discharge rides shall be unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.10'>Whoever touches anything that was under him shall be unclean until evening. He who carries any of those things shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.11'>And whomever the one who has the discharge touches, and has not rinsed his hands in water, he shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.12'>The vessel of earth that he who has the discharge touches shall be broken, and every vessel of wood shall be rinsed in water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.13'>And when he who has a discharge is cleansed of his discharge, then he shall count for himself seven days for his cleansing, wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in running water; then he shall be clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.14'>On the eighth day he shall take for himself two turtledoves or two young pigeons, and come before Jehovah, to the door of the tent of meeting, and give them to the priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.15'>And the priest shall offer them, the one as a sin offering and the other as a burnt offering. Thus the priest shall make atonement for him before Jehovah because of his discharge.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.16'>And when a mans semen goes out from him during sexual intercourse, then he shall wash all his flesh in water, and be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.17'>Any garment and any skin on which there is semen shall be washed with water, and be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.18'>And the woman with whom the man lies, when there is semen of sexual intercourse, shall bathe in water, and be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.19'>If a woman has a discharge, and the discharge from her flesh is blood, she shall be impure seven days; and whoever touches her shall be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.20'>Everything that she lies on during her impurity shall be unclean; and everything that she sits on shall be unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.21'>Whoever touches her bed shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.22'>And whoever touches anything that she sat on shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.23'>If anything is on her bed or on anything on which she sits, when he touches it, he shall be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.24'>And if a man lies with her to have intercourse, so that her impurity is upon him, he shall be unclean seven days; and every bed on which he lies shall be unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.25'>If a woman has a discharge of blood for many days, other than at the time of her menstruation, or if it flows beyond her usual time of menstruation, all the days of her unclean discharge shall be as the days of her menstruation. She is unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.26'>Every bed on which she lies all the days of her discharge shall be to her as the bed of her menstruation; and whatever she sits on shall be unclean, as the uncleanness of her menstruation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.27'>Whoever touches those things shall be unclean; he shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.28'>But if she is cleansed of her discharge, then she shall count for herself seven days, and after that she shall be clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.29'>And on the eighth day she shall take for herself two turtledoves or two young pigeons, and bring them to the priest, to the door of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.30'>And the priest shall offer the one as a sin offering and the other as a burnt offering, and the priest shall make atonement for her before Jehovah for the discharge of her uncleanness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.31'>Thus you shall separate the children of Israel from their uncleanness, lest they die in their uncleanness when they defile My tabernacle that is among them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.32'>This is the law for one who has a discharge, and for him who emits semen and is unclean by it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.15.33'>and for her who is unwell because of her menstruation, and for one who has a discharge, either man or woman, and for him who lies with her who is unclean.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.16'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses after the death of the two sons of Aaron, when they drew near before Jehovah, and died;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.2'>and Jehovah said to Moses: Speak to Aaron your brother that he not come at all times into the Holy Place inside the veil, before the mercy seat which is on the ark, that he not die; for I will appear in the cloud above the mercy seat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.3'>Thus shall Aaron come into the Holy Place: with the blood of a young bull as a sin offering, and of a ram as a burnt offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.4'>He shall put the holy linen tunic and the linen trousers on his flesh; he shall be girded with a linen sash, and with the linen turban he shall be wrapped. These are holy garments. Therefore he shall wash his flesh in water, and put them on.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.5'>And he shall take from the congregation of the children of Israel two kids of the goats as a sin offering, and one ram as a burnt offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.6'>And Aaron shall bring near the bull as a sin offering for himself, and make atonement for himself and for his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.7'>He shall take the two goats and present them before Jehovah at the door of the tent of meeting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.8'>And Aaron shall cast lots for the two goats: one lot for Jehovah and one lot for the scapegoat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.9'>And Aaron shall bring the goat on which the lot of Jehovah fell, and offer it as a sin offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.10'>And the goat on which the lot fell to be the scapegoat shall be presented alive before Jehovah, to make atonement with it, and to let it go as the scapegoat into the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.11'>And Aaron shall bring the bull of the sin offering which is for himself, and make atonement for himself and for his house, and shall kill the bull as the sin offering for himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.12'>And he shall take a censer full of burning coals of fire from the altar before Jehovah, with his hands full of spiced incense beaten fine, and bring it inside the veil.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.13'>And he shall put the incense on the fire before Jehovah, that the cloud of incense may cover the mercy seat that is on the Testimony, that he not die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.14'>And he shall take some of the blood of the bull and sprinkle it with his finger on the mercy seat on the east side; and before the mercy seat he shall sprinkle some of the blood with his finger seven times.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.15'>And he shall kill the goat of the sin offering for the people, bring its blood inside the veil, do with that blood as he did with the blood of the bull, and sprinkle it on the mercy seat and before the mercy seat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.16'>Thus he shall make atonement for the Holy Place, because of the uncleanness of the children of Israel, and because of their transgressions, for all their sins; and thus he shall do for the tent of meeting which remains among them in the midst of their uncleanness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.17'>And no man shall be in the tent of meeting when he goes in to make atonement in the Holy Place, until he comes out. And he shall make atonement for himself, for his house, and for all the assembly of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.18'>And he shall go out to the altar that is before Jehovah, and make atonement for it, and shall take some of the blood of the bull and some of the blood of the goat, and put it on the horns of the altar all around.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.19'>And he shall sprinkle some of the blood on it with his finger seven times, cleanse it, and sanctify it from the uncleanness of the children of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.20'>And when he has made an end of atoning for the Holy Place, the tent of meeting, and the altar, he shall bring the live goat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.21'>And Aaron shall lay both his hands on the head of the live goat, confess over it all the iniquities of the children of Israel, and all their transgressions, and all their sins, putting them upon the head of the goat, and shall send it away into the wilderness by the hand of a man who is there, ready.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.22'>And the goat shall bear upon itself all their iniquities to a separate land; and he shall release the goat in the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.23'>And Aaron shall come into the tent of meeting, shall take off the linen garments which he put on when he went into the Holy Place, and shall leave them there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.24'>And he shall wash his flesh with water in the holy place, put on his garments, come out and offer his burnt offering and the burnt offering of the people, and make atonement for himself and for the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.25'>The fat of the sin offering he shall burn on the altar with smoke.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.26'>And he who released the goat as the scapegoat shall wash his clothes and bathe his flesh in water, and afterward come into the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.27'>The bull for the sin offering and the goat for the sin offering, whose blood was brought in to make atonement in the Holy Place, shall be carried outside the camp. And they shall burn in the fire their skins, their flesh, and their dung.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.28'>And he who burns them shall wash his clothes and bathe his flesh in water, and afterward come into the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.29'>This shall be a perpetual statute for you: In the seventh month, on the tenth day of the month, you shall afflict your souls, and do no work, whether a native or a stranger who sojourns among you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.30'>For on that day the priest shall make atonement for you, to cleanse you from all your sins, that you may be clean before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.31'>It is a sabbath observance of rest for you, and you shall afflict your souls. It is a perpetual statute.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.32'>And the priest, who is anointed and whose hand is confirmed to serve as priest in his fathers place, shall make atonement, and put on the linen clothes, the holy garments;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.33'>and he shall make atonement for the Holy Sanctuary, and he shall make atonement for the tent of meeting and for the altar, and he shall make atonement for the priests and for all the people of the assembly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.16.34'>This shall be a perpetual statute for you, to make atonement for the children of Israel, for all their sins, once a year. And he did as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.17'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.2'>Speak to Aaron, to his sons, and to all the children of Israel, and say to them, This is the thing which Jehovah has commanded, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.3'>Any man of the house of Israel who kills an ox or lamb or goat in the camp, or who kills it outside the camp,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.4'>and does not bring it to the door of the tent of meeting to offer an offering unto Jehovah before the tabernacle of Jehovah, blood shall be imputed to that man. He has shed blood; and that man shall be cut off from among his people;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.5'>so that the children of Israel may bring their sacrifices which they offer in the open field, that they may bring them unto Jehovah at the door of the tent of meeting, to the priest, and offer them as peace offerings unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.6'>And the priest shall sprinkle the blood on the altar of Jehovah at the door of the tent of meeting, and burn the fat with smoke for a soothing aroma unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.7'>They shall no more offer their sacrifices to goats, after whom they have played the harlot. This shall be a perpetual statute for them throughout their generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.8'>Also you shall say to them: Any man of the house of Israel, or of the strangers who sojourn among you, who offers a burnt offering or sacrifice,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.9'>and does not bring it to the door of the tent of meeting, to offer it unto Jehovah, that man shall be cut off from among his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.10'>And any man of the house of Israel, or of the strangers who sojourn among you, who eats any blood, I will set My face against that soul who eats blood, and will cut him off from among his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.11'>For the soul of the flesh is in the blood, and I have given it to you upon the altar to make atonement for your souls; for it is the blood that makes atonement for the soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.12'>Therefore I have said to the children of Israel, No one among you shall eat blood, nor shall any stranger who sojourns among you eat blood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.13'>Any man of the sons of Israel, or of the strangers who sojourn among you, who hunts and catches any animal or flying creature that may be eaten, he shall pour out its blood and cover it with dust;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.14'>for it is the soul of all flesh. Its blood is its soul. Therefore I said to the children of Israel, You shall not eat the blood of any flesh, for the soul of all flesh is its blood. Whoever eats it shall be cut off.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.15'>And every soul who eats what died naturally or what was torn by beasts, whether he is a native or a sojourner, he shall both wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening. Then he shall be clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.17.16'>But if he does not wash them nor bathe his flesh, then he shall bear his iniquity.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.18'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.2'>Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them: I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.3'>According to the doings of the land of Egypt, where you have dwelt, you shall not do; and according to the doings of the land of Canaan, where I am bringing you, you shall not do; nor shall you walk in their ordinances.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.4'>You shall do My judgments and keep My ordinances, to walk in them: I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.5'>You shall therefore keep My statutes and My judgments, which if a man does, he shall live by them: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.6'>None of you shall approach the flesh of anyone who is kin to him, to uncover their nakedness: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.7'>The nakedness of your father or the nakedness of your mother you shall not uncover. She is your mother; you shall not uncover her nakedness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.8'>The nakedness of your fathers wife you shall not uncover; it is your fathers nakedness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.9'>The nakedness of your sister, the daughter of your father, or the daughter of your mother, whether born at home or elsewhere, their nakedness you shall not uncover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.10'>The nakedness of your sons daughter or your daughters daughter, their nakedness you shall not uncover; for theirs is your own nakedness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.11'>The nakedness of your fathers wifes daughter, begotten by your father; she is your sister; you shall not uncover her nakedness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.12'>You shall not uncover the nakedness of your fathers sister; she is near of kin to your father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.13'>You shall not uncover the nakedness of your mothers sister, for she is near of kin to your mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.14'>You shall not uncover the nakedness of your fathers brother: You shall not approach his wife; she is your aunt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.15'>You shall not uncover the nakedness of your daughter-in-law; she is your sons wife; you shall not uncover her nakedness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.16'>You shall not uncover the nakedness of your brothers wife; it is your brothers nakedness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.17'>You shall not uncover the nakedness of a woman and her daughter, nor shall you take her sons daughter or her daughters daughter, to uncover her nakedness. They are near of kin to her. It is wickedness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.18'>Nor shall you take a woman and her sister, to vex her, to uncover her nakedness, while the other is alive.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.19'>Also you shall not approach a woman to uncover her nakedness during her menstrual uncleanness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.20'>Moreover you shall not give seed to your neighbors wife through intercourse, to defile yourself with her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.21'>And you shall not give any of your seed to pass through the fire to Molech, nor shall you profane the name of your God: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.22'>You shall not lie with a male as with a female. It is an abomination.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.23'>Nor shall you mate with any beast, to defile yourself with it. Nor shall any woman stand before a beast to mate with it. It is perversion.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.24'>Do not defile yourselves with any of these things; for by all these the nations which I am casting out before you have been defiled;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.25'>for the land is defiled. Therefore I am visiting its depravity upon it, and the land is vomiting out its inhabitants.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.26'>You shall therefore keep My statutes and My judgments, and shall not do any of these abominations, neither the native nor any stranger who sojourns among you</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.27'>(for all these abominations the men who were in the land before you have done, and the land is defiled),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.28'>that the land not also vomit you out when you defile it, as it vomited out the nations that were before you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.29'>For whoever does any of these abominations, the persons who do them shall be cut off from among their people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.18.30'>Therefore you shall keep My charge, so that you do not do any of these abominable customs which were done before you, and that you do not defile yourselves by them: I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.19'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.2'>Speak to all the congregation of the children of Israel, and say to them: You shall be holy, for I Jehovah your God am holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.3'>Every one of you shall revere his mother and his father, and keep My Sabbaths: I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.4'>Do not turn to idols, nor make for yourselves molten gods: I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.5'>And if you offer a sacrifice of peace offerings unto Jehovah, you shall offer it of your own free will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.6'>It shall be eaten the same day you offer it, and on the next day. And if any remains until the third day, it shall be burned with fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.7'>And if it is eaten to be devoured on the third day, it is unclean; it shall not be accepted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.8'>Therefore anyone who eats it shall bear his iniquity, because he has profaned the holy thing of Jehovah; and that soul shall be cut off from his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.9'>When you reap the harvest of your land, you shall not completely reap the corners of your field, nor shall you gather the gleanings of your harvest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.10'>And you shall not glean your vineyard, nor shall you gather every grape of your vineyard; you shall leave them for the poor and the sojourner: I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.11'>You shall not steal, nor deceive, nor lie to one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.12'>And you shall not swear by My name for falsehood, nor shall you profane the name of your God: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.13'>You shall not extort your neighbor, nor rob him. The wages of one who is hired shall not remain with you all night until morning.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.14'>You shall not curse the deaf, nor put a stumbling block before the blind, but shall fear your God: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.15'>You shall do no injustice in judgment. You shall not be partial to the poor, nor honor the person of the mighty. In righteousness you shall judge your neighbor.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.16'>You shall not go about as a talebearer among your people; nor shall you take a stand against the blood of your neighbor: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.17'>You shall not hate your brother in your heart. You shall reprove to correct your neighbor, and not bear sin because of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.18'>You shall not take vengeance, nor bear any grudge against the children of your people, but you shall love your neighbor as yourself: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.19'>You shall keep My statutes. You shall not breed your livestock with other kinds. You shall not sow your field with mixed seed. Nor shall a garment mixed with linen and wool come upon you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.20'>When a man lies with the seed of intercourse with a woman, who is betrothed to a husband, and who has not been ransomed to be redeemed, nor been given her freedom; there shall be punishment, but they shall not be put to death; because she was not free.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.21'>And he shall bring his trespass offering unto Jehovah, to the door of the tent of meeting, a ram as a trespass offering.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.22'>The priest shall make atonement for him with the ram of the trespass offering before Jehovah for his sin which he has sinned. And the sin which he has sinned shall be forgiven him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.23'>When you come into the land, and have planted all kinds of trees for food, then you shall consider their fruit as uncircumcised. Three years it shall be as uncircumcised to you. It shall not be eaten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.24'>But in the fourth year all its fruit shall be holy, for praise unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.25'>And in the fifth year you shall eat its fruit, that it may yield to you its increase: I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.26'>You shall not eat anything with the blood, nor shall you practice divination nor fortunetelling.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.27'>You shall not shave around the corners of your head, nor shall you spoil the edges of your beard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.28'>You shall not make any cuttings in your flesh for the dead, nor put any etched marks on you: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.29'>Do not defile your daughter, to cause her to be a harlot, that the land not fall into prostitution, and the land become full of wickedness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.30'>You shall keep My Sabbaths and reverence My sanctuary: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.31'>You shall not turn to mediums nor seek out fortunetellers, to be defiled by them: I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.32'>You shall rise before the gray headed and honor the presence of an old man, and fear your God: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.33'>And if a stranger sojourns with you in your land, you shall not mistreat him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.34'>The stranger who sojourns among you shall be to you as one born among you, and you shall love him as yourself; for you were sojourners in the land of Egypt: I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.35'>You shall do no injustice in judgment, in measurement of size, weight, or measure.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.36'>You shall have just scales, just weights, a just ephah, and a just hin: I am Jehovah your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.19.37'>therefore you shall keep all My statutes and all My judgments, and do them: I am Jehovah.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.20'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.2'>Again, you shall say to the children of Israel: Any of the children of Israel, or of the strangers who sojourn in Israel, who gives any of his seed to Molech, shall be executed to death. The people of the land shall stone him with stones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.3'>I will set My face against that man, and will cut him off from his people, because he has given his seed to Molech, to defile My sanctuary and profane My holy name.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.4'>And if the people of the land should conceal to hide their eyes from the man, when he gives his seed to Molech, and they do not kill him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.5'>then I will set My face against that man and against his family; and I will cut him off from his people, along with all who prostitute themselves with him to commit adultery with Molech.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.6'>And the soul who turns to mediums and fortunetellers, to commit adultery with them, I will set My face against that soul and cut him off from his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.7'>Sanctify yourselves therefore, and be holy, for I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.8'>And you shall keep My statutes, and do them: I am Jehovah who sanctifies you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.9'>And each one who curses his father or his mother shall be executed to death. He has cursed his father or his mother. His blood shall be upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.10'>The man who commits adultery with another mans wife, he who commits adultery with his neighbors wife, the adulterer and the adulteress, shall be executed to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.11'>The man who lies with his fathers wife has uncovered his fathers nakedness; both of them shall be executed to death. Their blood shall be upon them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.12'>If a man lies with his daughter-in-law, both of them shall be executed to death. They have brought about perversion. Their blood shall be upon them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.13'>If a man lies with a male as one lies with a woman, both of them have committed an abomination. They shall be executed to death. Their blood shall be upon them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.14'>If a man marries a woman and her mother, it is wickedness. They shall be burned with fire, both he and they, that there may be no wickedness in your midst.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.15'>If a man mates with a beast, he shall be executed to death, and you shall kill the beast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.16'>If a woman approaches any beast and mates with it, you shall kill the woman and the beast. They shall die the death. Their blood is upon them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.17'>If a man takes his sister, his fathers daughter or his mothers daughter, and gives attention to her nakedness and she gives attention to his nakedness, it is shameful. And they shall be cut off in the eyes of the sons of their people. He has uncovered his sisters nakedness. He shall bear his iniquity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.18'>If a man lies with a woman when she is unwell and uncovers her nakedness, he has exposed her flow, and she has uncovered the flow of her blood. Both of them shall be cut off from among their people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.19'>You shall not uncover the nakedness of your mothers sister nor of your fathers sister, for that would uncover his near of kin. They shall bear their iniquity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.20'>If a man lies with his aunt, he has uncovered his uncles nakedness. They shall bear their sin; they shall die childless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.21'>If a man takes his brothers wife, it is an unclean thing. He has uncovered his brothers nakedness. They shall be childless.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.22'>You shall therefore keep all My statutes and all My judgments, and do them, that the land where I am bringing you to dwell may not vomit you out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.23'>And you shall not walk in the statutes of the nations which I am casting out before you; for they have done all these things, and therefore I abhor them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.24'>But I have said to you, You shall inherit their land, and I will give it to you to possess, a land flowing with milk and honey. I am Jehovah your God, who has set you apart from the peoples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.25'>You shall therefore distinguish between clean beasts and unclean, between unclean flying creatures and clean, and you shall not make your souls detestable by beast or by flying creature, or by any kind of living thing that moves on the ground, which I have set apart from you as unclean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.26'>And you shall be holy unto Me, for I, Jehovah, am holy, and have set you apart from the peoples, that you should be Mine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.20.27'>A man or a woman who is a medium or a fortuneteller shall be executed to death; they shall stone them with stones. Their blood shall be upon them.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.21'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.1'>And Jehovah said to Moses, Speak to the priests, the sons of Aaron, and say to them: No one shall be defiled for the dead among his people,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.2'>except for his relatives who are nearest to him: his mother, his father, his son, his daughter, and his brother;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.3'>also his virgin sister who is near to him, who has had no husband, for her he may be defiled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.4'>Otherwise, being a ruler among his people, he shall not be defiled to profane himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.5'>They shall not make any bald place on their heads, nor shall they shave the corners of their beards nor make any cuttings in their flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.6'>They shall be set apart to their God and not profane the name of their God, for they offer the offerings of Jehovah by fire, and the bread of their God; therefore they shall be holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.7'>They shall not take a wife who commits harlotry or a defiled woman, nor shall they take a woman put away from her husband; for he is holy unto his God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.8'>Therefore you shall consecrate him, for he offers the bread of your God. He shall be holy to you, for I Jehovah, who sanctify you, am holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.9'>The daughter of any priest, if she profanes herself by committing harlotry, she profanes her father. She shall be burned with fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.10'>He who is the high priest among his brethren, upon whose head the anointing oil was poured and who is consecrated to wear the garments, shall not uncover his head nor tear his clothes;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.11'>nor shall he go near any dead person, nor defile himself for his father or his mother;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.12'>nor shall he go out of the sanctuary, nor profane the sanctuary of his God; for the consecration of the anointing oil of his God is upon him: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.13'>And he shall take a wife in her virginity.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.14'>A widow or a divorced woman or a defiled woman or a harlot; these he shall not marry; but he shall take a virgin of his own people as wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.15'>Nor shall he profane his seed among his people, for I Jehovah sanctify him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.16'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.17'>Speak to Aaron, saying: No man of your seed throughout their generations, who has any blemish, shall approach to offer the bread of his God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.18'>For any man who has a blemish shall not approach: a man blind or lame, mutilated or deformed,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.19'>a man who has a broken foot or broken hand,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.20'>or is a hunchback or a dwarf, or a man who has a defect in his eye, or itch or scab, or with crushed testicles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.21'>No man of the seed of Aaron the priest, who has a blemish, shall come near to offer the offerings by fire unto Jehovah. He has a blemish; he shall not come near to offer the bread of his God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.22'>He may eat the bread of his God, both the set apart, holy, and the holy;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.23'>only, he shall not enter the veil nor approach the altar, because he has a blemish; that he not profane My sanctuaries; for I am Jehovah who sanctifies them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.21.24'>Thus Moses spoke to Aaron and his sons, and to all the children of Israel.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.22'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.2'>Speak to Aaron and his sons, that they set themselves apart from the holy things of the children of Israel, and that they do not profane My holy name by what they consecrate to Me: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.3'>Say to them: Anyone of your seed throughout your generations, who goes near the holy things which the children of Israel consecrate unto Jehovah, while he has uncleanness upon him, that soul shall be cut off from before My face: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.4'>Any man of the seed of Aaron, who is a leper or has a discharge, shall not eat of the holy things until he is clean. And whoever touches anything made unclean by a corpse, or a man whose seed goes out through intercourse,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.5'>or whoever touches any swarming thing by which he is unclean, or any person by whom he is unclean, whatever his uncleanness may be;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.6'>the soul who has touched any such thing shall be unclean until evening, and shall not eat of the holy things unless he washes his flesh with water.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.7'>And when the sun goes down he shall be clean; and afterward he may eat the holy things, because it is his food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.8'>Whatever dies naturally or is torn by beasts he shall not eat, to defile himself with it: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.9'>They shall therefore keep My ordinance, lest they bear sin for it and die thereby, if they profane it: I, Jehovah, sanctify them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.10'>No stranger shall eat of the holy things; one who sojourns with the priest, or a hired servant, shall not eat of the holy things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.11'>But if the priest buys a soul with his money, he may eat it; and one who is born in his house may eat his food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.12'>If the priests daughter is married to a man who is a stranger, she shall not eat of the offerings of the holy things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.13'>But if the priests daughter is a widow or divorced, and has no child, and has returned to her fathers house as in her youth, she shall eat her fathers food; but no stranger shall eat it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.14'>And if a man eats of the holy things unintentionally, then he shall add a fifth part and give it to the priest with the holy thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.15'>They shall not profane the holy things of the children of Israel, which they offer unto Jehovah,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.16'>nor allow them to bear the iniquity of the guilt offering when they eat the holy things; for I, Jehovah, sanctify them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.17'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.18'>Speak to Aaron and his sons, and to all the children of Israel, and say to them: Any man of the house of Israel, or of the sojourners in Israel, who presents his offering for any of his vows or for any of his freewill offerings, which they offer unto Jehovah as a burnt offering;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.19'>you shall offer of your own will a male that is whole from the cattle, from the sheep, or from the goats.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.20'>You shall not offer whatever has a blemish, for it shall not be acceptable for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.21'>And whoever offers a sacrifice of peace offerings unto Jehovah to fulfill his vow, or a freewill offering from the cattle or the sheep, it shall be perfect to be accepted; there shall be no blemish in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.22'>Those that are blind or broken or maimed, or have an ulcer or itch or scabs, you shall not offer unto Jehovah, nor make an offering by fire of them upon the altar unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.23'>A bull or a lamb that has anything deformed or dwarfed you may offer as a freewill offering, but for a vow it shall not be accepted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.24'>You shall not offer unto Jehovah what is bruised or crushed, or torn or cut; you shall not do it in your land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.25'>Nor from a foreigners hand shall you offer any of these as the bread of your God, because their corruption is in them, and blemishes are in them. They shall not be accepted for you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.26'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.27'>When a bull or a sheep or a goat is born, it shall be with its mother seven days; and from the eighth day and onward it shall be acceptable as an offering by fire unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.28'>However, with the cow or ewe, do not kill both her and her young on the same day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.29'>And when you offer a sacrifice of thanksgiving unto Jehovah, offer it of your own will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.30'>On the same day it shall be eaten; you shall leave none of it until morning: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.31'>Therefore you shall keep My commandments, and do them: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.32'>You shall not profane My holy name, but I will be treated holy among the children of Israel. I am Jehovah who sanctifies you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.22.33'>who is bringing you out of the land of Egypt, to be your God: I am Jehovah.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.23'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.2'>Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them: The set feasts of Jehovah, which you shall proclaim as holy convocations, these are My appointed times:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.3'>Six days shall work be done, but the seventh day is a Sabbath observance of rest, a holy convocation. You shall do no work; it is the Sabbath of Jehovah in all your dwellings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.4'>These are the set feasts of Jehovah, holy convocations, which you shall proclaim in their appointed seasons:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.5'>On the fourteenth day of the first month at evening is the Passover unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.6'>And on the fifteenth day of the same month is the Feast of Unleavened Bread unto Jehovah; seven days you shall eat unleavened bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.7'>On the first day you shall have a holy convocation; you shall do no labor of work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.8'>And you shall offer an offering by fire unto Jehovah for seven days; and the seventh day shall be a holy convocation; you shall do no labor of work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.9'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.10'>Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them: When you come into the land which I am giving to you, and have reaped its harvest, and have brought a sheaf of the firstfruits of your harvest to the priest;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.11'>he shall wave the sheaf before Jehovah, to be accepted for you; on the day after the Sabbath the priest shall wave it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.12'>And you shall offer on that day, when you wave the sheaf, a male lamb of the first year, that is whole, as a burnt offering unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.13'>Its grain offering shall be two-tenths of an ephah of fine flour mixed with oil, an offering by fire unto Jehovah, for a soothing aroma; and its drink offering shall be one-fourth of a hin of wine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.14'>You shall eat neither bread nor roasted grain nor fruit until the same day that you have brought an offering unto your God; it shall be a perpetual statute throughout your generations in all your dwellings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.15'>And when you have counted for yourselves from the day after the Sabbath, the day that you bring the sheaf of the wave offering, seven Sabbaths shall be completed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.16'>Count fifty days up to the day after the seventh Sabbath; and you shall offer a new grain offering unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.17'>You shall bring from your dwellings two wave loaves of two-tenths of an ephah. They shall be of fine flour; they shall be baked with leaven. They are the firstfruits unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.18'>And you shall offer with the bread, seven lambs of the first year that are whole, one young bull, and two rams. They shall be a burnt offering unto Jehovah, with their grain offering and their drink offerings, an offering by fire for a soothing aroma unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.19'>And you shall sacrifice one kid of the goats as a sin offering, and two male lambs of the first year as a sacrifice of peace offerings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.20'>The priest shall wave them with the bread of the firstfruits as a wave offering before Jehovah, with the two lambs. They shall be holy unto Jehovah for the priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.21'>And you shall make a proclamation on the same day: it is a holy convocation to you. You shall do no labor of work. It shall be a perpetual statute in all your dwellings throughout your generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.22'>When you reap the harvest of your land, you shall not completely reap to the corners of your field when you reap, nor shall you gather any gleaning from your harvest. You shall leave them for the poor and for the sojourner: I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.23'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.24'>Speak to the children of Israel, saying: In the seventh month, on the first day of the month, you shall have a Sabbath observance, a memorial of shouting with trumpet blasts, a holy convocation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.25'>You shall do no labor of work; and you shall offer an offering by fire unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.26'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.27'>Also the tenth day of this seventh month shall be a Day of Atonement. It shall be a holy convocation for you; you shall afflict your souls, and bring an offering by fire unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.28'>And you shall do no work on that same day, for it is a Day of Atonement, to make atonement for you before Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.29'>For any soul that is not afflicted on that same day shall be cut off from his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.30'>And any soul who does any work on that same day, that soul I will destroy from among his people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.31'>You shall do no work; it shall be a perpetual statute throughout your generations in all your dwellings.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.32'>It shall be to you a Sabbath observance of rest, and you shall afflict your souls; on the ninth day of the month at evening, from evening to evening, you shall observe your sabbath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.33'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.34'>Speak to the children of Israel, saying: The fifteenth day of this seventh month shall be the Feast of Booths for seven days unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.35'>On the first day there shall be a holy convocation. You shall do no labor of work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.36'>For seven days you shall offer an offering by fire unto Jehovah. On the eighth day you shall have a holy convocation, and you shall offer an offering by fire unto Jehovah. It is a solemn assembly, and you shall do no labor of work.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.37'>These are the set feasts of Jehovah which you shall proclaim: holy convocations, to offer an offering by fire unto Jehovah, a burnt offering and a grain offering, a sacrifice and drink offerings, every matter for the day on its day;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.38'>besides the Sabbaths of Jehovah, besides your gifts, besides all your vows, and besides all your freewill offerings which you give unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.39'>Also on the fifteenth day of the seventh month, when you have gathered in the crops of the land, you shall keep the feast of Jehovah for seven days; on the first day there shall be a Sabbath observance, and on the eighth day a Sabbath observance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.40'>And you shall take for yourselves on the first day the fruit of majestic trees, branches of palm trees, the boughs of leafy trees, and willows of the brook; and you shall rejoice before Jehovah your God for seven days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.41'>You shall hold it as a feast unto Jehovah for seven days in the year. It shall be a perpetual statute throughout your generations. You shall hold it in the seventh month.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.42'>You shall dwell in booths for seven days. All who are natives of Israel shall dwell in booths,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.43'>that your generations may know that I made the children of Israel dwell in booths when I brought them out of the land of Egypt: I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.23.44'>Thus Moses declared to the children of Israel the feasts of Jehovah.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.24'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.2'>Command the children of Israel that they bring to you pure oil of beaten olives for the light, to make the lamps burn continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.3'>Outside the veil of the Testimony, in the tent of meeting, Aaron shall arrange it from evening until morning before Jehovah continually; it shall be a perpetual statute throughout your generations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.4'>He shall arrange the lamps on the pure lampstand before Jehovah continually.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.5'>And you shall take fine flour and bake twelve cakes with it. Two-tenths of an ephah shall be in each cake.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.6'>You shall set them in two rows, six to a row, on the pure table before Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.7'>And you shall put pure frankincense on each row, that it may be on the bread for a memorial, an offering by fire unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.8'>Every Sabbath day he shall set it in order before Jehovah continually, from the children of Israel for a perpetual covenant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.9'>And it shall be for Aaron and his sons, and they shall eat it in the holy place; for it is set apart, holy, to him from the offerings of Jehovah by fire, by a perpetual statute.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.10'>Now the son of an Israelite woman, whose father was Egyptian, went out among the children of Israel; and this son of the Israelite woman and a man of Israel struggled together in the camp.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.11'>And the son of the Israelite woman blasphemed the Name and cursed; and so they brought him to Moses. (His mothers name was Shelomith, the daughter of Dibri, of the tribe of Dan.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.12'>And they put him in confinement, that the mouth of Jehovah might be declared to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.13'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.14'>Take him who has cursed outside the camp; and let all who heard him lay their hands on his head, and let all the congregation stone him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.15'>And you shall speak to the children of Israel, saying: Whoever curses his God shall bear his sin.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.16'>And whoever blasphemes the name of Jehovah shall be executed to death. All the congregation shall stone him with stones, the sojourner as well as him who is born in the land. When he blasphemes the Name, he shall be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.17'>Any one who strikes the soul of a man shall be executed to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.18'>Whoever strikes the soul of a beast shall make good; soul for soul.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.19'>If a man causes a blemish to his neighbor, as he has done, so shall it be done to him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.20'>break for break, eye for eye, tooth for tooth; as he has given a blemish to a man, so shall it be done to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.21'>And whoever kills a beast shall make compensation; but whoever kills a man shall be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.22'>You shall have the same law for the sojourner and for the native; for I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.24.23'>And Moses spoke to the children of Israel; and they took him who had cursed outside the camp, and stoned him with stones. Thus the children of Israel did as Jehovah had commanded Moses.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.25'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses on Mount Sinai, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.2'>Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them: When you come into the land which I am giving you, then the land shall keep a sabbath unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.3'>Six years you shall sow your field, and six years you shall prune your vineyard, and gather its produce;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.4'>but in the seventh year there shall be a rest of Sabbath observance for the land, a sabbath unto Jehovah. You shall neither sow your field nor prune your vineyard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.5'>What grows of its own accord of your harvest you shall not reap, nor gather the grapes of your untended vine, for it is a year of rest for the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.6'>And the sabbath of the land shall be food for you: for you, your male and female servants, your hired man, and the stranger who sojourns with you,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.7'>for your livestock and the beasts that are in your land; all its produce shall be for food.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.8'>And you shall count seven sabbaths of years for yourself, seven times seven years; and the time of the seven sabbaths of years shall be to you forty-nine years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.9'>Then you shall cause the shofar of jubilation to sound on the tenth day of the seventh month; on the Day of Atonement you shall make the shofar to pass throughout all your land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.10'>And you shall consecrate the fiftieth year, and proclaim liberty throughout all the land to all its inhabitants. It shall be a Jubilee for you; and each of you shall return to his possession, and each of you shall return to his family.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.11'>The fiftieth year shall be a Jubilee to you; in it you shall neither sow nor reap what grows of its own accord, nor gather the grapes of your untended vine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.12'>For it is the Jubilee; it shall be holy to you; you shall eat its produce from the field.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.13'>In the Year of Jubilee, each of you shall return to his possession.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.14'>And if you sell anything to your neighbor or buy from your neighbors hand, you shall not oppress one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.15'>According to the number of years after the Jubilee you shall buy from your neighbor, and according to the number of years of crops he shall sell to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.16'>According to the multitude of years you shall increase its price, and according to the fewer number of years you shall diminish its price; for he sells to you according to the number of the crops.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.17'>Therefore you shall not oppress one another, but you shall fear your God; for I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.18'>Thus you shall do My statutes and keep My judgments, and do them; and you shall dwell in the land in safety.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.19'>And the land shall yield its fruit, and you shall eat your fill, and dwell there in safety.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.20'>And if you say, What shall we eat in the seventh year, since we shall not sow nor gather in our produce?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.21'>Then I will command My blessing upon you in the sixth year, and it shall produce crops enough for three years.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.22'>And you shall sow in the eighth year, and eat old produce until the ninth year; until its produce comes in, you shall eat of the old harvest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.23'>The land shall not be sold in perpetuity, for the land is Mine; for you are strangers and sojourners with Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.24'>And in all the land of your possession you shall grant redemption of the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.25'>If one of your brethren becomes poor, and has sold some of his possession, and if his redeeming relative comes to redeem it, then he may redeem what his brother sold.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.26'>Or if the man has no one to redeem it, but he himself becomes able to redeem it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.27'>then let him count the years since its sale, and restore the remainder to the man to whom he sold it, that he may return to his possession.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.28'>But if he is not able to have it restored to himself, then what was sold shall remain in the hand of him who bought it until the Year of Jubilee; and in the Jubilee it shall go out, and he shall return to his possession.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.29'>If a man sells a house in a walled city, then he may redeem it within a whole year after it is sold; within a full year he may redeem it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.30'>But if it is not redeemed within the space of a full year, then the house in the walled city shall be confirmed permanently to him who bought it, throughout his generations. It shall not go out in the Jubilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.31'>However the houses of villages which have no wall around them shall be considered as the fields of the land. They may be redeemed, and they shall go out in the Jubilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.32'>Nevertheless the cities of the Levites, and the houses in the cities of their possession, the Levites always have the right of redemption.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.33'>And if a man redeems a house from the Levites, then the house that was sold in the city of his possession shall go out in the Jubilee; for the houses in the cities of the Levites are their possession among the children of Israel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.34'>But the field of the common land of their cities shall not be sold, for it is their perpetual possession.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.35'>If one of your brethren becomes poor, and his hand has become shaky, then you shall support him, like a stranger or a sojourner, that he may live with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.36'>Take no usury or interest from him; but fear your God, that your brother may live with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.37'>You shall not give him your money at interest, nor give him your food at a profit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.38'>I am Jehovah your God, who has brought you out of the land of Egypt, to give you the land of Canaan and to be your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.39'>And if one of your brethren who dwells by you becomes poor, and has sold himself to you, you shall not compel him to serve as a slave.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.40'>As a hired servant and a sojourner he shall be with you, and shall serve you until the Year of Jubilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.41'>And then he shall depart from you; he and his children with him; and shall return to his own family. He shall return to the possession of his fathers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.42'>For they are My servants, whom I brought out of the land of Egypt; they shall not be sold as slaves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.43'>You shall not rule over him with harshness, but you shall fear your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.44'>And as for your male and female slaves whom you may have from the nations that are around you, from them you shall buy male and female slaves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.45'>Moreover you shall buy the children of the strangers who sojourn among you, and their families who are with you, which they beget in your land; and they shall be your property.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.46'>And you shall take them as an inheritance for your children after you, to inherit them as a possession; they shall be your permanent slaves. But regarding your brethren, the children of Israel, you shall not rule over one another with harshness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.47'>Now if a sojourner or stranger close to you becomes rich, and one of your brethren who dwells by him becomes poor, and sells himself to the stranger or sojourner close to you, or to a member of the strangers family,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.48'>after he is sold he may be redeemed again. One of his brothers may redeem him;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.49'>or his uncle or his uncles son may redeem him; or anyone who is near of kin to him in his family may redeem him; or if he is able he may redeem himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.50'>Thus he shall reckon with him who bought him: The price of his sale shall be according to the number of years, from the year that he was sold to him until the Year of Jubilee; it shall be according to the time of a hired servant for him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.51'>If there are still many years remaining, according to them he shall repay the price of his redemption from the money with which he was bought.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.52'>And if there remain but a few years until the Year of Jubilee, then he shall reckon with him, and according to his years he shall repay him the price of his redemption.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.53'>He shall be with him year by year as a hired servant, and he shall not rule with harshness over him before your eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.54'>And if he is not redeemed in these years, then he shall go out in the Year of Jubilee; he and his children with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.25.55'>For the children of Israel are servants to Me; they are My servants whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt: I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.26'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.1'>You shall not make idols for yourselves; neither a carved image nor a sacred pillar shall you rear up for yourselves; nor shall you set up an image of stone in your land, to bow down to it; for I am Jehovah your God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.2'>You shall keep My Sabbaths and reverence My sanctuary: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.3'>If you walk in My statutes and keep My commandments, and do them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.4'>then I will give you rain in its season, the land shall yield its produce, and the trees of the field shall yield their fruit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.5'>Your threshing shall last till the time of vintage, and the vintage shall last till the time of sowing; you shall eat your bread to the full, and dwell in your land safely.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.6'>I will give peace in the land, and you shall lie down, and no one shall make you afraid; I will rid the land of evil beasts, and the sword shall not go through your land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.7'>You shall chase your enemies, and they shall fall by the sword before you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.8'>Five of you shall chase a hundred, and a hundred of you shall put ten thousand to flight; your enemies shall fall by the sword before you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.9'>For I will look on you favorably and make you fruitful, multiply you and establish My covenant with you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.10'>You shall eat the old harvest, and clear out the old because of the new.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.11'>I will set My tabernacle among you, and My soul shall not abhor you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.12'>I will walk among you and be your God, and you shall be My people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.13'>I am Jehovah your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, that you should not be their slaves; I have broken the bands of your yoke and made you walk upright.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.14'>But if you do not obey Me, and do not do all these commandments,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.15'>and if you despise My statutes, or if your soul abhors My judgments, so that you do not do all My commandments, but break My covenant,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.16'>I also will do this to you: I will even appoint terror over you, wasting disease and fever which shall consume the eyes and cause pining away of soul. And you shall sow your seed in vain, for your enemies shall eat it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.17'>I will set My face against you, and you shall be smitten by your enemies. Those who hate you shall reign over you, and you shall flee when no one pursues you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.18'>And after all this, if you do not obey Me, then I will chastise you seven times more for your sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.19'>I will break the pride of your power; I will make your heavens like iron and your earth like bronze.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.20'>And your strength shall be spent in vain; for your land shall not yield its produce, nor shall the trees of the land yield their fruit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.21'>And if you walk contrary to Me, and are not willing to obey Me, I will bring upon you seven times more plagues, according to your sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.22'>I will also send wild beasts among you, which shall rob you of your children, destroy your livestock, and make you few in number; and your highways shall be desolate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.23'>And if by these things you do not let yourselves be corrected by Me, but walk contrary to Me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.24'>then I also will walk contrary to you, and I will punish you yet seven times for your sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.25'>And I will bring a sword against you that shall execute the vengeance of the covenant; when you are gathered together within your cities I will send pestilence among you; and you shall be delivered into the hand of the enemy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.26'>And when I have cut off your supply of bread, ten women shall bake your bread in one oven, and they shall bring back your bread by weight, and you shall eat and not be satisfied.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.27'>And after all this, if you do not obey Me, but walk contrary to Me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.28'>then I also will walk contrary to you in fury; and I, even I, will chastise you seven times for your sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.29'>And you shall eat the flesh of your sons, and you shall eat the flesh of your daughters.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.30'>And I will destroy your high places, cut down your incense altars, and cast your carcasses upon the carcasses of your idols; and My soul shall abhor you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.31'>And I will lay your cities waste and bring your sanctuaries to desolation, and I will not smell your soothing aromas.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.32'>I will bring the land to desolation, and your enemies who dwell in it shall be astonished at it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.33'>I will scatter you among the nations and draw out a sword after you; your land shall be desolate and your cities waste.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.34'>Then the land shall enjoy its sabbaths as long as it lies desolate and you are in the land of your enemies; then the land shall rest and enjoy its sabbaths.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.35'>As long as it lies desolate it shall rest; because it did not rest on your sabbaths when you dwelt in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.36'>And as for those of you who are left, I will send faintness into their hearts in the lands of their enemies; the sound of a driven leaf shall cause them to flee; they shall flee as though fleeing from a sword, and they shall fall when no one is pursuing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.37'>They shall stumble over one another, as it were before a sword, when no one is pursuing; and you shall have no power to stand before your enemies.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.38'>You shall perish among the nations, and the land of your enemies shall consume you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.39'>And those of you who are left shall rot away in their iniquity in the lands of their enemies; also in their fathers iniquities, which are with them, they shall rot away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.40'>But if they confess their iniquity and the iniquity of their fathers, with their unfaithfulness in which they were unfaithful to Me, and that they also have walked contrary to Me,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.41'>and that I also have walked contrary to them and have brought them into the land of their enemies; if their uncircumcised hearts are humbled, and they accept their guilt;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.42'>then I will remember My covenant with Jacob, and My covenant with Isaac and My covenant with Abraham I will remember; and I will remember the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.43'>The land also shall be forsaken by them, and shall be satisfied with its sabbaths while it lies desolate without them; they shall accept their guilt, because they had despised My judgments and because their soul had abhorred My statutes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.44'>Yet for all that, when they are in the land of their enemies, I will not reject them, nor shall I abhor them, to utterly destroy them and break My covenant with them; for I am Jehovah their God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.45'>But for their sake I will remember the covenant of their ancestors, whom I brought out of the land of Egypt in the eyes of the nations, that I might be their God: I am Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.26.46'>These are the statutes and judgments and laws which Jehovah has set between Himself and the children of Israel on Mount Sinai by the hand of Moses.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Lev.27'>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.1'>And Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.2'>Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them: When a man makes an extraordinary vow of his soul unto Jehovah by valuation,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.3'>if your valuation is of a male from twenty years old up to sixty years old, then your valuation shall be fifty shekels of silver, according to the shekel of the sanctuary.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.4'>If it is a female, then your valuation shall be thirty shekels;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.5'>and if from five years old up to twenty years old, then your valuation for a male shall be twenty shekels, and for a female ten shekels;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.6'>and if from a month old up to five years old, then your valuation for a male shall be five shekels of silver, and for a female your valuation shall be three shekels of silver;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.7'>and if from sixty years old and above, if it is a male, then your valuation shall be fifteen shekels, and for a female ten shekels.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.8'>But if he is too poor to pay your valuation, then he shall present himself before the priest, and the priest shall set a value for him; according to what he who vowed is able to afford, the priest shall value him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.9'>If it is an animal that men may bring as an offering unto Jehovah, all that anyone gives unto Jehovah shall be holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.10'>He shall not substitute it nor exchange it, good for bad or bad for good; and if he at all exchanges beast for beast, then both it and the one exchanged for it shall be holy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.11'>If it is an unclean beast which they do not offer as an offering unto Jehovah, then he shall present the beast before the priest;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.12'>and the priest shall set a value for it, whether it is good or bad; as you, the priest, value it, so it shall be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.13'>But if he pays to redeem it, then he shall add one-fifth to your valuation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.14'>And when a man consecrates his house to be holy unto Jehovah, then the priest shall set a value for it, whether it is good or bad; as the priest values it, so it shall stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.15'>If he who consecrated it will redeem his house, then he shall add one-fifth of the money of your valuation to it, and it shall be his.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.16'>If a man consecrates unto Jehovah part of a field of his possession, then your valuation shall be according to the seed for it. A homer of barley seed shall be valued at fifty shekels of silver.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.17'>If he consecrates his field from the Year of Jubilee, according to your valuation it shall stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.18'>But if he consecrates his field after the Jubilee, then the priest shall reckon to him the money due according to the years that remain till the Year of Jubilee, and it shall be deducted from your valuation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.19'>And if he who consecrates the field will pay to redeem it, then he shall add one-fifth of the money of your valuation to it, and it shall be confirmed to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.20'>But if he does not redeem the field, or if he has sold the field to another man, it shall not be redeemed anymore;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.21'>but the field, when it goes out in the Jubilee, shall be holy unto Jehovah, as a devoted field; it shall be the possession of the priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.22'>And if a man consecrates unto Jehovah a field which he has bought, which is not the field of his possession,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.23'>then the priest shall reckon to him the worth of your valuation, up to the Year of Jubilee, and he shall give your valuation on that day as a holy offering unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.24'>In the Year of Jubilee the field shall return to him from whom it was bought, to the one who owns the land as a possession.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.25'>And all your valuations shall be according to the shekel of the sanctuary: twenty gerahs to the shekel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.26'>But the firstborn of the beasts, which is the firstborn unto Jehovah, no man shall consecrate; whether ox or sheep: it is already Jehovahs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.27'>And if it is an unclean beast, then he shall redeem it according to your valuation, and shall add one-fifth to it; or if it is not redeemed, then it shall be sold according to your valuation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.28'>Nevertheless no devoted thing that a man may devote unto Jehovah of all that he has, both man and beast, or the field of his possession, shall be sold or redeemed; every devoted thing is set apart, holy, unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.29'>No devoted thing, devoted for destruction by men, shall be redeemed, but shall die the death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.30'>And all the tithe of the land, whether of the seed of the land or of the fruit of the tree, is Jehovahs. It is holy unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.31'>If a man will pay to redeem any of his tithes, he shall add one-fifth to it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.32'>And concerning the tithe of the herd or the flock, of whatever passes under the rod, the tenth one shall be holy unto Jehovah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.33'>He shall not inquire whether it is good or bad, nor shall he exchange it; and if he makes a change to exchange it, then both it and the one exchanged for it shall be holy; it shall not be redeemed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Lev.27.34'>These are the commandments which Jehovah commanded Moses for the children of Israel on Mount Sinai.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>