<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='XXX' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='XXX'>
        <title>VW-Edition 2006</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject/>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>English translation of the Bible from the Masoretic and Textus Receptus Hebrew/Greek texts. A 'literal' translation with the readability of a NKJV or MKJV. In print: www.a-voice.org/bible-vw/print.htm  "About this Edition" www.a-voice.org/bible-vw/preface.htm</description>
        <publisher>A Voice in the Wilderness, POBox 9531, Spokane, WA 99209, USA (www.a-voice.org)</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>XXX</identifier>
        <source/>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>Freely copy and distribute</coverage>
        <rights>This module is not to be sold. Do not modify or reconfigure for other software without authorization from publisher</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div osisID='Mark' type='book'>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.1'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.1'>The beginning of the gospel of Jesus Christ, the Son of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.2'>As it is written in the Prophets: Behold, I send My messenger before Your face, who will prepare Your way before You.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.3'>The voice of one crying in the wilderness: Prepare the way of the Lord; make His paths straight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.4'>John came immersing in the wilderness and preaching an immersion of repentance for the remission of sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.5'>And all the land of Judea, and those from Jerusalem, went out to him and were all immersed by him in the Jordan River, confessing their sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.6'>Now John was clothed with camels hair and with a leather waistband around his waist, and he ate locusts and wild honey.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.7'>And he preached, saying, There comes One after me who is mightier than I, whose sandal strap I am not worthy to stoop down and loose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.8'>I indeed immerse you in water, but He will immerse you in the Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.9'>And it came to pass in those days that Jesus came from Nazareth of Galilee, and was immersed by John in the Jordan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.10'>And immediately, coming up from the water, He saw the heavens parting and the Spirit descending upon Him like a dove.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.11'>And a voice came from Heaven, You are My beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.12'>And immediately the Spirit drove Him into the wilderness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.13'>And He was there in the wilderness forty days, tempted by Satan, and was with the wild beasts; and the angels ministered to Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.14'>Now after John was put in prison, Jesus came into Galilee, preaching the gospel of the kingdom of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.15'>and saying, The time is fulfilled, and the kingdom of God is at hand. Repent, and believe in the gospel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.16'>And as He walked by the Sea of Galilee, He saw Simon and Andrew his brother casting a net into the sea; for they were fishermen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.17'>And Jesus said to them, Come after Me, and I will make you to become fishers of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.18'>And they immediately left their nets and followed Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.19'>And when He had gone a little farther from there, He saw Jacob the son of Zebedee, and John his brother, who also were in the boat mending their nets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.20'>And immediately He called them, and they left their father Zebedee in the boat with the hired servants, and went after Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.21'>And they went into Capernaum, and immediately on the Sabbath He entered the synagogue and taught.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.22'>And they were astonished at His doctrine, for He taught them as one having authority, and not as the scribes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.23'>Now there was a man in their synagogue with an unclean spirit. And he cried out,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.24'>saying, Let us alone! What have we to do with You, Jesus of Nazareth? Did You come to destroy us? I know who You are; the Holy One of God!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.25'>But Jesus rebuked him, saying, Be quiet, and come out of him!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.26'>And when the unclean spirit had convulsed him and cried out with a loud voice, he came out of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.27'>And they were all amazed, so that they questioned among themselves, saying, What is this? What new doctrine is this? For with authority He commands even the unclean spirits, and they obey Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.28'>And immediately His fame spread throughout all the region around Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.29'>And as soon as they had come out of the synagogue, they entered the house of Simon and Andrew, with Jacob and John.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.30'>But Simons wifes mother lay sick with a fever, and at once they told Him about her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.31'>So He came and took her by the hand and lifted her up, and immediately the fever left her. And she served them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.32'>And at evening, when the sun had set, they brought to Him all who were sick and those who were demon-possessed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.33'>And the whole city was gathered together at the door.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.34'>And He healed many who were sick with various diseases, and cast out many demons; and He did not allow the demons to speak, because they knew Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.35'>And in the morning, having risen a long while before daylight, He went out and departed to a solitary place; and there prayed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.36'>And Simon and those who were with Him followed after Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.37'>And when they found Him, they said to Him, Everyone is looking for You.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.38'>But He said to them, Let us go into the neighboring towns, that I may preach there also, because for this purpose I have come forth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.39'>And He was preaching in their synagogues throughout all Galilee, and casting out demons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.40'>Now a leper came to Him, begging Him, kneeling down to Him and saying to Him, If You are willing, You can make me clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.41'>And Jesus, moved with compassion, stretched out His hand and touched him, and said to him, I am willing; be made clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.42'>And as soon as He had spoken, immediately the leprosy departed from him, and he was cleansed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.43'>And He strictly warned him and sent him away at once,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.44'>and said to him, See that you say nothing to anyone; but go your way, show yourself to the priest, and offer for your cleansing those things which Moses commanded, as a testimony to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.45'>However, he went out and began to proclaim it freely, and to spread the matter, so that Jesus could no longer openly enter the city, but was outside in deserted places; and they came to Him from every direction.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.2'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.1'>And again He entered Capernaum after some days, and it was heard that He was in the house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.2'>And immediately many gathered together, so that there was no longer room to receive them, not even near the door. And He preached the Word to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.3'>And they came to Him, bringing a paralytic who was carried by four men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.4'>And when they could not come near Him because of the crowd, they uncovered the roof where He was. So when they had dug through, they let down the bed on which the paralytic was lying.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.5'>When Jesus saw their faith, He said to the paralytic, Son, your sins are forgiven you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.6'>But some of the scribes were sitting there and reasoning in their hearts,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.7'>Why does this Man speak blasphemies like this? Who can forgive sins except for One, God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.8'>And immediately, when Jesus perceived in His spirit that they reasoned thus within themselves, He said to them, Why do you reason these things in your hearts?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.9'>Which is easier: To say to the paralytic, Your sins are forgiven you; or to say, Arise, take up your bed and walk?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.10'>But that you may know that the Son of Man has authority on earth to forgive sins; He said to the paralytic,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.11'>I say to you, Arise, take up your bed, and go to your house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.12'>And immediately he arose, took up the bed, and went out in the presence of them all, so that all were amazed and glorified God, saying, We never saw anything like this!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.13'>Then He went out again by the sea; and all the multitude came to Him, and He taught them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.14'>And as He passed by, He saw Levi the son of Alphaeus sitting at the tax office. And He said to him, Follow Me. So he arose and followed Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.15'>And it happened, as He was dining in Levis house, that many tax collectors and sinners also sat together with Jesus and His disciples; for there were many, and they followed Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.16'>And when the scribes and Pharisees saw Him eating with the tax collectors and sinners, they said to His disciples, How is it that He eats and drinks with tax collectors and sinners?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.17'>When Jesus heard it, He said to them, Those who are well have no need of a physician, but those who are sick. I did not come to call the righteous, but sinners, to repentance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.18'>And the disciples of John and of the Pharisees were fasting. And they came and said to Him, Why do the disciples of John and of the Pharisees fast, but Your disciples do not fast?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.19'>And Jesus said to them, Can the sons of the bridechamber fast while the bridegroom is with them? As long as they have the bridegroom with them they cannot fast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.20'>But the days will come when the bridegroom will be taken away from them, and then they will fast in those days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.21'>No one sews a piece of unshrunk cloth on an old garment; or else the new piece pulls away from the old, and the tear is made worse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.22'>And no one puts new wine into old wineskins; or else the new wine bursts the wineskins, the wine is spilled, and the wineskins are ruined. But new wine must be put into new wineskins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.23'>Now it happened that He went through the grainfields on the Sabbath; and as they went His disciples began to pluck the heads of grain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.24'>And the Pharisees said to Him, Behold, why do they do what is not lawful on the Sabbath?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.25'>But He said to them, Have you never read what David did when he was in need and hungry, he and those with him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.26'>how he went into the house of God in the days of Abiathar the high priest, and ate the Bread of Presentation, which is not lawful to eat, except for the priests, and also gave to those who were with him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.27'>And He said to them, The Sabbath was made for man, and not man for the Sabbath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.28'>Therefore the Son of Man is also Lord of the Sabbath.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.3'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.1'>And He entered the synagogue again, and a man was there who had a withered hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.2'>So they watched Him closely, whether He would heal him on the Sabbath, so that they might accuse Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.3'>And He said to the man who had the withered hand, Stand up in the middle.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.4'>And He said to them, Is it lawful on the Sabbath to do good or to do evil, to save life or to kill? But they kept silent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.5'>And when He had looked around at them with anger, being grieved at the hardness of their hearts, He said to the man, Stretch out your hand. And he stretched it out, and his hand was restored as whole as the other.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.6'>And the Pharisees went out and immediately took counsel with the Herodians against Him, how they might destroy Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.7'>But Jesus withdrew with His disciples to the sea. And a great multitude from Galilee followed Him, and from Judea</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.8'>and Jerusalem and Idumea and beyond the Jordan; and those from Tyre and Sidon, a great multitude, when they heard how many things He was doing, came to Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.9'>And He said to His disciples that a small boat should be kept ready for Him because of the multitude, that they might not press upon Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.10'>For He healed many, such that, as many as had plagues lunged upon Him in order to touch Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.11'>And the unclean spirits, whenever they saw Him, fell down before Him and cried out, saying, You are the Son of God!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.12'>But He sternly warned them that they should not make Him known.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.13'>And He went up on the mountain and called to Him those He Himself wanted. And they came to Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.14'>And He appointed twelve, that they might be with Him and that He might send them forth to preach,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.15'>and to have authority to heal sicknesses and to cast out demons:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.16'>Simon, to whom He gave the name Peter;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.17'>Jacob the son of Zebedee and John the brother of Jacob, to whom He gave the name Boanerges, that is, Sons of Thunder;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.18'>Andrew, Philip, Bartholomew, Matthew, Thomas, Jacob the son of Alphaeus, Thaddaeus, Simon the Canaanite;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.19'>and Judas Iscariot, who also betrayed Him. And they went into a house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.20'>And the multitude came together again, so that they were not even able to eat bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.21'>But when His next of kin heard about this, they went out to lay hold of Him, for they said, He is beside Himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.22'>And the scribes who came down from Jerusalem said, He has Beelzebub, and, by the ruler of the demons He casts out demons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.23'>So He called them to Himself and said to them in parables: How can Satan cast out Satan?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.24'>If a kingdom is divided against itself, that kingdom cannot stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.25'>And if a house is divided against itself, that house is not able to stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.26'>And if Satan has risen up against himself, and is divided, he cannot stand, but has an end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.27'>No one can enter a strong mans house and plunder his goods, unless he first binds the strong man. And then he will plunder his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.28'>Truly, I say to you, All sins will be forgiven the sons of men, and whatever blasphemies they may blaspheme;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.29'>but he who blasphemes against the Holy Spirit never has remission, but is subject to eternal damnation;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.30'>because they said, He has an unclean spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.31'>Then His brothers and His mother came, and standing outside they sent to Him, calling Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.32'>And a multitude was sitting around Him; and they said to Him, Behold, Your mother and Your brothers are seeking You outside.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.33'>But He answered them, saying, Who is My mother, or My brothers?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.34'>And He looked around in a circle at those who sat around Him, and said, Behold My mother and My brothers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.35'>For whoever does the will of God is My brother and My sister and mother.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.4'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.1'>And again He began to teach by the sea. And a great multitude was gathered to Him, so that He got into a boat and sat in it on the sea; and the whole multitude was on the land facing the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.2'>And He taught them many things by parables, and said to them in His teaching:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.3'>Listen. Behold, a sower went out to sow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.4'>And it happened, as he sowed, that some seed fell by the wayside; and the birds of the air came and devoured it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.5'>Some fell on stony ground, where it did not have much earth; and immediately it sprang up because it had no depth of earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.6'>But when the sun was up it was scorched, and because it had no root it withered away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.7'>And some seed fell among thorns; and the thorns grew up and choked it, and it yielded no fruit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.8'>But other seed fell on good ground and yielded fruit that sprang up, increased and produced: one thirtyfold, one sixty, and one a hundred.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.9'>And He said to them, He who has ears to hear, let him hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.10'>And when He was alone, those around Him with the twelve asked Him about the parable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.11'>And He said to them, To you it has been given to know the mystery of the kingdom of God; but to those who are outside, all things are in parables,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.12'>so that seeing they may see and not perceive, and hearing they may hear and not understand; lest they should convert, and their sins be forgiven them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.13'>And He said to them, Do you not understand this parable? How then will you understand all parables?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.14'>The sower sows the Word.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.15'>And these are the ones by the wayside where the Word is sown: When they hear, Satan comes immediately and takes away the Word that was sown in their hearts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.16'>These likewise are the ones sown on stony ground who, when they hear the Word, immediately receive it with joy;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.17'>and they have no root in themselves, and so endure only for a time. Afterward, when affliction or persecution arises on account of the Word, immediately they stumble.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.18'>And these are the ones sown among thorns; they are the ones who hear the Word,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.19'>and the cares of this world, the deceitfulness of riches, and the lusts for other things entering in choke the Word, and it becomes unfruitful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.20'>But these are the ones sown on good ground, those who hear the Word, receive it, and bear fruit: one thirtyfold, one sixty, and one a hundred.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.21'>And He said to them, Is a lamp brought to be put under a basket or under a bed? Is it not to be set on a lampstand?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.22'>For there is nothing hidden which will not be revealed, nor has anything been kept secret but what it will come to light.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.23'>If anyone has ears to hear, let him hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.24'>And He said to them, Take heed what you hear. With the same measure you use, it will be measured to you; and to you who hear, more will be given.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.25'>For whoever has, to him more will be given; but whoever does not have, even what he has will be taken away from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.26'>And He said, The kingdom of God is as if a man should scatter seed on the ground,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.27'>and should sleep and rise, night and day, and the seed should sprout and grow, he himself does not know how.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.28'>For the earth bears fruit by itself: first the blade, then the ear, after that the full grain in the ear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.29'>But when the fruit yields, immediately he puts in the sickle, because the harvest has come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.30'>And He said, To what shall we liken the kingdom of God? Or with what parable shall we compare it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.31'>It is like a grain of mustard seed which, when it is sown on the ground, is smaller than all the seeds on earth;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.32'>but when it is sown, it grows up and becomes greater than all herbs, and produces large branches, so that the birds of the air are able to nest under its shade.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.33'>And with many such parables He spoke the Word to them as they were able to hear it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.34'>But He did not speak to them without a parable. And when they were alone, He explained all things to His disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.35'>And the same day, when evening had come, He said to them, Let us cross over to the other side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.36'>And when they had sent away the multitude, they took Him along in the boat as He was. And other little boats were also with Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.37'>And a great windstorm arose, and the waves beat into the boat, so that it was already full.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.38'>But He was in the stern, asleep on a pillow. And they awoke Him and said to Him, Teacher, do You not care that we are perishing?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.39'>And He arose and rebuked the wind, and said to the sea, Be silent! Be muzzled! And the wind ceased and there was a great calm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.40'>And He said to them, Why are you so fearful? How is it that you have no faith?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.41'>And they feared exceedingly, and said to one another, Who can this be, that even the wind and the sea obey Him?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.5'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.1'>And they came to the other side of the sea, to the country of the Gadarenes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.2'>And when He had come out of the boat, immediately there met Him out of the tombs a man with an unclean spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.3'>who had his dwelling among the tombs; and no one was able to bind him, not even with chains,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.4'>because he had often been bound with shackles and chains. And the chains had been pulled apart by him, and the shackles broken in pieces; neither could anyone tame him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.5'>And continually, night and day, he was in the mountains and in the tombs, crying out and cutting himself with stones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.6'>And when he saw Jesus from afar, he ran and did homage to Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.7'>And he cried out with a loud voice and said, What have I to do with You, Jesus, Son of the Most High God? I adjure You by God that You do not torment me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.8'>For He said to him, Come out of the man, unclean spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.9'>And He asked him, What is your name? And he answered, saying, My name is Legion; for we are many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.10'>He also begged Him earnestly that He would not send them out of the country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.11'>Now a large herd of swine was feeding there near the mountains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.12'>So all the demons begged Him, saying, Send us into the swine, that we may enter into them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.13'>And Jesus immediately gave them permission. And the unclean spirits went out and entered the swine (there were about two thousand); and the herd ran violently down the steep place into the sea, and drowned in the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.14'>And those who fed the swine fled, and they told it in the city and in the country. And they went out to see what it was that had happened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.15'>And they came to Jesus, and saw the one who had been demon-possessed and had the legion, sitting and clothed and in his right mind. And they were afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.16'>And those who saw it told them how it happened to him who had been demon-possessed, and about the swine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.17'>And they began to beg Him to depart from their borders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.18'>And when He got into the boat, he who had been demon-possessed begged Him that he might be with Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.19'>However, Jesus did not permit him, but said to him, Go home to your friends, and tell them what great things the Lord has done for you, and how He has had compassion on you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.20'>And he departed and began to proclaim in Decapolis all that Jesus had done for him; and everyone marveled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.21'>And when Jesus had crossed over again by boat to the other side, a great multitude gathered to Him; and He was by the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.22'>And behold, one of the rulers of the synagogue came, Jairus by name. And when he saw Him, he fell at His feet</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.23'>and begged Him earnestly, saying, My little daughter lies at the point of death. Come and lay Your hands on her, that she may be healed, and she will live.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.24'>So Jesus went with him, and a great multitude followed Him and thronged Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.25'>And a certain woman had a flow of blood for twelve years,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.26'>and had suffered many things from many physicians. She had spent all that she had and was no better, but rather grew worse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.27'>When she heard about Jesus, she came behind Him in the crowd and touched His garment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.28'>For she said, If only I may touch His clothes, I shall be made well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.29'>And immediately the fountain of her blood was dried up, and she knew in her body that she was healed of the plague.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.30'>And Jesus, immediately knowing in Himself that power had gone out of Him, turned around in the crowd and said, Who touched My clothes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.31'>But His disciples said to Him, You see the multitude thronging You, and do You say, Who touched Me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.32'>And He looked around to see her who had done this thing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.33'>And the woman, fearing and trembling, knowing what had happened in her, came and fell down before Him and told Him all the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.34'>And He said to her, Daughter, your faith has made you well. Go in peace, and be healed of your plague.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.35'>While He was still speaking, some came from the ruler of the synagogues house who said, Your daughter is dead. Why trouble the Teacher any further?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.36'>As soon as Jesus heard the word that was spoken, He said to the ruler of the synagogue, Do not be afraid; only believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.37'>And He permitted no one to follow Him except Peter, Jacob, and John the brother of Jacob.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.38'>And He came to the house of the ruler of the synagogue, and saw a tumult and those who wept and wailed loudly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.39'>And when He came in, He said to them, Why do you make this commotion and weep? The child has not died, but is sleeping.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.40'>And they ridiculed Him. But when He had put them all outside, He took the father and the mother of the child, and those who were with Him, and entered where the child was lying.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.41'>And He took the child by the hand, and said to her, Talitha, koumi, which is translated, Little girl, I say to you, Arise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.42'>And immediately the girl arose and walked, for she was twelve years of age. And they were beside themselves with great amazement.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.43'>And He commanded them strictly that no one should know it, and said that something should be given to her to eat.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.6'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.1'>And He went out from there and came to His own country, and His disciples followed Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.2'>And when the Sabbath had come, He began to teach in the synagogue. And many hearing Him were astonished, saying, Where did this Man get these things? And what wisdom is this which is given to Him, that such works of power are performed by His hands?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.3'>Is this not the carpenter, the Son of Mary, and brother of Jacob, Joses, Judas, and Simon? And are not His sisters here with us? And they were offended at Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.4'>But Jesus said to them, A prophet is not without honor except in his own country, among his own kindred, and in his own house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.5'>And He could do no work of power there, except that He laid His hands on a few sick people and healed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.6'>And He marveled because of their unbelief. And He went about the villages in a circuit, teaching.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.7'>And He called the twelve to Himself, and began to send them out two by two, and gave them authority over unclean spirits,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.8'>and commanded them to take nothing for the journey except a staff; no bag, no bread, no copper in their money belts;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.9'>but to wear sandals, and not to put on two tunics.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.10'>And He said to them, In whatever place you enter a house, stay there till you depart from that place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.11'>And whoever will not receive you nor hear you, when you depart from there, shake off the dust under your feet as a testimony against them. Truly, I say to you, it will be more tolerable for Sodom and Gomorrah in the day of judgment than for that city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.12'>So they went out and preached that people should repent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.13'>And they cast out many demons, and anointed with oil many who were sick, and healed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.14'>Now King Herod heard of Him, for His name had become well known. And he said, John the Immerser has been raised from the dead, and therefore these powers are at work in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.15'>Others said, It is Elijah. And others said, It is a prophet, or like one of the prophets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.16'>But when Herod heard, he said, This is John, whom I beheaded; he has been raised from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.17'>For Herod himself had sent and laid hold of John, and bound him in prison because of Herodias, his brother Philips wife; for he had married her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.18'>For John had said to Herod, It is not lawful for you to have your brothers wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.19'>Therefore Herodias held it against him and wanted to kill him, but was not able;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.20'>for Herod feared John, knowing that he was a just and holy man, and he protected him. And when he heard him, he did many things, and heard him gladly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.21'>Then an opportune day came when Herod on his birthday made a feast for his nobles, the high officers, and the chief men of Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.22'>And when Herodias daughter herself came in and danced, and pleased Herod and those who sat with him, the king said to the girl, Ask me whatever you want, and I will give it to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.23'>He also swore to her, Whatever you ask me, I will give you, up to half of my kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.24'>So she went out and said to her mother, What shall I ask? And she said, The head of John the Immerser.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.25'>And immediately she came in with haste to the king and asked, saying, I want you to give me on a platter at once the head of John the Immerser.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.26'>And the king was exceedingly sorry; yet, because of the oaths and because of those who sat with him, he did not want to slight her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.27'>And immediately the king sent an executioner and commanded his head to be brought. And he went and beheaded him in prison,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.28'>brought his head on a platter, and gave it to the girl; and the girl gave it to her mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.29'>And when his disciples heard of it, they came and took away his corpse and laid it in a tomb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.30'>Then the apostles gathered to Jesus and told Him all things, both what they had done and what they had taught.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.31'>And He said to them, Come apart by yourselves to a deserted place and rest a while. For there were many coming and going, and they did not even have opportunity to eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.32'>So they departed to a deserted place in the boat by themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.33'>But the multitudes saw them departing, and many knew Him and ran there on foot from all the cities. They arrived before them and came together to Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.34'>And Jesus, when He came out, saw a great multitude and was moved with compassion for them, because they were like sheep not having a shepherd. So He began to teach them many things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.35'>And when the day was now far spent, His disciples came to Him and said, This is a deserted place, and already the hour is late.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.36'>Send them away, that they may go into the surrounding country and villages and buy themselves bread; for they have nothing to eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.37'>But He answered and said to them, You give them something to eat. And they said to Him, Shall we go and buy two hundred denarii worth of bread and give them something to eat?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.38'>But He said to them, How many loaves do you have? Go and see. And when they found out they said, Five, and two fish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.39'>Then He commanded them to make them all sit down in groups on the green grass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.40'>So they sat down in ranks, in hundreds and in fifties.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.41'>And when He had taken the five loaves and the two fish, He looked up to Heaven, blessed and broke the loaves, and gave them to His disciples to set before them; and the two fish He divided among them all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.42'>So everyone ate and was filled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.43'>And they took up twelve baskets full of fragments and of the fish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.44'>And those who had eaten the loaves were about five thousand men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.45'>And immediately He made His disciples get into the boat and go before Him to the other side, to Bethsaida, while He sent the multitude away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.46'>And when He had sent them away, He departed into the mountain to pray.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.47'>And when evening came, the boat was in the middle of the sea; and He was alone on the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.48'>And He saw them straining at rowing, for the wind was against them. And about the fourth watch of the night He came to them, walking on the sea, and would have passed them by.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.49'>And when they saw Him walking on the sea, they supposed it was a ghost, and cried out;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.50'>for they all saw Him and were troubled. But immediately He talked with them and said to them, Be of good courage. It is I; do not be afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.51'>And He went up into the boat to them, and the wind ceased. And they were greatly amazed in themselves beyond measure, and marveled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.52'>For they did not understand about the loaves, because their heart was hardened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.53'>And when they had crossed over, they came to the land of Gennesaret and drew to shore.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.54'>And when they came out of the boat, immediately the people recognized Him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.55'>ran through that whole surrounding region, and began to carry about on beds those who were sick to wherever they heard He was.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.56'>And wherever He entered into villages, cities, or in the country, they laid the sick in the marketplaces, and begged Him that they might just touch the hem of His garment. And as many as touched Him were made well.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.7'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.1'>Then the Pharisees and some of the scribes came together to Him, having come from Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.2'>And when they saw some of His disciples eat bread with defiled, that is, with unwashed hands, they found fault.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.3'>For the Pharisees and all the Jews do not eat unless they wash their hands with the fist, holding the tradition of the elders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.4'>And when they come from the marketplace, they do not eat unless they wash. And there are many other things which they have received and hold, like the dipping of cups, pitchers, copper vessels, and couches.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.5'>So the Pharisees and scribes asked Him, Why do Your disciples not walk according to the tradition of the elders, but eat bread with unwashed hands?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.6'>He answered and said to them, Well did Isaiah prophesy concerning you hypocrites, as it is written: This people honors Me with their lips, but their heart is far away from Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.7'>And in vain they revere Me, teaching as doctrines the commandments of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.8'>For laying aside the commandment of God, you hold the tradition of men; the dipping of pitchers and cups, and many other such things you do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.9'>And He said to them, Full well you set aside the commandment of God, that you may keep your tradition.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.10'>For Moses said, Honor your father and your mother; and, He who curses father or mother, let him die the death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.11'>But you say, If a man says to his father or mother, Whatever profit you might have received from me is Corban (that is, a gift),</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.12'>then you no longer let him do anything for his father or his mother,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.13'>making the Word of God of no effect through your tradition which you have handed down. And many such things you do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.14'>And when He had called all the multitude to Himself, He said to them, Hear Me, everyone, and understand:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.15'>There is nothing that enters a man from outside which is able to defile him; but the things which come out of him, those are the things that defile a man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.16'>If anyone has ears to hear, let him hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.17'>And when He had entered a house away from the crowd, His disciples asked Him concerning the parable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.18'>So He said to them, Are you thus without understanding also? Do you not perceive that whatever enters a man from outside cannot defile him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.19'>because it does not enter his heart but his stomach, and goes out as waste? Thus He was purifying all foods.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.20'>And He said, What comes out of a man, that defiles a man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.21'>For from within, out of the heart of men, proceed evil thoughts, adulteries, sexual perversions, murders,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.22'>thefts, covetousness, wickedness, deceit, licentiousness, an evil eye, blasphemy, pride, foolishness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.23'>All these evil things come from within and defile a man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.24'>From there He arose and went to the region of Tyre and Sidon. And He entered a house and wanted no one to know it, but He could not be hidden.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.25'>For a woman whose young daughter had an unclean spirit heard about Him, and she came and fell at His feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.26'>The woman was a Greek, a Syro-Phoenician by birth, and she begged Him to cast the demon out of her daughter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.27'>But Jesus said to her, Let the children be filled first, for it is not good to take the childrens bread and throw it to the little dogs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.28'>And she answered and said to Him, Yes, Lord, yet even the little dogs under the table eat from the childrens crumbs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.29'>Then He said to her, For this saying go your way; the demon has gone out of your daughter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.30'>And when she had come to her house, she found the demon gone out, and her daughter lying on the bed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.31'>And again, departing from the region of Tyre and Sidon, He came through the middle of the region of Decapolis to the Sea of Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.32'>And they brought to Him one who was deaf and had an impediment in his speech, and they begged Him to put His hand on him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.33'>And He took him aside from the multitude, and put His fingers in his ears, and He spat and touched his tongue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.34'>Then, looking up to Heaven, He sighed, and said to him, Ephphatha, that is, Be opened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.35'>And immediately his ears were opened, and the bond of his tongue was loosed, and he spoke correctly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.36'>And He commanded them that they should tell no one; but the more He commanded them, the more widely they proclaimed it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.37'>And they were astonished beyond measure, saying, He has done all things well. He makes both the deaf to hear and the mute to speak.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.8'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.1'>In those days, the multitude being very great and having nothing to eat, Jesus called His disciples to Him and said to them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.2'>I have compassion on the multitude, because they have now continued with Me three days and have nothing to eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.3'>And if I send them away hungry to their own houses, they will faint on the way; for some of them have come from afar.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.4'>And His disciples answered Him, How can one satisfy these people with bread here in the wilderness?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.5'>He asked them, How many loaves do you have? And they said, Seven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.6'>So He commanded the multitude to sit down on the ground. And He took the seven loaves and gave thanks, broke them and gave them to His disciples to set before them; and they set them before the multitude.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.7'>And they also had a few small fish; and having blessed them, He said to set them also before them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.8'>So they ate and were filled, and they took up seven baskets of leftover fragments.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.9'>And those who had eaten were about four thousand. And He sent them away,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.10'>and immediately got into the boat with His disciples, and came into the region of Dalmanutha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.11'>And the Pharisees came out and began to dispute with Him, seeking from Him a sign from Heaven, testing Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.12'>But He sighed deeply in His spirit, and said, Why does this generation seek a sign? Truly I say to you, As if a sign will be given to this generation!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.13'>And He left them, and getting into the boat again, departed to the other side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.14'>Now the disciples had forgotten to take bread, and they did not have more than one loaf with them in the boat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.15'>And He charged them, saying, Take heed, beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and the leaven of Herod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.16'>And they reasoned among themselves, saying, It is because we have no bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.17'>But Jesus, knowing, said to them, Why do you reason because you have no bread? Do you not yet perceive nor understand? Is your heart still hardened?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.18'>Having eyes, do you not see? And having ears, do you not hear? And do you not remember?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.19'>When I broke the five loaves for the five thousand, how many baskets full of fragments did you take up? They said to Him, Twelve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.20'>Also, when I broke the seven for the four thousand, how many baskets full of fragments did you take up? And they said, Seven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.21'>So He said to them, How is it you do not understand?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.22'>Then He came to Bethsaida; and they brought a blind man to Him, and begged Him to touch him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.23'>So He took the blind man by the hand and led him out of the town. And when He had spit on his eyes and put His hands on him, He asked him if he saw anything.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.24'>And he looked up and said, I see men like trees, walking.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.25'>Then He put His hands on his eyes again and made him look up. And he was restored and saw everyone clearly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.26'>Then He sent him away to his house, saying, Neither go into the town, nor tell anyone in the town.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.27'>And Jesus and His disciples went out to the towns of Caesarea Philippi; and on the road He asked His disciples, saying to them, Who do men say that I am?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.28'>So they answered, John the Immerser; but some say, Elijah; and others, one of the prophets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.29'>He said to them, But who do you say that I am? Peter answered and said to Him, You are the Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.30'>And He charged them that they should tell no one about Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.31'>And He began to teach them that it is necessary for the Son of Man to suffer many things, and be rejected by the elders and chief priests and scribes, and be killed, and after three days to rise again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.32'>And He spoke this word openly. And Peter took Him aside and began to rebuke Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.33'>But when He had turned around and looked at His disciples, He rebuked Peter, saying, Get behind Me, Satan! For you are not mindful of the things of God, but the things of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.34'>And when He had called the people to Himself, with His disciples also, He said to them, Whoever desires to come after Me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.35'>For whoever desires to save his life will lose it, but whoever loses his life for My sake and the gospels will save it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.36'>For what will it profit a man if he gains the whole world, and loses his own soul?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.37'>Or what will a man give in exchange for his soul?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.38'>For whoever is ashamed of Me and My words in this adulterous and sinful generation, of him the Son of Man also will be ashamed when He comes in the glory of His Father with the holy angels.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.9'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.1'>And He said to them, Truly, I say to you that there are some standing here who will not taste death till they see the kingdom of God coming with power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.2'>Now after six days Jesus took Peter, Jacob, and John, and led them up into a high mountain apart by themselves; and He was transfigured before them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.3'>And His clothes became shining, exceedingly white, like snow, such as no fuller on earth is able to whiten them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.4'>And Elijah appeared to them with Moses, and they were talking with Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.5'>And Peter answered and said to Jesus, Rabbi, it is good for us to be here; and let us make three tabernacles: one for You, one for Moses, and one for Elijah;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.6'>because he did not know what to say, for they were greatly afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.7'>And a cloud came and overshadowed them; and a voice came out of the cloud, saying, This is My beloved Son. Hear Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.8'>And suddenly, when they had looked around, they saw no one anymore, but only Jesus with themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.9'>Now as they came down from the mountain, He commanded them that they should tell no one the things they had seen, till the Son of Man should rise from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.10'>So they kept this word to themselves, questioning what rising from the dead might be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.11'>And they asked Him, saying, Why do the scribes say that Elijah must come first?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.12'>And He answered and said to them, Truly, Elijah comes first and restores all things. And how it is written concerning the Son of Man, that He must suffer many things and be treated with contempt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.13'>But I say to you that Elijah has also come, and they did to him whatever they wished, as it is written of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.14'>And when He came to the disciples, He saw a great multitude around them, and scribes disputing with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.15'>And immediately, when they saw Him, all the people were greatly amazed, and running to Him, greeted Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.16'>And He questioned the scribes, What are you disputing with them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.17'>And one of the crowd answered and said, Teacher, I brought You my son, who has a mute spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.18'>And wherever it seizes him, it throws him down; he foams, gnashes his teeth, and withers away. So I spoke to Your disciples, that they should cast it out, but they were not able.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.19'>He answered him and said, O unbelieving generation. How long shall I be with you? How long shall I bear with you? Bring him to Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.20'>And they brought him to Him. And when he saw Him, immediately the spirit convulsed him, and he fell on the ground and wallowed, foaming.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.21'>So He asked his father, How long has this been happening to him? And he said, From childhood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.22'>And often he has thrown him both into the fire and into the water to destroy him. But if You are able to do anything, have compassion on us and help us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.23'>Jesus said to him, If you are able to believe, all things are possible to him who believes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.24'>And immediately the father of the child cried out and said with tears, Lord, I believe! Help my unbelief!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.25'>When Jesus saw that the people came running together, He rebuked the unclean spirit, saying to it, Deaf and mute spirit, I command you, Come out of him and enter him no more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.26'>And the spirit cried out, convulsed him greatly, and came out of him. And he became as if dead, so that many said, He has died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.27'>But Jesus took him by the hand and lifted him up, and he arose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.28'>And when He had come into the house, His disciples asked Him privately, Why could we not cast it out?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.29'>And He said to them, This kind can come out by nothing but prayer and fasting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.30'>And they departed from there and passed through Galilee, and He did not want anyone to know it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.31'>For He taught His disciples and said to them, The Son of Man is being delivered into the hands of men, and they will kill Him. And after He is killed, He will rise the third day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.32'>But they did not understand this word, and were afraid to ask Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.33'>And He came to Capernaum. And when He was in the house He asked them, What was it you disputed among yourselves on the road?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.34'>But they kept silent, for on the road they had disputed among themselves as to who was greater.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.35'>And He sat down, called the twelve, and said to them, If anyone desires to be first, he shall be last of all and servant of all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.36'>And He took a little child and set him in the midst of them. And when He had taken him in His arms, He said to them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.37'>Whoever receives one of these little children in My name receives Me; and whoever receives Me, receives not Me but Him who sent Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.38'>And John answered Him, saying, Teacher, we saw someone who does not follow us casting out demons in Your name, and we forbade him because he does not follow us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.39'>But Jesus said, Do not forbid him, for no one who does a work of power in My name will soon afterward be able to speak evil of Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.40'>For he who is not against us is on our behalf.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.41'>For whoever gives you a cup of water to drink in My name, because you belong to Christ, Truly, I say to you, He will by no means lose his reward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.42'>But whoever causes one of these little ones who believe in Me to stumble, it is better for him if a millstone is hung around his neck, and he be thrown into the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.43'>If your hand makes you stumble, cut it off. It is better for you to enter into life maimed, rather than having two hands, to go to Gehenna, into the fire that shall never be quenched;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.44'>where their worm does not die, and the fire is not quenched.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.45'>And if your foot makes you stumble, cut it off. It is better for you to enter life lame, rather than having two feet, to be cast into Gehenna, into the fire that shall never be quenched;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.46'>where their worm does not die, and the fire is not quenched.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.47'>And if your eye makes you stumble, pluck it out. It is better for you to enter the kingdom of God with one eye, rather than having two eyes, to be cast into the fire of Gehenna;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.48'>where their worm does not die, and the fire is not quenched.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.49'>For everyone will be salted with fire, and every sacrifice will be salted with salt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.50'>Salt is good, but if the salt loses its saltiness, how will you season it? Have salt in yourselves, and be at peace with one another.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.10'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.1'>Then He arose from there and came into the borders of Judea by the other side of the Jordan. And multitudes came together to Him again, and as He was accustomed, He taught them again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.2'>And the Pharisees came and asked Him, Is it lawful for a man to put away his wife? testing Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.3'>And He answered and said to them, What did Moses command you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.4'>They said, Moses permitted a man to write a certificate of divorce, and to put her away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.5'>And Jesus answered and said to them, Because of the hardness of your heart he wrote you this precept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.6'>But from the beginning of the creation, God made them male and female.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.7'>For this reason a man shall leave his father and mother and cleave to his wife,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.8'>and the two shall become one flesh; so then they are no longer two, but one flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.9'>Therefore what God has yoked together, let not man separate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.10'>In the house His disciples also asked Him again about the same matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.11'>So He said to them, Whoever shall put away his wife and marry another commits adultery against her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.12'>And if a woman shall put away her husband and be married to another, she commits adultery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.13'>And they brought little children to Him, that He might touch them; but the disciples rebuked those who brought them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.14'>But when Jesus saw it, He was indignant and said to them, Let the little children come to Me, and do not forbid them; for of such is the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.15'>Truly, I say to you, Whoever does not receive the kingdom of God as a little child will by no means enter it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.16'>And He took them up in His arms, put His hands on them, and blessed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.17'>And as He was going out on the road, one came running, knelt before Him, and asked Him, Good Teacher, what shall I do that I may inherit eternal life?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.18'>So Jesus said to him, Why do you call Me good? No one is good except One, God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.19'>You know the commandments: Do not commit adultery, Do not murder, Do not steal, Do not bear false witness, Do not defraud, Honor your father and your mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.20'>And he answered and said to Him, Teacher, all these things I have observed from my youth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.21'>Then Jesus, looking at him, loved him, and said to him, One thing you lack: Go your way, sell whatever you have and give to the poor, and you will have treasure in Heaven; and come, take up the cross, and follow Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.22'>But he was sad at this word, and went away sorrowful, for he had many possessions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.23'>And Jesus looked around and said to His disciples, How hard it is for those who have riches to enter the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.24'>And the disciples were astonished at His words. But Jesus answered again and said to them, Children, how hard it is for those who trust in riches to enter the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.25'>It is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.26'>And they were greatly astonished, saying among themselves, Who then is able to be saved?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.27'>But Jesus looked at them and said, With men it is impossible, but not with God; for with God all things are possible.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.28'>Then Peter began to say to Him, Behold, we have left everything and followed You.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.29'>So Jesus answered and said, Truly, I say to you, there is no one who has left house or brothers or sisters or father or mother or wife or children or lands, on account of Me and the gospel,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.30'>who shall not receive a hundredfold now in this time; houses and brothers and sisters and mothers and children and lands, with persecutions; and in the age to come, eternal life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.31'>But many who are first will be last, and the last first.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.32'>Now they were on the road, going up to Jerusalem, and Jesus was going before them; and they were amazed. And as they followed they were afraid. Then He took the twelve aside again and began to tell them the things that were about to happen to Him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.33'>Behold, we are going up to Jerusalem, and the Son of Man will be delivered to the chief priests and to the scribes; and they will condemn Him to death and deliver Him to the Gentiles;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.34'>and they will mock Him, and scourge Him, and spit on Him, and kill Him. And the third day He will rise again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.35'>Then Jacob and John, the sons of Zebedee, came to Him, saying, Teacher, we want You to do for us whatever we ask.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.36'>And He said to them, What do you want Me to do for you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.37'>They said to Him, Grant us that we may sit, one on Your right hand and the other on Your left, in Your glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.38'>But Jesus said to them, You do not know what you ask. Are you able to drink the cup that I drink, and be immersed with the immersion that I am immersed with?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.39'>They said to Him, We are able. So Jesus said to them, You will indeed drink the cup that I drink, and with the immersion I am immersed with you will be immersed;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.40'>but to sit on My right hand and on My left is not Mine to give, but it is for those for whom it has been prepared.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.41'>And when the ten heard it, they began to be indignant with Jacob and John.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.42'>But Jesus called them to Himself and said to them, You know that those who seem to rule over the Gentiles lord it over them, and their great ones exercise authority over them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.43'>But it shall not be so among you; but whoever desires to become great among you shall be your servant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.44'>And whoever of you desires to become first shall be slave of all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.45'>For even the Son of Man did not come to be served, but to serve, and to give His life a ransom for many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.46'>And they came to Jericho. And as He went out of Jericho with His disciples and a great multitude, blind Bartimaeus, the son of Timaeus, sat by the road begging.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.47'>And when he heard that it was Jesus of Nazareth, he began to cry out and say, Jesus, Son of David, have mercy on me!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.48'>And many warned him to be quiet; but he cried out all the more, Son of David, have mercy on me!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.49'>So Jesus stood still and commanded him to be called. Then they called the blind man, saying to him, Be of good courage. Arise, He is calling you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.50'>And throwing aside his garment, he arose and came to Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.51'>And Jesus answered and said to him, What do you want Me to do for you? And the blind man said to Him, My Master, that I may see again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.52'>And Jesus said to him, Go your way; your faith has made you well. And immediately he saw again and followed Jesus on the road.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.11'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.1'>And when they drew near to Jerusalem, to Bethphage and Bethany, at the Mount of Olives, He sent two of His disciples;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.2'>and said to them, Go into the village opposite you; and as soon as you have entered it you will find a colt tied, on which no one has sat. Loose it and bring it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.3'>And if anyone says to you, Why do you do this? say, The Lord has need of it, and immediately he will send it here.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.4'>So they went their way, and found the colt tied by the door outside on the street, and they loosed it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.5'>But some of those who stood there said to them, What are you doing, loosing the colt?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.6'>And they spoke to them just as Jesus had commanded. So they let them go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.7'>And they brought the colt to Jesus and threw their clothes on it, and He sat on it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.8'>And many spread their clothes on the road, and others cut down leafy branches from the trees and spread them on the road.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.9'>And those who went before and those who followed cried out, saying: Hosanna! Blessed is He who comes in the name of the Lord!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.10'>Blessed is the kingdom of our father David that comes in the name of the Lord! Hosanna in the Highest!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.11'>And Jesus went into Jerusalem and into the temple. So when He had looked around at all things, as the hour was already late, He went out to Bethany with the twelve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.12'>And the next day, when they had come out from Bethany, He was hungry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.13'>And seeing from afar a fig tree having leaves, He went to see if perhaps He would find something on it. When He came to it, He found nothing but leaves, for it was not the season for figs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.14'>And answering Jesus said to it, Let no one eat fruit from you ever again. And His disciples heard it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.15'>So they came to Jerusalem. And Jesus went into the temple and began to drive out those who bought and sold in the temple, and overturned the tables of the money changers and the seats of those who sold doves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.16'>And He would not allow anyone to carry any vessel through the temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.17'>And He taught, saying to them, Is it not written, My house shall be called a house of prayer for all nations? But you have made it a den of thieves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.18'>And the scribes and chief priests heard it and sought how they might destroy Him; for they feared Him, because all the crowd was astonished at His doctrine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.19'>And when evening had come, He went out of the city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.20'>Now in the morning, as they passed by, they saw the fig tree dried up from the roots.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.21'>And Peter, remembering, said to Him, Rabbi, behold, the fig tree which You cursed has withered away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.22'>And Jesus answered and said to them, Have faith in God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.23'>For truly I say to you, whoever says to this mountain, Be removed and be cast into the sea, and does not doubt in his heart, but believes that what he says will be done, it will be to him, whatever he says.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.24'>Therefore I say to you, Everything whatever you ask when you pray, believe that you receive, and it will be to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.25'>And whenever you stand praying, if you have anything against anyone, forgive, that your Father in Heaven may also forgive you your trespasses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.26'>But if you do not forgive, neither will your Father in Heaven forgive your trespasses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.27'>And they came again to Jerusalem. And as He was walking in the temple, the chief priests, the scribes, and the elders came to Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.28'>And they said to Him, By what authority do You do these things? And who gave You this authority to do these things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.29'>And Jesus answered and said to them, I also will ask you one question, and answer Me; and I will tell you by what authority I do these things:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.30'>The immersion of John; was it from Heaven or from men? Answer Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.31'>And they reasoned among themselves, saying, If we say, From Heaven, He will say, Why then did you not believe him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.32'>But if we say, From men; they feared the people, for all counted John to have truly been a prophet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.33'>So they answered and said to Jesus, We do not know. And Jesus answered and said to them, Neither will I tell you by what authority I do these things.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.12'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.1'>And He began to speak to them in parables: A man planted a vineyard and set a hedge around it, dug a wine vat and built a tower. And he leased it to vinedressers and went into a far country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.2'>And at the season he sent a servant to the vinedressers, that he might receive some of the fruit of the vineyard from the vinedressers.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.3'>And they took him and beat him and sent him away empty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.4'>And again he sent to them another servant, and at him they threw stones, wounded him in the head, and sent him away shamefully treated.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.5'>And again he sent another, and him they killed; and many others, beating some and killing some.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.6'>Therefore still having one son, his beloved, he also sent him to them last, saying, They will reverence my son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.7'>But those vinedressers said among themselves, This is the heir. Come, let us kill him, and the inheritance will be ours.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.8'>So they took him and killed him and cast him out of the vineyard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.9'>Therefore what will the owner of the vineyard do? He will come and destroy the vinedressers, and give the vineyard to others.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.10'>Have you not even read this Scripture: The stone which the builders rejected has become the head of the corner;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.11'>this came about from the Lord, and it is marvelous in our eyes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.12'>And they sought to lay hold on Him, but feared the multitude, for they knew He had spoken the parable against them. So they left Him and went away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.13'>And they sent to Him some of the Pharisees and the Herodians, to catch Him in His words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.14'>And when they had come, they said to Him, Teacher, we know that You are true, and care about no one; for You do not regard the person of men, but teach the way of God in truth. Is it lawful to give tribute to Caesar, or not?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.15'>Shall we give, or shall we not give? But He, knowing their hypocrisy, said to them, Why do you test Me? Bring Me a denarius that I may see it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.16'>So they brought it. And He said to them, Whose image and inscription is this? They said to Him, Caesars.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.17'>And Jesus answered and said to them, Render to Caesar the things that are Caesars, and to God the things that are Gods. And they marveled at Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.18'>Then some Sadducees, who say there is no resurrection, came to Him; and they asked Him, saying:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.19'>Teacher, Moses wrote to us that if a mans brother dies, and leaves his wife behind, and leaves no children, his brother should take his wife and raise up seed for his brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.20'>Now there were seven brothers. The first took a wife; and dying, he left no seed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.21'>And the second took her, and he died; nor did he leave any seed. And the third likewise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.22'>So the seven had her and left no seed. Last of all the woman also died.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.23'>Therefore, in the resurrection, when they rise, whose wife will she be? For all seven had her as wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.24'>Jesus answered and said to them, Are you not therefore in error, because you do not know the Scriptures nor the power of God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.25'>For when they rise from the dead, they neither marry nor are given in marriage, but are like angels in Heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.26'>But concerning the dead, that they are raised, have you not read in the book of Moses, how God spoke to him at the bush, saying, I am the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.27'>He is not the God of the dead, but the God of the living. You are therefore greatly in error.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.28'>And one of the scribes came, and having heard them reasoning together, perceiving that He had answered them well, asked Him, Which is the first commandment of all?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.29'>Jesus answered him, The first of all the commandments is: Hear, O Israel, the Lord our God, the Lord is one.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.30'>And you shall love the Lord your God with all your heart, with all your soul, with all your mind, and with all your strength. This is the first commandment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.31'>And the second, like it, is this: You shall love your neighbor as yourself. There is no other commandment greater than these.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.32'>So the scribe said to Him, Well said, Teacher. You have spoken the truth, for there is one God, and there is no other besides Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.33'>And to love Him with all the heart, with all the understanding, with all the soul, and with all the strength, and to love ones neighbor as oneself, is more than all the whole burnt offerings and sacrifices.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.34'>And when Jesus saw that he answered wisely, He said to him, You are not far from the kingdom of God. And after that no one dared question Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.35'>Then Jesus answered and said, while He taught in the temple, How is it that the scribes say that the Christ is the son of David?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.36'>For David himself said by the Holy Spirit: The Lord said to my Lord, Sit at My right hand, till I make Your enemies Your footstool.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.37'>Therefore David himself calls Him Lord; how is He then his son? And the large crowd heard Him gladly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.38'>And He said to them in His teaching, Beware of the scribes, who desire to go around in long robes, love greetings in the marketplaces,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.39'>the chief seats in the synagogues, and the chief places at feasts,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.40'>who devour widows houses, and for a pretense make long prayers. These will receive surpassing condemnation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.41'>And Jesus sat opposite the treasury and saw how the people threw money into the treasury. And many who were rich threw in much.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.42'>Then one poor widow came and threw in two mites, which make a quadrans.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.43'>So He called His disciples to Himself and said to them, Truly, I say to you that this poor widow has thrown in more than all those who have thrown into the treasury;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.44'>for they all threw in out of their abundance, but she out of her poverty threw in all that she had, her whole livelihood.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.13'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.1'>And as He went out of the temple, one of His disciples said to Him, Teacher, see what manner of stones and what buildings!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.2'>And Jesus answered and said to him, Do you see these great buildings? Not one stone shall be left upon another, that shall not be thrown down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.3'>And as He sat on the Mount of Olives opposite the temple, Peter, Jacob, John, and Andrew questioned Him privately,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.4'>Tell us, when will these things be? And what will be the sign when all these things are about to be fulfilled?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.5'>And Jesus, answering them, began to say: Take heed that no one leads you astray.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.6'>For many will come in My name, saying, I AM, and will lead many astray.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.7'>But when you hear of wars and rumors of wars, do not be troubled; for it is necessary for such things to come about, but the end is not yet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.8'>For nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom. And there will be earthquakes in various places, and there will be famines and troubles. These are the beginnings of travail.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.9'>But take heed to yourselves, for they will deliver you up to councils, and you will be beaten in the synagogues. You will be brought before rulers and kings for My sake, for a testimony to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.10'>And the gospel must first be preached to all the nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.11'>But when they lead you away and deliver you up, do not be anxious beforehand, or premeditate what you will speak. But whatever is given you in that hour, speak that; for it is not you speaking, but the Holy Spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.12'>Now brother will betray brother to death, and a father his child; and children will rise up against parents and cause them to be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.13'>And you will be hated by everyone on account of My name. But he who endures to the end shall be kept safe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.14'>So when you see the abomination of desolation, spoken of by Daniel the prophet, standing where it ought not (let the reader understand), then let those who are in Judea flee to the mountains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.15'>And let him who is on the housetop not go down into the house, nor enter to take anything out of his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.16'>And let him who is in the field not go back to get his clothes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.17'>But woe to those who are pregnant and to those who are nursing babies in those days!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.18'>And pray that your flight may not be in winter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.19'>For in those days there will be affliction, such as has not been since the beginning of the creation which God created until this time, nor ever shall be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.20'>And unless the Lord had shortened those days, no flesh would be kept safe alive; but because of the elect, whom He chose, He has shortened the days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.21'>Then if anyone says to you, Look, here is the Christ; or, Look, He is there; do not believe it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.22'>For false christs and false prophets will arise and show signs and wonders to cause, if possible, even the elect to go astray.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.23'>But take heed; behold, I have foretold you all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.24'>But in those days, after that affliction, the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give its light;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.25'>the stars of heaven will be falling, and the powers in the heavens will be shaken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.26'>And they will see the Son of Man coming in the clouds with great power and glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.27'>And then He will send His angels, and gather together His elect from the four winds, from the farthest part of earth to the farthest part of heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.28'>Now learn this parable from the fig tree: When its branch has already become tender, and puts forth leaves, you know that summer is near.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.29'>So you also, when you see these things happening, know that it is near; at the doors.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.30'>Truly, I say to you, This generation will by no means pass away till all these things take place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.31'>Heaven and earth will pass away, but My words will by no means pass away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.32'>But of that day and hour no one knows, not the angels in Heaven, nor the Son, except the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.33'>Take heed, watch and pray; for you do not know when the time is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.34'>It is like a man going to a far country, who left his house and gave authority to his servants, and to each his work, and commanded the doorkeeper to watch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.35'>Watch therefore, for you do not know when the master of the house is coming; in the evening, at midnight, at the crowing of the rooster, or in the morning;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.36'>that, coming suddenly, he not find you sleeping.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.37'>And what I say to you, I say to all: Watch.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.14'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.1'>After two days it was the Passover and the Feast of Unleavened Bread. And the chief priests and the scribes sought how they might take Him by deceit and put Him to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.2'>But they said, Not during the Feast, lest there be an uproar of the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.3'>And being in Bethany at the house of Simon the leper, as He sat at the table, a woman came having an alabaster flask of very costly ointment of spikenard. And she broke the flask and poured it on His head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.4'>But there were some who were indignant within themselves, and said, Why was this ointment wasted?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.5'>For it might have been sold for more than three hundred denarii and given to the poor. And they murmured against her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.6'>But Jesus said, Let her alone. Why do you trouble her? She has done a good work toward Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.7'>For you have the poor with you always, and whenever you wish you may do them good; but you do not always have Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.8'>She has done what she was in a position to do. She has come beforehand to anoint My body for burial.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.9'>Truly, I say to you, Wherever this gospel is preached in the whole world, what this woman has done will also be told as a memorial to her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.10'>Then Judas Iscariot, one of the twelve, went to the chief priests to deliver Him to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.11'>And when they heard it, they were glad, and promised to give him money. So he sought how he might conveniently betray Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.12'>Now on the first day of Unleavened Bread, when they killed the Passover, His disciples said to Him, Where do You want us to go and prepare, that You may eat the Passover?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.13'>And He sent out two of His disciples and said to them, Go into the city, and a man will meet you carrying a pitcher of water; follow him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.14'>And wherever he goes in, say to the master of the house, The Teacher says, Where is the guest room in which I may eat the Passover with My disciples?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.15'>And he will show you a large upper room, furnished and prepared; make ready for us there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.16'>So His disciples went out, and came into the city, and found it just as He had said to them; and they prepared the Passover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.17'>And in the evening He came with the twelve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.18'>Now as they sat and ate, Jesus said, Truly, I say to you, one of you who eats with Me will betray Me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.19'>And they began to be grieved, and to say to Him one by one, Surely not me? And another said, Surely not me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.20'>And He answered and said to them, It is one of the twelve, who dips with Me in the dish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.21'>The Son of Man truly goes just as it is written of Him, but woe to that man by whom the Son of Man is betrayed! It would have been good for that man if he had never been born.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.22'>And as they were eating, Jesus took bread, blessed and broke it, and gave it to them and said, Take, eat; this is My body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.23'>And He took the cup, and when He had given thanks He gave it to them, and they all drank from it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.24'>And He said to them, This is My blood of the New Covenant, which is poured out for many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.25'>Truly, I say to you, I will no more drink of the fruit of the vine until that day when I drink it new in the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.26'>And when they had sung a hymn, they went out to the Mount of Olives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.27'>And Jesus said to them, All of you will be made to stumble because of Me this night, for it is written: I will strike the Shepherd, and the sheep will be scattered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.28'>But after I have been raised, I will go before you into Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.29'>Peter said to Him, Even if all are made to stumble, yet not I.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.30'>And Jesus said to him, Truly, I say to you that today, even this night, before the rooster crows twice, you will deny Me three times.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.31'>But he spoke more vehemently, If I need to die with You, I will not deny You! And they all said likewise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.32'>And they came to a place which was named Gethsemane; and He said to His disciples, Sit here while I pray.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.33'>And He took Peter, Jacob, and John with Him, and He began to be in dread and deeply distressed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.34'>And He said to them, My soul is exceedingly sorrowful, even to death. Stay here and watch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.35'>And He went a little farther, and fell on the ground, and prayed that if it were possible, the hour might pass from Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.36'>And He said, Abba, Father, all things are possible to You. Take this cup away from Me; nevertheless, not what I will, but what You will.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.37'>And He came and found them sleeping, and said to Peter, Simon, are you sleeping? Were you not strong enough to watch one hour?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.38'>Watch and pray, that you not enter into temptation. The spirit truly is willing, but the flesh is weak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.39'>And again He went away and prayed, and spoke the same words.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.40'>And when He returned, He found them asleep again, for their eyes were heavy; and they did not know what to answer Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.41'>And He came the third time and said to them, Sleep on now and take your rest. It is enough. The hour has come; behold, the Son of Man is being delivered into the hands of sinners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.42'>Rise up, let us be going. Behold, the one betraying Me is at hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.43'>And immediately, while He was still speaking, Judas, one of the twelve, with a great multitude with swords and clubs, came from the chief priests and the scribes and the elders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.44'>And His betrayer had given them a signal, saying, Whomever I kiss, it is He; seize Him and lead Him away safely.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.45'>And as soon as He had come, immediately he went up to Him and said to Him, Rabbi, Rabbi! and kissed Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.46'>And they laid their hands on Him and took Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.47'>And one of those who stood by drew his sword and struck the servant of the high priest, and cut off his ear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.48'>And Jesus answered and said to them, Have you come out, as against a robber, with swords and clubs to take Me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.49'>I was with you daily in the temple teaching, and you did not seize Me. But the Scriptures must be fulfilled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.50'>And they all forsook Him and fled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.51'>And a certain young man followed Him, having a linen cloth thrown around his naked body. And the young men laid hold of him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.52'>and he left the linen cloth and fled from them naked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.53'>And they led Jesus away to the high priest; and with him were assembled all the chief priests, the elders, and the scribes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.54'>And Peter followed Him at a distance, right into the courtyard of the high priest. And he sat with the servants and warmed himself at the fire.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.55'>And the chief priests and all the council sought testimony against Jesus to put Him to death, but found none.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.56'>For many bore false witness against Him, but their testimonies were not the same.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.57'>And some rose up and bore false witness against Him, saying,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.58'>We heard Him say, I will destroy this temple made with hands, and within three days I will build another made without hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.59'>And neither in this was their testimony the same.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.60'>And the high priest stood up in the midst and asked Jesus, saying, Do You answer nothing? What is it these men witness against You?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.61'>But He kept silent and answered nothing. Again the high priest questioned Him, saying to Him, Are You the Christ, the Son of the Blessed?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.62'>Jesus said, I AM. And you will see the Son of Man sitting at the right hand of the Power, and coming with the clouds of Heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.63'>Then the high priest tore his clothes and said, What further need do we have of witnesses?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.64'>You have heard the blasphemy! What does it appear to you? And they all condemned Him to be worthy of death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.65'>And some began to spit on Him, and to cover His face, and to beat Him with the fist, and to say to Him, Prophesy! And the officers struck Him with slaps.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.66'>Now as Peter was below in the courtyard, one of the servant girls of the high priest came.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.67'>And when she saw Peter warming himself, she looked at him and said, You also were with Jesus of Nazareth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.68'>But he denied it, saying, I neither know nor understand what you are saying. And he went out on the porch, and a rooster crowed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.69'>And the servant girl saw him again, and began to say to those who stood by, This is one of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.70'>And he denied it again. And a little later those who stood by said to Peter again, Surely you are one of them; for you are a Galilean, and your speech agrees.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.71'>Then he began to curse and swear, I do not know this man of whom you speak!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.72'>And a second time the rooster crowed. And Peter remembered the word that Jesus had said to him, Before the rooster crows twice, you will deny Me three times. And when he thought on it, he wept.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.15'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.1'>And immediately, in the morning, the chief priests held a consultation with the elders and scribes and the whole council; and they bound Jesus, led Him away, and delivered Him to Pilate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.2'>And Pilate asked Him, Are You the King of the Jews? He answered and said to him, It is as you say.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.3'>And the chief priests accused Him of many things, but He answered nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.4'>Then Pilate asked Him again, saying, Do You answer nothing? Behold how many things they witness against You!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.5'>But Jesus still answered nothing, so that Pilate marveled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.6'>Now at the feast he was accustomed to releasing one prisoner to them, whomever they asked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.7'>And there was one named Barabbas, who was in bonds with his fellow rebels; they had committed murder in the insurrection.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.8'>And the multitude, crying aloud, began to ask him to do just as he had always done for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.9'>But Pilate answered them, saying, Do you want me to release to you the King of the Jews?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.10'>For he knew that the chief priests had delivered Him up because of envy.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.11'>But the chief priests stirred up the crowd, so that he should rather release Barabbas to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.12'>So Pilate answered and said to them again, What then do you want me to do with Him whom you call the King of the Jews?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.13'>And they cried out again, Crucify Him!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.14'>Then Pilate said to them, Why, what evil has He done? But they cried out all the more, Crucify Him!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.15'>So Pilate, intending to gratify the crowd, released Barabbas to them; and he delivered Jesus, after he had scourged Him, to be crucified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.16'>And the soldiers led Him away into the hall called Praetorium, and they called together the whole garrison.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.17'>And they clothed Him with purple; and they wove a crown of thorns, put it on Him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.18'>and began to salute Him, Hail, King of the Jews!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.19'>And they struck Him on the head with a reed and spat on Him; and bending the knee, they bowed to Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.20'>And when they had mocked Him, they took the purple off Him, put His own clothes on Him, and led Him out to crucify Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.21'>And they compelled a certain man, Simon a Cyrenian, the father of Alexander and Rufus, as he was coming out of the country and passing by, to bear His cross.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.22'>And they brought Him to the place Golgotha, which is translated, Place of a Skull.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.23'>And they gave Him wine mixed with myrrh to drink, but He did not take it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.24'>And when they crucified Him, they divided His garments, casting lots for them to determine what every man should take.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.25'>And it was the third hour, and they crucified Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.26'>And the inscription of His accusation was written above: THE KING OF THE JEWS.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.27'>And they also crucified two robbers with Him, one on His right and the other on His left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.28'>And the Scripture was fulfilled which says, And He was numbered with the transgressors.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.29'>And those who passed by blasphemed Him, wagging their heads and saying, Aha! You who destroy the temple and build it in three days,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.30'>save Yourself, and come down from the cross!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.31'>Likewise the chief priests also, mocking among themselves with the scribes, said, He saved others, but He is not able to save Himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.32'>Let the Christ, the King of Israel, descend now from the cross, that we may see and believe. Even those who were crucified with Him reviled Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.33'>And when the sixth hour had come, there was darkness over the whole land until the ninth hour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.34'>And at the ninth hour Jesus cried out with a loud voice, saying, Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani? which is translated, My God, My God, why have You forsaken Me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.35'>And some of those who stood by, when they heard that, said, Behold, He is calling for Elijah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.36'>And someone ran and filled a sponge full of vinegar, put it on a reed, and gave it to Him to drink, saying, Let Him alone; let us see if Elijah will come to take Him down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.37'>And Jesus cried out with a loud voice, and breathed His last.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.38'>And the veil of the temple was torn in two from top to bottom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.39'>And when the centurion, who stood opposite Him, saw that He cried out like this and breathed His last, he said, Truly this Man was the Son of God!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.40'>There were also women looking on from afar, among whom were Mary Magdalene, Mary the mother of Jacob the Less and of Joses, and Salome,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.41'>who also followed Him and ministered to Him when He was in Galilee, and many other women who came up with Him to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.42'>Now when evening had come, because it was the Preparation Day, that is, the day before the Sabbath,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.43'>Joseph of Arimathea, a prominent council member, who was himself waiting for the kingdom of God, coming, boldly went in to Pilate and asked for the body of Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.44'>And Pilate marveled that He had already died; and summoning the centurion, he asked him if He had been dead for awhile.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.45'>And when he found out from the centurion, he granted the body to Joseph.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.46'>And he bought fine linen, took Him down, and wrapped Him in the linen. And he laid Him in a tomb which had been hewn out of the rock, and rolled a stone against the door of the tomb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.47'>And Mary Magdalene and Mary the mother of Joses observed where He was laid.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.16'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.1'>Now when the Sabbath was past, Mary Magdalene, Mary the mother of Jacob, and Salome bought spices, that they might come and anoint Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.2'>And very early in the morning, on the first day of the week, they came to the tomb at sunrise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.3'>And they said among themselves, Who will roll away the stone from the door of the tomb for us?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.4'>But when they looked up, they saw that the stone had been rolled away; for it was very large.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.5'>And entering the tomb, they saw a young man clothed in a white robe sitting on the right side; and they were afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.6'>But he said to them, Do not be afraid. You seek Jesus of Nazareth, who was crucified. He is risen! He is not here. See the place where they laid Him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.7'>But go, tell His disciples, and Peter, that He is going before you into Galilee; there you will see Him, as He said to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.8'>So they went out quickly and fled from the tomb, for they trembled and were astonished. And they said nothing to anyone, for they were afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.9'>Now when He arose early on the first day of the week, He appeared first to Mary Magdalene, out of whom He had cast seven demons.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.10'>She went and told those who had been with Him, as they mourned and wept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.11'>And when they heard that He lives and was seen by her, they did not believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.12'>After that, He appeared in another form to two of them as they walked and went into the country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.13'>And they went and reported it to the rest, but they did not believe them either.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.14'>Later He appeared to the eleven as they sat at the table; and He rebuked their unbelief and hardness of heart, because they did not believe those who had seen Him after He had been raised.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.15'>And He said to them, Go into all the world and preach the gospel to every creature.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.16'>He who believes and is immersed will be saved; but he who does not believe will be condemned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.17'>And these signs will follow those who believe: In My name they will cast out demons; they will speak with new tongues;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.18'>they will take up serpents; and if they drink anything deadly, it will by no means hurt them; they will lay hands on the sick, and they will be well.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.19'>So then, after the Lord had spoken to them, He was taken up into Heaven, and sat down at the right hand of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.20'>And they went forth and preached everywhere, the Lord working with them and confirming the Word through the signs following. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>