<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='wcl' xml:lang='he'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='wcl'>
        <title>Westminster Leningrad Codex</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator/>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>Hebrew OT WLC (Consonants and Vowels)</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description>This text began as an electronic transcription by Whitaker and Parunak of the 1983 printed edition of Biblia Hebraica Stuttgartensia (BHS). The transcription is called the Michigan-Claremont electronic text and was archived at the Oxford Text Archive (OTA) in 1987. Since that time, the text has been modified to conform to the photo-facsimile of the Leningrad Codex, Firkovich B19A, residing at the Russian National Library, St. Petersberg; hence the change of name. This version contains all 6 of the textual elements of the OTA document: consonants, vowels, cantillation marks, "paragraph" (pe, samekh) markers, and ketib-qere variants. Morphological divisions may be added later. The BHS so-called "paragraph" markers (pe and samekh) do not actually occur in the Leningrad Codex. The editors of BHS use them to indicate open space deliberately left blank by the scribe. Pe ("open" paragraph) represents a space between verses, where the new verse begins on a new column line. This represents a major section of the text. Samekh ("closed" paragraph) represents a space of less than a line between verses. This is understood to be a subdivision of the corresponding "open" section. Since these markers represent an actual physical feature of the text, they have been retained. The transcription was based on the "Supplement to the code manual for the Michigan Old Testament" by Alan Groves.The WLC is maintained by the Westminster Hebrew Institute, Philadelphia, PA (http://whi.wts.edu/WHI).</description>
        <publisher>Free Bible Software Group</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>wcl</identifier>
        <source>http://unbound.biola.edu/index.cfm?method=downloads.showDownloadMain</source>
        <language type='IETF'>he</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Public Domain</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div osisID='Obad' type='book'>
      <chapter osisID='Obad.1'>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.1'>חֲזֹון עֹבַדְיָה כֹּה־אָמַר אֲדֹנָי יְהוִה לֶאֱדֹום שְׁמוּעָה שָׁמַעְנוּ מֵאֵת יְהוָה וְצִיר בַּגֹּויִם שֻׁלָּח קוּמוּ וְנָקוּמָה עָלֶיהָ לַמִּלְחָמָה׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.2'>הִנֵּה קָטֹן נְתַתִּיךָ בַּגֹּויִם בָּזוּי אַתָּה מְאֹד׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.3'>זְדֹון לִבְּךָ הִשִּׁיאֶךָ שֹׁכְנִי בְחַגְוֵי־סֶּלַע מְרֹום שִׁבְתֹּו אֹמֵר בְּלִבֹּו מִי יֹורִדֵנִי אָרֶץ׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.4'>אִם־תַּגְבִּיהַּ כַּנֶּשֶׁר וְאִם־בֵּין כֹּוכָבִים שִׂים קִנֶּךָ מִשָּׁם אֹורִידְךָ נְאֻם־יְהוָה׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.5'>אִם־גַּנָּבִים בָּאוּ־לְךָ אִם־שֹׁודְדֵי לַיְלָה אֵיךְ נִדְמֵיתָה הֲלֹוא יִגְנְבוּ דַּיָּם אִם־בֹּצְרִים בָּאוּ לָךְ הֲלֹוא יַשְׁאִירוּ עֹלֵלֹות׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.6'>אֵיךְ נֶחְפְּשׂוּ עֵשָׂו נִבְעוּ מַצְפֻּנָיו׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.7'>עַד־הַגְּבוּל שִׁלְּחוּךָ כֹּל אַנְשֵׁי בְרִיתֶךָ הִשִּׁיאוּךָ יָכְלוּ לְךָ אַנְשֵׁי שְׁלֹמֶךָ לַחְמְךָ יָשִׂימוּ מָזֹור תַּחְתֶּיךָ אֵין תְּבוּנָה בֹּו׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.8'>הֲלֹוא בַּיֹּום הַהוּא נְאֻם  יְהוָה וְהַאֲבַדְתִּי חֲכָמִים מֵאֱדֹום וּתְבוּנָה מֵהַר עֵשָׂו׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.9'>וְחַתּוּ גִבֹּורֶיךָ תֵּימָן לְמַעַן יִכָּרֶת־אִישׁ מֵהַר עֵשָׂו מִקָּטֶל׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.10'>מֵחֲמַס אָחִיךָ יַעֲקֹב תְּכַסְּךָ בוּשָׁה וְנִכְרַתָּ לְעֹולָם׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.11'>בְּיֹום עֲמָדְךָ מִנֶּגֶד בְּיֹום שְׁבֹות זָרִים חֵילֹו וְנָכְרִים בָּאוּ [שַׁעֲרֹו כ] (שְׁעָרָיו ק) וְעַל־יְרוּשָׁלִַם יַדּוּ גֹורָל גַּם־אַתָּה כְּאַחַד מֵהֶם׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.12'>וְאַל־תֵּרֶא בְיֹום־אָחִיךָ בְּיֹום נָכְרֹו וְאַל־תִּשְׂמַח לִבְנֵי־יְהוּדָה בְּיֹום אָבְדָם וְאַל־תַּגְדֵּל פִּיךָ בְּיֹום צָרָה׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.13'>אַל־תָּבֹוא בְשַׁעַר־עַמִּי בְּיֹום אֵידָם אַל־תֵּרֶא גַם־אַתָּה בְּרָעָתֹו בְּיֹום אֵידֹו וְאַל־תִּשְׁלַחְנָה בְחֵילֹו בְּיֹום אֵידֹו׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.14'>וְאַל־תַּעֲמֹד עַל־הַפֶּרֶק לְהַכְרִית אֶת־פְּלִיטָיו וְאַל־תַּסְגֵּר שְׂרִידָיו בְּיֹום צָרָה׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.15'>כִּי־קָרֹוב יֹום־יְהוָה עַל־כָּל־הַגֹּויִם כַּאֲשֶׁר עָשִׂיתָ יֵעָשֶׂה לָּךְ גְּמֻלְךָ יָשׁוּב בְּרֹאשֶׁךָ׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.16'>כִּי כַּאֲשֶׁר שְׁתִיתֶם עַל־הַר קָדְשִׁי יִשְׁתּוּ כָל־הַגֹּויִם תָּמִיד וְשָׁתוּ וְלָעוּ וְהָיוּ כְּלֹוא הָיוּ׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.17'>וּבְהַר צִיֹּון תִּהְיֶה פְלֵיטָה וְהָיָה קֹדֶשׁ וְיָרְשׁוּ  בֵּית יַעֲקֹב אֵת מֹורָשֵׁיהֶם ׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.18'>וְהָיָה בֵית־יַעֲקֹב אֵשׁ וּבֵית יֹוסֵף לֶהָבָה וּבֵית עֵשָׂו לְקַשׁ וְדָלְקוּ בָהֶם וַאֲכָלוּם וְלֹא־יִהְיֶה  שָׂרִיד לְבֵית עֵשָׂו כִּי יְהוָה דִּבֵּר׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.19'>וְיָרְשׁוּ הַנֶּגֶב אֶת־הַר עֵשָׂו וְהַשְּׁפֵלָה אֶת־פְּלִשְׁתִּים וְיָרְשׁוּ אֶת־שְׂדֵה אֶפְרַיִם וְאֵת שְׂדֵה שֹׁמְרֹון וּבִנְיָמִן אֶת־הַגִּלְעָד׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.20'>וְגָלֻת הַחֵל־הַזֶּה לִבְנֵי יִשְׂרָאֵל אֲשֶׁר־כְּנַעֲנִים עַד־צָרְפַת וְגָלֻת יְרוּשָׁלִַם אֲשֶׁר בִּסְפָרַד יִרְשׁוּ אֵת עָרֵי הַנֶּגֶב׃</verse>
        <verse osisID='Obad.1.21'>וְעָלוּ מֹושִׁעִים בְּהַר צִיֹּון לִשְׁפֹּט אֶת־הַר עֵשָׂו וְהָיְתָה לַיהוָה הַמְּלוּכָה׃</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>