<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='Wesley' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='Wesley'>
        <title>Wesley's NT</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>http://www.code-off.de/wiki/index.php/ZefaniaXML:Textkonverter</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description/>
        <publisher>somebody</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>Wesley</identifier>
        <source>http://www.e-sword.net/usermods/</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Without payment you have received; without payment you are to give.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div osisID='2John' type='book'>
      <chapter osisID='2John.1'>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.1'>The elder unto the elect Kuria and her children, whom I love in the truth, and not I only, but likewise all who know the truth, For the truth's sake,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.2'>which abideth in us, and shall be with us for ever.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.3'>Grace be with you, mercy and peace from God the Father, and from Jesus Christ, the Son of the Father, in truth and love.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.4'>I rejoiced greatly that I found of thy children walking in the truth, as we received commandment from the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.5'>And now I beseech thee, Kuria, (not as writing a new commandment to thee, but that which we had from the beginning ) that we may love one another.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.6'>And this is love, that we walk after his commandments. This is the commandment as ye have heard from the beginning, that ye may walk in it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.7'>For many seducers are entered into the world, who confess not Jesus Christ that came in the flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.8'>This is the seducer and the antichrist. Look to yourselves, that we lose not the things we have wrought, but receive a full reward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.9'>Whosoever transgresseth and abideth not in the doctrine of Christ, hath not God:</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.10'>he that abideth in the doctrine of Christ, he hath both the Father and the Son. If any come to you, and bring not this doctrine,</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.11'>receive him not into your house, neither bid him God speed. For he that biddeth him God speed, is partaker of his evil deeds.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.12'>Having many things to write to you, I was not minded to write with paper and ink: but I trust to come to you and speak face to face, that our joy may be full.</verse>
        <verse osisID='2John.1.13'>The children of thy elect sister salute thee. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>