<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<osis xmlns='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace' xsi:schemaLocation='http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace http://www.bibletechnologies.net/osisCore.2.1.1.xsd' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'>
  <osisText osisRefWork='Bible' osisIDWork='Wesley' xml:lang='en'>
    <header>
      <revisionDesc>
        <date>2010-02-26</date>
        <p>initial OSIS 2.1.1 version</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork='Wesley'>
        <title>Wesley's NT</title>
        <contributor/>
        <creator>http://www.code-off.de/wiki/index.php/ZefaniaXML:Textkonverter</creator>
        <creator role='encoder'>ZefToOsis 1.0.0</creator>
        <subject>holy bible</subject>
        <date>2009-01-20</date>
        <description/>
        <publisher>somebody</publisher>
        <type type='OSIS'>Bible</type>
        <identifier type='OSIS'>Wesley</identifier>
        <source>http://www.e-sword.net/usermods/</source>
        <language type='IETF'>en</language>
        <relation/>
        <coverage>provide the bible to the world</coverage>
        <rights>Without payment you have received; without payment you are to give.</rights>
        <scope/>
        <refSystem>Bible</refSystem>
      </work>
    </header>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  <div osisID='Mark' type='book'>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.1'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.1'>The beginning of the gospel of Jesus Christ, the Son of God: As it is written in the prophets,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.2'>Behold I send my messenger before thy face, who shall prepare thy way before thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.3'>The voice of one crying aloud in the wilderness, Prepare ye the way of the Lord, make his paths straight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.4'>John baptized in the wilderness and preached the baptism of repentance, for the remission of sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.5'>And there went out to him all the land of Judea, and all they of Jerusalem, and were baptized of him in the river Jordan, confessing their sins.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.6'>And John was clothed with camels hair, and with a leathern girdle about his loins, and ate locusts and wild honey,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.7'>And proclaimed, saying, There cometh after me one mightier than I, the latchet of whose shoes I am not worthy to stoop down and unloose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.8'>I indeed have baptized you with water; but he will baptize you with the Holy Ghost.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.9'>And in those days, Jesus came from Nazareth of Galilee, and was baptized by John at Jordan.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.10'>And coming up from the water, straitway he saw the heavens opened, and the Spirit like a dove descending upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.11'>And a voice came from heaven, Thou art my beloved Son, in whom I delight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.12'>And immediately the Spirit leadeth him out into the wilderness. And he was there in the wilderness forty days,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.13'>tempted by Satan, and was with the wild-beasts; and the angels served him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.14'>Now after John was put in prison, Jesus came into Galilee, preaching the gospel of the kingdom of God,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.15'>Saying, The time is fulfilled, and the kingdom of God is at hand: repent ye, and believe the gospel.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.16'>And walking by the sea of Galilee, he saw Simon and Andrew his brother,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.17'>casting a net into the sea (for they were fishers) And Jesus said to them, Come ye after me, and I will make you fishers of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.18'>And straightway leaving their nets, they followed him. And having gone thence a little farther,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.19'>he saw James the son of Zebedee and John his brother, who were also in the vessel, mending their nets:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.20'>And he called them; and immediately leaving their father Zebedee in the vessel with the hired servants, they went after him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.21'>And they go into Capernaum. And straightway on the sabbath, he went into the synagogue and taught.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.22'>And they were astonished at his teaching; for he taught them as one having authority, and not as the scribes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.23'>And there was in their synagogue a man heaving an unclean spirit, and he cried out, saying, Let us alone:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.24'>what have we to do with thee, Jesus of Nazareth? Art thou come to destroy us? I know thee who thou art, the Holy one of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.25'>And Jesus rebuked him, saying, Hold thy peace and come out of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.26'>And the unclean spirit having torn him, and cried with a loud noise, came out of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.27'>And they were all amazed, so that they questioned among themselves, saying, What is this? What new teaching is this? For with authority he commandeth even the unclean spirits and they obey him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.28'>And immediately his fame went forth into all the country of Galilee round about.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.29'>And coming out of the synagogue, they entered forthwith into the house of Simon and Andrew, with James and John.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.30'>And Simon's wife's mother lay ill of a fever, and immediately they tell him of her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.31'>And he came and taking her by the hand, lifted her up; and straightway the fever left her, and she waited on them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.32'>And in the evening, when the sun was set, they brought to him all that were diseased, and them that were possessed with devils.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.33'>And the whole city was gathered together at the door.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.34'>And he healed many that were ill of divers diseases, and cast out many devils, and suffered not the devils to say that they knew him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.35'>And in the morning, rising a great while before day, he went out and departed into a desert place and prayed there.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.36'>And Simon and they that were with him followed after him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.37'>And having found him, they say to him, All men seek thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.38'>And he saith to them, Let us go to the neighbouring towns, that I may preach there also: for therefore am I come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.39'>And he preached in their synagogues throughout all Galilee, and cast out devils.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.40'>And there came to him a leper beseeching him and kneeling down to him and saying to him, If thou wilt, thou canst make me clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.41'>And Jesus, moved with tender compassion, putting forth his hand, touched him, and saith to him, I will; be thou clean.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.42'>And when he had spoken, immediately the leprosy departed from him and he was cleansed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.43'>And having straitly charged him, he forthwith sent him away, And saith to him, See thou say nothing to any man;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.44'>but go, shew thyself to the priest, and offer for thy cleansing what Moses commanded, for a testimony to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.1.45'>But he going out published it much and blazed abroad the matter, so that he could no more openly enter into the city; but he was without in desert places: and they came to him from every quarter.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.2'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.1'>And again he entered into Capernaum after some days; and it was heard that he was in the house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.2'>And immediately many were gathered together, so that there was no room for them, no, not even about the door.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.3'>And he spake the word to them. And they come to him, bringing a paralytic, borne of four.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.4'>And not being able to come nigh him for the croud, they uncovered the roof where he was, and having broken it up, they let down the couch whereon the paralytic lay.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.5'>Jesus seeing their faith, said to the paralytic, Son, thy sins are forgiven thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.6'>But certain of the scribes were sitting there, and reasoning in their hearts, Why doth this man thus speak blasphemies?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.7'>Who can forgive sins, but God only?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.8'>And Jesus immediately knowing in his spirit, that they so reasoned in themselves, said to them, Why reason ye thus in your hearts?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.9'>Which is easier? To say to the paralytic, Thy sins are forgiven thee?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.10'>Or to say, Arise, and take up thy couch and walk? But that ye may know, that the Son of man hath authority on earth to forgive sins: (He saith to the paralytic) I say to thee,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.11'>Arise, and take up thy couch, and go to thine house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.12'>And immediately he arose, and taking up his couch, went forth before them all; so that they were all amazed and glorified God, saying, We never saw it thus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.13'>And he went forth again by the sea-side, and all the multitude came to him, and he taught them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.14'>And passing by, he saw Levi, the son of Alpheus sitting at the custom-house, and saith to him, Follow me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.15'>And he arose and followed him. And as Jesus sat at meat in his house, many publicans and sinners sat also together with Jesus and his disciples; for there were many, and they followed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.16'>And the scribes and Pharisees seeing him eat with publicans and sinners, said to his disciples, How is it that he eateth and drinketh with publicans and sinners? And Jesus hearing it saith to them-</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.17'>They that are whole need not a physician, but they that are sick: I came not to call the righteous, but sinners to repentance.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.18'>And the disciples of John and of the Pharisees used to fast: and they come and say to him, Why do the disciples of John and of the Pharisees fast, but thy disciples fast not?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.19'>And Jesus said to them, Can the children of the bride-chamber fast, while the bridegroom is with them? As long as they have the bridegroom with them, they cannot fast.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.20'>But the days will come, when the bridegroom shall be taken away from them; and then shall they fast in those days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.21'>No man seweth a piece of new cloth on an old garment: else the new piece that filleth it up taketh away from the old, and the rent is made worse.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.22'>And no man putteth new wine into old leathern-bottles; else the new wine bursteth the bottles, and the wine is spilt, and the bottles are lost; but new wine must be put into new bottles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.23'>And he went thro' the corn-fields on the sabbath day: and his disciples as they went, plucked the ears of corn.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.24'>And the Pharisees said to him, Behold, why do they on the sabbath that which is not lawful?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.25'>And he said to them, Have ye never read what David did, when he had need and was hungry he and they that were with him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.26'>How he went into the house of God in the days of Abiathar the high priest, and ate the shew-bread, which it is not lawful for any but the priests to eat, and gave also to them who were with him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.27'>And he said to them, The sabbath was made for man, not man for the sabbath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.2.28'>Moreover the Son of man is Lord also of the sabbath.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.3'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.1'>And he entered again into the synagogue: and there was a man there who had a withered hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.2'>And they watched him, whether he would heal him on the sabbath, that they might accuse him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.3'>And he saith to the man that had the withered hand, Stand forth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.4'>And he saith to them, Is it lawful to do good on the sabbath, or to do evil? To save life or to kill?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.5'>But they held their peace. And looking round upon them with anger, being grieved for the hardness of their hearts, he saith to the man, Stretch forth thine hand. And he stretched it forth: and his hand was restored.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.6'>And the Pharisees going out, straightway took counsel with the Herodians against him, how they might destroy him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.7'>Then Jesus withdrew with his disciples to the sea: and a great multitude from Galilee followed him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.8'>And from Judea, and from Jerusalem, and from Idumea, and from beyond Jordan; and they about Tyre and Sidon, a great multitude, having heard what great things he did, came to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.9'>And he spake to his disciples, that a boat should wait on him, because of the multitude, lest they should throng him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.10'>For he had healed many, so that they rushed in upon him, as many as had plagues.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.11'>And unclean spirits when they saw him fell down before him and cried, saying, Thou art the Son of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.12'>And he straitly charged them, not to make him known.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.13'>And he goeth up into a mountain, and calleth to him whom he would, and they came to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.14'>And he ordained twelve, that they might be with him, and that he might send them forth to preach,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.15'>And to have power to heal diseases and to cast out devils.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.16'>And Simon he surnamed Peter: And James the son of Zebedee,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.17'>and John the brother of James (and he surnamed them Boanerges,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.18'>that is, the sons of thunder) And Andrew, and Philip, and Bartholomew, and Matthew, and Thomas, and James the son of Alpheus, and Thaddeus,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.19'>and Simon the Canaanite, And Judas Iscariot, who also betrayed him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.20'>And they come into an house: And the multitude cometh together again, so that they could not so much as eat bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.21'>And his relations hearing of it, came out to lay hold on him; for they said, He is beside himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.22'>But the scribes who had come down from Jerusalem said, He hath Beelzebub, and by the prince of the devils casteth he out devils.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.23'>And calling them to him, he said to them in parables, How can Satan cast out Satan?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.24'>If a kingdom be divided against itself, that kingdom cannot stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.25'>And if an house be divided against itself, that house cannot stand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.26'>If Satan then be risen up and divided against himself, he cannot stand, but hath an end.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.27'>None can enter into the strong one's house and plunder his goods, unless he first bind the strong one, and then he will plunder his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.28'>Verily I say to you, All sins shall be forgiven the sons of men and blasphemies wherewith soever they shall blaspheme.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.29'>But he that shall blaspheme against the Holy Ghost hath never forgiveness, but is liable to eternal damnation:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.30'>Because they said, He hath an unclean spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.31'>Then come his brethren and his mother, and standing without, sent to him, calling him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.32'>And the multitude sat about him; and they say to him, Behold, thy mother and thy brethren without seek for thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.33'>And he answered them, saying, Who is my mother or my brethren?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.34'>And looking round on them who sat about him, he said, Behold my mother and my brethren.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.3.35'>For whosoever shall do the will of God, the same is my brother and sister and mother.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.4'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.1'>And again he taught by the sea-side, and a great multitude was gathered to him, so that going into the boat, he sat in the sea, and the whole multitude was by the sea on the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.2'>And he taught them many things by parables, and said to them in his teaching, Hearken:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.3'>Behold, a sower went out to sow.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.4'>And as he sowed, some fell by the way-side, and the birds of the air came and devoured it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.5'>And some fell on stony ground, where it had not much earth; and immediately it sprung up, because it had no depth of earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.6'>But when the sun was up, it was scorched, and because it had no root, it withered away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.7'>And some fell among thorns, and the thorns grew up and choked it, and it yielded no fruit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.8'>And other fell on good ground, and yielded fruit springing up and increasing, and brought forth, some thirty, and some sixty, and some an hundred.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.9'>And he said, He that hath ears to hear, let him hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.10'>And when he was alone, they that were about him, with the twelve, asked him of the parable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.11'>And he said to them, To you it is given to know the mystery of the kingdom of God: but to them that are without, all things are in parables:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.12'>So that seeing they see, and do not perceive, and hearing they hear, and do not understand; lest at any time they should be converted, and their sins should be forgiven them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.13'>And he saith to them, Know ye not this parable? How then will ye know all parables?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.14'>The sower soweth the word. And these are they by the way-side, where the word is sown;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.15'>but when they have heard, Satan cometh immediately, and taketh away the word sown in their hearts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.16'>And these are they likewise who have received the seed on stony ground, who when they have heard the word, immediately receive it with joy: But have not root in themselves, and so indure but for a time:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.17'>afterward when affliction or persecution ariseth because of the word, they are presently offended.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.18'>And these are they that have received it among thorns,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.19'>who hear the word, And the cares of this world, and the deceitfulness of riches, and the desires of other things entering in, choke the word, and it becometh unfruitful.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.20'>And these are they that have received it on the good ground, who hear the word and receive it, and bring forth fruit, some thirty fold, some sixty, and some an hundred.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.21'>And he said to them, Is a candle brought to be cut under a bushel or under a bed, and not to be set on a candlestick?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.22'>For there is nothing hid, which shall not be manifested, neither was any thing kept secret, but that it might come abroad.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.23'>If any man hath ears to hear, let him hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.24'>And he said to them, Take heed what ye hear. With what measure ye mete, it shall be measured to you, and to you that hear, shall more be given.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.25'>For he that hath, to him shall be given; but he that hath not, from him shall be taken even that which he hath.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.26'>And he said, So is the kingdom of God, as if a man should cast seed into the ground,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.27'>And should sleep and rise night and day, and the seed should spring and grow up he knoweth not how.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.28'>For the earth bringeth forth fruit of itself, first the blade, then the ear, after that, the full corn in the ear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.29'>But when the fruit is brought forth, immediately he putteth in the sickle, because the harvest is come.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.30'>And he said, Whereto shall we liken the kingdom of God? Or with what comparison shall we compare it?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.31'>It is like a grain of mustard seed, which when it is sown in the earth, is one of the least of the seeds that are in the earth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.32'>But when it is sown it groweth up and becometh greater than all herbs, so that the birds of the air may lodge under the shadow of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.33'>And with many such parables spake he the word to them, as they were able to hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.34'>But without a parable spake he not to them: and in private he expounded all things to his disciples.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.35'>And the same day, in the evening he saith to them, Let us go over to the other side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.36'>And having sent away the multitude, they take him as he was in the boat. And there were with him other little vessels.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.37'>And there ariseth a great storm of wind, and the waves beat into the boat, so that it was now full.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.38'>But he was asleep on the pillow, in the stern of the boat. And they awake him and say to him, Master, carest thou not that we perish?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.39'>And he arose and rebuked the wind, and said to the sea, Peace; be still. And the wind ceased and there was a great calm.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.40'>And he said to them, Why are ye so fearful? How is it, that ye have not faith?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.4.41'>And they feared exceedingly, and said one to another, Who is this, that even the wind and the sea obey him?</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.5'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.1'>And they came to the other side of the sea, into the country of the Gadarenes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.2'>And as he came out of the boat, there met him immediately out of the tombs a man with an unclean spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.3'>Who had his dwelling among the tombs, and no man could bind him, no not with chains.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.4'>For he had been often bound with fetters and chains, and the chains had been plucked asunder, by him, and the fetters broken in pieces; and no man could tame him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.5'>And always night and day, he was in the tombs, and in the mountains, crying and cutting himself with stones.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.6'>But seeing Jesus afar off, he ran and worshiped him, And crying with a loud voice,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.7'>said, What have I to do with thee, Jesus, Son of the most high God? I adjure thee by God, that thou torment me not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.8'>(For he had said to him, Come out of the man, thou unclean spirit.)</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.9'>And he asked him, What is thy name? And he answered saying, My name is Legion; for we are many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.10'>And he earnestly besought him, that he would not send them away out of the country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.11'>Now there was there at the mountain a great herd of swine feeding.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.12'>And all the devils besought him, saying, Send us to the swine, that we may go into them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.13'>And Jesus forthwith gave them leave. And the unclean spirits going out, entered into the swine, and the herd rushed down the steep into the sea, (they were about two thousand) and were choked in the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.14'>And they that fed the swine fled, and told it in the city and in the country. And they went out to see that which was done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.15'>And they come to Jesus and see the demoniac, sitting and clothed and in his right mind: and they were afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.16'>And they saw it told them how it befell that demoniac, and also concerning the swine.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.17'>And they prayed him to depart out of their coasts.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.18'>And as he went into the boat, he that had been possessed with the devils, besought him, that he might be with him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.19'>But Jesus suffered him not, but said to him, Go home to thy friends, and tell them how great things the Lord hath done for thee, and hath had compassion on thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.20'>And he departed and published in Decapolis, how great things Jesus had done for him. And all men marvelled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.21'>And when Jesus was passed over again by boat to the other side, much people was gathered to him, and he was near the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.22'>And there cometh one of the rulers of the synagogue, Jairus by name, and seeing him, falleth at his feet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.23'>And besought him greatly, saying, My little daughter is at the point of death:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.24'>come and lay thy hands on her that she may be healed, and she shall live. And he went with him, and much people followed him and thronged him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.25'>And a certain woman who had had an issue of blood twelve years, And had suffered many things of many physicians,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.26'>and had spent all that she had, and was nothing bettered,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.27'>but rather grown worse, Having heard of Jesus, came in the croud behind, and touched his garment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.28'>For she said, If I but touch his clothes, I shall be whole.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.29'>And the fountain of her blood was straightway dried up, and she knew in her body, that she was healed of that plague.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.30'>And Jesus immediately knowing in himself, that virtue had gone out of him, turning about in the croud said, Who touched my clothes?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.31'>And his disciples said to him, Thou seest the multitude thronging thee, and sayest thou, Who touched me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.32'>And he looked round to see her that had done this.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.33'>And the woman fearing and trembling, knowing what was done in her, came and fell down before him, and told him all the truth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.34'>And he said to her, Daughter, thy faith hath made thee whole: go in peace, and continue whole of thy plague.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.35'>While he yet spake, they come from the ruler of the synagogue's house, saying, Thy daughter is dead: why troublest thou the Master farther?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.36'>When Jesus heard the word spoken he saith to the ruler of the synagogue, Fear not; only believe.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.37'>And he suffered no man to follow him, save Peter, and James, and John the brother of James.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.38'>And he cometh to the house of the ruler of the synagogue, and seeth a tumult, and them that wept and wailed greatly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.39'>And coming in, he saith to them, Why make ye this ado and weep? The damsel is not dead, but sleepeth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.40'>And they laughed him to scorn. But having put them all out, he taketh the father and the mother of the damsel, and them that were with him, and goeth in where the damsel was lying.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.41'>And taking the damsel by the hand he said to her, Talitha cumi, which is, being interpreted, Damsel, (I say to thee) arise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.42'>And straightway the damsel arose and walked: for she was twelve years old. And they were astonished with a great astonishment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.5.43'>And he charged them straitly, that no man should know it, and commanded that something should be given her to eat.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.6'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.1'>And he went out from thence and came into his own country, and his disciples follow him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.2'>And on the sabbath he taught in the synagogue, and many hearing were astonished, saying, Whence hath this man these things? And what wisdom is this that is given him, that such mighty works are wrought by his hands?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.3'>Is not this the carpenter? The son of Mary, the brother of James and Joses, and of Judas and Simon! And are not his sisters here with us? And they were offended at him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.4'>And Jesus said to them, A prophet is not without honour, but in his own country, and among his own kindred, and in his own house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.5'>And he could do no miracle there, save that he laid his hands on a few sick and healed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.6'>And he marvelled because of their unbelief. And he went round about thro' the villages teaching.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.7'>And he calleth to him the twelve, and sent them forth by two and two, and gave them power over unclean spirits;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.8'>And commanded them to take nothing for the journey, save a staff only; no scrip, no bread, no mony in their purse;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.9'>But be shod with sandals, and not to put on two coats.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.10'>And he said to them, Wheresoever ye enter into an house, there abide till ye depart from that place.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.11'>And whosoever shall not receive you nor hear you, departing thence shake off the dust under your feet, for a testimony against them. Verily I say to you, it shall be more tolerable for Sodom and Gomorrah in the day of judgment than for that city.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.12'>And they went out and preached, that men should repent.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.13'>And they cast out many devils, and anointed with oil many that were sick and healed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.14'>And king Herod heard (for his name was spread abroad) and he said, John the Baptist is risen from the dead, and therefore divine powers exert themselves in him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.15'>Others said, It is Elijah: and others said, It is a prophet, as one of the prophets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.16'>But Herod hearing thereof, said, This is that John whom I beheaded: he is risen from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.17'>For Herod himself had sent and apprehended John, and bound him in prison, for Herodias sake, his brother Philip's wife, for he had married her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.18'>For John had said to Herod, It is not lawful for thee, to have thy brother's wife.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.19'>Therefore Herodias was incensed against him, and was desirous to have killed him; but she could not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.20'>For Herod reverenced John, knowing that he was a just and holy man, and preserved him: and when he heard him, he did many things, and heard him gladly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.21'>And a convenient day being come, when Herod on his birth-day made a feast, for his lords, captains, and principal men of Galilee:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.22'>When the daughter of Herodias had come in and danced and pleased Herod, and his guests, the king said to the damsel, Ask of me whatsoever thou wilt, and I will give it thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.23'>And he sware to her, Whatsoever thou shalt ask me, I will give thee, to the half my kingdom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.24'>And she went out and said to her mother, What shall I ask? And she said, The head of John the Baptist.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.25'>And coming in quickly with haste to the king she asked, saying, I will that thou give me immediately in a charger the head of John the Baptist.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.26'>And the king was exceeding sorry: yet for his oath's sake, and for the sake of his guests, he would not reject her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.27'>And immediately the king sent one of his guard, and commanded his head to be brought.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.28'>And he went and beheaded him in the prison, And brought his head in a charger and gave it to the damsel, and the damsel gave it to her mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.29'>And the disciples hearing it, came and took up his corpse and laid it in a tomb.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.30'>And the apostles gather themselves together to Jesus, and told him all things, both what they had done and what they had taught.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.31'>And he said to them, Come ye yourselves apart into a desert place, and rest a while. For there were many coming and going, and they had no leisure so much as to eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.32'>And they departed into a desert place by boat privately.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.33'>And many saw them departing and knew him, and ran a foot thither from all the cities, and outwent them, and came together to him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.34'>And Jesus coming out saw a great multitude, and was moved with tender compassion for them; because they were as sheep having no shepherd, and he taught them many things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.35'>And when the day was now far spent, the disciples coming to him said, This is a desert place, and it is now late.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.36'>Send them away, that they may go into the country and villages round about, and buy themselves bread; for they have nothing to eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.37'>He answered and said to them, Give ye them to eat. And they say to him, Shall we go and buy two hundred pennyworth of bread, and give them to eat?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.38'>He saith to them, How many loaves have you? Go and see. And when they knew, they said, Five, and two fishes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.39'>And he commanded them to make all sit down by companies on the green grass.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.40'>And they sat down in ranks, by hundreds and by fifties.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.41'>And taking the five loaves, and the two fishes, looking up to heaven, he blessed, and gave them to the disciples to set before them: and he divided the two fishes among them all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.42'>And they all ate and were satisfied.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.43'>And they took up twelve baskets full of the fragments and of the fishes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.44'>And they that had eaten of the loaves, were about five thousand men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.45'>And straightway he constrained his disciples to go into the boat, and go before to the other side toward Bethsaida, while he sent away the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.46'>And having sent them away, he went to a mountain to pray.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.47'>And in the evening, the boat was in the midst of the sea, and he alone on the land.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.48'>And he saw them toiling in rowing; for the wind was contrary to them. And about the fourth watch of the night he cometh to them, walking on the sea, and would have passed by them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.49'>But they seeing him walking on the sea, supposed it had been an apparition, and cried out.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.50'>(For they all saw him and were troubled.) And immediately he talked with them, and saith to them, Take courage: it is I: be not afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.51'>And he went up to them into the boat, and the wind ceased: and they were amazed in themselves above measure and wondered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.52'>For they considered not the miracle of the loaves; for their heart was hardened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.53'>And having passed over, they came to the land of Gennesaret, and drew to shore.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.54'>And when they were come out of the boat, they knew him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.55'>And ran thro' the whole country round about, and brought about in beds them that were ill, where they heard he was.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.6.56'>And wheresoever he entered into villages, cities, or country-places, they laid the sick in the streets, and besought him that they might touch if it were but the hem of his garment; and as many as touched him were made whole.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.7'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.1'>Then come together to him the Pharisees and certain of the scribes, who came from Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.2'>And they saw some of his disciples eat bread with defiled, that is, unwashen hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.3'>Now the Pharisees and all the Jews, except they wash their hands to the wrist, eat not, holding the tradition of the elders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.4'>And coming from the market, unless they wash, they eat not: and many other things there are which they have received to hold, the washings of cups and pots and brasen vessels and couches.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.5'>Then the Pharisees ask him, Why walk not thy disciples, according to the tradition of the elders, but eat bread with defiled hands?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.6'>He answering said to them, Well hath Isaiah prophesied of you hypocrites, as it is written, This people honoureth me with their lips, but their heart is far from me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.7'>But in vain do they worship me, teaching for doctrines the commandments of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.8'>For leaving the commandment of God, ye hold the tradition of men, the washing of pots and cups: and many other such like things ye do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.9'>And he said to them, Full well ye abolish the commandment of God, that ye may keep your own tradition.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.10'>For Moses said, Honour thy father and thy mother, and, Whoso revileth father or mother, he shall surely die.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.11'>But ye say, If a man shall say to his father or mother, It is Corban, that is, a gift, by whatsoever thou mightest have been profited by me: he shall be free.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.12'>And ye suffer him no more to do ought for his father or his mother;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.13'>Abrogating the word of God by your traditions which ye have delivered: and many such like things ye do.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.14'>And calling all the multitude, he said to them, Hearken to me every one of you and consider.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.15'>There is nothing entering into a man from without, which can defile him; but the things which come out of him, these are they that defile the man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.16'>If any man have ears to hear, let him hear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.17'>And when he was come from the multitude into the house, his disciples asked him concerning the parable.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.18'>And he saith to them, Are even ye so without understanding? Do ye not perceive, That whatsoever entereth into a man from without, cannot defile him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.19'>Because it entereth not into his heart, but into the belly, and goeth into the vault, purging all meats.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.20'>And he said, That which cometh out of the man, that defileth the man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.21'>For from within, out of the heart of man proceed evil thoughts, adulteries, fornications, murders,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.22'>Thefts, covetousness, wickedness, deceit, lasciviousness, envy, evil speaking, pride, foolishness.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.23'>All these evils come from within, and defile the man.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.24'>And he arose and went thence into the borders of Tyre and Sidon. And entring into an house, he would have had no man know it; but he could not be hid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.25'>For a woman whose young daughter had an unclean spirit,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.26'>having heard of him, came and fell at his feet, (The woman was a Greek, a Syrophenician by nation) and besought him to cast the devil out of her daughter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.27'>But Jesus said to her, Let the children first be satisfied; for it is not right to take the childrens bread and cast it to the dogs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.28'>She answered and said to him, True, Lord: yet the dogs under the table eat of the children's crumbs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.29'>And he said to her, For this saying, go: the devil is gone out of thy daughter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.30'>And going to her house, she found the devil gone out and her daughter lying on the bed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.31'>And departing again from the borders of Tyre and Sidon, he came to the sea of Galilee, thro' the midst of the country of Decapolis.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.32'>And they bring to him one that was deaf and had an impediment in his speech, and beseech him to put his hand upon him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.33'>And taking him aside from the multitude, he put his fingers into his ears, and spitting, touched his tongue.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.34'>And looking up to heaven, he groaned and saith to him, Ephphatha, that is, be opened.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.35'>And straightway his ears were opened, and the string of his tongue was loosed, and he spake plain.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.36'>And he charged them to tell no man; but the more he charged them, so much the more a great deal they published it,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.7.37'>And were beyond measure astonished, saying, He hath done all things well; he maketh both the deaf to hear and the dumb to speak.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.8'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.1'>In those days, the multitude being very great, and having nothing to eat,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.2'>Jesus calling his disciples saith to them, I have compassion on the multitude, because they continue with me now three days, and have nothing to eat.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.3'>And if I send them away fasting to their own home, they will faint by the way; for divers of them come from far.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.4'>And his disciples answered him, Whence can one satisfy these men with bread here in the wilderness?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.5'>And he asked them, How many loaves have ye?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.6'>And they said, Seven. And he commanded the people to sit down on the ground; and taking the seven loaves, having given thanks, he brake and gave to his disciples to set before them: and they did set them before the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.7'>And they had a few small fishes: and having blessed them, he commanded, to set them also before them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.8'>So they did eat and were satisfied; and they took up of the fragments that were left, seven baskets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.9'>And they that had eaten were about four thousand: and he sent them away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.10'>And straightway going into the boat with his disciples he came into the parts of Dalmanutha.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.11'>And the Pharisees came forth and questioned with him, seeking of him a sign from heaven, tempting him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.12'>And sighing deeply in his spirit, he said, Why doth this generation seek a sign? Verily I say to you, There shall no sign be given to this generation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.13'>And he left them and taking boat again, went to the other side.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.14'>Now they had forgotten to take bread; nor had they in the boat with them any more than one loaf.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.15'>And he charged them, Take heed, beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and of the leaven of Herod.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.16'>And they reasoned among themselves, saying, We have no bread.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.17'>And Jesus knowing it saith to them, Why reason ye, because ye have no bread? Perceive ye not yet, neither consider? Have ye your heart yet hardened?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.18'>Having eyes, see ye not? And having ears, hear ye not? And do not ye remember?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.19'>When I brake the five loaves among the five thousand, how many baskets full of fragments took ye up? They say to him, Twelve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.20'>And when the seven among four thousand, how many baskets full of fragments took ye up?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.21'>And they said, Seven. And he said to them, How is it, that ye do not understand?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.22'>And he cometh to Bethsaida. And they bring to him a blind man, and beseech him to touch him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.23'>And taking the blind man by the hand, he led him out of the town, and having spit on his eyes, and put his hands upon him, he asked him, If he saw ought?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.24'>And looking up he said, I see men, as trees walking.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.25'>Then he put his hands again on his eyes and made him look up, and he was restored and saw all men clearly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.26'>And he sent him away to his house, saying, Neither go into the town, nor tell it to any in the town.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.27'>And Jesus went out and his disciples into the towns of Cesarea Philippi. And in the way he asked his disciples, saying to them, Whom do men say that I am?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.28'>And they answered, John the Baptist; but some say Elijah; and others, one of the prophets.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.29'>And he saith to them, But whom say ye that I am? And Peter answering saith to him, Thou art the Christ.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.30'>And he charged them that they should tell no man of him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.31'>And he began to teach them, that the Son of man must suffer many things, and be rejected by the elders and the chief priests and scribes, and be killed, and after three days rise again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.32'>And he spake that saying openly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.33'>And Peter taking hold of him, rebuked him. But he turning about, and looking on his disciples rebuked Peter, saying, Get thee behind me, Satan; for thou savourest not the things of God, but the things of men.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.34'>And when he had called the people to him, with his disciples also, he said to them, Whosoever is willing to come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross and follow me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.35'>For whosoever will save his life, shall lose it; but whosoever shall lose his life, for my sake and the gospels, he shall save it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.36'>For what shall it profit a man, if he shall gain the whole world, and lose his own soul?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.37'>Or what shall a man give, in exchange for his soul?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.8.38'>For whosoever shall be ashamed of me and of my words in this adulterous and sinful generation, of him also shall the Son of man be ashamed, when he cometh in the glory of his Father, with the holy angels.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.9'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.1'>And he said to them, Verily I say unto you, there are some of them that stand here, who shall not taste of death, till they see the kingdom of God coming with power.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.2'>And after six days Jesus taketh with him Peter and James and John, and carrieth them up into an high mountain, by themselves apart, and was transfigured before them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.3'>And his raiment became shining, exceeding white, as snow, such as no fuller on earth can whiten.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.4'>And there appeared to him Elijah with Moses, and they talked with Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.5'>And Peter answering faith to Jesus, Master, it is good for us to be here; and let us make three tents, one for thee, and one for Moses, and one for Elijah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.6'>For he knew not what to say; for they were sore afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.7'>And there was a cloud that overshadowed them, and a voice came out of the cloud, This is my beloved Son; hear him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.8'>And suddenly looking round, they saw no man any more, save Jesus only with themselves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.9'>And as they came down from the mountain, he charged them to tell no man what things they had seen, till the Son of man were risen from the dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.10'>And they laid hold on that saying, questioning one with another, What meaneth, Till he were risen from the dead?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.11'>And they asked him, saying, Why say the scribes, that Elijah must come first?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.12'>And he answering told them, Elijah verily coming first, restoreth all things: and, how it is written of the Son of man, that he must suffer many things, and be set at naught.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.13'>But I say to you, Elijah is come, as it is written of him: and they have done to him whatsoever they listed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.14'>And coming to his disciples, he saw a great multitude about them, and the scribes questioning with them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.15'>And straightway all the multitude seeing him, were greatly amazed, and running to him, saluted him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.16'>And he asked the scribes, What question ye with them? And one of the multitude answering said,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.17'>Master, I have brought to thee my son, who hath a dumb spirit.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.18'>And wheresoever he taketh him, he teareth him, and he foameth and gnasheth with his teeth and pineth away. And I spake to thy disciples to cast him out, and they could not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.19'>He answereth them and saith, O faithless generation, how long shall I be with you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.20'>How long shall I suffer you? Bring him to me. And they brought him to him. And when he saw him, immediately the spirit tore him, and he fell on the ground, and wallowed foaming.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.21'>And he asked his father, How long is it since this came to him? And he said, From a little child.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.22'>And it hath often cast him both into the fire and into the water to destroy him; but if thou canst do any thing, have compassion on us and help us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.23'>Jesus saith to him, If thou canst believe, all things are possible to him that believeth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.24'>And straightway the father of the child crying out, said with tears, Lord, I do believe: help thou mine unbelief.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.25'>And Jesus seeing that the multitude came running together, rebuked the unclean spirit, saying, Thou deaf and dumb spirit, I command thee, come out of him, and enter no more into him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.26'>And having cried and rent him sore, he came out; and he was as dead, so that many said, He is dead.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.27'>But Jesus taking him by the hand, lifted him up, and he arose.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.28'>And when he was come into an house, his disciples asked him privately, Why could not we cast him out?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.29'>And he said to them, This kind can come forth by nothing but by prayer and fasting.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.30'>And departing thence, they passed thro' Galilee, and he was not willing that any should know it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.31'>For he taught his disciples and said to them, The Son of man is delivered into the hands of men; and they will kill him, and after he hath been killed, he shall rise the third day.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.32'>But they understood not that saying, and were afraid to ask him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.33'>And he came to Capernaum. And being in the house, he asked them, What was it ye disputed among yourselves by the way?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.34'>But they held their peace; for they had been debating among themselves in the way, Who should be greatest?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.35'>And sitting down, he called the twelve and saith to them, If any man desire to be first, let him be the last of all, and the servant of all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.36'>And taking a little child, he set him in the midst of them, and embracing him he said to them, Whosoever shall receive one such little child in my name,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.37'>receiveth me: and whosoever shall receive me, receiveth not only me, but him that sent me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.38'>And John answered him, saying, Master, we saw one casting out devils in thy name, who followeth not us, and we forbad him, because he followeth not us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.39'>And Jesus said, Forbid him not; for there is no one who shall do a miracle in my name, who can readily speak evil of me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.40'>For he that is not against you, is for you. For whosoever shall give you a cup of cold water to drink in my name,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.41'>because ye belong to Christ, verily I say to you, he shall in no wise lose his reward.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.42'>And whosoever shall offend one of the little ones that believe in me, it were better for him that a millstone were hanged about his neck, and he were cast into the sea.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.43'>And if thy hand offend thee, cut it off: it is good for thee to enter into life maimed, than having two hands, to go into hell, into the fire that never shall be quenched:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.44'>Where their worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.45'>And if thy foot offend thee, cut it off: it is good for thee to enter halt into life, than having two feet to be cast into hell, into the fire that never shall be quenched: Where their worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.46'>And if thine eye offend thee, pluck it out:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.47'>it is good for thee, to enter into the kingdom of God having one eye, than having two eyes to be cast into hell-fire:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.48'>Where their worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.49'>For every one shall be salted with fire, and every sacrifice shall be salted with salt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.9.50'>Salt is good: but if the salt have lost its saltness, wherewith will ye season it? Have salt in yourselves, and have peace one with another.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.10'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.1'>And he arose and cometh thence into the coasts of Judea, thro' the country beyond Jordan: and the multitudes resort to him again, and as he was wont, he taught them again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.2'>And the Pharisees coming asked him, Is it lawful for a man to put away his wife?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.3'>Tempting him. And he answering said to them, What did Moses command you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.4'>They said, Moses suffered to write a bill of divorce, and to put her away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.5'>And Jesus answering said to them, For your hardness of heart he wrote you this precept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.6'>But from the beginning of the creation God made them male and female.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.7'>For this cause shall a man leave his father and mother, and cleave to his wife:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.8'>And they twain shall be one flesh; so then they are no more twain but one flesh.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.9'>What therefore God hath joined together, let not man put asunder.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.10'>And in the house his disciples asked him again of the same matter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.11'>And he saith to them, Whosoever shall put away his wife and marry another, committeth adultery against her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.12'>And if a woman shall put away her husband, and be married to another, she committeth adultery.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.13'>And they brought little children to him that he might touch them; but the disciples rebuked those that brought them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.14'>But Jesus seeing it was much displeased and said to them, Suffer little children to come to me, and forbid them not: for of such is the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.15'>Verily I say to you, Whosoever shall not receive the kingdom of God as a little child, he shall in no wise enter therein.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.16'>And taking them up in his arms, he put his hands upon them and blessed them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.17'>And as he was going out into the way, one running and kneeling to him, asked him, Good Master, what shall I do, that I may inherit eternal life?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.18'>But Jesus saith to him, Why callest thou me good? There is none good but one, that is God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.19'>Thou knowest the commandments, Do not commit adultery, Do not murder, Do not steal, Do not bear false witness, Defraud not, Honour thy father and mother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.20'>And he answering said to him, Master, all these have I kept from my childhood.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.21'>Then Jesus looking upon him, loved him, and said to him, One thing thou lackest: Go, sell whatsoever thou hast, and give to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven: and come, follow me, taking up thy cross.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.22'>But he was sad at that saying, and went away grieved; for he had great possessions.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.23'>And Jesus looking round said to his disciples, How hardly shall they that have riches enter into the kingdom of God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.24'>And the disciples were astonished at his words. But Jesus answering again saith to them, Children, how hard is it for them that trust in riches, to enter into the kingdom of God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.25'>It is easier for a camel to go thro' the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.26'>And they were astonished out of measure, saying to each other, Who then can be saved?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.27'>And Jesus looking upon them said, With men it is impossible, but not with God, for with God all things are possible.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.28'>And Peter said to him, Lo, we have left all and followed thee. And Jesus answering said,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.29'>Verily I say to you, there is none that hath left house, or brethren, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands for my sake and the gospel's,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.30'>But he shall receive an hundred fold now in this time, houses and brethren and sisters and mothers and children and lands with persecutions, and in the world to come eternal life.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.31'>But many that are first shall be last, and the last first.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.32'>And they were in the way going up to Jerusalem, and Jesus went before them. And they were amazed, and as they followed, they were afraid. And taking the twelve again, he told them what things should befall him:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.33'>Behold, we go up to Jerusalem, and the Son of man shall be betrayed to the chief priests and the scribes: and they will condemn him to death, and deliver him to the Gentiles.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.34'>And they will mock him and scourge him and spit upon him and kill him. And the third day he will rise again.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.35'>And James and John the sons of Zebedee come to him, saying, Master, we would that thou shouldest do for us what we shall ask.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.36'>And he said to them, What would ye that I should do for you?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.37'>They said to him, Grant us to sit one on thy right-hand, and one on thy left-hand in thy glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.38'>But Jesus said to them, Ye know not what ye ask. Can ye drink of the cup that I drink of, and be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.39'>And they said to him, We can. And Jesus said to them, Ye shall indeed drink of the cup that I drink of, and be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.40'>But to sit on my right-hand and on my left, is not mine to give, but to them for whom it is prepared.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.41'>And the ten hearing it, were much displeased with James and John.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.42'>But Jesus calling them, saith to them, Ye know that they who rule over the Gentiles, lord it over them, and their great ones exercise authority upon them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.43'>But it shall not be so among you; but whosoever desireth to be great among you, shall be your servant.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.44'>And whosoever desireth to be the chief, shall be the servant of all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.45'>For the Son of man came not to be served, but to serve, and to give his life a ransom for many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.46'>And they come to Jericho. And as he went out of Jericho with his disciples and a great multitude, blind Bartimeus, the son of Timeus, sat by the way-side begging.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.47'>And when he heard, It is Jesus of Nazareth, he cried out and said, Jesus, thou Son of David, have mercy on me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.48'>And many charged him to hold his peace; but he cried so much the more a great deal, Thou Son of David, have mercy on me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.49'>And Jesus standing still, commanded him to be called. And they call the blind man, saying to him, Take courage; rise; he calleth thee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.50'>And casting away his garment, he rose and came to Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.51'>And Jesus answering said to him, What wilt thou that I should do for thee? The blind man said to him, Lord, that I may receive my sight.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.10.52'>And Jesus said, Go; thy faith hath saved thee. And immediately he received his sight, and followed him in the way.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.11'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.1'>And when they were come nigh to Jerusalem to Bethphage and Bethany,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.2'>at the mount of Olives, he sendeth two of his disciples, And saith to them, Go ye into the village over against you, and as soon as ye enter it, ye shall find a colt tied, whereon never man sat: loose and bring him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.3'>And if any say to you, Why do ye this? Say, The Lord hath need of him; and straightway he will send him hither.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.4'>And they went and found the colt tied, without, in the street, and they loose him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.5'>And some of them that stood there said, What do ye, loosing the colt?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.6'>And they said to them, as Jesus had commanded; and they let them go.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.7'>And they brought the colt to Jesus, and cast their garments on him, and he sat on him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.8'>And many spread their garments in the way: and others cut down branches from the trees, and strewed them in the way.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.9'>And they that went before, and they that followed after cried, saying, Hosanna: Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.10'>Blessed be the kingdom of our father David that cometh: Hosanna in the highest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.11'>And Jesus entered into Jerusalem, and into the temple, and having looked round about upon all things, it being now evening, he went out to Bethany with the twelve.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.12'>And on the morrow, as they were coming from Bethany, he was hungry.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.13'>And seeing a fig-tree afar off, having leaves, he came, if haply he might find any thing thereon: and coming to it, he found nothing but leaves, for it was not a season of figs.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.14'>And he answering said to it, No man eat fruit of thee hereafter for ever: And his disciples heard it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.15'>And they come to Jerusalem. And Jesus going into the temple, drove out them that bought and sold in the temple, and overthrew the tables of the mony-changers,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.16'>and the seats of them that sold doves, And suffered not that any one should carry any vessel thro' the temple.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.17'>And he taught, saying to them, Is it not written, My house shall be called of all nations an house of prayer? But ye have made it a den of thieves.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.18'>And the scribes and chief priests heard it and sought how they might destroy him: for they feared him, because all the people was astonished at his teaching.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.19'>And when evening was come, he went out of the city. And passing by in the morning,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.20'>they saw the fig-tree dried up from the roots.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.21'>And Peter remembring, saith to him, Master, behold the fig-tree which thou cursedst is withered away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.22'>And Jesus answering saith to them, Have faith in God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.23'>For verily I say to you, Whosoever shall say to this mountain, Be thou removed and cast into the sea, and not doubt in his heart, but believe that the things which he saith shall come to pass, he shall have whatsoever he saith.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.24'>Therefore I say to you, What things soever ye ask in prayer, believe that ye shall receive, and ye shall have them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.25'>But when ye stand praying, forgive, if ye have ought against any, that your Father who is in heaven, may forgive you also your trespasses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.26'>But if ye do not forgive, neither will your Father who is in heaven forgive your trespasses.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.27'>And they come again to Jerusalem. And as he was walking in the temple, the chief priests, and the scribes, and the elders come to him and say to him, By what authority dost thou these things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.28'>And who gave thee authority to do these things?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.29'>Jesus answering said to them, I also will ask you one question, and answer me, and I will tell you by what authority I do these things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.30'>Was the baptism of John of heaven or of men?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.31'>And they reasoned among themselves, saying, If we say, from heaven, he will say, Why then did ye not believe him?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.32'>But if we say, of men: they feared the people; for all accounted John, that he was indeed a prophet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.11.33'>And they answering say to Jesus, We cannot tell. And Jesus answering saith to them, Neither tell I you, by what authority I do these things.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.12'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.1'>And he said to them in parables, A man planted a vineyard, and set an hedge about it, and digged a wine-fat, and built a tower, and let it out to husbandmen, and went into a far country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.2'>And at the season he sent a servant to the husbandmen, to receive from the husbandmen of the fruit of the vineyard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.3'>But they took him, and beat him, and sent him away empty.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.4'>And again he sent to them another servant: and at him they cast stones, and wounded him in the head, and sent him away shamefully handled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.5'>And again he sent another, and him they killed; and many others, beating some and killing some.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.6'>Having yet therefore one son his well-beloved, he sent him also last to them, saying, They will reverence my son.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.7'>But those husbandmen said among themselves, This is the heir: come, let us kill him, and the inheritance shall be ours.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.8'>And they took him and killed him, and cast him out of the vineyard.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.9'>What therefore will the lord of the vineyard do? He will come and destroy the husbandmen, and will give the vineyard to others.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.10'>And have ye not read this scripture? The stone which the builders rejected, is become the head of the corner?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.11'>This was the Lord's doing, and it was marvellous in our eyes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.12'>And they sought to seize him, but feared the multitude; for they knew he had spoken the parable against them; and leaving him, they went away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.13'>And they send to him certain of the Pharisees, and of the Herodians, to catch him his talk.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.14'>And they coming say to him, Master, we know that thou art true, and carest for no man; for thou regardest not the person of men, but teachest the way of God in truth. Is it lawful to give tribute to Cesar, or not?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.15'>Shall we give, or shall we not give? But he knowing their hypocrisy, said to them, Why tempt ye me? Bring me a penny, that I may see it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.16'>And he saith, Whose is this image and superscription?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.17'>They say to him, Cesar's. And Jesus answering said to them, Render to Cesar the things that are Cesar's, and to God the things that are God's. And they marvelled at him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.18'>Then come to him the Saducees, who say there is no resurrection, and they asked him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.19'>saying, Master, Moses wrote to us, If a man's brother die, and leave a wife, and leave no children, that his brother should take his wife, and raise up seed to his brother.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.20'>There were seven brethren, and the first took a wife, and dying, left no seed.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.21'>And the second took her and died, neither left he any seed; and the third likewise.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.22'>And the seventh took her and left no seed. Last of all died the woman also.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.23'>In the resurrection therefore, when they shall rise, whose wife shall she be of them?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.24'>For the seven had her to wife. And Jesus answering said to them, Do ye not therefore err, because ye know not the scriptures, neither the power of God?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.25'>For when they rise from the dead, they neither marry nor are given in marriage, but are as the angels who are in heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.26'>And touching the dead, that they rise, Have ye oot read in the book of Moses, how in the bush God spake to thim, saying, I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.27'>He is not the God of the dead, but the God of the living. Ye therefore greatly err.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.28'>And one of the scribes came, and having heard them disputing together, and perceiving that he had answered them well, asked him, Which is the first commandment of all?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.29'>And Jesus answered him, The first of all the commandments is, Hear, O Israel; the Lord our God is one Lord.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.30'>And thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy mind, and with all thy strength.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.31'>This is the first commandment. And the second is like unto it, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself. There is no other commandment greater than these.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.32'>And the scribe said to him, Excellently well, Master! Thou hast said the truth: for He is one: and there is no other but he.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.33'>And to love him with all the heart, and with all the understanding, and with all the mind, and with all the strength, and to love his neighbour as himself, is more than all whole burnt-offerings and sacrifices.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.34'>And Jesus, seeing that he answered discreetly, said to him, Thou art not far from the kingdom of God. And no man after that durst question him any more.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.35'>And Jesus answering, as he taught in the temple, said, How say the scribes, that Christ is the Son of David?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.36'>For David himself said by the Holy Ghost, The Lord saith to my Lord, Sit thou on my righthand, till I make thine enemies thy footstool.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.37'>David therefore himself calleth him Lord: How is he then his son? And a great multitude heard him gladly.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.38'>And he said to them in his teaching, Beware of the Scribes, who love to go in long sobes,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.39'>and to be saluted in the market-places, And the chief seats in the synagogues, and the uppermost places at feasts: Who devour widows houses, and for a pretence make long prayers:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.40'>these shall receive the greater damnation.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.41'>And Jesus sitting over-against the treasury, beheld how the people cast mony into the treasury: and many that were rich cast in much.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.42'>And a poor widow coming, cast in two mites, which make a farthing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.43'>And calling his disciples, he saith to them, Verily I say to you, that this poor widow hath cast in more than they all who have cast into the treasury.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.12.44'>For they all did cast in of their abundance: but she of her penury did cast in all that she had, even her whole living.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.13'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.1'>And as he went out of the temple, one of his disciples saith to him, Master, see what manner of stones, and what manner of buildings!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.2'>And Jesus answering said to him, Seest thou these great buildings? There shall not be left one stone upon another that shall not be thrown down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.3'>And as he sat on the mount of Olives, over-against the temple, Peter and James and John and Andrew asked him privately,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.4'>Tell us, when shall these things be? And what shall be the sign when all these things shall be fulfilled?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.5'>And Jesus answering said, Take heed lest any deceive you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.6'>For many will come in my name saying, I am Christ, and will deceive many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.7'>But when ye shall hear of wars and rumours of wars, be not troubled; for it must be; but the end is not yet.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.8'>For nation shall rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom: and there shall be earthquakes in divers places, and there shall be famines and troubles: these are the beginning of sorrows.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.9'>But take heed to yourselves for they will deliver you to councils, and ye shall be beaten in synagogues, and shall be brought before rulers and kings for my sake, for a testimony to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.10'>And the gospel must first be published among all nations.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.11'>But when they shall hale you and deliver you up, take no thought beforehand what ye shall speak, neither do ye premeditate: but whatsoever shall be given you in that hour, that speak; for it is not yet that speak, but the Holy Ghost.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.12'>Now the brother shall betray the brother to death, and the father the son: and children shall rise up against their parents, and cause them to be put to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.13'>And ye shall be hated of all men for my name's sake; but he that endureth to the end, he shall be saved.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.14'>But when ye shall see the abomination of desolation spoken of by Daniel the prophet standing where it ought not, (let him that readeth understand) then let them that are in Judea flee to the mountains:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.15'>And let not him that is on the house-top go down into the house, neither enter in, to take any thing out of his house.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.16'>And let not him that is in the field, turn back to take up his garment.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.17'>But wo to them that are with child, and to them that give suck in those days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.18'>And pray ye that your flight be not in the winter.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.19'>For in those days shall be affliction, such as was not from the beginning of the creat`on, which God created until now, neither shall be.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.20'>And unless the Lord had shortened those days, no flesh should be saved: but for the elect's sake whom he hath chosen, he hath shortened those days.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.21'>Then if any man say to you, Lo, here is Christ, or lo, he is there, believe it not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.22'>For false Christs and false prophets shall rise, and shall shew signs and wonders, to seduce, if it were possible, even the elect.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.23'>But take ye heed: behold, I have foretold you all things.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.24'>But in those days, after that tribulation, the sun shall be darkened, and the moon shall not give her light,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.25'>And the stars of heaven shall fall, and the powers that are in the heavens shall be shaken.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.26'>And then shall they see the Son of man coming in the clouds, with power and great glory.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.27'>And then shall he send his angels, and gather together his elect, from the four winds, from the uttermost part of the earth, to the uttermost part of heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.28'>Now learn a parable from the fig-tree. When its branch is now tender and putteth forth leaves, ye know that summer is near.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.29'>So likewise when ye see these things come to pass, know that he is nigh, even at the door.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.30'>Verily I say to you, this generation shall in no wise pass, till all these things be done.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.31'>Heaven and earth shall pass away, but my words shall in no wise pass away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.32'>But of that day and hour knoweth no one, no, not the angels that are in heaven, neither the Son, but the Father.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.33'>Take heed; watch and pray: for ye know not when the time is.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.34'>For the Son of man is as a man taking a far journey, who left his house, and gave authority to his servants, and to each his work, and commanded the porter to watch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.35'>Watch ye therefore; for ye know not when the master of the house cometh; at evening, or at midnight, or at cock-crowing, or in the morning:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.36'>Lest coming suddenly he find you sleeping.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.13.37'>And what I say to you, I say to all, Watch.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.14'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.1'>And after two days was the feast of the passover and of unleavened bread; and the chief priests and the scribes sought how they might apprehend him by subtlety, and put him to death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.2'>But they said, Not at the feast, lest there be a tumult of the people.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.3'>And he being in Bethany in the house of Simon the leper, as he sat at table, there came a woman having an alabaster box of ointment, of spikenard, very costly; and shaking the box, she poured it on his head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.4'>But there were some that had indignation within themselves, and said, Why was this waste of the ointment made?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.5'>For it might have been sold for more than three hundred pence and given to the poor. And they murmured at her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.6'>But Jesus said, Let her alone: why trouble ye her? She hath wrought a good work on me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.7'>For ye have the poor always with you, and when ye will, ye may do them good; but me ye have not always.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.8'>She hath done what she could: she hath before-hand embalmed my body for the burial.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.9'>Verily I say to you, wheresoever this gospel shall be preached throughout the whole world, what she hath done shall be spoken of also, for a memorial of her.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.10'>And Judas Iscariot, one of the twelve, went to the chief priests, to betray him unto them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.11'>And hearing it they were glad, and promised to give him mony. And he sought how he might conveniently betray him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.12'>And on the first day of unleavened bread, when they killed the Passover, his disciples say to him, Where wilt thou that we go and prepare, that thou mayst eat the passover?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.13'>And he sendeth two of his disciples, and saith to them, Go ye into the city, and there shall meet you a man carrying a pitcher of water: follow him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.14'>And wheresoever he shall go in, say ye to the man of the house, The Master saith, Where is the guest-chamber, where I shall eat the Passover with my disciples?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.15'>And he will shew you a large upper room furnished: there make ready for us.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.16'>And his disciples went, and came into the city, and found as he had said to them. And they made ready the passover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.17'>And in the evening he cometh with the twelve. And as they sat and ate,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.18'>Jesus said, Verily I say to you, one of you that eat with me will betray me.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.19'>And they were sorry, and said to him one by one, Is it I?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.20'>And another, Is it I? And he answering said to them, It is one of the twelve, that dippeth with me in the dish.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.21'>The Son of man indeed goeth as it is written of him; but wo to that man by whom the Son of man is betrayed: it had been good for that man, if he had not been born.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.22'>And as they ate, Jesus took bread, and blessed, and brake it, and gave to them, and said, Take, eat: this is my body.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.23'>And he took the cup, and having given thanks, gave it them, and they all drank of it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.24'>And he said to them, This is my blood of the New Testament, which is shed for many.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.25'>Verily I say to you, I will drink no more of the fruit of the vine, till that day that I drink it new in the kingdom of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.26'>And having sung the hymn, they went out toward the mount of Olives.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.27'>And Jesus saith to them, Ye all will be offended at me this night; for it is written, I will smite the shepherd, and the sheep shall be scattered.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.28'>But after I am risen, I will go before you into Galilee.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.29'>But Peter said to him, Tho' all men shall be offended, yet will not I.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.30'>Jesus saith to him, Verily I say to thee, That thou to-day, this night, before the cock crow twice, wilt deny me thrice.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.31'>But he said the more vehemently, If I must die with thee, I will in no wise deny thee. In like manner also said they all.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.32'>And they come to a place named Gethsemane; and he saith to his disciples, Sit here while I shall pray.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.33'>And he taketh with him Peter and James and John; and he began to be sore amazed and in deep anguish, And saith to them,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.34'>My soul is exceeding sorrowful, even to death; tarry ye here and watch.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.35'>And going forward a little, he fell on the ground, and prayed, that, if it were possible, the hour might pass from him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.36'>And he said, Abba, Father, all things are possible to thee: take away this cup from me: yet not what I will, but what thou wilt.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.37'>And he cometh and findeth them sleeping, and saith to Peter, Simon, sleepest thou?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.38'>Couldest thou not watch one hour? Watch and pray, lest ye enter into temptation; the spirit indeed is willing, but the flesh is weak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.39'>And going again he prayed, speaking the same words. And returning,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.40'>he found them asleep again (for their eyes were heavy) and they knew not what to answer him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.41'>And he cometh the third time and saith to them, Sleep on now, and take your rest. It is enough. The hour is come: behold the Son of man is betrayed into the hands of sinners.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.42'>Rise up; let us go: lo he that betrayeth me is at hand.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.43'>And immediately, while ye yet spake, cometh Judas, one of the twelve, and with him a great multitude, with swords and clubs, from the chief priests, and the scribes, and the elders.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.44'>Now he that betrayed him had given them a signal, saying, Whomsoever I shall kiss, is he: seize and lead him away safely.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.45'>And when he was come, he goeth straightway to him, and saith, Master, Master!</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.46'>And kissed him? And they laid their hands on him, and took him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.47'>And one of them that stood by, drew a sword, and smote the servant of the high priest, and cut off his ear.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.48'>And Jesus answering said to them, Are ye come as against a robber, with swords and clubs, to take me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.49'>I was daily with you in the temple teaching, and ye took me not; but the scriptures must be fulfilled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.50'>Then they all forsook him and fled. And a certain young man followed him, having a linen cloth cast about his naked body;</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.51'>and the young men laid hold on him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.52'>And he left the linen cloth, and fled from them naked.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.53'>And they led Jesus away to the high priest, and with him were assembled all the chief priests, and the elders and scribes.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.54'>And Peter followed him afar off, even into the palace of the high priest, and sat with the officers, and warmed himself.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.55'>Then the chief priests and all the council sought for witness against Jesus, to put him to death, and found none.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.56'>For many bore false witness against him; but their evidences were not sufficient.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.57'>And there arose certain, and bore false witness against him,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.58'>saying, We heard him say, I will destroy this temple made with hands, and within three days I will build another made without hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.59'>And neither so was their evidence sufficient. Then the high priest standing up in the midst,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.60'>asked Jesus, saying, Answerest thou nothing?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.61'>What is it which these witness against thee? But he held his peace and answered nothing. Again the high priest asked him and said to him, Art thou the Christ, the Son of the Blessed?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.62'>And Jesus said, I am: and ye shall see the Son of man, sitting on the right-hand of power, and coming with the clouds of heaven.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.63'>Then the high priest rent his clothes and saith, What farther need have we of witnesses?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.64'>Ye have heard the blasphemy: what think ye? And they all condemned him to deserve death.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.65'>And some began to spit on him, and to cover his face, and to buffet him, and to say to him, Prophesy, And the officers smote him with the palms of their hands.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.66'>And as Peter was in the hall below, there cometh one of the maids of the high priest.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.67'>And seeing Peter warming himself, she looked on him and said, Thou wast also with Jesus of Nazareth.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.68'>But he denied, saying, I know not, neither understand I what thou meanest. And he went out into the porch, and the cock crew.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.69'>And the maid saw him again, and said to them that stood by, This is one of them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.70'>And he denied it again. And a little after, those that stood by, said again to Peter, Surely thou art one of them; for thou art a Galilean, and thy speech agreeth thereto.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.71'>Then he began to curse and to swear, I know not this man of whom ye speak.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.14.72'>And the second time the cock crew. And Peter called to mind the word that Jesus had said to him, Before the cock crow twice, thou wilt deny me thrice. And he covered his head and wept.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.15'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.1'>And straightway in the morning the chief priests consulted with the elders and scribes, and the whole council, and having bound Jesus, carried him away, and delivered him to Pilate.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.2'>And Pilate asked him, Art thou the king of the Jews? And he answering said to him, Thou sayst it.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.3'>And the chief priests accused him of many things; but he answered nothing.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.4'>And Pilate asked him again, saying, Answerest thou nothing?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.5'>Behold how many things they witness against thee. But Jesus answered nothing any more, so that Pilate marvelled.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.6'>Now at every feast he released to them one prisoner, whomsoever they would.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.7'>And there was one named Barabbas, who lay bound with them that had made insurrection with him, who had committed murder in the insurrection.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.8'>And the multitude crying aloud, desired him to do as he had ever done for them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.9'>And Pilate answered them, saying, Will ye that I release to you the king of the Jews?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.10'>(For he knew that the chief priests had delivered him for envy) But the chief priests stirred up the people to desire,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.11'>that he would rather release Barabbas to them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.12'>And Pilate answering said to them again, What will ye then that I do to him whom ye call the king of the Jews?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.13'>And they cried out again, Crucify him. Then Pilate said to them, Why, what evil hath he done?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.14'>And they cried out the more exceedingly, Crucify him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.15'>And Pilate, willing to satisfy the people, released Barabbas to them, and having scourged Jesus, delivered him to be crucified.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.16'>And the soldiers led him away into the hall called Pretorium, and call together the whole troop.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.17'>And they clothe him with purple, and having platted a crown of thorns, put it about his head.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.18'>And they saluted him, Hail, king of the Jews.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.19'>And they smote him on the oead with a cane, and spit upon him, and bowing their knees, did him homage.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.20'>And when they had mocked him, they took off the purple robe from him, and put his own clothes on him, and led him out to crucify him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.21'>And they compel one Simon a Cyrenian, who was passing by, coming out of the country, the father of Alexander and Rufus, to bear his cross.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.22'>And they bring him to the place, Golgotha, which is, being interpreted, the place of a skull.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.23'>And they gave him to drink wine mingled with myrrh; but he received it not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.24'>And when they had crucified him, they parted his garments, casting lots upon them, what every man should take.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.25'>And it was the third hour, when they crucified him. And there was an inscription of his written over,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.26'>THE KING OF THE JEWS.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.27'>And with him they crucify two thieves, one on his right-hand, and one on his left.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.28'>And the scripture was fulfilled which saith, And he was numbered with the transgressors.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.29'>And they that passed by, reviled him, wagging their heads and saying, Ah, thou that destroyest the temple,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.30'>and buildest it in three days, Save thyself, and come down from the cross.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.31'>In like manner also the chief priests mocking said one to another, with the scribes, He saved others; cannot he save himself?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.32'>Let the Christ, the king of Israel, come down now from the cross, that we may see and believe. They also that were crucified with him reviled him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.33'>And when the sixth hour was come, there was darkness over all the earth until the ninth hour.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.34'>And at the ninth hour Jesus cried with a loud voice, Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani? Which is, being interpreted, My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken me?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.35'>And one of them that stood by, hearing it said, Behold, he calleth Elijah.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.36'>And one ran and filling a sponge with vinegar, put it on a cane, and gave him to drink, saying, Let alone; let us see if Elijah will come to take him down.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.37'>And Jesus cried with a loud voice, and expired.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.38'>And the veil of the temple was rent in twain, from the top to the bottom.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.39'>And the centurion, who stood over-against him, seeing that having so cried he expired, said, Truly this man was the Son of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.40'>There were also women, beholding from afar, among whom was Mary Magdalene and Mary the mother of James the less, and of Joses, and Salome:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.41'>Who also when he was in Galilee, followed him and ministered to him, and many other women who had come up with him to Jerusalem.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.42'>And the evening being now come, (because it was the preparation, that is,</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.43'>the day before the sabbath) Joseph of Arimathea, an honourable counsellor, who also waited for the kingdom of God, came and went in boldly to Pilate, and asked the body of Jesus.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.44'>And Pilate marvelled that he was dead already: and calling to him the centurion, he asked, If he had been any while dead?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.45'>And when he knew it of the centurion, he gave the body to Joseph.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.46'>And having bought fine linen, he took him down, and wrapped him in the linen, and laid him in a sepulchre, which was hewn out of a rock, and rolled a stone to the door of the sepulchre.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.15.47'>And Mary Magdalene and Mary the mother of Joses, beheld where he was laid.</verse>
      </chapter>
      <chapter osisID='Mark.16'>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.1'>And when the sabbath was over, Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James and Salome, had bought spices, that they might come and embalm him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.2'>And very early in the morning, the first day of the week, they come to the sepulchre, at the rising of the sun.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.3'>And they said one to another, Who shall roll us away the stone from the door of the sepulchre?</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.4'>(For it was very great:) And looking up, they saw that the stone was rolled away.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.5'>And entering into the sepulchre, they saw a young man, sitting on the right-side, clothed in a white robe; and they were affrighted.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.6'>He saith to them, Be not affrighted: ye seek Jesus of Nazareth, who was crucified. He is risen: he is not here. Behold the place where they laid him.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.7'>But go, tell his disciples, and Peter, He goeth before you into Galilee: there shall ye see him, as he said to you.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.8'>And going out, they fled from the sepulchre; for they trembled and were amazed: and they said nothing to any; for they were afraid.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.9'>Now when Jesus was risen early, the first day of the week, he appeared first to Mary Magdalene, out of whom he had cast seven devils.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.10'>She went and told them that had been with him, as they mourned and wept.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.11'>But they, hearing that he was alive, and had been seen of her, believed not.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.12'>After that he appeared in another form unto two of them, as they were walking, going into the country.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.13'>And they went and told it to the rest, neither believed they them.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.14'>Afterwards he appeared to the eleven, sitting at meat, and upbraided them with their unbelief and hardness of heart, because they believed not them who had seen him after he was risen.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.15'>And he said to them, Go ye into all the world, and preach the gospel to every creature.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.16'>He that believeth and is baptized, shall be saved; but he that believeth not, shall be damned.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.17'>And these signs shall follow them that believe: in my name they shall cast out devils:</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.18'>they shall speak with new tongues: They shall take up serpents, and if they drink any deadly thing, it shall in no wise hurt them: they shall lay hands on the sick, and they shall recover.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.19'>So then the Lord, after he had spoken to them, was received up into heaven, and sat on the right-hand of God.</verse>
        <verse osisID='Mark.16.20'>And they went forth, and preached every where, the Lord working with them, and confirming the word with signs following.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div></osisText>
</osis>